<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="EatInte"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>










<TEI.2 id="EatInte">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">His Interpreter</title>
<title type="sort">his interpreter</title>
<author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
<editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">55</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">EatInte</idno>
<date value="2004">2004</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475920</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">His Interpreter</title>
<title level="j">The Woman's Home Companion (September 1899); (October 1899).</title>
<title type="sort">his interpreter</title>
<author>Onoto Watanna [pseud., Winnifred Eaton]</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>The Onoto Watanna texts have been submitted to the Electronic Text Center by Jean Lee Cole to aggregate a collection of the
writings by Winnifred Eaton.</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>[physical description of text]</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Crowell &amp; Kirkpatrick Co</publisher>
<pubPlace>Springfield, Ohio</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Original illustrations by C. Allan Gilbert.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2004-06">June 2004</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags. Added pseudonym to author field.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="part" n="1" id="d3">
<head>His Interpreter <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Woman's Home Companion</hi> (September 1899; October 1899) <lb/>

By Onoto Watanna <lb/>
Part I.<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> </head>



     <p>The American sat at his desk, intently studying some

plans and sketches that were spread before him. His fine,

fair face was drawn with his intense absorption in his task,

and the heavy lines on his forehead showed he was puzzled

over something regarding it. Often he would turn from his

plans to a large book, and run his hand down a list of

figures, frowning heavily as if<ref target="n2">[2]</ref> their volume annoyed him.

After a time, he pushed the book and maps from him, and

running his hand wearily through his hair, leaned back in

his chair, with half-closed eyes and irresolute mouth and

chin.</p><p>

     A polite Japanese looked in at him from an adjoining

office with the calm, half wondering, wholly unreadable

countenance peculiar to the better class of Japanese.</p><p>

     The American observed him at the door, and called to

him:</p><p>

     “Ah, Inouye! Just a minute!”</p><p>

     The American's crisp, nervous explanation to his

interpreter was listened to with the gravest attention, the

latter scarcely commenting until the American had ceased

speaking. Then he leaned over the plans and studied them

silently a moment.</p><p>

     “I don't see that I've made it particularly clear to

you, Inouye,” the American put in, hastily, lighting a cigar

and watching with half-closed eyes his assistant's apparent

interest in the plans.</p><p>

     “It's like this. I have the contract all right, and

Takamine is willing to put up a good part of the money. You

understand that thus far I have merely represented an

American syndicate. Now I have the choice of taking up the

work with the sole financial help of Takamine, pushing it

along and doubtless making a pretty good profit for both of

us; but owing to the slenderness of our financial resources,

we could only afford to do the work in a limited way. Of

course, it might make a pretty big thing for both Takamine

and myself, but I cannot help wanting to push so splendid an

opportunity to its fullest extent, and do the work on an

immense scale. This is only possible with the financial aid,

or, indeed, by my putting things entirely into the hands of

the syndicate, and then perhaps profits would not accrue for

some time. Of course, I understand there would be,” he

repeated, “a big profit for both Takamine and myself if I

simply pushed it along at once, without advising the

syndicate; but the deuce is that I can scarcely do that

without seriously impairing and perhaps altogether breaking

my relations with the syndicate, and somehow—well, I can't

afford to do that.”</p><p>

     His handsome face clouded with perplexity and

dissatisfaction. The Japanese raised his head from the

plans, and asked, calmly:</p><p>

     “Is there greater profit in the work, Mr. Arthurs,

should the American syndicate take the contract?”</p><p>

     The American shifted in his seat, nervously turning

over the sides of his blotter.</p><p>

     “Well, a more general profit, Inouye. The syndicate has

controlled all my work thus far. I am anxious to get other

contracts on top of this one, and I would more likely be

able to get them if I carried out this one with the

assistance of the syndicate. Couldn't afford to do it alone.

This, if properly carried out, means only the beginning of

an immense lot of work—the cars, the miles of rail I have

calculated building in the future, could only be

accomplished with the aid of the syndicate. The question is

whether I shall merely carry out this contract and make

immediate profits for myself and Takamine, or let the

syndicate put up the big cash, buy American material, and—

well, make a fortune for the syndicate, too. You understand

in America these syndicates are immensely wealthy. With the

mere permit of the Japanese government the rest comes easily

enough. If the contract passes into the hands of the

syndicate it means a good position, and in time a good

fortune, for myself; but in that event it passes out of

Takamine's hands altogether, he being merely one of a good

many stockholders.”</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>The Japanese walked to the door and looked out across

the blue fields. He was not thinking of the American's

plans. His mind was absorbed in the image of a young maiden,

the daughter of Takamine. At one time he had been almost as

a son to Takamine, whose hospitable doors were constantly

open to receive him. With the over-hasty conceit and

impetuosity of a young man, his friend's kindness to him

made him overbold, so that he had asked the father for the

daughter in marriage. Takamine was a wealthy man, though

perhaps of not such high birth as Inouye. Nevertheless he

was indignant that his generosity and interest as a

benefactor to the young man, and which had procured him the

position he presently occupied with the American, should be

apparently imposed upon, for it seemed to Takamine, who had

something of the arrogance of the wealthy Japanese, that no

one but a man in his own position should aspire to his

daughter's hand.</p><p>

     Before the great reformation of the government system,

such an offer from Inouye, even in his impoverished state,

would have been considered a high compliment, as he belonged

to that class of people called the Shizoku (nobles), while

Takamine would have been recognized merely as a citizen or

rich merchant. But since the reformation all classes of

people became recognized equally, and there was no line of

distinction drawn whatever, save that which nobility and

high position, aided by wealth, could carry out, although

the nobles secretly resented the change and instinctively

felt their superiority in spite of fallen fortunes.</p><p>

     So Inouye bitterly thought of the refusal he had

received, and with all the stubbornness of his class

rebelled against it. Moreover, his heart was quite set on

the girl Haru for a bride, and it was with bitter jealousy

he imagined her the bride of another, for Haru was the

embodiment of everything that was sweet, beautiful, dainty,

and noble.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>“Well, Inouye, what would you do about it?” the

American's voice broke in on him.</p><p>

     Inouye had made himself, as confidential secretary and

interpreter, almost indispensable to the American, and

because of the coolness and wisdom he had shown in all

things, the more careless man was used to relying a great

deal on his opinion. Inouye's face was rather pale.</p><p>

     “If the syndicate pushes the work you will in the long

run make as much, if not more, profit. Is it not so?” he

asked.</p><p>

     “Well—yes,” said the American, slowly. “And it would

also give me a certain standing in America among railroad

men.”</p><p>

     “And Mr. Takamine?” inquired the Japanese, quietly.</p><p>

     The American laid the paper-knife he had been fingering

nervously down on the desk. His voice was almost fretful.</p><p>

     “I wish he had stayed out of this thing altogether,” he

said, irritably. “I've got the contract, anyhow, and the

syndicate could build the road just as well without his

purse. I simply wanted his aid with the government in

getting the contract; but he was shrewd enough to smell a

good thing for himself, and now, I fear, is in it to stay. I

can't very well go back on him, but I'll be hanged if I care

to push the work along solely on his and my account.”</p><p>

     The dark, thoughtful face of the Japanese was averted a

moment as the American continued:</p><p>

     “I'm only afraid if I do let the syndicate push it that

his capital will be almost entirely absorbed for some time,

and that he will realize nothing whatever on it for some

years. He'd get his money back in time, doubled, but it

would take some years, perhaps, before profits would accrue

and dividends be declared. The deuce is, he won't put in a

small part of his fortune, but every available yen he wants

to throw into the road.”</p><p>

     “I think,” said Inouye, deliberately, “I would hand the

whole thing to the syndicate. It would be better for you

altogether, for the syndicate and for this country. I would

not spoil so large a piece of work for one person.”</p><p>

     His gentle, slow voice paused, and the American

listened attentively to him.</p><p>

     “As you say, in the end it will mean loss to no one.

Only because the work will be doubled in its volume will the

time for profit be farther off.”</p><p>

     The American closed his book with a snap and began

folding the contracts and maps.</p><p>

     “I believe you are right, Inouye,” he said; “I will

have you write the syndicate later, and in the meantime

write as courteous a letter as possible to Takamine,



<pb n="10"/>



letting him know what we have decided upon, and explaining

that profits will be doubled for him in the end. By the way,

there's no use mentioning the time when profits begin to

accrue. He would not understand that, and we must have his

help with the government for the first eight months at

least. Use your diplomacy, and make me a translation of the

letter for my file before sending it out.”</p><p>

     There was a half-perceptible smile on the interpreter's

face as he withdrew.</p><p>

     It was some months before the work could be even begun

on the road, for communication between America and Japan is

slow, and Mr. Arthurs was obliged to submit most of his

plans directly to the syndicate, although the latter had

become so delighted with his success in obtaining, through

Takamine, various governmental concessions and privileges

that they put the utmost trust in the young man, and

permitted him to push forward the work largely on his own

responsibility.</p><p>

     The American had taken a larger suite of offices, and

there were a couple of new Japanese clerks sitting in the

outer offices of “The American Oriental Railroad Co.”</p><p>

     Inouye's desk had been moved into the same office as

the American's, and the pushing of the work forward depended

as much on him as on the promoter himself.</p><p>

     Arthurs was a queer mixture of shrewdness and weakness.

With the keenness of a veteran promoter he planned out a

work so extensive that it threatened to absorb all smaller

railways then existing in Japan. In spite of this he

depended almost entirely on Inouye for the execution of his

plans, and because of his confidence in him had appointed

him assistant manager of the company. The American soon

found it almost impossible to take a step without the

assistance of Inouye, and indeed it was Inouye who gave the

orders and saw they were carried out. There was scarcely a

suggestion that Inouye made which was not agreed to by

Arthurs, and in this way practically the entire management

lay in the hands of the Japanese.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>Everything went smoothly with the company, and the

American, having put the responsibility on the shoulders of

Inouye, found leisure to see something of the country itself

and take interest in the people. Like most foreigners, he

soon succumbed to the dolce far niente of the atmosphere,

and took his pleasures in a leisurely fashion. Indeed, there

are few foreigners visiting Japan who look upon the country

otherwise than as almost a pleasure resort; and though they

arrive with all the ambition and vigor of the West, they

soon slip off their commercial coats to don those of quiet

peace, restfulness, and sunshine. The ease and luxury which

pervade the life of the higher class of Japanese is

contagious, perhaps, to the foreigner, and the same

listlessness soon makes itself manifest among them after a

short residence there and when business cares press not too

heavily. Of course, the merchant-class people are ever alert

with a constant, keen eye for business, but this class of

Japanese are seldom as attractive to the foreigner as the

remnant of the old Samourai class. To pleasures they are

addicted. Local fêtes, flowers of every season, snow and the

full moon, all these give the better classes pretexts for

forming convivial parties which meet in picturesque tea-

houses and drink the tiny cups of hot saké, waited upon by

the dazzling, tripping waitresses, and constantly cheered

and entertained by the gaiety and accomplishments of the

ever-present geisha.</p><p>

     With the usual abandon and extravagance of an American,

Arthurs plunged into this novel and strangely fascinating

life of gaiety and dissipation, which, though fully as

attractive as that of his own country, yet nevertheless was

seldom unhealthful, because seldom carried to excess. In

fact, he grew happier and stronger under its influence. He

was never bored, seldom melancholy. The geisha-girls kept

him on a constant strain of mirth and sentiment, and the

beauty of the scenery was restful enough for even the most

weary man of the world.</p><p>

     Like most foreigners, the only native women he came in

contact with were merely the geisha or dancing girls, and

his ideas of Japanese women were entirely founded on the

life of these girls, believing them typical of the Japanese

woman. And with the usual susceptibility of a young man he

fell in love with a fresh face, a newer grace, a brighter

eye or redder lips each day.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>It was two years later. Takamine, who had as yet had

little or scarcely any return for his invested money, grew

more nervous each day. He had put the greater part of his

wealth in the railroad, hoping to realize a profit from it

very soon. To live in the extravagant style he had always

done, and give his sons and daughter fitting educations, was

a constant drain on his purse, already so badly depleted by

his investment. Three of his sons were abroad, being

educated in foreign lands, and there remained with him only

his youngest child, Haru, who was motherless. She was the

sunshine of the old man's life, and he made great plans for

her future. His influence with the government had not been

as great of late. He had been worsted in a recent election

for governor of the province. He felt he would have gained

this position had he been able to spend his money more

lavishly, but with so much of it tied up in stocks and bonds

of the railroad he did not feel encouraged to do so.</p><p>

     In the meanwhile, Arthurs' position had grown in

prominence; his salary was increased threefold, and he

himself was one of the largest stockholders of the company.

The railroad had progressed rapidly, and already included

many miles of rail.</p><p>

     Yet in spite of the evident prosperity of the road, and

the fact that it had already begun paying a small quarterly

dividend to its stockholders, Takamine's financial affairs

became more straitened. He had speculated heavily, and was

gambling away the remnants of his fortune. His last and only

resource was his investment with the railroad, and he vainly

tried to sell the bonds. The Japanese are not, as a rule, a

speculative people. Had he been in America he doubtless

could have sold his bonds at even more than their face

value; but in Japan it was different. The people, though

vastly interested in the progress of the road, were yet

niggardly in putting out any of their money, and when they

did, it was only in small sums. In fact, the stockholders of

the road were almost entirely English and Americans, and

although Takamine had put nearly forty thousand dollars into

the concern (and this is a fortune in Japan), he was

anything but the largest stockholder of the company; for

whereas he had paid in hard cash for all his stock, many of

the stockholders had either been presented with or were

supposed to have worked for a good part.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>


     <p>One morning when the American sauntered into the office

in his white flannels, looking anything but business-like,

he found Inouye at a desk writing out a long contract, and

sitting on the edge of the secretary's table, he inquired as

to its contents.</p><p>

     The young Japanese flushed a trifle, but answered quite

readily that it was a legal betrothal contract.</p><p>

     “A—a wh-what?” said the American, dropping his half-

smoked cigar from between his fingers.</p><p>

     “I wish to marry,” said Inouye, smiling a trifle. “I

have been partially betrothed for some years now,” he added,

quietly.</p><p>

     “The deuce you have! Rather ambiguous, that

'partially.'”</p><p>

     The Japanese fingered the contract lovingly with his

small, beautifully manicured fingers.</p><p>

     “That is,” he added, slowly, “I have never had the

consent of the father or of the girl, but—I have been

determined it should be, and it will be!” he ended,

convincingly. The American whistled softly.</p><p>

     “Hum! And what is she like? One of those delightful

little yum-yum creatures who walk on their heels and trip on

their toes, so that you never know whether they are dancing

or merely walking? One of those cherry-lipped, peepy-eyed

little witches who blow you a kiss to-day and a pout to-

morrow?”</p><p>

     Inouye frowned.</p><p>

     “She is not like that,” he said, briefly. “Those are

females—only females,” he added, in disgust.</p><p>

     The American sat up straight his chair and stared with

round eyes of wonder at the other.</p><p>

     “Females!”</p><p>

     Inouye had turned a half-angry red.</p><p>

     “You foreigners never can understand in Japan the

difference between a Japanese lady and a—a—mere female;

that is what I call the ones you describe.”</p><p>

     The American laughed outright. “You're a queer fellow,

Inouye,” he said. “My acquaintance with your countrywomen

has been rather limited, I suppose.”</p><p>

     “But you have had no acquaintance with my

countrywomen,” said the Japanese, proudly and doggedly.</p><p>

     The American leaned back in his chair and mused, and

the interpreter continued writing his contract in fine

Japanese figures.</p><p>

     “When is it coming off?” the American interrupted.</p><p>

     “It will depend if her father agrees,” the other

replied; and added, with a touch of satisfaction in his

voice, “I think he now will.”</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>He raised his head from his work and looked at the

American, smiling pleasantly. “Her name is Haru,” he said,

and a soft light shone for a moment in his eyes.</p><p>

     “Haru,” repeated the American, softly. “What a pretty

name! It means 'spring,' does it not?”</p><p>

     “Yes,” said Inouye, “it means spring. She will be the

very spring of my life. She is daughter to Takamine,” he

added, briefly.</p><p>

     The American sat stock-still. He remembered the

incident three years before of the young man's proposal and

refusal, of how he (Arthurs) had been told by Inouye to

encourage the old man to invest as much as possible, and

later of the pitiful state of Takamine's finances. The cold,

emotionless face of his young secretary looked a trifle

relentless and unscrupulous, and in a flash he understood

just what the deteriorated fortunes of Takamine would mean

to Inouye—deteriorated, however, only for a time, for he

would eventually make immense profits on his investment.

Mingled with the American's quick comprehension of the work

of Inouye was a feeling of admiration at the quietness and

skill with which he had carried it out, no one being

sufferer therefrom save perhaps old Takamine, and he would

be only for a short time. All this passed through the mind

of the American with lightning rapidity. The Japanese found

his slow, sharp words enigmatical when he broke the silence.</p><p>

     “You are a pretty clever fellow, Inouye. I believe you

would sweep anything aside that stood in your way in order

to attain your end.”</p><p>

     Inouye did not reply, and after a time the American

continued, deliberately: “You will marry a bride seemingly

poor, in reality wealthy. Our road is bound to be a

superlative success, as you know. Her father is one of the

largest stockholders, though the old fool, I believe, has

grown to think his bonds so much waste paper.”</p><p>

     Arthurs got up from his seat and walked up and down the

room, his hands thrust in his pockets, while Inouye watched

him a trifle anxiously. He stopped by Inouye's chair, and

said, quite gently:</p><p>

     “Well, I'm glad for you, my boy, and wish you every

happiness. Don't blame you, either, if you love the girl.

She must be very—er—pretty and sweet for you to have

waited so long and taken such pains to win her. Of course

she reciprocates your affection?”</p><p>

     “That,” said Inouye, evasively, “will come after

marriage. It is always so in Japan. We do not love before

marriage. We merely expect to love.”</p><p>

     The American was silent.</p>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>Part I was published in the September issue, and Part II
in October.</p></note>
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>“as their volume” in original.</p></note>
</div1>

<div1 type="part" n="2" id="d4">
<head>Part II.</head>


     <p>Long after the clerks had closed their desks and ink-

stands for the day, and until the sun began to sink to rest,

the American remained in his office absently glancing over

stray newspapers, though taking no note of what he read. His

house adjoined his office, and his man had been over twice

to call him to his supper. At the second call Arthurs locked

his heavy desk, and with the keys jingling in his hand,

passed absently out. But that evening he did not visit the

tea-houses on the hill after supper. Instead he remained

quietly indoors. His thoughts kept wandering to Inouye and

his betrothed. He could not help being interested in the

girl whom Inouye had been in such a hurry to defend from the

imputation that she was a “female.” He smiled whimsically as

he thought of this, and wondered whether she would be happy

after marriage with Inouye.</p><p>

     “If she is like the rest of them she will be,” he

thought, half scornfully. He would not acknowledge to

himself that the reason why he did not go to the tea-houses

now was because of Inouye's half-contemptuous allusion to

the geisha and dancing girls. It ruffled him when he

recalled Inouye's remark, “But you have had no acquaintance

with my countrywomen.” After all, that was true. All the

Japanese women he had met had been dancing and tea-house

geisha girls. He had thought them charming. He had not often

come in contact with the daughters of the nobles; indeed, he

could not recollect ever having seen any of them. They did

not live in the city, as a rule, or when they did, they

lived in great seclusion, seldom frequenting the street save

on their way to the hills and mountains, when they rode past

in graceful robes in their kurummas<ref target="n3">[3]</ref>. There were some

Japanese women who worked in offices and hospitals, he had

heard, but he had never spoken to any of them, and in

appearance they reminded him of English and American women,

as they wore European clothes, and most of them had been

educated abroad. Arthurs felt a desire to know something of

the real Japanese ladies of whom Inouye had spoken.</p>



                        <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>That same night the American had a visit paid him at

quite a late hour. He was preparing to retire for the night

when the light tapping of his man on his wall made him push

back the folding fusuma<ref target="n4">[4]</ref>. He took the card and read the

name, “Mr. I. Takamine.” The American tossed the card into a

tray, and in a few minutes was with his guest.</p><p>

     The old man was sitting sadly and forlornly on one of

the American's rather high chairs, and because he was such a

very little man he looked in the half-light almost like a

child. After the usual exchange of compliments, the old man

drew from under his hakama<ref target="n5">[5]</ref> a document. It was the betrothal

contract Inouye had made out that afternoon. In trembling

voice the old man inquired as to whether he had anything to

expect from his investment soon, and upon the assurance of

the American, said in halting English, “Then can this not

worry me.”</p><p>

     The American scanned the contract curiously, but as he

was unacquainted with the language was unable to make out

what it meant until Takamine said:</p><p>

     “You will understand that I want marry my daughter to

some one that I approve. I approve this young man, but I

must also approve what can give. He is poor, and my daughter

not understand to be poor. I thing that if I go lose my

money on this invest I will marry my daughter to Mr. Inouye.

And if I not lose my invest I keep her with me, and marry

her to some man with much rich also. So I come ask you that

I lose my invest.”</p><p>

     The American listened to him gravely, and when he had

finished speaking he said:</p><p>

     “But Inouye is hardly a poor man. He is practically the

manager of the whole business here, and is, in fact,

receiving quite a large salary. He might make your daughter

a very good husband. He is honest, conscientious, and—but

you doubtless know his character and good qualities. His

prospects are good at present.”</p><p>

     The old man's face brightened.</p><p>

     “If you lig' that my daughter marry with Inouye—”</p><p>

     “No,” the American interrupted, a trifle provoked. “I

merely wanted to explain things to you. You see, when Inouye

first came to me he was poor enough. His services have been

invaluable to me. The road has kept growing, and I have

advanced him considerably; and I judge from the clever way

in which he looks after the work he is in a fair way to

promotion right along.”</p><p>

     Takamine looked very much impressed, as the American's

words always went a great way with all who knew him. He rose

to his feet, bowing politely and humbly.</p><p>

     “I am thousand thanks to you until before I die,” he

said. “I shall consider—the proposition?”</p><p>

     The American smiled pleasantly.</p><p>

     “If the young people like each other I wouldn't stand

in their way,” he said, feeling quite fatherly and

benevolent.</p><p>

     The Japanese's polite eyes shifted ever so little. “My

daughter not lig', but that I lig' I make her that she

lig'.”</p><p>

     As he passed out, bowing at every step, the American

felt a sudden shiver at his heart.</p><p>

     “Poor little thing!” he said, half vaguely, to himself.

“I suppose he'll barter her to the highest bidder.” The

thought made him restless through the night. He felt an

instinctive pity and sympathy for Haru, as he remembered how

Inouye had refused to give him a direct answer as to whether

she cared for him; and now the father had lifted the veil a

bit, and he had a conception of the mute rebellion the girl

must have shown.</p>



                       <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>Haru's little heart was very heavy, and there was no

gaiety in her smile, which was pathetic and sad. Her father

tried to rally her out of her sadness, telling her that soon

he was going to betroth her to a young man who was good,

fine-looking, of noble parentage, and who would perhaps give

her all the luxuries she had always known. But the girl

protested pitifully, declaring she wanted not to be married,

and that her heart was set on going to her brothers, and

receiving, like them, a foreign education. Haru belonged to

that type of Japanese woman rarely seen in Japan save in the

homes of the noble and wealthy. Her mother had been of noble

parentage, and it was from her the girl inherited her innate

modesty and native beauty and grace. Like most Japanese

women, she was small; her face was oval, the features very

regular, with small mouth, and eyes that had a pathetic,

subdued look about them. But her eyes were larger than the

average Japanese eye, being wide as the Shizoku ladies'

usually are. Her little hands and feet would have served as

artists' models, and the soft, rounded neck that rose

gracefully above her kimono was slender, with a grace and

strength that made it wonderfully pleasing and attractive.

Although she had attended the finest schools for girls, she

was still wishful for a higher education, which her father

had been slow in gratifying owing to his desire to make an

early marriage for her. Haru was past eighteen, and quite

old enough to marry. Her father spoke to her constantly on

the subject, and since his interview with the American, and

others he had had since with him and with Inouye, he had

ever been urging her to marry Inouye. He loved her very

dearly, and did not wish to force her into a marriage that

would be obnoxious to her, but he was determined that she

should, as soon as he could get her reconciled, become

formally betrothed to some one before she reached her

nineteenth year.</p><p>

     “He will make a good husband,” he told her of Inouye

many times a day, and the girl would say:</p><p>

     “But I like not him, my father,” which would irritate

the old man very much, and he would make harsh answer:</p><p>

     “Who then you like? Who then must I give you to?”</p><p>

     “Not any one, my father,” the girl would say, clinging

to him. “Let me stay by you, and take care of you when you

shall be very old.”</p><p>

     But Takamine was stubborn, and would answer, “No! then;

because you are fair and my daughter, you must marry and

bring me more children.”</p>



                       <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>One day, when the air was very still, and the cherry-

blossoms were falling from the trees, and the very birds

hushed their little breaths because of the beauty of the

scene, and then thrilled of a sudden with their joy, the

American visited at the house of Takamine. The old man was

quite flattered, for the American had become a very big man

in the city, and every one honored and loved him because of

his kindness to all. Haru was playing Karutta<ref target="n6">[6]</ref> at the side

of the house with a friend, and as the American's tall

figure passed up the little garden walk to the house, the

girls nimbly stepped out of view, though they peeped

curiously at him from behind a bank of wisteria and ferns.</p><p>

     Takamine lived quite a good distance from the city. The

American was invited in the most polite manner to enter the

house and spend the afternoon with the old man indoors. He

saw nothing of the daughter, though once or twice he fancied

he heard a ripple of laughter in the next room. Finally he

asked his host bluntly whether he could not see Haru. The

old man bowed politely, and said she would appear at the

dinner-table.  Just when the sun began to tip over the hills

some one drew aside the sliding fusuma screens between the

rooms, and the American saw before him a pretty, bright room

and a couple of maids preparing the dinner. His host bade

him enter this room, and as he passed through he saw a

little form clad in a rose-colored kimona [sic] with red flowers

in her hair sitting on a mat. He could not see her face at

first because her head was bending almost to the floor in

her greeting to her father's guest. The old man introduced

them, and once more the girl's little head almost touched

the ground.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>Arthurs had never before dined at a Japanese private

house, though he had now been three years in the country. He

had lived like most foreigners who come to the country—half

the time at the American hotel, and half the time in his

Japanese-American house. As he gravely took his seat on a

mat placed for him, he saw Haru's face. The eyes were

downcast and refused to look at him. The man's heart rose in

his throat, for she was very beautiful. From the floor,

padded perhaps five feet with soft rice-straw, to the

exquisite walls, the rich silk robes of Haru and her father,

the dainty china placed before him, Arthurs recognized the

home of Japanese wealth. He could not have told what he ate.

He had made a solemn resolve to follow the national

etiquette and eat all placed before him, and this he did in

the most heroic manner. Often through the meal he found his

eyes wandering to the girl, as she lifted her little bowl of

rice with one hand and daintily manipulated the chop-sticks

with the other.</p>



<pb n="12"/>



     <p>Although Takamine spoke a great deal to him through the

meal, the girl never once addressed him. Once Arthurs

himself addressed her, asking if she had ever met an

American lady, and the girl had turned her face to her

father, who replied for her, saying that she had had an

American teacher once who had taught her the language and

physical exercises.</p><p>

     Arthurs found himself wishing to hear her say

something, and impatiently wondered to himself whether she

was dumb.</p><p>

     After the dinner they retired into the room where he

had formerly sat. Then Haru lit sticks of incense in the

room, and brought trays with cigarettes for her father and

the American. She herself found a seat in the shadow, where

the American could not see her well, though he felt that her

turn was now come, and that, shaded in her retreat, she was

studying and observing him as he sat awkwardly in Japanese

fashion.</p>



                      <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>After this first visit Arthurs came with fair

regularity for some time, and soon became a welcome and

familiar guest of the house. His persistence in his calls

had been more than repaid, for now Haru was permitted to

talk a little with him, though always in the presence of her

father. She would glide about in the room in the prettiest

ways, bringing odd, comfortable cushions and wraps for her

father and guest to sit on. But the greatest treat the

American had was one night when her father had bidden her

bring her samisen<ref target="n7">[7]</ref>, and she had played ever so gently on it,

and sang to them in the moonlight in a weird, sweet voice,

which was plaintive with longing and so subdued that it gave

one a suggestion of the woman heart beneath. Arthurs had

heard the Japanese geisha-girls sing before, and many of

them had sung much like this, but he did not know it,

because they had not the same interest and fascination for

him, with all their brilliancy, as this gentle little

Japanese lady, who obeyed the enforced rules and etiquette

of her class.</p><p>

     The American was in love in earnest this time. He

forgot all about Inouye, all about the promises he had made

to him to become more familiar with the father so that he

might have more power in making him take the boy as son-in-

law. He knew only that Haru's voice was sweeter than

anything he had ever heard, that her little shiny head was

prettier than anything he had ever seen, and that she was

the most desirable thing on earth.</p><p>

     One day he broached for the first time the subject of

the girl's marriage.</p><p>

     “In my country,” he said, speaking more for Haru than

her father, “the women choose their own husbands just like

the men choose their wives. That is,” he corrected himself,

“they seldom marry any one they don't want to.”</p><p>

     The girl's eyes were lowered. Arthurs saw a flush creep

over her face, and the little fingers on the samisen

trembled.</p><p>

     Haru spoke English very prettily, and for the old man's

pleasure they generally conversed in that language.</p><p>

     “Here,” said Takamine, with conviction that his own

country was wiser, “our daughters marry whom we choose for

them.”</p><p>

     “Ah, yes. Then I suppose your daughter, Haru-san, will

not marry whom she chooses?”</p><p>

     Takamine smiled. “I will try to please her,” he said,

simply, and the girl's wistful face relaxed.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>It was six months since the date on which Inouye had

drawn up his betrothal contract and had presented it to

Takamine. During this time the American had become an almost

daily visitor at Takamine's house, and the old man was quite

seriously under obligations to him, for at a time when he

found his resources were running down to a low ebb he had

half apologetically offered his bonds for sale to the

American himself. This Arthurs rather brusquely refused,

assuring the old man that the profits would eventually be

such that he felt Takamine ought to wait still awhile

longer, but knowing of his absolute present need for money,

he advanced Takamine a sum of money, asking no security

therefor whatever. Takamine told Haru that he was under

eternal obligations to the American. He knew of only one way

in which he felt he could give genuine pleasure to him—that

was to grant his request, made some months ago, giving his

daughter in marriage to Inouye, the friend of the American.

As her father recounted all the kindness he had received

from the American, and enlarged on it, Haru answered never a

word, but sat very pale and quiet, her eyes looking far out

with an expression of longing and sadness in them that the

old man could not fathom. When the father asked her if she

would not now be a dutiful daughter and help him to fill his

obligations, she passively assented, smiling so gently and

meekly that the father put his hand lovingly on her head,

and said she was ever his dutiful and loving daughter.</p>



                        <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>Two mornings later, as the American sat at his desk

signing a batch of letters that Inouye had dictated to the

stenographer, Inouye, who stood at his elbow, said very

softly:</p><p>

     “When you are not much busy I would wish to speak of

some private business.”</p><p>

     The American pushed the letters aside, and looked up at

the young man with his usual kind, attentive smile.</p><p>

     “Well, Inouye,” I'm at leisure now,” he said,

encouragingly.</p><p>

     Inouye looked at him the least bit uneasily, and then

began to thank him in the formal words of a Japanese to his

benefactor for his kindly offices in his behalf, finally

telling the American of his betrothal to Haru. The American

did not interrupt him once as he spoke, but the keen eyes of

the Japanese saw a gray shadow creep over his face.</p><p>

     When Inouye had finished, the American wheeled slowly

around on his chair. He had no word of comment to make.

Suddenly he got up abruptly from his seat and crossed to the

door. He stood looking out at the endless glow of the

Oriental landscape with a sudden tightening of his heart-

strings, with a pain that was terrible in its numbness and

helplessness. A couple of doves in a neighboring cote were

crooning mournfully, and two little geisha-girls waved their

hands joyously at him.</p><p>

     He was thinking of Haru, just as Inouye had done three

years before, and he had forgotten his interpreter and his

work—forgotten all save that the joyous daydream in which

he had reveled ever since that first day he had met her was

all passing away, and that life was not worth the living now

that it had ceased.</p><p>

     The Japanese watched him with a penetrating look.

Perhaps he guessed the truth. He could not restrain the half

smile of triumph as he realized how he had worsted the

American. A formal betrothal in Japan is almost as binding

as a marriage. When the gifts are exchanged in token of

engagement the pair live on, each feeling they belong to the

other, and as a rule the time is very short between the

betrothal and the marriage ceremony.</p><p>

     Inouye did not break in on his master's reverie. On the

contrary, he returned to his desk, and started at his work

in his usual methodical way. After a time the American also

returned to his desk, and the Japanese, glancing sideways at

him, saw him nervously fingering a half-withered red flower.

It had lain on the American's desk for some days, and no one

had removed it.</p><p>

     Later, when Inouye brought some papers and letters to

be signed, the American went through them calmly, but his

face was quite pale. No word passed between them beyond a

few questions and answers about the work. Perhaps the

American shrank ever so slightly as his secretary stood by

his chair.</p>



                        <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>Early in the afternoon he closed his desk, and passed

out of the office with the pale, absent-minded face he had

worn all day.</p><p>

     He hailed a kurumma, and jumping into it gave orders to

the kurumaya to drive him to Takamine's house.</p><p>

     The American had found no word to say to Inouye,

because in his usually<ref target="n8">[8]</ref> generous and happy heart had risen a

deep indignation and rage against Inouye. He knew Inouye had

left him no grounds to attack him. What could he say? He

only knew that he had loved Haru for months now, and for

this reason he had sought her out constantly. Inouye knew

this, and had taken advantage of it to work on Takamine, and

make him believe it was on his behalf the American had

singled him out and paid him so much attention.</p><p>

     He thought of little Haru, and how her voice had

trembled when she said:</p><p>

     “Japanese ladies naever lofe where they marry.”</p><p>

     He had looked in her eyes and whispered, “Promise me,

Haru, that you will be an exception.”</p><p>

     A cloud had gathered across her face, and she had

raised it pitifully to him.</p><p>

     “How can I then help?” she said, vaguely, and the first

tears Arthurs had seen in Japan clouded her eyes, and shone

glistening there. Had he misinterpreted that look when he

had imagined she had half reproached him, and if she wished

to reproach him then, did his heart not tell him it was

because she knew he loved her?</p><p>

     Takamine was surprised at such an early call, but

welcomed his guest as courteously as ever. Haru was nowhere

in sight, and the American felt strangely weak and hardly

knew himself what he had come for.</p><p>

     “Inouye tells me of his betrothal,” he said, abruptly,

looking the old man in the face. Takamine's face beamed.</p><p>

     “Ah, yes,” he said, bowing his head again and again,

and folding his hands in blissful satisfaction. “We are

waiting for the brothers to return to the wedding from

abroad,” he added.</p><p>

     “Does—er—Haru care? Will—a—does she love Inouye?”</p><p>

     “Oh, yes, yes!” answered the old man, hastily, shrewdly

conscious that this would please an American.</p>



                        <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>His assent astonished Arthurs, and he hardly knew how

to proceed. He looked about the room at the objects that had

become so familiar and dear to him, and he felt the same

strangling at his heart as when Inouye had broken the news

to him. But his pain gave him speech this time.</p><p>

     “I don't believe it,” he said, harshly. “She has

herself told me repeatedly she did not care for him.”

     Takamine was trembling.</p><p>

     “My daughter was most rude that she tell you that. I

assure that this will be happy marriage that you have

helpd.”</p><p>

     “I helped!” said Arthurs, wildly, walking up and down

the room. “In what way? You are all mistaken, Takamine. You

have been deceived. I never countenanced the—a—match. I

never—I thought Haru— Confound it, she is too good for the

beggar! He has deceived all of us in the matter.”</p><p>

     The little Japanese gentleman wabbled after him across

the matting in trepidation and astonishment.</p><p>

     “But you—you tell me—some months that come—you speak

he is good, and for him you ask. For this I marry her with

him, because that I like you much and would please.”</p><p>

     “It must be stopped, Takamine!” said the young man,

hotly, pausing in his walk and looking down at his little

host. “Yes,” he repeated, “it must be stopped—unless,” and

his voice wavered, “unless it is true that she—that Haru

told you she cared for him.”</p><p>

     There was a rustle at the other side of the fusuma, and

by the way it was shaking Arthurs knew some one was standing

close to it listening. Then a little broken voice trilled

out:</p><p>

     “It not true—I not tell that I care.”</p><p>

     The ludicrousness of the situation was lost on the

American, who had become accustomed to such things in Japan,

and knew that any one in the next room in a Japanese house

could hear and through small holes see as plainly as if in

the same room. He turned and faced the direction of the

voice, saying:</p><p>

     “No, Haru, I don't believe you could care for him,

after—after all we have said to each other.”</p><p>

     Takamine sat on his mat in silent misery and shame.</p><p>

     “What for shall we do?” he said, looking helplessly at

the American, who had so thoroughly taken his household by

storm; and he added, ambiguously, “Do as you please that you

like it or not.”</p>



                          <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>The American forgot all about Japanese etiquette. He

pushed the sliding screen back. There was Haru, standing

perfectly still, her back turned to them, an odd little

figure with head drooping half in shame, though she showed a

strange willingness to stay with them.</p><p>

     The American turned her round, a silent, obedient

little figure to his every touch. Then he looked down at her

and saw she was weeping.</p><p>

     “Haru,” he whispered, softly, “do you love Inouye?”</p><p>

     The girl shook her head violently. Old Takamine came

beside her also, and watched the American in a half-

fascinated way.</p><p>

     “Who do you love, Haru?”</p><p>

     “The Amerikazan—him I lofe,” she said, scarcely above

a whisper, and Arthurs laughed outright in very joyousness.</p><p>

     “You see,” he said to the astounded father. “I told you

you were mistaken—that Haru did not love Inouye”; and as

the girl smiled through her tears he added, very tenderly,

“I knew what I was talking about.”</p><p>

     A silence eloquent in its sadness and helplessness fell

between them. Both Haru and her father were sad and

hopeless, but the American's face shone with delight at the

girl's confession.</p><p>

     “The thing to be done now,” he said, in his usual

authoritative way, “is to have this betrothal contract

broken at once. Then we'll make a new one for Haru and

myself, and as I am to go to America on business soon, I'll

take Haru with me, on our honeymoon. Ever hear of a

honeymoon, Haru? Then she'll have her heart's desire—seeing

foreign lands.”</p><p>

     Takamine rocked back and forth in distress.</p><p>

     “If that Inouye will not release—this is most

binding.”</p><p>

     “He will release,” said the American, with a glint in

his eyes, stooping over the old man and reassuring him with

his usual confidence.</p><p>

     Before leaving them he turned and took Haru in his arms

before her father, and raising her little, tearful flower-

face, kissed her so tenderly and lovingly on the lips that

the girl's face shone with its artless pleasure.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>“It's like this,” the American said to Inouye a couple

of hours later. “Haru does not love you. She does love me.”</p><p>

     Inouye was perfectly silent. If he felt any indignation

he would not let the American see it.</p><p>

     “Will you release her?” said the American,

encouragingly.</p><p>

     “No!” said the Japanese.</p><p>

     “Will you tell me why?” said Arthurs, sharply. “Have

you any particular affection for her? You have often told me

you have not.”</p><p>

     The Japanese was dogged, and Arthurs continued:</p><p>

     “Now, I'll tell you, Inouye. I think I know you pretty

well. You are too ambitious to have much sentiment in you.

You are a first-class man for this company. As one of the

directors of the road I can advance you here just as I

choose. I want to return to America, for various reasons.

Some one must fill my place.”</p><p>

     He leaned across the table, and looked full at Inouye.</p><p>

     “If you want this place I can give it to you. If you do

not want it, keep on persecuting a girl who does not care

anything about you. Make her father wretched, and—er—

perhaps lose your present position in the end.”</p><p>

     Arthurs felt like a conspirator after saying this,

though he knew it was the only way to conquer Inouye.</p><p>

     The young Japanese remained with hands clasped on the

desk, immovable, thinking bitterly. After a while he rose,

and said very politely to the American:</p><p>

     “I will accept the position you offer.”</p>

<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>kurumma: like a jinrikisha (i.e., rickshaw), a term much
more commonly used by Eaton;  a carriage pulled by human
runners.</p></note>
<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>fusuma: sliding doors used in Japanese houses, constructed
of light wooden frames with opaque paper panels.</p></note>
<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>hakama: formal outer garment traditionally worn by the
samurai.</p></note>
<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>Karutta: a Japanese card game; the name comes from the
Portuguese word “carta” (Portuguese traders were the first
Europeans to come to Japan, in the 16th century).</p></note>
<note id="n7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p>samisen: stringed instrument with an elongated neck and
three strings.</p></note>
<note id="n8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p>“usual” in original.</p></note>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
