<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="EatYoun"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>









<TEI.2 id="EatYoun">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Where the Young Look Forward to Old Age</title>
<title type="sort">where the young look forward to old age</title>
<author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
<editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">EatYoun</idno>
<date value="2004">2004</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475944</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Where the Young Look Forward to Old Age</title>
<title level="j">Ladies' Home Journal: 8 (February 1899)</title>
<title type="sort">where the young look forward to old age</title>
<author>Onoto Watanna [pseud., Winnifred Eaton]</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>The Onoto Watanna texts have been submitted to the Electronic Text Center by Jean Lee Cole to aggregate a collection of the
writings by Winnifred Eaton.</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>[physical description of text]</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Curtis Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2004-06">June 2004</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3">

	<head>Where the Young Look Forward to Old Age<lb/>
		<hi rend="italic">Ladies' Home Journal</hi> 8 (February 1899)<lb/>
		By Onoto Watanna</head>

     <p>Perhaps one of the sweetest characteristics of the

Japanese is their innate love, obedience, and respect for

their parents. The Japanese character in this respect has

not its parallel the world over. To a Japanese the word

“duty” might be said to be the most significant word in the

language. But the Japanese interpretation of the word has a

far different meaning to the generally accepted one. Duty,

to a Japanese, means not merely obedience and discipline,

but strong, sweet, cultivated, parental devotion. I use the

word “cultivated” because this feeling has been and is

cultivated in Japan. Nevertheless it does not lose its

naturalness. On the contrary, this devotion of the young for

the old—the adoration of the parent by the child—becomes a

natural cultivation. It is exemplified not only in the

larger and formal acts of Japanese life, but in the minutest

and smallest detail. The little Japanese child obeys without

question, and generally in a lovable, willing manner, the

gentle “demand” of its parents, and even in cases where the
parents are harsh the natural love of authority is still

there and the child is obedient.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>The parents' word is always law in Japan, and perhaps

this accounts for the sweetness and gentleness of the

Japanese character. The Japanese are inherently an obedient

people. The old always take precedence of the young in all

things. An eager, impetuous young man, be he ever so

brilliant and clever, is not expected in Japan to have the

reason, the wisdom, and the foresight of an old man.

Therefore the old man comes first always. As a result, there

is, perhaps, more general happiness in Japan than anywhere

else in the world.</p><p>

     One might imagine that where duty is carried to the

extent it is in Japan the natural love is not so much in

evidence—I mean the actual affection, rather than the mere

duty, of a child to its parent. On the contrary, the natural

bond of affection between parents and children is nowhere so

wonderful as in Japan. No matter how unkind, unjust or even

wicked the parent may be, or how depraved, the child

invariably clings to that parent, even though, as is often

the case, its own nature be finer.</p><p>

     There exists in Japan a certain custom of adopting

“from the cradle.” A childless couple will very often adopt

a child, taking it generally as soon as it is born. The

child's real parents may have been people in every way

inferior to its adopted parents. The little one may be

reared by the foster-parents as if it were their own child,

and not allowed to know, when it is possible to conceal it,

who its real parents are. By exercising their influence over

it, and treating it with affection, the little one,

believing them to be its real parents, gives them, in

return, all the love that their own child would.

Unfortunately, these adoptions cannot always be kept secret,

and sooner or later the child, generally when it is just

stepping from childhood into youth, is apprised of the

truth. The consequence is remarkable. The child, to all

appearance, will be as respectful, obedient, and devoted to

its adopted parents, but there is something lacking,

something is gone that was there when it had believed the

foster-parents were indeed its own. The child, in such a

case, will endeavor in every way to conceal its feelings in

order that the parents may not regret their bargain.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



     <p>Still more surprising is the zeal with which the child

will set about to discover its real parents. Be they low or

high, they are nevertheless its blood kin, and in Japan the

blood tie is strong almost to exaggeration. In some cases

these adopted children will find that their true parents are

much inferior to the ones they have always loved, and while

they will respect and obey the latter, there is a strange,

indescribable affection for the real parents, even though

they be comparative strangers to them. This is a peculiar, I

might say inherent, characteristic of the Japanese—this

cleaving to kinship with a tenacity that is full of heroism,

and, indeed, not infrequently filled with pathos.</p><p>

     A very pretty custom in Japan is the praying and

speaking to the dead parents. Long after the death of good

parents, their children will talk and pray to them, and a

peculiarity is that they do not pray for blessings on

themselves, but they themselves bless the departed ones, for

it is said that the prayers and blessings of the living

affect the new life of the dead to this world. One can,

therefore, see how desirable it is to have the love of one's

children, so that for peace in the hereafter they may have

their blessings.</p><p>

     The Japanese religion exacts that no man may be very

wealthy and his relatives poor, and teaches that it is more

blessed to be old than young—two very beautiful things. Is

it not refreshing to find one spot on earth where age has no

terror to the young; where the young gladly look forward to

even extreme old age? There is no such thing as dread of old

age in Japan. And I wonder if in America we might not rob

age, old age, of its horror if we honored it more? Is it not

better to ever believe, as do the people of Japan, that the

old are ever the best?</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
