<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Amoy_Chinese_Girl">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Amoy, A Chinese Girl</title>
            <title type="sort">amoy, a chinese girl</title>
            <author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
            <editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to P5 conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>Joey Takeda</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">EatAmoy</idno>
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475907</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Amoy, A Chinese Girl</title>
                  <title level="j">The Woman`s Home Companion: 7-8. (November 1900)</title>
                  <title type="sort">amoy, a chinese girl</title>
                  <author>Onoto Watanna [pseud., Winnifred Eaton]</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <p>The Onoto Watanna texts have been submitted to the Electronic Text Center by Jean Lee Cole to aggregate a collection of the
writings by Winnifred Eaton.</p>
               </editionStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Crowell and Kirkpatrick Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Springfield, Ohio</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1900">1900</date>
                  <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
            <p xml:id="ETC_Amoy_Chinese_Girl">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="1900">1900</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng" usage="1">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords n="Location">
               <term>Japan</term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords>
               <term>fiction</term>
               <term>prose</term>
               <term>feminine</term>
               <term>Women Writers</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-01-04">Joey Takeda: Converted document from P4 (old <att>xml:id</att>: EatAmoy. Old filename: Amoy%20Chinese%20Girl.xml.)</change>
         <change when="2008-01">Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</change>
         <change when="2007-09">Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</change>
         <change when="2005-07">John Ivor Carlson: Corrector. Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</change>
         <change when="2004-06">Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center: corrector. Added TEI header and tags.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>


   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="story">

	           <head>Amoy, A Chinese Girl<lb/>
		             <hi rend="italic">The Woman`s Home Companion</hi> (November 1900): 7-8<lb/>
		
		By Onoto Watanna</head>

            <p>Only a short time ago she had been the very light of

the tea-garden.  No one could dance with the wild

extravagance, yet graceful delicacy, of Amoy, and no voice

was sweeter than hers; furthermore, she was wonderfully

pretty, with her little pursed mouth, bright eyes and rich

abundance of shiny hair; and besides being pretty and

clever, Amoy was gentle, modest and good, so you will see it

was no wonder that she was the favorite of all the patrons

of the house. Even the girls, who were usually so jealous

when one was more popular than another, could not help

liking Amoy.</p>
            <p>

     For two years, though a Chinese girl, she had lived the

public life of the geisha-girl in Japan, laughing, dancing,

singing for the entertainment of the guests; but this

existence had not spoilt her in the slightest. At the end of

the two years the girl still retained her native modesty and

grace.</p>
            <p>

     But now all was different; for some months—ever since

the air had become thick with dark rumors of war—Amoy had

been very unhappy. One day the manager had come into the tea-

garden, and to the great surprise of all the girls, had

spoken harshly to Amoy, whom he had always treated with

great consideration. This was the day that the declaration

of war against China had been published on blood-red paper.

From that day her life had become even more unhappy. Her

employer had lost all his former cordiality of manner toward

her, and the inmates of the house, the girls, even the very

servants, had begun to despise her; for was she not of a

nation at war with them, and whom it behooved them to hate?</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>But even this was not all. To the sorrow that had

resulted from her fall from favor was added the fear of

losing her position. Business was bad, for the young men

were all enlisting and the older ones were too much occupied

with the country's cause to find time for the distractions

the tea-houses offered. Mizutany, the manager, was beginning

to talk of discharging some of the girls, and well Amoy knew

that she would be the first to go. Amoy was all alone in

Japan. Away back in the province of Shantung, in China, she

had a half dozen little brothers and sisters and an old

father and mother. At a very early age she had gone out into

the world and made her living with a troupe of Chinese

jugglers and players who had come to Japan. Her unusual

beauty had attracted the attention of Mizutany, who made her

a tempting offer for her services, and she had entered his

employ. Among the frequenters of his tea-house she had

always appeared light and gay of heart, and no one ever

guessed how homesick and sad the girl became at times.</p>
            <p>

     The tea-house and gardens adjoined, and, in fact, were

connected with a public jinrikisha-stand which was just

outside the gardens, and very handy for the guests as they

went to and from the gardens. At the back of the jinrikisha-

stand was a large open shed, which served as a shelter

during storm. In this shed, up one flight of stairs, was a

large lumber-room, a dull, gloomy place, used both by the

jinrikisha-men and the tea-house people for the storing of

old goods, worn-out jinrikishas, broken musical instruments,

and other plunder. Few there were who would voluntarily take

the trouble to climb the rickety stairs unless it was

necessary to store away some useless thing; yet it was to

this old store-room that Amoy would come when her duties

were over. In it was an old-fashioned jinrikisha, its

linings worn to shreds, its calash top broken and its

beautifully lacquered sides all cracked and blistered. This

offered the softest seat in the room, however, and it swayed

gently to and fro. Amoy would often climb into the old

jinrikisha's heart, and there she would brood bitterly over

her unhappy lot.</p>



                        <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>The landlord of both the tea-house, managed by

Mizutany, and the jinrikisha-stand, was Inouye Izuma, a

young man said to be of considerable wealth. He was very

much esteemed for his general good-nature and kindness of

heart. Few gave more freely to the war fund than he, and

when the call for volunteers came from the government he was

one of the first to offer himself. With scores of others,

however, he was refused the chance of military service. But

unlike many of those who were refused, Izuma neither took

his life nor became gloomy or despondent. Perhaps the

government would need him later on. For this he held himself

in readiness, and turned himself with a cheerful heart to

the task of helping those at home. Many a family that had

given up sons for service in the war, and were suffering

poverty besides sorrow, found a son in Izuma, and found

great cheer in his encouraging smile and helping hand.</p>
            <p>

     When the news of the sinking of the Kowshing arrived,

and drove the city made with delight, Amoy crept up to the

old store-room to weep alone. The day without was beautiful,

and even the dark store-room was brightened by a few stray

gleams of sunshine that literally forced their way into the

place as though in protest that any spot should be in

darkness. Amoy was tired and in trouble. From words she had

overheard she knew she was on the point of being discharged,

and she was distracted. She prayed to all the gods to help

her. She even murmured a pitiful prayer to the Japanese

goddess of mercy, Kwannon, to soften the hearts of her

people—for Amoy had lived so long in Japan that she was

almost a Japanese in heart and spirit, even though not for

one moment did she ever forget her own country and people.</p>
            <p>

     All this time the old jinrikisha had rocked soothingly

back and forth, and even while she prayed, Amoy fell asleep.

The sunlight gleamed across her little head and seemed to

spread a halo around it. Among the useless relics and worn-

out vehicles and instruments she seemed more pretty than

ever she had before.</p>



                        <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>She had not been asleep fifteen minutes before the door

of the store-room was pushed open and Inouye Izuma and a

stranger came into the place.</p>
            <p>

     “I will show you the vehicle and you can see what

repairs are needed,” Izuma was saying. They moved over to a

jinrikisha that had met with an accident the previous day.</p>
            <p>

     “This is the—” continued Izuma, and then suddenly

broke off and stared with wide, fascinated eyes at the

sleeping girl. “Look!” he said to the other man. Then they

stood very still and gazed at the pretty picture.</p>
            <p>

     Izuma had certainly seen her before in the gardens, but

doubtless had never noticed her peculiar beauty, for he

seldom went to the gardens save on business with Mizutany,

and would merely encounter the girls in gay groups. Now he

stood beside Amoy, breathing very hard, and his eyes gleamed

and glowed the more they looked at her. Then very

reluctantly he turned them from her, and transacted his

business hastily with the other man, after which they passed

out together.</p>
            <p>

     But soon Izuma came back to the store-room, and,

crossing on tiptoe, stood for a long time by the sleeping

girl, gazing at her with all his heart in his eyes. When she

awoke he was still standing there, and she started up,

blushing, and looking very ashamed and frightened. Izuma was

blushing and confused, too, and they seemed like two pretty

children.</p>
            <p>

     “Ah! I must ask your pardon,” she said, and even her

little ears tingled.</p>
            <p>

     Izuma did not answer.</p>
            <p>

     “I—I was very tired,” the girl faltered, fearful that

she had offended him; for in these days she was very careful

not to offend when she could avoid it.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>“But is it comfortable to sleep here?” he asked,

gently.</p>
            <p>

     “No; not so comfortable as in the house,” she agreed;

“but—but I did not mean to sleep. I wished only to be

alone.”</p>
            <p>

     “Ah! Why?”</p>
            <p>

     She sighed. “You a Japanese and ask that?”

     They were talking in pure Japanese, which language the

girl spoke almost as fluently as her own; there was a

delightful little accent to her words, however.</p>
            <p>

     “Yes,” he answered; “I do not understand.”</p>
            <p>



               <pb n="8"/>



     “I—I am not Japanese. Perhaps you do not know?” she

murmured, her head drooping.</p>
            <p>

     “Yes, I know that. You are Chinese.”</p>
            <p>

     “Then—and everybody in Japan hates me.”</p>
            <p>

     “No, no—not everybody.”</p>
            <p>

     “Who does not?” she asked, bitterly.</p>
            <p>

     “I—I do not. I have seen you often, and I have never

disliked you—never hated you, and now—” the sentence

remained unfinished, but his face was eloquent.</p>
            <p>

     “I must go now,” she said, jumping up nervously.</p>
            <p>

     “But why did you come here?” he asked.</p>
            <p>

     “To be sad, to weep, to break my heart alone,” she

answered, with a burst of passion.</p>
            <p>

     “Ah, but is pain more bearable alone?”</p>
            <p>

     “Alas, I have none to share it with me!”</p>
            <p>

     “But me!” he exclaimed, eagerly.  “Let me share it with

you!”</p>
            <p>

     “But you are Japanese,” she said, quietly, and left him

musing all alone in the semi-darkness of the store-room.</p>



                      <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>The next day Izuma's man carried a huge bunch of cherry-

blossoms into the tea-house and laid them at Amoy's feet.

The girl understood, and grew quite pale.</p>
            <p>

     “For me—are they for me?” she asked, unsteadily.</p>
            <p>

     “Yes.”</p>
            <p>

     A number of the geisha-girls were looking curiously on,

wondering who it was that had sent the flowers. Amoy buried

her delightful little nose in the blossoms. She was pale and

rosy in turns.</p>
            <p>

     “Tell him—” she began, “ah, let me see; who—who sends

the flowers?” She knew, but preferred to hear his name

spoken.</p>
            <p>

     The man told her, a touch of surprise in his voice.

Still Amoy hesitated. From somewhere in the street outside

came the triumphant beat of the drum and the brazen call of

the bugle. Amoy raised her little chin, and handed the

flowers back to the man.</p>
            <p>

     “Tell him—tell him I cannot take them now. Tell him

that—that I must wait till the war is done. That,” she

hesitated, her voice faltering, “that I shall marry one of

my own countrymen.”</p>
            <p>

     Her lips trembled when the man took the flowers,

obediently, bowing very politely; and she stood still in the

path, watching him until he had disappeared from sight.</p>
            <p>

     “Look,” said one of the girls; “she has returned his

flowers.”</p>
            <p>

     “Maybe she is too good for a Japanese,” another

sneered.</p>
            <p>

     Their curiosity as to the sender of the flowers got the

better of them, for proposals were not plentiful in these

times. “Who is he?” they asked.</p>
            <p>

     She told them quietly, and they were surprised and

envious, for Izuma was wealthy and wielded much influence;

while Amoy—why, she was but a geisha-girl, and a Chinese

one at that!</p>
            <p>

     “Why did you refuse him?”</p>
            <p>

     “Because he—perhaps—despises my—my people,” she

said, proudly.</p>
            <p>

     “Well, he does not despise you or he would not have

offered himself. You are very foolish.”</p>
            <p>

     “I am of my people,” said Amoy, simply.</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>Now her sorrows in the tea-house were over. Mizutany,

having heard of the proposal, suddenly became kind. Surely

if Inouye, his master, wished the girl for a bride, she

should be treated with great respect.</p>
            <p>

     For three days there was no further sign from Izuma.

Then his man returned. It was a poem this time; very

beautiful, very flowery. Her eyes, her hair, her lips, her

hands, her grace, modesty, and goodness—upon these it dwelt

through all its many lines. The girl quivered.</p>
            <p>

     “Tell him,” she said, “that—here is his poem. I cannot

take it. I send it back.”</p>
            <p>

     “Amoy, you are a fool!” the girls told her. “Why don't

you marry him? We wish we had the chance. Are you betrothed

to some one in China?”</p>
            <p>

     “No; but—but I will be, some day. I can't marry of a

nation that is an enemy of mine.”</p>
            <p>

     And the third visit of Izuma's man found her still

resolute. She knew it would be the last visit.</p>
            <p>

     “Tell him—tell him I shall marry a man of my own

country. That—ah! here are his flowers again. I cannot

receive them. I return them.” And with that she turned her

back on the man. Only for a moment, however, then she

flashed around; but the man was gone, and she felt faint.

She ran like the wind after him, out of the gate and across

the little rice-field, and she called to him, brokenly, as

she ran, “No, no! I will take them! Give them to me! Tell

him—tell him—Ah-h!”</p>



                         <p rend="center">*    *    *</p>



            <p>She involuntarily started back. Izuma himself was

before her.</p>
            <p>

     “What is it?”</p>
            <p>

     “The flowers!” she gasped.</p>
            <p>

     He grew pale. The man was out of sight now. He had gone

to Izuma's house. The young man had grown nervous and

restless and could not wait there, so had come down to his

shop near the garden.</p>
            <p>

     “You return the flowers again, Amoy?” he asked,

shivering.</p>
            <p>

     “Yes—no, no, no, no, no!” she said. “I will keep them!

I want them! Oh, give them to me! I wished to wait, that was

all—to wait till the war was done! I did not wish to marry

while there was war, but—but I must keep them now—the

flowers—and—”</p>
            <p>

     “The war is over,” he said, gently. “Peace has been

declared.”</p>
            <p>

     “And the flowers?” Her voice trembled and fluttered

into appeal.</p>
            <p>

     “I will bring them next time myself, Amoy.”</p>

         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
