<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Count_Oguris_Quest">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Count Oguri`s Quest</title>
            <title type="sort">count oguri s quest</title>
            <author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
            <editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to P5 conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>Joey Takeda</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">EatCoun</idno>
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475912</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive</title>

            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Count Oguri`s Quest</title>
                  <title level="j">Smart Set 8.4 (December 1902):143-147.</title>
                  <title type="sort">count oguri s quest</title>
                  <author>Onoto Watanna [pseud. Winnifred Eaton]</author>
                  <editor>Jean Lee Cole</editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>pp. 143-147.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Ess Ess Pub. Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1902">1902</date>
                  <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVA Call Number: PS 3525 .E43 S53</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
            <p xml:id="ETC_Count_Oguris_Quest">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="1902">1902</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng" usage="1">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>fiction</term>
               <term>prose</term>
               <term>feminine</term>
               <term>Women Writers</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-01-04">Joey Takeda: Converted document from P4 (old <att>xml:id</att>=EatCoun; old filename=Count_Oguris_Quest.xml.</change>
         <change when="2008-01">Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</change>
         <change when="2007-09">Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</change>
         <change when="2005-07">John Ivor Carlson: Corrector. Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</change>
         <change when="2004-06">Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center: corrector. Added TEI header and tags.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>


   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="story">
            <head>Count Oguri's Quest<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Smart Set</hi> 8.4 (December 1902):143-147.<lb/>

By Onoto Watanna<lb/>
            </head>

            <p>Despite his course at an American college, Count Oguri
was a temperamental pariah. While he desired keenly to live
upon terms of social intimacy with many persons, and while,
not infrequently, he himself had made advances, there was
that in his manner tending to the ultimate overthrow of all
such ambitions. There was a diffidence in his mental
attitude that led, not only to an embarrassed manner, but
gave, as well, the appearance and qualities of a marplot.
Oguri had lain awake long to plan, in detail, some interview
or meeting that was to bring him the friendship of Cullen,
the full-back, or Wright, “the star debater,” and, having
settled the minutiae of proper familiarity with his
associates, had gone down to breakfast, only to ask for the
salt in a tone of voice that instantly attracted to himself
the full gaze of the tableful.</p>
            <p>
     He could not analyze the situation lucidly enough to
determine just why they stared; they themselves could not
have told, but he and they both realized that there was a
strained something in his voice to confound him and to
startle them. Then, for days, he would refrain from asking
for anything, the experience of the one occasion vitiating
the resolution of a fortnight.</p>
            <p>
     When Count Oguri had again fought himself up to the
proper pitch of pitiful daring, he would attempt the
interviews. But, at the slightest evidence in the individual
of that collective stare over the salt incident, his courage
would evaporate into mere nervous giddiness. The incident
would be reported duly by the sought-for one, and would take
its place in the archives of accusation against the good-
fellowship of Count Oguri.</p>
            <p>
     Such was the temperamental impediment of Oguri, and,
when it is added that he was a Japanese, the second element
in the dissatisfaction that Oguri aroused is stated. Friends
were kept away by his dispositional failing, as well as
because of his nationality.</p>
            <p>
     Then, too, the understanding of Count Oguri, while
easily outstripping that of his contemporaries in the taking
to itself of the principles and facts of sciences and
languages, could not admit unto itself any comprehension of
characteristic student customs.</p>
            <p>
     When a group of sophomores entered the rooms of the
“Jap Slimer,” for the purpose of imparting to his “benighted
Oriental understanding some slight compendium and
illustrated appendix of the college custom of hazing,” Oguri
could not recognize his urgent need of it.</p>
            <p>
     “My pagan friend,” said a sophomore, “you must prove
your ability as a 'Slimer,' by drinking this bottle of milk
and singing that classical ditty, 'I'm a Pea-green
Freshman.'”</p>
            <p>
     The Japanese leaped to a pair of iron dumb-bells lying
in a corner. “What you call this?” he shouted. “You call
this civilization? I call it barbarism.”</p>
            <p>
     Then, without further words, Count Oguri attacked his
enemies, swinging the iron objects with long reach, and

<pb n="144"/>

with the earnest purpose of clearing the room, or of killing
an enemy. He cleared the room.</p>
            <p>
     After that, the sophomores let him alone, giving him up
as one without a sense of humor. His classmates, however,
discerning in this act a germ of class spirit, decided
suddenly that they had misjudged the grim-featured Japanese.
They called upon him in bodies. Again Oguri was afforded an
opportunity of getting on with his fellows, but again did
the shyness and diffidence of his disposition declare
themselves his enemies. His classmates concluded that his
act of bravado was animal instinct brought to bay, and not
calculated class spirit. His own eagerly desirous
personality had remained embarrassedly in the background. No
one discerned that he wished to be a good-fellow before
everything, but could not show it.</p>
            <p>
     College life has no toleration for the man who, as a
freshman, cannot conform to its traditions, and to the
unpopularity Oguri's temperament brought was added a measure
of college displeasure. He was doubly cut off from his
fellows' inner life; nevertheless, he did not think of
leaving the college. He was bent upon becoming as American
as possible, and this early failure did not deter him from
going on with his course.</p>
            <p>
     It was observed, during his next year, that Count
Oguri, unlike many who had objected vigorously to hazing as
freshmen, took no title to his privilege of hazing in turn
those whom time had placed beneath his academic feet. In his
last two years, when upper-classman rank gave him authority
over under-classmen, he used the higher rank and its
perquisites only to protect some unhappy freshman.</p>
            <p>
     When Count Oguri, in accord with his Americanizing
intention, left the collegiate hill where four highly
fruitful, if unhappy, years had added their touch of
development, and took his bachelor apartment on Fifth
Avenue, he thought with joy that his outcast state was at an
end. Here he could make a new beginning. He would put aside
all his American past with his enemies and acquaintances—
for there was none he called friend—he would even drop the
almost repellent attitude, assumed during his last college
term, and again approach the world in a spirit of
fellowship. If no other way presented itself, his title and
wealth would open a way into a society which, though perhaps
bourgeois and sordid, must contain, almost against its will,
the one man or woman who should be that thing he had dreamed
of always, but never possessed: a friend.</p>
            <p>
     With his general cleansing of old linen and putting off
of old garments, he had decided to include his late
associates. His entrance into the new world that streamed
past his windows in carriages and automobiles, that surged
by on the sidewalks, and that stretched out in fashionable
brownstone as far as his roving eye could discern—his
entrance into this world, which, perchance, contained for
him its simple and single point of sympathy, should be due
to none of those who had misunderstood him. A way would open
itself, of that he was assured.</p>
            <p>
     A way did open itself, but in a fashion quite foreign
to the imaginings of Count Oguri. One morning, his valet
laid before him a sealed envelope, with his name inscribed
in feminine strokes. Oguri held it in doubting fingers.</p>
            <p>
     “I feel,” he told himself, “that there is something
within that packet which will have its influence upon my
future.”</p>
            <p>
     Still he toyed with it, taking delight in painting its
possibilities. Then, with a sudden movement, he tore it
open. Count Oguri was invited to send his cheque in payment
for the inclosed tickets admitting the bearer into the inner
temples of a famous hotel. The occasion was a gathering of
fashionables, whose ultimate idea was exclusiveness, though
there was a side suggestion of charity. Decidedly, wealth
and fashion had sought out Oguri.</p>
            <p>

               <pb n="145"/>

     The Count sent his cheque. There followed closely upon
this event a season when his temperamental difficulties were
overlooked by those who paid him attention. If he nervously
chattered in his idiomatic English, he was made to feel that
they thought him charming, witty. If the silence of
embarrassment came to the relief of his fluttering tongue,
he was graced with a high-caste reserve of manner. Oguri,
before whose eyes the newly-kindled fires of sycophancy
shone too brilliantly for clear sight, was momentarily
dazzled and deceived.</p>
            <p>
     “I am losing, at last, that pitiful uncertainty, that
honorable palsy which afflicted me,” he thought. “Now I am
myself; I am liked for myself.”</p>
            <p>
     He sighed with something he took to be satisfaction.
     “But have I found complete sympathy?” he inquired of
himself.</p>
            <p>
     He knew he had not. Yet these people seemed to like him
for his personal qualities; they seemed to desire his
company.</p>
            <p>
     After a dance in a two-streeted, two-named
establishment, Oguri and a young fellow, whom some recent
ingenuous “street” operation had embittered, found
themselves in the Hyphen café for a parting stimulant.</p>
            <p>
     “It's a miserable, hollow show, this seeming to enjoy
yourself,” sighed Oguri's vis-à-vis.</p>
            <p>
     The Japanese was puzzled. “What is?” he asked.
     “Oh, this social game. It's heartless and all for a
profit.” The young man spoke bitterly.</p>
            <p>
     In his partially awakened joy of life, the Japanese
felt that he could aid the other. He said:</p>
            <p>
     “No, my friend, it is not that. Take my case. Once, I
was bitter against men; I wanted to be upon good terms, but
they wouldn't understand me; now, I have lots of friends who
want nothing.”</p>
            <p>
     “Don't they, though?” The other was gulping down his
carbonic and whiskey. “You wait!”</p>
            <p>
     “Wait?”</p>
            <p>
     “Just wait a week. I've been observing your case. I see
signs of its coming due in less time than that—three days.”
     “I do not understand you. That, perhaps—” Oguri
indicated the bottle at the other's hand.</p>
            <p>
     The man became nettled.</p>
            <p>
     “Why, don't you know,” he exclaimed, “that there are
men up there”—his finger was jerked vaguely toward the
ceiling in the ballroom's direction—“who want to become
well acquainted, only in order to rob you through some fake
companies; want to swindle you out of your money? And don't
you know that there are women—?”</p>
            <p>
     “No, no, no!”</p>
            <p>
     “Why, there are plenty of women there that for your
title and money would marry—even you!”</p>
            <p>
     “Am I so repulsive then that you say, 'even me'?”
     The other looked him squarely in the eye, with the
brutality of the American who has passed through several
castes within a short time.</p>
            <p>
     “Well, you're hardly our most esteemed type of beauty,”
he drawled.</p>
            <p>
     The frankness of this man's bad manners destroyed for
Count Oguri any value his note of warning might have had. He
was only annoyed, not angry, and still less convinced of his
friends' ulterior motives.</p>
            <p>
     Yet, the time came when Oguri was again forced to
consider himself an outcast. It was after several men had
approached him for loans or investments, and a number of
women had caused the idea to penetrate his consciousness
that wealth is universally appreciated by women, and that a
dark husband does not lessen the value of a title, be the
land of that title as far away in distance and imagination
as Japan from America.</p>
            <p>
     Then the old bitterness of disposition fell darkly
about Oguri. For a time, his emotions were numbed through
its operations. As the warmth of his own inner flame thawed
him out, a light flashed across his purposes. He reasoned
thus:</p>
            <p>
     “All my life long I have sought

<pb n="146"/>

sympathy. I was ready to give it to others, but selfishly,
merely that I might in turn obtain it. I have been selfish.
I will devote myself to the study of my fellow-man. Then
shall I find sympathy and happiness.” He paused. “Ah, there
it is again,” he exclaimed. “I seek happiness selfishly,
through unselfishness! No; I shall seek an interest in
affairs that others may be happy, and, if by the way I
myself find happiness, it shall be not my motive, but my
incidental reward.”</p>
            <p>
     During the days of his social appearances, Oguri had
come in contact with a number of persons who were unselfish,
so far as the limitations of their natures permitted. They
had asked him for contributions for this or that East Side
work, or for a fund for the benefit of this or that
dependent class. They had accepted his cheques with a real
sense of gratitude, but still without any measure of
understanding or sympathy for him. They were moral examples,
but their very goodness made them too narrow to entertain
other than the merest surface feeling for one of alien race.</p>
            <p>
     His new plan of life led Count Oguri to continue his
subscriptions to their worthy activities. A young student of
sociology, in need of funds to extend his course, managed to
find him out. In this way Oguri became a benefactor. Yet he
ever remained a pariah. The influences of his past life were
too recent upon him and had made him too analytical to enjoy
his occupation. Still, with his old-time persistence, he
swung along his course, fairly kicking himself along the
path of altruism. In time, this brought him a share of
newspaper attention. “The Japanese philanthropist” was a
picturesque object for the imaginations of reporters.</p>
            <p>
     One day, as a member of the visitor's committee, he was
urged to visit the island where the waifs of a metropolis
were housed. Oguri was not eager to go, but his firm
conscience, molded out of the morbid materials thrown up by
constant introspection, would not permit him to decline. He
went.</p>
            <p>
     When Count Oguri, with the large party of his
associates, entered the foundling asylum, and saw on the
lower floor rows of tiny tables but a few inches from the
ground, with chairs about large enough for a doll, he felt a
new interest. The diminutive, the natural expression of
affection appealed to him, emotional outcast as he was, in a
way to defy his most searching analysis. Yes, he was glad he
had sometimes made a contribution that had helped a child.</p>
            <p>
     On the floor above, the entire party was admitted to a
ward in which were the youngest foundlings, though none in
the place was more than two years old. Nurses were few. On
the floor a number of the larger infants were at feeble
play. There were a few faded playthings, the common property
of this poor childhood.</p>
            <p>
     The entrance of the visiting party set the ward into
instant commotion. From healthy, young, and weak throats, at
once went up a wail. There was a pause of irresolution upon
the part of the invaders. A little girl, standing still in
the center of the room, dropped her faded rag doll, and
stared about her with perfect self-possession. Then, while
the visitors stood motionless, she walked directly, if
unsteadily, to Count Oguri. At his knees, she paused; her
hand reached up to him; her lips made a sound of kissing.</p>
            <p>
     “I lub you,” she said.</p>
            <p>
     Oguri, dumb and amazed, stared at her. The nurse
hurried forward.</p>
            <p>
     “She's quite a noticing child,” the woman said; “she
picked you out because you're so dark and foreign-looking.”</p>
            <p>
     “Oh,” said Oguri, as he turned coldly away.</p>
            <p>
     The visiting party's stay was brief, but, during its
continuance, the little girl kept her eyes riveted on Oguri.
Only the nurse's attention kept her away from the Japanese.</p>
            <p>
     The party left the ward through the winding corridor,
Oguri in the rear.

<pb n="147"/>

Just before a turn hid him from the child's view, Oguri
looked back.</p>
            <p>
     The little girl had followed him to the door, beyond
whose limits the discipline of the place had taught her not
to go.</p>
            <p>
     A childish foot struck the floor with childish
insistence.</p>
            <p>
     “Tum back,” a childish voice called, passionately, as
the little girl pointed insistently to her faded rag doll.</p>
            <p>
     It was an appeal straight to the heart of Oguri. It
reached him. With quick strides, he went back. The child was
in his arms. Within him, all the bitterness of the past
melted in the tears that streamed down his face.</p>
            <p>
     “I lub you,” whispered a little voice.</p>
            <p>
     Here, at last, was the sympathy, the love he had
sought. It had come to him; it was his forever.</p>
            <p>
     With the child in his arms, the Japanese turned to the
laughing group that had come back to see the issue.</p>
            <p>
     “What are you going to do with the child, Count?” asked
a woman.</p>
            <p>
     “Adopt her. She is mine for this world and the next,”
he said, solemnly.</p>
            <p>
     Three days later, the Japanese consul was called upon
to arrange that Count Oguri might return to his native
Nippon with his little heiress, and the matter was finally
settled.</p>
            <p>
     “What, before all the gods, Count Oguri, are you to do
with an American child over there?” asked the mystified
consul at the railroad station.</p>
            <p>
     Oguri eased the little girl's position in his arms,
before he answered. Then:</p>
            <p>
     “To teach her two things—without which all are
destitute in body, and outcasts in soul—sympathy and love.”</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
