<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Daughter of Two Lands</title>
            <title type="sort">daughter of two lands</title>
            <author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
            <editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">EatDaug</idno>
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475913</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive</title>

            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>
               <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Daughter of Two Lands</title>
                  <title level="j">Red Book Magazine 14.1 (November 1909): 33-48.</title>
                  <title type="sort">daughter of two lands</title>
                  <author>Onoto Watanna [pseud. Winnifred Eaton]</author>
                  <editor>Jean Lee Cole</editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Illustrator</resp>
                     <name>W.H.D. Koerner</name>
                  </respStmt>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>pp. 33-48</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Redbook Pub. Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1909">1909</date>
                  <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: OCLC: 21175639</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the
preceding line.</p>
            <p xml:id="ETC_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical
groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="1902">1902</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng" usage="1">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>fiction</term>
               <term>prose</term>
               <term>feminine</term>
               <term>Women Writers</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-01-04">Joey Takeda: Converted document from P4 (old <att>xml:id</att>=EatDaug; old filename=Daughter_of_Two_Lands.xml.</change>
         <change when="2008-01">Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</change>
         <change when="2007-09">Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</change>
         <change when="2005-07">John Ivor Carlson: Corrector. Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</change>
         <change when="2004-06">Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center: corrector. Added TEI header and tags.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="story">
            <head>Daughter of Two Lands<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Red Book Magazine</hi> 14.1 (November 1909): 33-48.<lb/>
By Onoto Watanna<lb/>
Illustrated by W.H.D. Koerner
</head>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>I.</head>

               <p>It seemed more like a smart tea or reception than an
auction sale. Society women, gorgeously gowned, chatted
eagerly with each other, or pushed their way to the front.
Their eyes were bright and keen, their faces flushed with
that eager expression which games of chance always bring to
the features of American women, giving them a curiously
sexless look, and, in a moment, robbing them of all their
vaunted beauty.</p>
               <p>
  Knowing well the nature of his customers, the auctioneer
had chosen a fitting place for his wares, and the latter
were spread out with sumptuous taste. Such a collection was
indeed unlikely to be offered again within the span of a
life-time. The Chinese treasures had been gathered by an
American diplomat during a few years' sojourn in the Orient.
One object of art or archaic treasure after another was
sold; a fortune was already piled up for the late owner of
the treasure.</p>
               <p>
  “I'm just played out—and broke!” breathlessly confessed a
flossy-haired little matron, who was arrayed in fleecy
finery suitable for a fête. She tapped off on her fingers
the various articles she had acquired, gloatingly triumphing
over having obtained this or that bit of bronze or
porcelain.</p>
               <p>“What did you get, Mr. Carruthers?”</p>

               <pb n="34"/>

               <p>A half-whimsical smile flickered around the lips of the
cadaverous gentleman, whose own private collections were
famous. His wife giggled with half-chiding pride in her
husband's attainments.</p>
               <p>
  “He paid five hundred dollars for one of Buddha's best
back teeth,” she said flippantly.</p>
               <p>“Nonsense,” protested the man.</p>
               <p>
  “It's a fact,” insisted the woman shrilly, her high nasal
voice curiously unpleasant, “and anyhow if it wasn't that
exactly, it was something equally as silly—a temple relic
of some obscure sort.”</p>
               <p>
  “What I'd like to know,” chipped in a third woman of the
party, a good-looking young individual of the “horsey” type,
“is this: Granted that the Wardwells were the particularly
cherished pets of many high officials in China, and
therefore—er—came naturally by—well—some of this, how on
earth, will you tell me, did they acquire temple treasures,
archaeological specimens, and—what not? I always thought
the Chinese held such things so sacred that not even the
priests—or the Emperors for that matter—could either give
them away or sell them. How came the formidable 'foreign
devils' by such treasure, my friends?”</p>
               <p>
  The blonde-haired lady had finished her calculations and
snapped closed her note book.</p>
               <p>
  “Those are questions, my dear,” said she, smilingly, “for
the 'heathen chinee' to ask—not us.”</p>
               <p>
  The girl who sat beside her leaned suddenly forward. She
had bought nothing and had sat throughout the sale with her
hands clasped spasmodically in her muff, her eyes down-
drooped, as though she dared not raise them. Her voice
trembled slightly.</p>
               <p>
  “I always thought,” she said—and there was the least
foreign lisp in her speech—“that the receivers of stolen
goods were as culpable as—the thieves.”</p>
               <p>
  “Tut, tut,” exclaimed Mrs. Fanton—she of the flossy hair.
“What did you buy, my dear?”</p>
               <p>“Nothing, at all.”</p>
               <p>“No?”</p>
               <p>
  Mrs. Fanton looked at her sharply, and even the renowned
collector regarded her with some anxiety.</p>
               <p>
  “You don't think them spurious, do you?” asked his wife in
a tone of dismay.</p>
               <p>
  There was a moment of anxious silence before the

<pb n="35"/>

girl answered. She raised a pair of intensely dark eyes.</p>
               <p>
  “No—they are the real thing,” she said, and then, almost
whispering: “That's why I could not—would not—have them.”</p>
               <p>
  “Silly child!” exclaimed Mrs. Fanton, in a tone of relief.
“You, a little half-Jap, disdaining rare treasures like
these. Listen to her, Lieutenant Burrows—do!”</p>
               <p>
  The latter had been standing behind the girl's chair
throughout the afternoon, though they had scarcely spoken.
He had brought her to this sale of oriental loot, and had
watched her with mixed feelings, as she sat throughout it
with averted face, all her brightness gone—shocked out of
her.</p>
               <p>
  “I suppose,” went on Mrs. Fanton, with a side glance at
the girl that was half caressing, half cattish, “that
Sakura, as a Japanese, simply wants to show her contempt for
mere Chinese art—eh?”</p>
               <p>
  “Believe that, if you wish,” said the girl, rising
suddenly, “and—good-bye, Mrs. Fanton.”</p>
               <p>
  “Going? Good-bye, dear.” And she turned to whisper the
girl's history to her companions before she was barely out
of sight.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>II.</head>

               <p>Walking swiftly down Fifth Avenue, scarcely conscious of
her companion, Sakura's tumultuous heart beat rebelliously.
She turned quickly at the half-soothing, half-humorous tone
of Burrows.</p>
               <p>“Well—I didn't do it, you know,” he protested.</p>
               <p>
  “No—not you!” she said passionately, “but—your
countrymen. Oh, to think,” she cried, “of the brazenness of
it all! The open, bragging, public display!”</p>
               <p>
  “Most of it was loot,” admitted the Lieutenant, “but then,
the Wardwells were no worse than others, though of course it
was too bad in an ambassador. You should have seen the
French and German and English people licking up the stuff.
You should have been in China at the Boxer period. That was
the time of plenty, I can tell you. Got a thing or two
myself for that matter.” Fishing into a vest pocket he
brought up a single mandarin stone, a thing of beauty, pink,
glossy, and quite as large as a walnut.</p>
               <p>
  “Want it?” he asked, noting, with unconcealed admiration,
the color mantling the girl's cheeks.</p>
               <p>
  “Want it!” she cried impulsively, taking the stone, and
looking at it with wide eyes. “Yes—for that purpose!” And
she threw it into the gutter, as if it were something
unclean.</p>
               <p>The young man's face fell.</p>
               <p>
  ““Well, I didn't steal it,” said he ruefully. “I bought it
from one of my men who—”</p>
               <p>“Stole it for you,” she finished bitterly.</p>
               <p>
  They walked on in silence for some time. She spoke at
last,<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> tremulously, the sound of tears in her voice.</p>
               <p>“Tony, I'm sorry I threw away your—your stone,” she said.</p>
               <p>
  “Don't say that,” he begged, almost pleadingly, “I can't
bear to have you speak to me like that. You can throw away
anything of mine you want—even my—heart!”
  She shook her head wearily. The color had died down from
her face, leaving it pale and wistful. All the passionate
indignation which had throbbed within her was stilled now.
She was not thinking of a country's wrongs, but hearing and
seeing only her young American lover. He was there vividly
before her, big, strong, so good to look at.</p>
               <p>
  “Don't you know what I mean?” he urged in his insistent
way. “I've told you often enough.”</p>
               <p>
  “I do know what you mean,” she answered softly, “but I
wouldn't throw away your heart, Tony.”</p>
               <p>
  “You'd keep it?” he demanded eagerly, pressing, close to
her, unmindful that they were on the street.</p>
               <p>
  “No,” she said, “I couldn't even—take it, Tony.”
  “Why?” he demanded, hoarsely.</p>
               <p>
  They were before her house now, and she stood with one
little hand pressed against the great stone colonial pillar.
  “Because of such things as this afternoon—that sale, and
all that it meant,” she said.</p>
               <p>“How does it concern me?” he pleaded.</p>
               <p>
  “Don't you see? You are American, and I—why, I am half
Japanese—Eurasian. I've lived here—in my mother's home
most of my life, but I know, deep in my heart, I am more
Japanese than anything else.”</p>
               <p>
  “If you could see yourself now—as I see you—you wouldn't
say it. Why you are as Western as I am,” he protested.</p>
               <p>

                  <pb n="38"/>

  “In my dress, perhaps. In my looks even, to a degree; but
not in my heart! Ah, don't you see how everything about me
yearns over the Orient when anything really vital touches
it? Sometimes when people speak slightingly of the Japanese
or Chinese I want to run away—to flee far, far away from
them, because of the terrible hatred that surges in me! How
could I marry an American, feeling as I do?”</p>
               <p>“I'm an individual. Marry me as such, Sakura-san.”</p>
               <p>
  “Why, Tony, you are a soldier, more American indeed than a
mere citizen, because you are one of your country's
appointed defenders.”</p>
               <p>
  Their eyes met, hers piteous, his with an honest appeal in
them she could not have long resisted.</p>
               <p>“That's the answer then,” he said, bravely.</p>
               <p>“Yes—”</p>
               <p>
  Her hand came timidly from her muff, and touched his just
for a second. Then she fled up the steps. At the top she
turned and saw him, still waiting there below.</p>
               <p>
  “Ah,” she breathed, “maybe—at another time. But not—to-
day!”</p>
               <note xml:id="n1_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> 
                  <p>“at least tremulously” in original.</p>
               </note>
            </div>

            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>III.</head>

               <p>“Of what are you thinking, Sakura?” asked her aunt. “Your
face looks positively tragic.”</p>
               <p>The girl sat up with a slight shiver.</p>
               <p>
  “Oh,” she said, with that curious directness which some of
her acquaintances found so quaint and attractive and others
so disconcerting, “I was thinking about Japan—and my
childhood there. Do you know, Aunt Margaret, I think, to the
expatriate, the land of his birth must always be rose-
colored in his dreams.”</p>
               <p>
  “I insist,” said her aunt, stiffly, “that you are not an
expatriate in any sense of the word. It is absurd to
consider yourself anything but American.”</p>
               <p>
  The girl's long dark eyes narrowed slightly, but she
ignored her aunt's assertion, and continued dreamily.</p>
               <p>
  “To me, Japan looms dimly in my mind as a sort of
fairyland of happiness—all flowers and smiles! It is when
people are wronging Japan, I know how deeply I love her!”</p>
               <p>
  “The memories of childhood are always gilded,” said her
aunt, tartly.</p>
               <p>
  “Yes,” said Sakura eagerly, “they are gilded—our memories
of childhood, and isn't it good they are? Oh, it's the one
really beautiful, innocent part of our lives that we can
always look back upon without the least shadow of regret—
isn't it, dear Aunt Margaret?”</p>
               <p>
  “Your present period of life is happy—innocent, is it
not, Sakura?”</p>
               <p>
  “I don't know! I don't know!” cried the girl, restlessly
clasping and unclasping her hands, the vague sound of tears
in her voice. “Sometimes such—such terrible emotions come
over me. I want to hurt—to injure people!”</p>
               <p>
  “Now, Sakura, I know exactly what is troubling you. You
are reading all that rubbish in the papers about the
possibility of war with Japan. Even if it does come, you
have nothing to fear!”</p>
               <p>
  “Fear!” She turned bodily around in her seat, her eyes
wide, blazing at her aunt. “You think me capable of—”</p>
               <p>
  “Why not? I would be if I were of your nationality. But as
I said, you have nothing to fear, because no one here
regards you as Japanese, and if you will only listen to
Lieutenant—”</p>
               <p>The girl came quickly to her feet.</p>
               <p>“D-don't speak of him, even. Don't! I cannot even—now!”</p>
               <p>
  She began pulling on her gloves, as if about to make her
departure. There was a flush of fever in her cheeks. Her
eyes were unnaturally bright. In the restlessness of her
mood she had come to her aunt's house to see her younger
cousins, and found her aunt home alone.</p>
               <p>
  “If you take my advice,” said the older lady, with rough
kindliness in her tone, “you will do away with all this
Japanese hysteria. Your duty is to the man you love, first
of all!”</p>
               <p>
  “Is it, though?” asked the girl in a suffocating voice.
“Is it? In my father's country we turn instinctively first
to the authors of our being. They should come first, by
every natural law, and yet—and yet. Oh! how account for
this treacherous impulse in us that makes us desert—betray-
-our parent for the stranger whom we love!”</p>
               <p>
  “Desert! Betray! You are impossible, Sakura! In what way,
pray, will you betray your father in marrying Lieutenant
Burrows?”</p>
               <p>

                  <pb n="40"/>

  “Father does not wish it. He has made—other plans for
me,” she said, piteously.</p>
               <p>
  “And you, raised and bred as you have been in this
twentieth-century, enlightened, civilized country, would
submit to a low and degrading oriental arrangement of that
sort? Do you wish me to believe that?”</p>
               <p>
  “No, no!” cried the girl wildly. “That is not what I
meant, but in refusing my father's wishes, can I—dare I do
the other thing?”</p>
               <p>“Why not? Did he not himself dare likewise—once?”</p>
               <p>Sakura turned pearly white.</p>
               <p>
  “My mother!” she said faintly, and covered her face with
her little shaking hands.</p>
               <p>
  Her aunt put an affectionate arm about her, but she still
spoke severely.</p>
               <p>
  “Yes, your mother, dear. He married her in spite of the
disapproval of all her own and his family. And he took her
to his home. What a martyrdom!”</p>
               <p>
  The girl shook her head mutely, but her aunt continued
inexorab1y.</p>
               <p>
  “It was, indeed. Why, no American girl can realize what it
is to marry a Japanese of title and be taken back to his
antagonistic relatives—for they always are antagonistic
beneath their surface of insincere smiles. Your mother's
case is a distinct example.”</p>
               <p>
  “My honorable grandparents loved my mother,” Sakura said,
in a passionate voice that trembled with her effort to
control it. “They tried to—to be kind to her. They simply
did not understand, nor did she. How could they? But I—I
understand, Aunt Margaret, for I am of both countries—
daughter of both lands!”</p>
               <p>
  “It was an unfortunate situation all around,” said her
aunt. “From the first her parents and I predicted what would
happen. There she was, a spoiled, proud American girl,
thrust down in the midst of a family whose whole thought and
life were centered in an ancient oriental civilization. Why,
she never even stepped into the streets, or drove abroad in
her palanquin, or whatever they call it, but a dozen
officious relatives dogged her footsteps. They expected her
to become as they were, because, forsooth, she was a woman,
and therefore should adopt her husband's mode of life. She
wore their dress, ate their food, though it nauseated, and
then—then—why your Japanese grandmother actually

<pb n="42"/>

suggested that she blacken her teeth in signal that she was
married, that youth was behind her, and her aim should be to
repel, not attract, other men who might see her!”</p>
               <p>
  “She was very—old my grandmother!” said Sakura softly,
“and she was of the ancient school, Aunt Margaret. But she
was good, good! How can I tell you how good she was? You do
not want to know—you would not believe if I told you. And
yet—sometimes, I close my eyes, and I feel the touch of her
withered old fingers about my face again. She is stroking my
cheek—oh, so softly, so sweetly; and now she is twisting my
hair—it always distressed her because it curled so
rebelliously about my face, as a child—and trying to
confine it in the conventional topknot, and mother would
pull it down when she saw me, and grandmother would roll it
up again, patiently and persistently. I never understood—
then, but now—”</p>
               <p>
  “Your mother was distinctly in the right,” said her aunt,
stiffly. “When she left your grandmother's home, how could
she know that in Japan that would be regarded as a scandal?
Her husband accompanied her. What absurd rule was that which
made a wife take up her residence in the house of her
husband's parents? No free-born girl of the slightest spirit
could have endured it.”</p>
               <p>
  “Yet—I think my mother was happier in my grandparents'
shiro<ref target="n2">[2]</ref> than in the new house, Aunt Margaret.”</p>
               <p>
  “That was because your father and his relatives made her
feel as if she were a criminal. I think the only reason your
father finally brought her back to America was because he
realized that her presence in Japan could only bring pain
and havoc in his parents' household.”</p>
               <p>Sakura went quickly to her father's defense.</p>
               <p>
  “No, you wrong him, Aunt Margaret. He brought her back
because she was unhappy, and he stayed here throughout all
these years, when I know he longed to return to Japan. When
mother died, he seemed to take it so for granted that I
would return with him, and I think that was the cruelest
blow of all—that I should fail him—when he needed me
most!”</p>
               <p>
  “When it came to a flat choice between Japan and America,”
said her aunt didactically, “you naturally chose America.”</p>
               <p>

                  <pb n="43"/>

  “It wasn't that,” cried the girl, sharply. A scarlet stain
rose to her cheeks and brow, tingeing her neck, even. “Aunt
Margaret,” she said, “I—I—had met—Tony!”</p>

               <note xml:id="n2_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> 
                  <p>shiro: castle.</p>
               </note>
            </div>

            <div type="section" n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>

               <p>A few days later she was sitting at her desk, writing to
him. She wanted to see him—badly. Then her maid brought in
a letter from her father, and her hands fell limply upon the
sheet before her.</p>
               <p>
  Her hair hung in a glossy, dusky cloud about her. A
dressing gown, all silken and lace, a feminine, exquisite
thing, fell about her in long, loose folds as she stood up
slowly. For a moment her glance, almost unconsciously,
wandered about her room, the delicately tinted, faintly
perfumed chamber of an American girl of refinement and
wealth. The dressing table with its pieces of chaste ivory,
the chintz-covered chairs, the soft white mull curtains,
topped with the colonial ruffle of the same chintz; and the
flowered ceiling, the old rose-covered<ref target="n3">[3]</ref> rugs, the long
cheval glass—all part of the life to which she had thought,
but a moment since, she purely belonged.</p>
               <p>
  She read her father's letter through slowly, studiously,
her face becoming fixed and stern. Suddenly she reached
over, and catching up the sheets of that other letter she
had been writing, deliberately tore them across. The clear-
eyed, winning face of Lieutenant Burrows looked up at her
insistently from the photograph on her desk. She turned it
over. Then, as though something snapped within her, she ran
to the window seat, slipped to her knees, and hid her face.</p>
               <p>
  The stars came out in the dark vault of heaven. Night was
beautiful, even in this city of monstrosities. Below, in the
darkly glistening street, the flaming eyes of countless
automobiles went glimmering by. The distant clang of the
street cars, the grumbling roar of the great city floated up
to the girl as she crouched there by the window. What
menacing, engulfing tones they seemed to her! Like those of
a monstrous enemy, closing in about, as if to throttle a
frailer adversary.</p>
               <p>
  Presently her weakness passed. Tossing back her head
bravely, she gathered up the great mass of hair into her
hands, coiling it securely against her neck. She dressed
quickly and without ringing for her maid's

<pb n="44"/>

assistance. Nor did the latter accompany her, as, slipping
into a taxicab, she gave to the driver the address of the
Japanese consul.</p>
               <p>
  She did not falter once in the task her father had set
her. She was buoyed up chiefly by the many accounts of the
Japanese subjects in San Francisco, at this time appearing
daily in the American papers. Half-American herself, though
she was motherless, she exaggerated the importance of even
the most insignificant of these incidents, and when the
papers loudly proclaimed the probability of war, she firmly
believed it. At an age when a girl's head is full of
transient ideals—false or otherwise—Sakura greedily read
and learned all she could of other women before her who had
served their countries, as she wished to serve hers, and,
indeed, as her father had ordered her to do.</p>
               <p>
  She was now pure Japanese. All thought of self, of
friends, of relatives even, for she had many here in America-
-must be put aside. And love! Duty was the greatest word in
the language of her ancestors. Every thought now must be
concentrated upon the accomplishment of one purpose only.</p>
               <p>
  Thus, she sought her friends and relatives only when she
needed to make use of them, and with her eyes wide open, she
accepted the invitation to visit at the home of her lover's
parents, and traveled down to Washington.</p>
               <p>
  There, in the house of a cabinet officer, the father of
the man who loved her, she learned all she had set herself
to learn, and with copies of plans and maps of certain
American forts and points of weaknesses, she suddenly cut
short her visit—and disappeared.</p>
               <p>
  Lieutenant Burrows was stationed at F——— when a letter
from home apprised him of the visit of the Countess Sakura
Sano. Impetuously he cursed his luck. She, it seems, so
wrote his mother, had unexpectedly accepted possibly the
fiftieth invitation they had tendered her. There was no end
to the teas, and parties, and what not, given in her honor,
and, as his mother lovingly wrote, she had endeared herself
to both his father and herself. Of course the Lieutenant
instantly applied for leave of absence, and after an
unnecessary amount of red-taped delay, obtained it; but the
day before he reached Washington the prized guest had

<pb n="46"/>

unexpectedly been called away. He followed her to New York,
presuming she had returned to her home. There he found the
house closed. Inquiry among her relatives revealed the fact
that every one believed she had gone to a different place!</p>

               <note xml:id="n3_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> 
                  <p>“old-rose covered” in original.</p>
               </note>
            </div>

            <div type="section" n="5">
               <head>V.</head>

               <p>On a morning in the month of May, Sakura Sano crept out on
deck, and saw the first shadowy outlines of the land of her
birth. She had been ill, with a dull heavy fever of the
brain. The unnatural strain and excitement which had buoyed
her up for months had suddenly snapped, and nervous break-
down had ensued.</p>
               <p>
  For many days she had lain in her cabin, staring wide-eyed
at the patch of sky and water which swirled tempestuously by
her. Her maid, a devoted Frenchwoman, who petted and
mothered her as if she were a baby, tried to arouse her from
the lethargy into which she seemed to have fallen, but
vainly. Events of the past few months revolved and revolved
through the girl's tired mind. Far away now from America—
ah, farther every day!—slowly all she had suffered there
was being forgotten, minimized, obliterated.</p>
               <p>
  At first she had thought with triumph of the success she
had achieved, of the wit of the Oriental, as persistently
she called herself, which had outmatched that of the
cleverest of American statesmen. Oh! How vainly had they
breathed their contempt for insignificant little Japan. But
they would see! She would show them—aye, point out to Japan
all their colossal weaknesses. Like the giant in the
scientific jiujitsu<ref target="n4">[4]</ref>, whose very bulk and strength
constituted his chief frailty, to the agile-footed, dwarfed
opponent, so would America be pricked by the despised pigmy
in the very heart of her strength.</p>
               <p>
  Thus the fevered thoughts seethed unceasingly through her
tangled mind. Then came a period when she would think of
individuals—men, women, girls she had known and lived among
in America. She would recall this and that incident of the
past, and lie there smiling over old, dear memories.</p>
               <p>
  So, at last, she came to think of Anthony Burrows! She
could remain there no longer, still and quiet. Like some
imprisoned creature, she paced her little cabin,

<pb n="47"/>

daring not to show her face outside the room; scarcely
daring to look at herself, because the wild-eyed, pale-faced
girl who stared back at her from the mirror seemed to accuse
her of some secret guilt.</p>
               <p>
  And now at last, in sight of the home of her dreams,
rather than her memory, Sakura stood and gazed. Ah, surely
not alone to those who have been born under its blessed
shadow, Fuji-yama's enchanting beauty holds one in
enraptured thrall! There, in the purple air, enshrouded like
a goddess of purity, in fleecy clouds of white, the peerless
cone stood revealed in all its golden glory. She felt, as
she gazed, justified, forgiven, purged of what had lain as
heavy on her soul as crime.</p>
               <p>
  “For you!” she whispered, breathless. “Oh, my beloved home-
-for you I have done it!”</p>

               <note xml:id="n4_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> 
                  <p>jiujitsu: a form of Japanese martial arts.</p>
               </note>
            </div>

            <div type="section" n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>

               <p>Boys were selling newspapers in the streets, sheets no
larger than a piece of American note paper. The Countess
Sano, driving abroad in her lacquer jinrikisha<ref target="n5">[5]</ref>, stopped her
carriage boy to buy such a paper. As she looked at it, she
turned pale and crushed the sheet viciously in her hand.</p>
               <p>
  “Let me see it,” commanded her father, who was with her,
and, as she released the crumpled paper to him, he laughed
at the hideous picture upon it—a caricature of the American
President.</p>
               <p>
  “Well,” inquired the Count, good-humoredly, “what do you
think of this work of art?”</p>
               <p>“It is vile!” she declared in a strangled voice.</p>
               <p>
  Several days later, at her father's house, she heard the
arrival of the Japanese men of power to whom she was to
reveal her secret. Now, in the guest room, ceremoniously
welcomed by her father, they were waiting for her—Sakura.
How much did they know? she asked her beating heart. What
had her father told them? And then she experienced an
uplifting sense of strange relief in the knowledge that he
could have told no more than he knew. Always she had put off
the day of revelation, saying that it would be time enough
when the information should be actually needed. Now!</p>
               <p>
  The sudden sliding of a door startled her. Only a maid,
prying. “Okusama<ref target="n6">[6]</ref>'s honorable service? What could the humble
one do to oblige her excellency?</p>
               <p>

                  <pb n="48"/>

  “Nothing! I—I—want nothing, maidens.”</p>
               <p>
  To the great, empty chamber again, to pace back and forth,
back and forth. Not a single article of furniture was there
in the room, just that clear, clean expanse of exquisitely
matted floor and paneled sliding walls; as, in the homes of
the rich and cultured Japanese, works of art in themselves.
Once she had thought ardently of possessing such a home
again; now the thought filled her with a sense of
desolation. There came to her mind vividly, as though she
still were in it, a picture of that room of hers in far-away
America—America which she was never again to see!</p>
               <p>
  A fit of shivering seized her. She looked about her
wildly, as if desperately in search of something.</p>
               <p>“Betray America!—her dear dead mother's home!”</p>
               <p>
  She crouched down by the great trunk which had come across
the seas with her from that far-off land. It was the only
article in the room not purely Japanese. Her hands
trembling, she unlocked the trunk and opened it. Then she
searched for the papers and plans they were waiting for
below in the ozashiki<ref target="n7">[7]</ref>. How they creaked under her touch—
these crackling, treacherous papers! She glanced backward,
across her shoulder, furtively, fearfully, like a thief
about to steal; and as she looked, the Frenchwoman who loved
and served her, pushed the sliding doors softly open, and
she saw Anthony Burrows standing there, looking gravely down
at her.</p>
               <p>
  So white was her face, her expression so agonized and
tragic that for a moment he stared at her in amazement. Then
he crossed swiftly to her.</p>
               <p>
  She began to plead with him wildly, her little hands
clasped frantically about the papers.</p>
               <p>
  “Oh—if you truly love me—you will understand and forgive
me. I cannot do it—I cannot do it! D-don't you see why? I—
I—am as much—I belong to you! It is here I am an alien—”</p>
               <p>
  She was wrenching the papers apart, tearing them into tiny
pieces.</p>
               <p>
  When she had finished, she looked up at him, mutely
regarding her. Then, while below the men of power still
waited, she fluttered into his sheltering arms, like one
broken and exhausted.</p>
               <note xml:id="n5_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> 
                  <p>jinrikisha: carriage pulled by a human runner.</p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="n6_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> 
                  <p>okusama: wife; incorrect romanization of oku-san.</p>
               </note>
               <note xml:id="n7_Daughter_of_Two_Lands">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> 
                  <p>ozashiki: inner parlor; incorrect romanization of okuzashiki.</p>
               </note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
