<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Honorable_Movie_Takee_Sojin">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Honorable Movie Takee Sojin</title>
            <title type="sort">honorable movie takee sojin</title>
            <author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
            <editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <name>Reeve, Winifred, 1879-1954</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to P5 conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>Joey Takeda</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">EatSoji</idno>
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475938</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive</title>

            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Honorable Movie Takee Sojin</title>
                  <title level="j">Motion Picture Classic(March 1928)</title>
                  <title type="sort">honorable movie takee sojin</title>
                  <author>Winifred Reeve</author>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp/>
                     <name>Onoto Watanna [pseud. Winnifred Eaton]</name>
                  </respStmt>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>pp. 37, 72.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Brewster Publications</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Brooklyn, NY</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1928">1928</date>
                  <idno type="callNo">EatSoji</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>[Notes about the original source]</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
            <p xml:id="ETC_Honorable_Movie_Takee_Sojin">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="1928">1928</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng" usage="1">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>nonfiction</term>
               <term>prose</term>
               <term>feminine</term>
               <term>Women Writers</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-01-04">Joey Takeda: Converted document from P4 (old <att>xml:id</att>=EatSoji; old filename=Honorable_Movie_Takee_Sojin.xml.</change>
         <change when="2008-01">Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</change>
         <change when="2007-09">Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</change>
         <change when="2005-07">John Ivor Carlson: Corrector. Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</change>
         <change when="2004-07">Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center: corrector. Added TEI header and tags.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>




   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="article">
            <head>Honorable Movie Takee Sojin. <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Motion Picture Classic</hi> (March 1928) <lb/>
Onoto Watanna (Winifred Reeve)</head>
            <p/>
            <div type="section">
               <p>“Please to welcome to my house!”</p>
               <p>
     The words and the voice, with its fascinating accent,
took me back, in thought at least, to a country far across
the sea. I should have been entering a little house with a
deep blue or pink roof, with sliding walls of paper shoji,
wide spaces of shining matting, soft tatamis on which to
kneel. My hostess would be serving me tea in a tiny
handleless cup, and perhaps there would be a sweetmeat or
fruit on my plate, perhaps a little omelet formed in the
shape of a blossom. We would sit on the floor and sip our
tea and discuss the flower decoration in the slender vase or
the history of the kakemona scroll in the Tokonoma (Place of
Honor).</p>
               <p>
     But no! I was not in Japan. I was entering a very
ordinary little American house. At the door, smiling and
bowing, were Mr. And Mrs. Sojin Kamiyama.<ref target="n1">[1]</ref>
               </p>
               <note xml:id="n1_Honorable_Movie_Takee_Sojin">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> 
                  <p>“Kamijama” in original. Later, the name is spelled
“Kamijami.”</p>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Doug Grabbed Him</head>

               <p>All the world that goes to the movies has seen Sojin;
for since Douglas Fairbanks “discovered” the Japanese actor
and engaged him to play the Mongolian Prince in “The Thief
of Bagdad,” Sojin has supported the most prominent of the
stars. He will be recalled as the toothless Jewish jeweler
in “The Wanderer,” as the dapper, wise-cracking Americanized
Chinaman in “The Road to Mandalay,” as the coolie in “The
Sea Beast,” the Caliph in “The Lady of the Harem.” He was in
“Eve's Leaves,” had a prominent part in “The Bat,” and stole
the picture in “The Chinese Parrot.” He was in “East of
Suez,” “Proud Flesh” and numerous other well-known
productions.</p>
               <p>
     I had never been sure of Sojin's nationality. Now that
I had a “close-up,” as they say in pictures, of the man, I
still wondered. Then he told me he was born in Sendai, near
Matsushima Bay. Came enlightenment. Twenty-five hundred
years ago there was a Mongol invasion in that part of Japan.
An ancient memorial stone still proclaims the feat of the
Mongols. Though they perished, they left their imprint and
stamp upon the faces of the inhabitants of that region.
Sojin might be a Tartar or Mongol. He is above the average
height, has large eyes, a high nose and a sensitive mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Famous Across the Sea</head>

               <p>To start the conversation, I remarked that I had heard
of his fame as an actor and producer in Japan. Sojin looked
alarmed, glanced at his wife, made a deprecating motion and
assured me his fame was “very little.” Then something
unusual in a Japanese household occurred. Mrs. Sojin
contradicted her husband, something no obedient wife would
ever dare to do in Japan.</p>
               <p>
     “Ah! Is ver' greatest fame at Japan,” she said.</p>
               <p>
     Sojin looked disturbed and uncomfortable.</p>
               <p>
     “Excuse,” he said, and then added swiftly, no doubt to
placate his wife: “I speak not very kind English. My wife
speak very good.”</p>
               <p>
     I asked him whether in Japan he had produced the old
classical dramas.</p>
               <p>
     “Only at beginning of career. I am of very modern
school, madame,” he explained.</p>

               <pb n="72"/>

               <p>His wife put in eagerly: “My husband first pioneer in
new drama movement—Little theater, you understand. He make
first production in Shakespeare, Ibsen, Sudermann, Goethe—
many other—one hundred other!”</p>
               <p>
     I tried to imagine a Japanese audience watching a
performance of “The Doll's House,” The Master Builder,”
“Hedda Gabler,” “The Merchant of Venice,” “Hamlet,”
“Othello,” “Anthony and Cleopatra,” “Faust,” and the
Russian, German, and French plays, all of which were
included in Sojin's repertory.</p>
               <p>
     “Were these European plays successful?”</p>
               <p>
     “Very so,” said Sojin. Again Mrs. Sojin interposed,
eagerly: “Always plenty people come to theater. High class
people—intelligentsia—artist, writer, student, scholar.
All very hungry see my husband in European drama.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>He Knew His Foreigners</head>

               <p>Sojin here explained the really monumental task
achieved in studying and producing these plays in Japan.
There would be foreign companies touring there, and playing
in the chief cities. He would go to every performance,
intensively study the plays and the style of the acting. He
was, moreover, a pupil of Professor Tsubuchi, at Waseda
University, the scholar who translated into Japanese not
only Shakespeare, but Ibsen and the Russian, German, and
French classics.</p>
               <p>
     Sojin explained that he produced some of these plays as
Japanese. That is to say, he would transpose the originals
and adapt them so that the scene was Japan and the
characters Japanese. Thus Hamlet became Prince Hamura
Tashimura, son of the reigning Daimyo (Lord or Prince) of a
great feudal Province. Othello was a new-rich Prince, of
Pariah ancestry, as he was descended from the despised Eta
race. Desdemona was a Princess of high Patrician blood.
“King Lear” was a favorite with the Japanese. Sojin was
inclined to think that the plays of Shakespeare bore a
resemblance to many of the old Japanese classics.</p>
               <p>
     The stage is a subject near to the heart of Sojin, but
I presently brought the subject around to motion pictures.</p>
               <p>
     “Are the movies popular in Japan? Do the Japanese like
American pictures?”</p>
               <p>
     Sojin is slow at replying. He weighs a question and
sorts out his words. Then he answers with something of a
flash as if the answer had just occurred to him.</p>
               <p>
     “Ah! How like movie at Japan? Very much same as
American first like chop suey. You understand?”</p>
               <p>
     We laugh in complete understanding, but Mrs. Sojin puts
in almost breathlessly: “It is give shock, very strange,
queer, liddle bit suspicious, but very much like little
while.”</p>
               <p>
     Sojin who has come somewhat out of his shell by now,
likens the movie craze in Japan to an epidemic. Everybody
goes to the movies. The favorite stars are Charlie Chaplin,
Lillian Gish, Nazimova, Fairbanks and Hoot Gibson.</p>
               <p>
     “How do Japanese audiences react to the sex element in
American pictures?” I ask.</p>
               <p>
     Sojin considers. He has recourse to his wife. They
whisper a bit in Japanese, and then Mrs. Sojin in English:
“Sex—it is American make—Love—kiss—embrace.” She
illustrates, quite eloquently, with her hands. Sojin nods
and blinks with dazed comprehension. Then she continues:</p>
               <p>
     “Well, Japanese audience get one shock after one
another on American play. He's adjust to new kind shock. He
is shock, struck, kick, shooted at. All very different
Japanese ideal. Very much bewilder and delicious fright.”</p>
               <p>
     A pause, thoughtful on Sojin's part. Then leaning
forward, with his long sensitive hands flattened together,
he says: “Very significant thing I confide you. Three year
ago ninety per cent. Japanese people want foreign picture.
Ten per cent. ask Japanese picture. Today he is changing.
Eight per cent. Japanese people ask for Japanese picture.
Twenty per cent. demand foreign.”</p>
               <p>
     Mrs. Sojin deprecates this revelation.</p>
               <p>
     “You understand. Americans not like see all pictures of
Japanese or Chinese life maybe. Is same at Japan. You
understand? Sank you!”</p>

            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Hard Times in Filmdom</head>

               <p>It is a pleasure, it is delightful to hear Mrs. Sojin's
naïve and quaint speech. She has a most engaging smile and
her slightly high cheek bones are flushed rosily. It is she
who is careful to get in the information anent her husband's
ancestry and education. His family were samurai under the
Princes of Date. His father was a scholar. Sojin was
graduated at Waseda University. Also he learned “the arts of
picture” at the Tokyo Fine Arts School. It is worth while
quoting Mrs. Sojin verbatim:</p>
               <p>
     “My husband meditate deep on dramatic literature. He
forerun movement of young Japan. He is leader, pioneer of
new movement. He produce one hundred classical and modern
European plays. The name of young Sojin spreaded whole
country. He influence world of new thought. Meanwhile he
also write two novels which make him an excellent author.
About six year ago he leave Japan abruptly. We arrive Los
Angeles to study motion picture. In vain find any way into
movie. So we leave abruptly and travel over snowland of
Canada where we see fine auroras.</p>
               <p>
     “We come back and make little magazine. It is call
‘East and West.’ This be to make Japanese understand and be
friend to America. My husband create motto: ‘Super
Americanization’ and he teach America always friend Japan.
Meanwhile he cultivate his soul by fishing among mountain
and seashore. One day at San Pedro, where he angle for
tunnies, he meets with ‘Thief of Bagdad’ company. It was
then he is found out by Douglas Fairbanks for Mongolian
Prince. That's begin. Now every company like to have him
play some part no one play so well as my husband.”</p>

            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Thunder Is All His</head>

               <p>Mrs. Sojin's apple-red cheeks are as bright as her
eyes, which are kindling with devotion and fervor. Not once
has she mentioned the fact that she herself was a famous
star in Japan, and she has delicately avoided mention of the
love affair that developed between her husband and his
charming leading lady, now Mrs. Sojin Kamiyama. Sojin is
inclined to be diffident. He has that rare quality possessed
by a true artist—modesty.</p>
               <p>
     Before I leave I put a last question:</p>
               <p>
     “Mr. Sojin, do you think Japan and America will ever be
at war?”</p>
               <p>
     Sojin's eyes dilate indignantly. Then “Impossible!
Japan cherishes intelligence. What for would she destroy
what she has built? It is for interest both America and
Japan be friends.”</p>
               <p>
     We say good-bye in Japanese.</p>
               <p>
     “Sayonara.”</p>
               <p>
     “Sayonara. Happy dreams.”</p>
               <p>
     Mrs. Sojin runs down the terrace after me. She puts a
package in my hand. A little souvenir of Japan. I look back
at little Mrs. Sojin, and in the language of the movies, the
scene “lap dissolves” out and into Sojin and his wife in
Japanese costume. The terraces are lined with plum trees in
spring blossom and the house on the hill “fades” into the
outlines of a pagoda. I can hear the wind bells tinkling in
a faint breeze.</p>
            </div>

         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
