<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Marriage of Okiku-San</title>
            <title type="sort">marriage of okiku san</title>
            <author>Watanna, Onoto, 1879-1954</author>
            <editor>Cole, Jean Lee</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp/>
               <name>Eaton, Winnifred, 1879-1954</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Jean Lee Cole</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
               <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">37</num> kilobytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
            <idno type="ETC">EatOkik</idno>
            <date when="2004">2004</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p n="copyright">Copyright © 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
               <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475929</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive</title>

            <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
            <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>
               <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">The Marriage of Okiku-San</title>
                  <title level="j">Red Book Magazine (June 1910): 254-263</title>
                  <title type="sort">marriage of okiku san</title>
                  <author>Onoto Watanna [pseud. Winnifred Eaton]</author>
                  <editor>Jean Lee Cole</editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Illustrator</resp>
                     <name>Taka Spiro</name>
                  </respStmt>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>pp. 254-263</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Redbook Pub. Co.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1910">1910</date>
                  <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: OCLC: 21175639</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>
                     <p>[Notes about the original source]</p>
                  </note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the
preceding line.</p>
            <p xml:id="ETC_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical
groupings.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="1910">1910</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng" usage="1">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>fiction</term>
               <term>prose</term>
               <term>feminine</term>
               <term>Women Writers</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-01-04">Joey Takeda: Converted document from P4 (old <att>xml:id</att>=EatOkik; old filename=Marriage_of_Okiku-San.xml.</change>
         <change when="2008-01">Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</change>
         <change when="2007-09">Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library: Migration. Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</change>
         <change when="2005-07">John Ivor Carlson: Corrector. Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</change>
         <change when="2004-06">Jolie Sheffer, Electronic Text Center: corrector. Added TEI header and tags.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>


   <text>
      <body>

         <div type="story">
            <head>The Marriage of Okiku-San <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Red Book Magazine</hi> (June 1910): 254-263<lb/>
By Onoto Watanna<lb/>
Illustrated by Taka Spiro
</head>

            <p>Miss Kiku Taguchi was not an ordinary young lady. Her
father, a pompous, important individual, entertained a
distinct contempt for her insignificant sex. His wife was a
mere nonentity, a puppet, who vaguely repeated, parrot-like,
the paradoxes voiced by her lord. Hence, when this same lord
emphatically expressed his opinion concerning the proper
education for a female—this within twelve hours after the
birth of Okiku-san, Lady Taguchi assented, and promised
things. The result was a girl of naturally independent and
original disposition, trammeled by the contracted rules
common for women in Japan half a century before.</p>
            <p>
  Kiku knew by heart the great rules

<pb n="255a"/>

laid down by Confucius for her miserable sex. Aimlessly and
dully, she would repeat them from day to day, while her
vapid-faced mother, herself a product of the new Japan,
mechanically kept time on the small box desk by which she
was wont to squat.</p>
            <p>
  Okiku possessed an uncle who had been educated abroad, and
through this medium she had come to know of many attractive
things. His opinions were as emphatic as his brother's, but
they were entirely different. The emancipation of Japanese
women was his pet hobby, and so bitter was his denunciation
of the old-time method of repression and education of the
weaker sex, that he and his brother met only to argue and
oftentimes politely quarrel. Okiku's uncle, however, was a
man of real power and great wealth, and while Okiku's
father, who was in modest circumstances, might despise and
disagree with his opinions, he respected the aforesaid power
and also the considerable fortune to which his own daughter
would certainly succeed. The uncle was old, had no children
of his own, and would have none. A widower, he was devoted,
so he claimed, to the memory of his wife, and growled
contempt at the notion of marrying again merely in order to
have a progeny to pray for his soul after death.</p>
            <p>
  To him went Okiku, fretting under the home chains, and
feeling, rather than knowing, the electrical change of
thought among her sex in Japan. She wanted an education—a
real one, as she expressed it. To her bluff and sympathetic
uncle, at least, she dared to breathe her little hidden
secret hope—a desire to go abroad, to enter a foreign
school and college. This her uncle promised her she should
do, and the following day he paid a visit upon his brother.
Once alone with him, he went straight to the object of his
call, barely giving the more outwardly courteous one a
chance to run through the long gamut of civilities, usually
the rule—even with brothers.</p>
            <p>“Tomi, your girl is stupid, lazy, sleepy!”</p>
            <p>
  Tomi's lips became a straight line. Perfectly well he knew
that the foregoing statement was not true, but he believed
in the old-fashioned method of polite conversation, the
humble admission of the inferiority of one's self and one's
family.</p>
            <p>
  He said, in a tone that fiercely denied the words he
uttered:</p>
            <p>“It is miserably true. She is a stupid worm!”</p>
            <p>
  “Let us put our heads together then,” suggested Gonji
solemnly, “and see if we cannot devise some means to rectify
her unhappy imbecile condition.”</p>
            <p>
  “I listen to your enlightened words of wisdom,” said Tomi,
grimly sarcastic and still fiercely polite.</p>
            <p>
  “To the point then. What do you say to my niece going
abroad—say, to America—for a term of years?”</p>
            <p>
  In spite of himself, the father of Okiku leaped up in his
seat.</p>
            <p>
  “What!” he fairly shouted. “Have my daughter sent to the
country of barbarians, where civilization is only in its
infancy!”</p>
            <p>
  “Quiet!” urged Gonjil, pulling at a stubby little imperial
he had carefully copied from a French diplomat. “Let us talk
over the matter gently, reasonably.”</p>
            <p>
  “There is nothing to talk over,” said Tomi, controlling
himself. “The matter is quite settled.”</p>
            <p>
  Gonji arose, shrugging his shoulders slightly—a trick
also caught from the aforesaid diplomat.</p>
            <p>“I regret you value my humble opinion so poorly.”</p>
            <p>
  “Not at all, brother.” Tomi's voice was anxious. “I have
distinct ideas, as you know, in regard to the bringing up of
females. I believe in their suppression—their being kept in
their proper sphere. Nothing is more offensive to me than a
woman of modern education, a creature thinking for herself
like a man—without regard for the best rules laid down for
her sex, talking, walking, acting independently. Pah! It is
nauseating to think of even. Yet these women are the very
product of this foreign education you suggest for my stupid
but worthy daughter.”</p>
            <p>
  Gonji was drawing on his outer coat, a heavy tweed affair,
which fitted somewhat grotesquely over his Japanese
underdress.</p>
            <p>

               <pb n="256"/>

  “Well, I'm off then. Er—by the way, did I speak to you of
my intention to adopt a son or daughter?”</p>
            <p>
  His brother's face turned livid, withered. He could not
reply.</p>
            <p>
  “You see,” went on Gonji seriously, “I am not as young as
I was, and I feel the necessity of providing myself with a
proper heir. I had looked upon Okiku in that light, but she
has been a disappointment to me. I wish to leave my estate
to one who has been raised according to some of my own
ideas.”</p>
            <p>
  “She is only a female,” said Tomi huskily, “yet believe
me, though it is her father speaking, she is an admirable
example of her despised sex. She is meek, submissive,
filial, obedient—having all the qualities most admirable in
a woman. What more could you possibly desire?”</p>
            <p>
  “Well, I believe in a higher education for a woman. She
will be at a disadvantage in society. Other members of her
sex are being cultivated, their minds improved. I should not
wish to be ashamed of her.”</p>
            <p>Tomi was silent, biting his underlip to repress his rage.</p>
            <p>
  “Let us make a truce,” he finally said. “Suggest some
alternative to a foreign education for Okiku and I will
readily assent.”</p>
            <p>
  “Good. What do you say to a year in Tokyo? There is an
excellent school there. All the members of the faculty are
graduates of American colleges, and one of them is herself
an American lady.”</p>
            <p>
  Tomi flipped his fan open to conceal his enraged face.
Then he closed it upon his palm, and pointed dumbly to the
mats they had vacated.</p>
            <p>“Condescend to sit.”</p>
            <p>
  Gonji smiled a bit, as he again removed his coat and
reseated himself comfortably. After both had taken several
whiffs from their pipes, Tomi began again:</p>
            <p>“Brother, there is an excellent seminary in Kyoto—”</p>
            <p>
  “I know all about it. Kept by an ancient dame of the old
school. No. Excuse me.”</p>
            <p>“In Kumommotta—”</p>
            <p>“Tokyo—or America. There—I have said it.”</p>
            <p>He emptied his pipe, tapping it upon the hibachi.</p>
            <p>
  “Well—well—er—at least you will consent to my imposing
one condition?”</p>
            <p>“By all means—if it is reasonable.”</p>
            <p>
  “Now education for a woman may be very well, if it is
immediately followed by a proper marriage. That is the only
antidote for the ill effects.”</p>
            <p>Gonji appeared to be ruminating.</p>
            <p>
  “So be it then. I'll grant that. Marriage is certainly a
worthy fate—even for a modern woman. Then it is settled.”</p>
            <p/>

            <p>Okiku's progress at the American school was little short
of remarkable. She became the favorite pupil of the
aforementioned American teacher, a spinster of forty sweet
summers. Here was a woman fit indeed to make all others of
her sex pause and take heed<ref target="n1">[1]</ref>. As fearless and outspoken as a
man—a superior man—she was a walking delegate for the
suffrage of her sex. Her theories and opinions she had
loudly voiced upon various small platforms in her own native
land, and now in a country where the condition of her sex
appealed to every indignant and outraged fiber within her,
she fairly hurled her views at the amazed and in truth
somewhat bewildered heads of her little oriental pupils.
They watched, fascinated, her mouth shoot forth riotously
its denunciation of all the laws which hitherto they had
regarded as quite sacred and necessary for their sex. Used
through centuries of oppression to yielding to a mind (or
rather body) stronger than their own, they now readily
yielded to the persuasive doctrine preached by this
“extraordinary foreign devil” teacher. She sent forth from
the school one pugnacious little disciple after another,
each to establish a new order of things in various
households.</p>
            <p>
  No pupil had listened to her words with such eager ears as
Okiku-san. Fresh from her life of subjection, she leaped
thirstily into the new order of thought. Her adored uncle
had previously pointed out to her the exceptional merits of
the foreign teacher, and she now shared his views in regard
to the strong-minded lady of the piercing blue eyes and high
cheekbones.</p>
            <p>

               <pb n="257"/>

  Okiku was to do wonders for the women of Japan! One year
in Tokyo, indeed! She was to have a career—a profession!
She should found this and that club for this and that
purpose, with uncle's money to aid and abet. Her suffering
sex would be so benefited that her name would be blessed in
the land. Little Okiku dreamed such dreams as surely never
before bewildered the head of any other little damsel of
Japan. She saw herself an oriental Mrs. Catt<ref target="n2">[2]</ref>. She gave not
a thought—she would have scorned to—to that contemptible
atom in human form known as “man,” or “mere man,” as the
foreign teacher expressed it. If she did think of him at
all, it was to recall with burning indignation all the
wrongs of the past put upon her sex. “But at last,” said
little Okiku-san, with fervor echoing the words of Miss
Simpson, “the proverbial worm is about to turn.”</p>
            <p>
  About this time, the year came to an end, and she was
abruptly summoned home. Tearfully she flew to her uncle's
hitherto comforting arms. He was curiously constrained. At
this time, he declared, he was occupied by a most absorbing
matter. He could not spare the time to travel to her
father's home. She had better obey the parental summons and
herself plead her cause. Too bad, but really uncle was
frightfully busy.</p>
            <p>
  Okiku noted through her tears, that uncle was also
frightfully attired, in a foreign suit, padded of shoulder
and plaid of vest.</p>
            <p>
  To the great Miss Simpson now went Okiku and poured out
her cup of sorrows. The lady hugged her chin, wiped her
glasses, and looked very thoughtful.</p>
            <p>
  “My dear, by all means go home. What I have taught you can
best be illustrated in the home. Believe me, the home is a
woman's real platform.”</p>
            <p>
  This remarkable statement served only further to bewilder
the heart-broken Okiku. She retired to her precious room, a
pathetic replica of some faraway Smith College room, and
sobbed passionately

<pb n="258"/>

with her head on the beautiful brass bed chosen by teacher
for Okiku. It had been a source of great wonder and awe to
both Okiku and her maid, but hardly of comfort, since the
twain slept under, not on, the bed itself.</p>
            <p>
  Dolefully she packed her fine modern clothes—the clothes
meant to be worn on that certain trip to America. Lingerie
in underwear, corsets, kid gloves, openwork stockings,
skirts, and what not. As she traveled homeward, a great lump
choking her poor little throat, she said savagely, with a
mind picture of her father's face when he should see the
contents of her trunks:</p>
            <p>
  “Anyhow man is inferior to woman. Certainly I shall let
all males so understand.”</p>
            <p>
  She had no sooner arrived home than they broached to her
the subject of matrimony. A youth had been selected—or
rather, Okiku's father had carefully selected the boy's
father as an excellent one to be allied to. There had been
some quiet negotiations between relatives of the two
families, the boy's uncle acting as a go-between.</p>
            <p>
  When they told Okiku, she said nothing. She went up to her
chamber and pulled the sliding doors behind her.</p>
            <p>
  “I wish I were dead!” she said. “I could not endure to
live with a man!”</p>
            <p>
  Then she fell into a deep reverie, her chin pillowed on
her folded hands. Presently she got up, opened a panel of
her room and took out a lacquer box. Rummaging among its
papers, she found what she sought, and, this spread before
her, she studied it thoughtfully:</p>
            <p>
  “A wife may be divorced for the following reasons:” read
the script.</p>

            <q>1. If she be disobedient to her parents-in-law.</q>

            <p>Okiku looked thoughtful.</p>
            <p>
  “Suppose they should beat me! That would be hard to bear,”
she said.</p>

                   <q>2. If she be childless.</q>

            <p>“Children will come, alas!” sighed little Okiku wisely.</p>

                    <q>3. If she be untrue.</q>

            <p>Kiku frowned.</p>

                    <q>4. If she be jealous.</q>

            <p>“Not I,” said Okiku, scornfully.</p>

                      <q>5. If she steal.</q>

            <p>“Impossible.”</p>

                  <q>6. If she talk too much.</q>

            <p>A dimple stole into either round cheek of little Kiku
Taguchi.</p>
            <p>“Well, I can talk!” said she.</p>

            <p/>

            <p>A few days later she sat in a room in which were assembled
the various members of the Taguchi and Hakemoto families.
They sat in a semi-circle, drinking tea and eating. Great
quantities of sake were also consumed, and of this beverage
Kiku herself was permitted to drink for the first time. She
ought to have felt quite a personage. The assemblage was in
her honor, hers and the boy's she had not yet even
condescended to look at.</p>
            <p>
  The sake brightened up her eyes and cheeks. Her ears
tingled. She wanted to talk. Also she had an inclination to
cry. She wished ardently all the time that she were dead.
Suddenly there flashed into her tangled mind the comforting
words of the divorce authority: “If she talk too much!”
Little Kiku's lips curled up. She astonished the assemblage
by an unexpected, eerie little laugh. Next moment she
sneezed.</p>
            <p>
  Later she found herself sitting opposite to a person, who
by his attire and manner she recognized as a tyrannical and
odious man. She looked up and said quickly, so that she
might not be interrupted by her officious father:</p>
            <p>
  “It is better you should know the truth. I talk all the
time!”</p>
            <p>
  Now when a pair of newly affianced people are thus for the
first time brought together, a somewhat gentle conversation
is expected to ensue. Sometimes where the twain have met
before, sentimental passages occur; but in any event it is
seldom that hostile words are spoken. Therefore, it is not
to be wondered at that the prospective bridegroom, when he
heard the words of Okiku, so far forgot himself as to leap
up like a rubber ball bouncing.</p>
            <p>
  Kiku saw that his face was red, that his eyes were round,
that his mouth fell agape. She inwardly described him as: “A
beast! Stupid and ugly, too!”—which was not a fair or true
description of the boy at all.</p>
            <p>

               <pb n="259"/>

  Before an open shoji<ref target="n3">[3]</ref> in the Sakura Hotel, Okiku stood
looking out at the scenery surrounding the place. She
appeared to be waiting or listening, for her attitude was
very alert, though she stood perfectly still, one little
hand pressed against her lips. Suddenly her brows drew
together. An expression, half frown, half smile, swept her
lips and remained in her eyes, giving them a curiously
defiant, almost aggressive aspect.</p>
            <p>
  Just then the doors were pushed apart and a young man came
into the room. Apparently he had been walking quickly, for
his face was very rosy and he wiped the perspiration from
his brow.</p>
            <p>Kiku turned about.</p>
            <p>
  “Oh, here you are at last,” said she in a complaining
voice. “Did you meet with an accident?”</p>
            <p>
  Before the half-reproachful, half-puzzled expression of
his eyes her own fell down. Without answering her question,
her husband, kneeling, opened one of his packages. The
wrappings were of fragrant tissue paper, and his clumsy
fingers attempted to undo them with care. At the sharp voice
of the girl, however, he stood up, looking at the package
uncertainly; then went to her and put it, without speaking,
into her hands.</p>
            <p>But she only said:</p>
            <p>
  “Most exalted lord, would the condescension be too great
for you to answer my humble and servile question?”</p>
            <p>
  Carelessly tearing away the paper covering, she revealed
the single rose he had bought her—an American Beauty, a
costly thing in Japan.</p>
            <p>Kiku colored, turned away.</p>
            <p>
  “Oh, Kiku!” said her husband, seizing her by the sleeve.
“Just turn around here. Was there ever such a sunset
before<ref target="n4">[4]</ref>? Why, what—?”</p>
            <p>
  She was looking at him, and something in her face held his
tongue-tied for a moment. Then he stammered:</p>
            <p>“How lovely you look to-night, Kiku-no!”</p>
            <p>She smiled brilliantly.</p>
            <p>
  “Oh,” said she, “but I talk all the time. You'd much
better divorce me.”</p>
            <p>
  “Well, sit down here for the present anyhow,” he urged,
pulling her down beside him. A bit timidly his arm stole
out, then settled confidently about her shoulders. She held
back, but his arm was strong and presently her head rested
under his chin. Reaching down, his lips found their way to
hers. At least he knew a few of the modern tricks.</p>
            <p>
  “I suppose,” said Okiku, intent on talking, “that that is
a—kiss?”</p>
            <p>“Yes,” said he.</p>
            <p>Then said little Okiku, who had determined upon a divorce:</p>
            <p>“It is good!”</p>
            <p>
  They had been married exactly one day. A sentimental uncle
had managed to separate them from the too closely pressed
relations. They were enjoying a modern novelty—a honeymoon
alone together in the mountains.</p>
            <p>
  “Oh!” said Jihei, laughing loudly, “how perfectly
enchanting you appear when you blush, Okiku-no!”</p>
            <p>
  “But I thought,” said Kiku, pouting and drawing away a
bit, “that men despised a mere female. Men are all tyrants—
beasts. We are merely their prey—their playthings. I won't
be a plaything! No indeed!”</p>
            <p>Jihei growled fiercely.</p>
            <p>
  “Whoo!” said he savagely. “We are horrible women-eaters.
Look out, mere female creature, I intend to gobble you up.”</p>
            <p>Whereupon he kissed her violently.</p>
            <p>
  After she had extricated herself, and breathlessly at
that:</p>
            <p>
  “Well but—you have got to find out about me. I t—talk
all—”</p>
            <p>
  “And so do I. Keep still—just for a moment. I am going to
whisper something in your ear. Don't tell anybody, because
these are terrible words for a Japanese to say, but Oho! I'm
something of a modern myself too, you know. Now pay heed!”</p>
            <p>He whispered into her little ear.</p>
            <p>“Did you hear?”</p>
            <p>She had turned actually pale.</p>
            <p>
  “That is an improper word!” said she in a faint, very
frightened voice.</p>
            <p>
  Jihei threw back his head. He laughed joyfully, like a
mischievous boy, rejoicing in his tricks.</p>
            <p>
  “Is it? 'Love' an improper word! Oh, well, I'll explain to
you some day what I mean.”</p>
            <p>

               <pb n="260"/>

  “Explain to me now.”</p>
            <p>
  “Oh, no, because you are way behind the times, Okiku-san.
Fancy a modern woman of Japan calling 'love' an improper
word! Fie!”</p>
            <p>
  She was much offended and forced herself free, sitting
poutingly apart from him to the extent of three or four
inches of distance.</p>
            <p>Jihei promptly reduced this considerably:</p>
            <p>
  “Very well, I will try to tell you then. Now the
foreigners—the westerners, you know—think they have a
patent upon the word. They say, to us, it has no meaning, or
if one, an improper one. But we know better, don't we, Kiku-
san? It's the feeling—the—the—greatest impulse in us. I
adore you, reverently, ideally. That's what I wanted to tell
you, Kiku-no.”</p>
            <p>“When did you first?” she stammered breathlessly.</p>
            <p>
  “At once—at the look-at meeting. I had been preparing for
it, you see—preparing for you. I intended to love you, and
I did. It was just as it should be.”</p>
            <p>
  “It was all quite wrong,” she sobbed. “Such a—a—marriage
is—against nature.” The words of Miss Simpson came to her
awkwardly.</p>
            <p>
  Jihei was silent a moment, but regarded her, smiling
confidently.</p>
            <p>“By and by we shall know,” he said, softly.</p>
            <p>The following day, seated by<ref target="n5">[5]</ref> the self-same shoji where
she had waited for her husband, Okiku sat reading a letter:</p>

            <q>
               <p>MY POOR LITTLE KIKU-SAN:</p>
               <p>By all means be firm. Bear in mind all I have taught
  you. That you, my most hopeful and best beloved pupil,
  should be absolutely forced into an odious union, at the
  very height of your mental development, seems horrible to
  me. I can only strenuously urge you not to succumb. If
  you do so, believe me, you will sink into that helpless,
  hopeless, crushed condition so pathetically common to
  your countrywomen. If you, who have been made to see the
  glorious possibilities of our sex, should succumb and go
  back to that obsolete position of Japanese women, slaves,
  not wives or true mates of their lords—not husbands—
  then, indeed, I will say my work has failed.</p>
               <p>
    Dear child, keep up a brave spirit. Though I smiled at
  the thought of your pathetic ruse to obtain your freedom,
  I also applaud it. By all means, if it will serve your
  purpose (Remember the end justifies the means)—Talk!</p>
            </q>

            <p>The sound of a splash was heard.</p>
            <p>

               <pb n="261"/>

  “Okiku!” called a cheery voice. “More towels, please!”</p>
            <p>
  She crushed the letter in her hand, then drew herself up
stiffly.</p>
            <p>“Call a servant, please!”</p>
            <p>
  “A servant! I want my wife to wait upon me! Hi! there,
wifey! Get me a towel—and hurry, please!”</p>
            <p>
  Her answer was to clap her hands loudly. To her summons
swiftly came a serving-maid who brought the desired towels
and took them to the commanding one within.</p>
            <p>
  A few moments later Jihei appeared. His shining round face
bore evidence of his recent bath. He was in excellent humor.
Pinching his wife's ear, he threw his arms carelessly about
her shoulders and drew her up against him, cheek to cheek.</p>
            <p>
  “What do you think, O-Kiku-san, we've got to cut our
beautiful honeymoon in two.”</p>
            <p>She turned about uneasily.</p>
            <p>
  “You see,” he went on, “my mother needs us at home. She's
getting pretty old, and really, someone ought to look after
her. What a godsend you will be to her!”</p>
            <p>
  Okiku's form had stiffened to a rigidity so repelling that
even the arm of the affectionate Jihei loosened. Now one of
the chief things against which Miss Simpson had preached was
the domination of the Japanese mother-in-law.</p>
            <p>
  As all the world knows, a daughter-in-law in Japan is a
very inferior person in the household of her husband's
mother. She can even be divorced by that lady, in the
absence of the husband. Her chief ambition is to please and
propitiate the dread lady, and to become later herself a
mother, when she will have her own household.</p>
            <p>
  In what glowing terms had not Miss Simpson painted the
position of the daughter-in-law in America? There things
were reversed. At the wish of the wife, the woman who has
borne the husband may be peremptorily ejected from his house-
-so said Miss Simpson. If she remained, her position was far
below that

<pb n="262"/>

of the wife in authority. In fact, her authority was quite
nil after the advent of the wife. She must take a “back
seat,” be careful of her speech, be meek, conciliating—
often serve the wife.</p>
            <p>
  “Why, what is the matter, Okiku? Did something bite you?
Let me—”</p>
            <p>
  He was quite ready to scratch her, declaring that the
mosquitoes were becoming unbearable.</p>
            <p>Okiku pushed his hand aside.</p>
            <p>“I want my own home!” she cried.</p>
            <p>
  “Your own home! Well, but where do you think I am taking
you to, then? Certainly you are to be one of us. My little
brothers and sisters will adore you, I am sure, and as for
my mother—”</p>
            <p>“You expect me to be her servant!”</p>
            <p>“Why, no, we keep servants—several.”</p>
            <p>
  “Oh, yes, I know quite all about it. A daughter-in-law is
just another servant. I won't bear it, indeed.”</p>
            <p>
  “O—Kiku! You must love my mother, and wish to do services
for her.”</p>
            <p>“You mean I am to wait upon her wishes?”</p>
            <p>
  “Why, certainly. That is a daughter's duty. It is proper.
She is an old woman.”</p>
            <p>
  “Don't touch me!” said Okiku in a suffocating voice. “Let
me pass, please,” and she rushed into her room, snapping the
doors tightly behind her.</p>
            <p>He did not follow her.</p>
            <p>
  So this was what she had come to! She, who was to be an
example to all her sex—she was to do the humble daughter-in-
law's service in the ancient way.</p>
            <p>
  “Never! Never! Never!” she cried, pacing up and down, and
spasmodically clapping her little hands together.</p>
            <p>
  By and by her anger passed away. She stood, as if
listening for some sound from the adjoining room. Up to the
present he had met all her rebellious outbursts with
embraces, rude, but also to the unconscious Kiku, desirable.
Now all was silence. What was he doing? Okiku hesitated a
minute, then silently she stepped over to the shoji.
Moistening her finger, she made a considerable hole in the
fusuma<ref target="n6">[6]</ref>. To this she applied her eye. Whatever she saw
within apparently was not what she expected, for with a
little petulant sound she opened the sliding doors and went
into the other room. Nobody at all was there. She looked
about her. The frown left her face. An anxious look came
into her eyes. Suddenly she ran across the room, and opened
wide the shoji onto the veranda.</p>
            <p>
  It was growing dark outside. She leaned forward, peering
about her. Then she sat still, waiting, growing steadily
more uneasy and agitated. When it was quite dark, she still
remained by the opened doors, and only when a maid came to
the rooms bearing lighted andons<ref target="n7">[7]</ref>, did she move from her
position. Too proud to question the servants, she could not
forbear speaking of what engaged her so utterly:</p>
            <p>
  “My husband—took letters to the village. It is quite a
walk, is it not? I trust a very good and safe road?”</p>
            <p>
  “Yes, mistress. But the young master has dropped one of
his letters, I fear. I picked it up on the threshold of your
room.”</p>
            <p>“Indeed. Well, give it to me.”</p>
            <p>
  When the servant was gone, she turned the letter over in
her hand and looked at the address. It was to his mother.
Okiku's hands began to tremble. Slowly her little finger
slipped under the flap of the envelope. It was very
carelessly closed and yielded at once to her pressure. She
took the note out. A moment she hesitated, and then:</p>
            <p>“No—no—I can't do it!”</p>
            <p>
  She was putting it back hastily, when her eye fell upon
these words—they were written very clearly and in
exceptionally large type:</p>

                   <q>SHE TALKS ALL THE TIME!</q>

            <p>Her heart suddenly ceased beating. She felt as if about to
faint. Her hand sought her throat.</p>
            <p>
  Her ruse then had succeeded after all! He was writing home
to his parents. “She talks all the time!” So she was to be
divorced!</p>
            <p>
  Slowly, her fingers shaking, she straightened out the
crumpled letter. Her eyes widened. She stared—a stifled
sound, half laugh, half sob, escaped her. The entire sheet
was covered with the one sentence: “She talks all the time!”</p>
            <p>
  Gods! How he wished to make his case clear to his parents!
Oh—!</p>

            <pb n="263"/>

            <p>She was about to tear the letter across, when a new terror
assailed her. Perhaps he had already divorced her—left her
here alone in the mountains!</p>
            <p>
  She tried to comfort herself with the thought of her “dear
teacher,” to whom she would go at once; but Miss Simpson's
face became fainter with every moment, until it seemed
extinguished altogether from her mind. In its place appeared
instead the round, boyish, cheerful countenance of Jihei!</p>
            <p>Suddenly she thought: “I have driven him away!”</p>
            <p>
  There was nothing particularly handsome or attractive
about her husband's face except its natural good humor and
affectionate expression, but to the mind's eye<ref target="n8">[8]</ref> of little
Okiku now it appeared surrounded with a pale, golden halo.</p>
            <p>She flew across the room, blindly calling him by name:</p>
            <p>“Jihei! Jihei!”</p>
            <p>A number of maids came running in at her summons.</p>
            <p>“My husband?” she cried shrilly.</p>
            <p>She appeared distraught.</p>
            <p>Just then someone came from out the shadow on the veranda.</p>
            <p>“Why, hello!” said he. “What is the trouble?”</p>
            <p>
  “Madame was anxious,” said a smiling maid. “She feared
harm had come to you on your trip to the village.”</p>
            <p>“But I have not been to the village,” said be.</p>
            <p>They withdrew discreetly, leaving the pair alone.</p>
            <p>
  Okiku had picked up her sleeve, and pressing it to her
eyes, she stood in the attitude of a child crying.</p>
            <p>“What is it, Okiku?”</p>
            <p>He was smiling as he stood behind her.</p>
            <p>
  “D-don't speak to me,” she said, “I—I know—know you wish
to divorce me, and—”</p>
            <p>“What made you think that?”</p>
            <p>“I s-saw your letter to your mother.”</p>
            <p>“You did! Well! Let me see it, please.”</p>
            <p>
  He undid the little fingers curled about it, smoothed it
out, and read through the epistle.</p>
            <p>
  “Why look, Okiku, did you notice what is written on the
flap of the envelope? Here, take your sleeve down.”</p>
            <p>
  She turned a little tear-stained face around, and, as his
arm closed about her, she read the writing on the envelope,
as he held it before her eyes:</p>
            <p>“This letter is for my little foolish wife only.”</p>
            <p>She turned bodily about in his arms.</p>
            <p>“Oh, Jihei!”</p>
            <p>
  “Let me hug you now, and then we'll both forget all about
it.”</p>
            <p>
</p>
            <p>A few moments later:</p>
            <p>
  “And now tell me, where did you get all your curious
notions about men and marriage?”</p>
            <p>
  “You see, uncle and teacher do not believe in marriages
such as we have in Japan, and they think an intellectual
woman should not marry, but have a career. I—I—really I
did hope to emancipate my sex in Japan.”</p>
            <p>“By divorcing me?”</p>
            <p>“But I didn't know—”</p>
            <p>“Well?”</p>
            <p>
  “That I loved you, and you see my life had been so cramped
at home I simply thought marriage would prove another cage
into which I would be shut.”</p>
            <p>
  “It will not be,” said he fervently, “for you see we are
starting right—with just one thing all unions ought to have-
-love!”</p>
            <p>“Miss Simpson thought that unnecessary.”</p>
            <p>“Did she? Now look here. This came a little while ago.”</p>
            <p>
  It was a telegram from Tokyo. Okiku's eyes were wide as
she read:</p>

                <q>“Married to-day at five P.M.”</q>

            <p>It was signed by both “teacher” and “uncle.”</p>


            <note xml:id="n1_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> 
               <p>“pause and heed” in original.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n2_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> 
               <p>Carrie Chapman Catt (1859-1947), suffragist and founder of
the League of Women Voters.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n3_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> 
               <p>shoji: paper screens or windows.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n4_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> 
               <p>“Was ever such a sunset before?” in original.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n5_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> 
               <p>“seated, seated by” in original.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n6_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> 
               <p>fusuma: sliding doors used in Japanese houses, constructed
of light wooden frames with opaque paper panels.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n7_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> 
               <p>andon: lantern with paper shades.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n8_Marriage_of_Okiku-San">
               <seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> 
               <p>“mind-eyes” in original.</p>
            </note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
