<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BecauseWeWereLonely1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Because We Were Lonely</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:33"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-10">Begin transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl33 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs= "facs:BecauseWeWereLonely1">
     <pb n="23"/>
      <body>
        
         <head>Because We Were Lonely</head>
         
         <div type="preface">
            <p>What if he was married! She needed him and he needed her. So, risking everything a good woman cherishes, she recklessly plunged—</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>I schemed and plotted to win another woman’s husband. In the beginning I did not even
               have the excuse of being in love with him. But deliberately and cold-bloodedly I set
               out to captivate the man, because I knew he could give me everything my lonely heart
               desired.</p>
            <p>I was a widow of a year. My husband had left me moderately provided for. I had a good
               social position. I had beauty and charm. My husband had been slavishly devoted to me,
               and after his death I was bewildered and restless without his guiding hand and
               companionship. I found it difficult to go places unescorted, and envied and resented
               other women with their husbands in attendance. I hated the rôle of <q>widow</q>, and
               determined that I would not be a widow long. </p>
            <p>There were but few eligible unmarried men in our town, and I was beginning to feel
               discouraged. Moreover, my tastes were extravagant and my income did not half suffice
               to gratify my cravings or luxurious and costly things.</p>
            <p>Our town is a live, prosperous one, with a population of a little under a hundred
               thousand. We have our clubs, our social cliques and organizations; the women of my
               set dress as well as the women of the larger cities, and we have our cars and country
               clubs, where we play tennis, gold, badminton, mahjong, and other games and sports. We
               all play bridge. Some of us are fiends at it.</p>
            <p>Before my husband’s death mine was an orchid existence. I lay abed till noon, when my
               maid prepared my bath and brought me my breakfast. I played bridge or mahjong all
               afternoon, and danced all evening. I couldn’t go to teas and parties after my
               husband’s death—not for a few months anyway, and my life became duller and narrower.
               I was restless and dissatisfied. Moreover, I missed my husband as a husband. Really,
               I was in a pathological condition at the time I met Jerry Wallace.</p>
            <p>It was at a country club dance—a dance that I had to sit out with the older women, as
               I was still <q>in mourning</q>. A friend, Jenny Doty, pointed him out to me. She
               said:</p>
            <p><q>Look who’s here—Gerald Wallace himself! Know him?</q></p>
            <p>I saw a man of about thirty-five. He was a large, athletic, man’s type of man,
               keen-eyed, ruddy, with an open-air look about him. He was not dancing, but seemed to
               be looking clear across the room at me. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><q>No—who is he? I never saw him before. New in our town?</q></p>
            <p><q>No, but he doesn’t go out much. Too busy making money</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Is that his wife with him?</q></p>
            <p><q>Oh no—just some girl. His wife’s in California. Been gone three years now fancy
                  leaving a man like that!</q></p>
            <p>A strange excitement went over me. I cannot explain it; I suppose it was psychic.
               Jenny was still chattering. </p>
     <pb n="29"/>
            <p><q>they say he’s staying till he can clear out with a cool million. Then, so they
                  say, he plans to join his wife</q>.</p>
            <p>His wife! From the very first, the thought of her excited and enraged me. I resented
               her. I hated her unreasonably, blindly. What sort of a woman was she to leave her
               husband, to follow the career of a writer? I am not intellectual, but I am
               accomplished too, in my way, and I know how to charm and attract and please men. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
         
            <p>I was planning that very moment to use my every wile to fascinate Jerry Wallace. I
               recognized him as the type of man I wanted—rich, attractive—a real man in every sense
               of the word, and I am frank to say that I did want a man. I wanted a lover. I wanted
               the protection and security of a husband. I wanted the lovely things, and the
               attentions and devotion that a rich man can give to a woman. </p>
            <p>So, as I said, I set out deliberately to court this man. I planned my campaign with
               care and craft. I learned everything I could about him—his habits, his tastes, his
               work, his past; how long his wife had been gone, what their life had been together,
               who she was, where they went, who were their particular friends.</p>
            <p>I even got his financial rating through Bradstreets. I learned that he was not
               over-fond of society, in the sense that I knew it. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>He was an outdoor man, rode horseback, played gold, went on long motor trips, went
               hunting and fishing. I learned that he was something of a book worm, was fond of
               music and the theater.</p>
            <p>I leaned—and how this irritated me!—that he had been passionately in love with his
               wife and since her departure had lived almost the life of a recluse. They had no
               children, and she had become dissatisfied with the restrictions and lack of literary
               opportunities of a small city.</p>
            <p>When I had learned all I thought was necessary, I started my campaign to win him, by
               going to his office with some stocks I had taken from my safety deposit box in the
               bank. He was a stock broker and I explained that I had been recommended to see him
               with regard to the disposal of my stocks. It was a business call, brief, pleasant;
               but I was playing my part well, and I knew I had made an impression on him. Just as I
               was about to leave, I asked him casually whether he played bridge. He replied, with
               one of his rare smiles, that although he did not play bridge, he could 
                <emph>learn</emph>. That broke the ice between us and gave me the exact lead
               I wanted. I smiled demurely back at him and said, <q>I’m considered a very good
                  teacher</q>.</p>
            <p>He burst out laughing at that, and I immediately joined in with him. He stopped
               abruptly, and I could see the interest in his eyes, as he deliberately looked me
               over. (I am sure I had never looked better in my life. My black and white half
               mourning was especially becoming to me!)</p>
            <p>After a moment he said, <q>When may we begin the lessons?</q></p>
            <p>I answered jokingly, <q>Tonight or never!</q></p>
            <p><q>Fine!</q> said he. <q>Tonight!</q></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
