<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BecauseWeWereLonely1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Because We Were Lonely</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl33"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Anonymous</name></author>. <title level="a">Because We Were Lonely</title>. <publisher ref="org:TrueStory"><title level="j">True Story Magazine</title></publisher>, <date when="1933-04">Apr.
                     1933</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">28-30, 92-96</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <!--Add information about previous citations or bibliographies using the source element-->
                     <!--
                        <recordHist>
                           <source target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        </recordHist>
                     -->
                     <availability>
                        <p>Original in Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds 15.15 at University of Calgary</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                  <!--
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                     </listBibl>
                  -->
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-06-30">Added note about source</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-06-21">Begin transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-10">Begin transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl33 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BecauseWeWereLonely1">
     <pb n="28"/>
      <body>
        
         <head>Because We Were Lonely</head>
         <epigraph>
            <q>
               <p>What if he was married! She needed him and he needed her. So, risking everything a good woman cherishes, she recklessly plunged—</p>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
         <div type="content">
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>I schemed and plotted to win another woman’s husband. In the beginning I did not even
               have the excuse of being in love with him. But deliberately and cold-bloodedly I set
               out to captivate the man, because I knew he could give me everything my lonely heart
               desired.</p>
            <p>I was a widow of a year. My husband had left me moderately provided for. I had a good
               social position. I had beauty and charm. My husband had been slavishly devoted to me,
               and after his death I was bewildered and restless without his guiding hand and
               companionship. I found it difficult to go places unescorted, and envied and resented
               other women with their husbands in attendance. I hated the rôle of <q>widow</q>, and
               determined that I would not be a widow long. </p>
            <p>There were but few eligible unmarried men in our town, and I was beginning to feel
               discouraged. Moreover, my tastes were extravagant and my income did not half suffice
               to gratify my cravings or luxurious and costly things.</p>
            <p>Our town is a live, prosperous one, with a population of a little under a hundred
               thousand. We have our clubs, our social cliques and organizations; the women of my
               set dress as well as the women of the larger cities, and we have our cars and country
               clubs, where we play tennis, gold, badminton, mahjong, and other games and sports. We
               all play bridge. Some of us are fiends at it.</p>
            <p>Before my husband’s death mine was an orchid existence. I lay abed till noon, when my
               maid prepared my bath and brought me my breakfast. I played bridge or mahjong all
               afternoon, and danced all evening. I couldn’t go to teas and parties after my
               husband’s death—not for a few months anyway, and my life became duller and narrower.
               I was restless and dissatisfied. Moreover, I missed my husband as a husband. Really,
               I was in a pathological condition at the time I met Jerry Wallace.</p>
            <p>It was at a country club dance—a dance that I had to sit out with the older women, as
               I was still <q>in mourning</q>. A friend, Jenny Doty, pointed him out to me. She
               said:</p>
            <p><q>Look who’s here—Gerald Wallace himself! Know him?</q></p>
            <p>I saw a man of about thirty-five. He was a large, athletic, man’s type of man,
               keen-eyed, ruddy, with an open-air look about him. He was not dancing, but seemed to
               be looking clear across the room at me. </p>
         
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p><q>No—who is he? I never saw him before. New in our town?</q></p>
            <p><q>No, but he doesn’t go out much. Too busy making money</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Is that his wife with him?</q></p>
            <p><q>Oh no—just some girl. His wife’s in California. Been gone three years now fancy
                  leaving a man like that!</q></p>
            <p>A strange excitement went over me. I cannot explain it; I suppose it was psychic.
               Jenny was still chattering. </p>
     <pb n="29"/>
            <p><q>they say he’s staying till he can clear out with a cool million. Then, so they
                  say, he plans to join his wife</q>.</p>
            <p>His wife! From the very first, the thought of her excited and enraged me. I resented
               her. I hated her unreasonably, blindly. What sort of a woman was she to leave her
               husband, to follow the career of a writer? I am not intellectual, but I am
               accomplished too, in my way, and I know how to charm and attract and please men. </p>
        
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
         
            <p>I was planning that very moment to use my every wile to fascinate Jerry Wallace. I
               recognized him as the type of man I wanted—rich, attractive—a real man in every sense
               of the word, and I am frank to say that I did want a man. I wanted a lover. I wanted
               the protection and security of a husband. I wanted the lovely things, and the
               attentions and devotion that a rich man can give to a woman. </p>
            <p>So, as I said, I set out deliberately to court this man. I planned my campaign with
               care and craft. I learned everything I could about him—his habits, his tastes, his
               work, his past; how long his wife had been gone, what their life had been together,
               who she was, where they went, who were their particular friends.</p>
            <p>I even got his financial rating through Bradstreets. I learned that he was not
               over-fond of society, in the sense that I knew it. </p>
        
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>He was an outdoor man, rode horseback, played gold, went on long motor trips, went
               hunting and fishing. I learned that he was something of a book worm, was fond of
               music and the theater.</p>
            <p>I leaned—and how this irritated me!—that he had been passionately in love with his
               wife and since her departure had lived almost the life of a recluse. They had no
               children, and she had become dissatisfied with the restrictions and lack of literary
               opportunities of a small city.</p>
            <p>When I had learned all I thought was necessary, I started my campaign to win him, by
               going to his office <pb n="30"/>with some stocks I had taken from my safety deposit box in the
               bank. He was a stock broker and I explained that I had been recommended to see him
               with regard to the disposal of my stocks. It was a business call, brief, pleasant;
               but I was playing my part well, and I knew I had made an impression on him. Just as I
               was about to leave, I asked him casually whether he played bridge. He replied, with
               one of his rare smiles, that although he did not play bridge, he could 
                <emph>learn</emph>. That broke the ice between us and gave me the exact lead
               I wanted. I smiled demurely back at him and said, <q>I’m considered a very good
                  teacher</q>.</p>
            <p>He burst out laughing at that, and I immediately joined in with him. He stopped
               abruptly, and I could see the interest in his eyes, as he deliberately looked me
               over. (I am sure I had never looked better in my life. My black and white half
               mourning was especially becoming to me!)</p>
            <p>After a moment he said, <q>When may we begin the lessons?</q></p>
            <p>I answered jokingly, <q>Tonight or never!</q></p>
            <p><q>Fine!</q> said he. <q>Tonight!</q></p>
            
     
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>And that was the beginning between us. It was all so dead easy to start with. One
               wouldthink he had been looking for just such a woman as i—for a home like mine to
               come to. And as for me—I knew what I wanted! I intended to have this man so
               completely under my control that I could get from him anything I desired. I suppose I
               would have scorned to consider myself the prdinary gold-digger. Mine was a
               scientifically planned scheme, and I intended to play my game and my man with
               technique and skill. Sometimes our best laid plans, however, come back like
               boomerangs to slay us. I thought I had myself so well in hand that I could make my
               own moves like a coldblooded chess player; and yet before I realized it I was
               enmeshed in my own web.</p>
            <p>The mere presence of this man had the power to obsess me with an almost overpowering
               sensuousness. The first time, he put his arms around me, I nearly lost my senses. He
               swept me literally off my feet. I realized I had fallen madly in love with him.</p>
            <p>We were both lonely. He was the loneliest man I had ever met. He was like a child,
               literally craving and hungering for affection and attention. He lived at a hotel,
               when all his inclinations were toward the intimacies and the comforts of a home. I
               made my home lovely for him. I would have things for dinner that he liked and could
               not get at the hotel or restaurants. I always looked my best, prettied up for him. I
               covered up my real character, which was somewhat temperamental and excitable, and I
               met him always when he came to my house after a day’s work at the office, with a
               smile, and I made him feel that the house was his, and that everything we did was to
               please him.</p>
            <p>I had my two little sons on hand when I knew he would be amused or interested. I
               never let them tire him. They were looking little fellows, and he took to them at
               once. The boys thought him great. We became a habit with him. He would come straight
               up from his office to my house, and he spent every spare moment with me. We went on
               week-end motor trips into the mountains or to the resorts, but we always took the
               boys with us!</p>
            <p>Propinquity means so much. Jerry had been actually hungering for the companionship
               and the tenderness of a woman, and that, I think, was what first attracted and drew
               him to me. That and my sex and beauty. He was not indifferent to these. No man could
               have been. I can say that without vanity, and you may be sure that I did everything
               in my power to make myself desirable and seductive. I held off as long as I humanly
               could, but no woman could have resisted him. </p>
            <p>He was a generous lover and, being very rich, his gifts were princely ones. Checks,
               stocks and bonds, diamonds, furs, a beautiful new car, a grand piano, a daily flower
               account—everything my heart could desire. I had all that, and I tried to assure
               myself that I had him too. And that was one of the curious parts of our affair. I
               never felt down in my heart that he was wholly mine. There was something about him,
               some reserve, that I could not reach. I don’t recall his ever actually telling me
               that he loved me. Many a time I sought to trap him into this admission. I would ask
               him, <q>Do you love me?</q></p>
    
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>He would turn the subject off with some joking reply such as, <q>Do you have to
                  ask?</q> Or, <q>Now what do you think?</q> but he never actually admitted it. Once
               he said that his actions spoke louder than words. I tried to be content with that. I
               told myself that he never would have lavished all those gifts upon me; he would not
               seek my company constantly; he could not have those intimate relations with me, if he
               did not love me, and when his arms were around me all the fears and ghosts of doubt
               seemed to disappear.</p>
            <p>There was one subject that became absolutely taboo between us. His wife. He would not
               discuss her with me. I could never induce him to talk about her. In the beginning,
               when he was putting himself out to be especially nice to me and court me, he would
               answer any question I asked about her in a monosyllable. For instance, I asked him if
               his wife played bridge. He replied no. I followed this with, <q>Well, how did you
                  amuse yourselves?</q></p>
            <p>He changed the subject abruptly, and said, <q>Looks like rain</q>.</p>
         <pb n="92"/>
            <p>Another time I asked him if she were pretty. He replied yes. I came out then with
                  <q>Prettier than I am?</q> He looked at me queerly then—almost appraisingly—and I
               did not like that look. </p>
            <p>I repeated my question, and he replied. <q>Let’s go on with the game</q>. We were
               playing bridge with a couple of friends I kept at him, though I realized it irritated
               him even to mention her name, but I had acquired an almost morbid interest in her. I
               wanted to force him to talk freely about her. I wanted to dig into his feelings, and
               find out how he felt toward her now. I was dying to have him say to me that he no
               longer cared anything at all about her. </p>
            <p>One day I said, <q>I hear she’s very clever—is she?</q></p>
            <p>I saw his eyes light for a moment, and then he replied evasively, <q>Cleverness is
                  not everything</q>.</p>
            <p>My heart leaped. I felt that he must mean that she lacked the qualities that I
               possessed and which endeared me to him. </p>
            <p>Imagine then how my heart sank, as, speaking almost as if to himself, he added,
                  <q>She was more than merely clever. She had everything a man wants in a
               woman</q>.</p>
            <p>He got up then—he had been sitting beside me—and he took a few strides up and down
               the room, his brows knitted as if in troubled thought. I could scarcely breathe. It
               seemed to me an intolerable thing that he should be walking up and down
               there—thinking of her. It seemed to me that what he had said about her was almost an
               affront to me. It was more than I could endure. </p>
            <p>He came back to where I was sitting on the davenport. He said, <q>I don’t want to
                  talk to you about my wife. It’s not decent</q>.</p>
            <p>I covered up my feelings. It was part of my role not to anger or irritate him, and I
               said with a brave smile, <q>All right, dear. I understand how you feel. I didn’t mean
                  to be inquisitive</q>.</p>
     
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>He made no comment, but he went home early that evening, and I had a bad night. I
               think I cried most of the night. I didn’t realize that I had begun to pay the
               penalty.</p>
            <p>They say I am a woman of tact and ingenuity. I have always had a good social
               position, and I thought a lot of my position in society. Of course, in a town of this
               size, it was impossible for Jerry and me to carry on an affair of this sort without
               people noticing it. I handled the matter with as much discretion as I could. </p>
            <p>Of course, it was impossible to pretend that he was merely a friend. I could not get
               away with that. So I told every one that he was an admirer, and I showed the presents
               he had given me, and I induced him to escort me to certain social functions.</p>
            <p>People became accustomed to seeing us together. They were very indulgent and assumed
               that we were engaged. Every one knew his wife had been gone several years, and they
               assumed that he would, in time, be divorced and, of course, then would marry me. I
               cultivated this idea. But I was mighty careful to give no inkling of the intimacy of
               our relations. People never suspected that my lover had a latchkey, and that he came
               back to my house after my boys were abed.</p>
            <p>Of course, I knew there were many people who gossiped about us. That was my fault. I
               was too garrulous. I could scarcely keep my secret. I was so foolishly in love that I
               was always talking about him. Out of a clear sky, I would find myself telling this or
               that woman that Jerry had taken me here or there or he had given me such and such a
               present. Then, of course, I was wearing far more expensive clothes than they knew I
               could afford. However I had the foresight always to end my confidences by saying that
               he had been separated so long from his wife, and it was only a matter of time before
               he would be divorced.</p>
            <p>As time passed, I became more and more anxious to legitimize our relations.</p>
            <p>Finally I summoned the courage to speak to him about it. I said, <q>Jerry, every one
                  asks me when we are going to be married</q>.</p>
            <p>He gave me a quick, queer look, then answered with mock seriousness, <q>A man should
                  be off with the old love before he is on with the new</q>.</p>
         
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p><q>Then why don’t you get off with the old love?</q> I said daringly.</p>
            <p>Her frowned at that and, after a moment, he said, <q>Ethel, you knew I was married
                  when we started this affair. It’s not so easy to get a divorce. I have no
                  grounds</q>.</p>
            <p><q>What about desertion? Isn’t that grounds enough</q>.</p>
            <p><q>No—my wife never deserted me</q>.</p>
            <p>He scowled, stood up, and seemed to kind of shake himself. Then he said, <q>Let’s not
                  discuss this—there’s a good girl</q>.</p>
            <p>But though I did not discuss it, it was on my mind. I could think of nothing else. I
               told myself, there was only one solution of our problem—divorce and marriage. I
               wanted him to marry me. Marriage became an obsession with me. And I kenw we were
               being talked about and suspected. I saw that in women’s faces—and men’s too. So I
               cast about for ways and means to force him to take some definite action.</p>
            <p>One day I said to him with assumed lightness, <q>You know, Jerry, if you don’t marry
                  me, I can sue you for damages</q>.</p>
            <p>He laughed back at me. </p>
       
            <p>After a moment he said, <q>My wife’s my insurance!</q></p>
            <p>I could have screamed—but I had to pretend to smile. </p>
           
            <p><q>What would happen</q>, I said, <q>if your wife and I should come face to
               face?</q></p>
           
            <p>He came back swiftly, as if the question amused him, <q><emph>She’d</emph>
               win!</q></p>
            <p>I hated her with the intensest hate. What right had she to all this power over him? I
               was being his real wife—not she—she was away out in California, amusing herself with
               her silly writing.</p>
            <p>How I wished and longed to say as much to him; but I did not dare. There was always
               something about him that held me at arm’s length and, as I have said, she was the one
               sensitive tabpp subject between us.</p>
            <p>My love for him grew more and more intense, and I had the desperate feeling that his
               was waning. In my desperation to hold him, I did indiscreet and foolish things. One
               day at a luncheon, one of the women said, <q>Isn’t Mr. Wallace married?</q></p>
            <p><q>Oh, they’ve been separated for ages</q>, I returned with assumed lightness. Then,
               plunging in further, I leaned over and said confidentially, <q>He’s going on to Reno
                  in a few weeks now to get his divorce</q>.</p>
            <p>Now I was up against it! I had to make good that boast. I knew the woman I had told
               it to would spread the story everywhere. Before I realized it people would stop me on
               the street to congratulate me. I worked my head to think out some way by which I
               could force him actually to go to Reno, to get a quick divorce. Once free, I felt
               sure I could induce him to marry me. I gave a dinner party, and invited twenty
               guests. Then I had a friend of mine—my lawyer, in fact—announce my engagement to
               Jerry Wallace. I didn’t dare to look at Jerry sitting next to me. But as I smiled
               happily, I knew he must be staring at me in utter amazement. I knew I had done a
               bold, wild, daring thing. How would he take it? What would he do? They drank a toast
               to us.</p>
            <p>Then every one crowded about him, shaking his hand, congratulating him, and so forth.
               When they were all gone, and we were standing in the reception hall, he spoke rather
               grimly.</p>
            <p><q>Well, Ethel, it seems you have put me on the spot</q>.</p>
        
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>I pretended I did not know what he meant. I had been as surprised as he was when Mr.
               Maclean, who, I said, must have been a little drunk, had made the announcement.
               Anyway, I declared, since we had been going everywhere together, naturally people did
               think we would marry. He stared at me in his odd, almost cold way, and then he
               said:</p>
            <p><q>As a gentleman, of course there’s only one thing for me to do</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Yes—yes! What are you going to do, Jerry?</q></p>
            <p>It seemed as if he would never answer. Then I saw that his thoughtful expression had
               somehow softened.</p>
            <p><q>Poor little girl!</q> he said almost tenderly. That was too much for me. I broke
               into wild weeping, and he put his arms about me and comforted me. While I cried, he
               kept reassuring me. I was not to worry any longer. He would do what I wanted. He’d go
               to Reno. There would be a divorce. After that—well—he spoke in his whimsical way: It
               would all be on the knees of the gods.</p>
            <p><q>You mean we will be married?</q> I asked tremulously.</p>
            <p>There was something almost humble in his voice as he answered, <q>If you’ll have
                  me</q>.</p>
            <p>Have him! I felt almost insanely happy!</p>
            <p>A week later he left, by automobile, for Reno. I went part of the way with him. It
               would be a five-day trip by <pb n="94"/></p>
            <p>motor. I would have given anything in the world to accompany him. But it was not to
               be and, although I journeyed back to Council City, my heart went with him.</p>
            <p>I began to count the days. Six weeks was the legal term of residence. He wrote to me
               at intervals of once or twice a week, and his letters were like himself, curiously
               guarded, and curt in tone. He wrote of his trip, of the climate, of his camp at Lake
               Tahoe, the Nevada side, of Reno, with its hectic atmosphere. Not one word or
               expression of love, save in the end, when he would sign his letters
                  <q>Affectionately, Gerald Wallace</q>. Never Jerry—always his full, formal name. I
               tried to write letters to him that would match his own—but I had already sent him
               several passionate love letters, reeking with my longing for him, and my hopes for
               our future. </p>
            <p>He had left Council City in the big car which I had thought was mine. As I had no
               other car, I was handicapped in getting around; so I bought an inexpensive 
                  coupé, and I wrote him about it, expecting him to send me a
               check by return mail to pay for it: but I received no such check.</p>
    
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>I was frightfully restless during this long time of waiting, and I affected a gayety
               that, at times, mounted almost to hysteria. I did the most imprudent things. In my
               anxiety to retain the respect and good will of the social world of which I had always
               been a part, I told every one that Mr. Wallace was in Reno for the purpose of
               acquiring a residence to secure a divorce. Friends began to give me engagement
               showers I had to live up to the role of an engaged woman, and I bought a hope chest
               and acquired a marvelous trousseau.</p>
            <p>I found myself acting, even to myself. Over and over again I would tell myself that I
               was engaged to Jerry Wallace; that he was coming back to marry me.</p>
            <p>I couldn’t keep my mouth shut. I even talked to the girls in the department stores
               where I bought my trousseau. Soon every one in town was discussing my impending
               marriage.</p>
            <p>People took it as a matter of course, and they thought that I was so lucky and so
               happy. I was going to marry one of the best catches in the town, a wealthy man; a
               handsome man, and one who must love me so much that he had actually gone to Reno to
               divorce his wife, in order to be free to marry me. Remember, Council City was a small
               city, taken all in all, and every one in the social world knew the affairs of
               everybody else. In a way, I was popular, but I knew too, that many of the women were
               jealous of me. Women are always jealous of members of their sex who are attractive to
               men. I was demonstrating that my beauty and charm and won for me one of the most
               desirable men in our town.</p>
            <p>Five weeks went by, four of which had been spent by Jerry Wallace in Nevada. I was
               obsessed by an inner fever. As I have said, I am not clever, and I found it difficult
               to write letters that I felt would interest him. I had recourse to pamphlets and
               books, from which I copiously plagiarized. I wrote him all about trees and nature and
               birds and brooks—and God knows what. I think now I must have been awfully silly to
               write him like that, and I can imagine what his reaction must have been, for he hated
               affectation and anything that was not natural. But I had to write something, and
               since he did not write me love letters, I had to fill mine with what I then flattered
               myself were literary phrases. What a fool I was!</p>
            <p>I made trips to his office, on one excuse and another. I learned from his office
               manager that he was in almost daily touch with Jerry, by long distance telephone, and
               I envied him and resented the fact that Jerry had not telephoned or telegraphed me
               once. </p>
            <p>One day I went to see his lawyer, and I almost passed out when he told me that Jerry
               had gone on to Los Angeles to see his wife about a final financial settlement. I was
               filled with a haunting terror. I dreaded the thought of his again coming into
               personal contact with his wife. I think I must have looked strange, for his lawyer
               explained to me that this meeting was necessary. He reassured me, and said that Mrs.
               Wallace’s lawyers had already corresponded with her husband’s Nevada attorneys, and
               the terms of the settlement had been agreed upon. He said that her lawyers had
               declared Mrs. Wallace was agreeable to the divorce.</p>
            <p>This, at least, gave me some relief. She was not going to contest the suit. None the
               less my hatred for her deepened, and I could not endure the thought of that meeting
               between them. What would they say to each other? What would they think? How would she
               look to him? I recalled his words, <q>She had everything a man wants</q>.</p>
            <p>To add to my distress at this time, he did not write to me or send me word for
               another two weeks, and I had no way of addressing him, for I did not know whether he
               was back in Nevada or still with her in Los Angeles. There was absolutely nothing I
               could do, save wait—wait—wait!</p>
       
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>The first I knew that he was on his way back to council City was when I read a note
               in the paper to the effect that he was expected in town on Saturday. You can imagine
               how I felt! That a newspaper should have word of his expected arrival (probably
               through his office) before I, who expected to be his wife, had. And I had to smile at
               people I met on the street, or who called upon me, and pretend that, of course, I
               knew he was coming, but that I had hoped to keep it a secret! A secret! As if I could
               keep anything that concerned him a secret!</p>
            <p>Finally his telegram came. He would arrive Saturday morning, and would call upon me
               at two. That was all the wire contained. It was signed with his full name.</p>
            <p> I spent half the day before he arrived at the beauty parlor. I spent the morning of
               the day, itself, in bed—to calm and quiet myself. I sent my boys away, for I wanted
               to see him alone—just we two, face to face again. Then after lunch, from one o’clock
               on, I began to wait for him. At two o’clock to the minute I heard the front door bell
               ring (he did not use his latchkey!) and forgetting my instruction to my maid, I
               rushed to the door, pulled it open and precipitated myself into his arms. We were
               standing in the hall. I became gradually conscious <pb n="95"/>of the fact that he was trying to release my arms from around his neck—that he was freeing himself of my grasp. When that was done, he gave himself a kind of little shake, and then he looked down at me and I saw that his face was stern and cold. </p>
            <p><q>Let us go inside</q>, he said. His voice was calm, level, cool. It had a guarded
               sound. I didn’t know what to do, what to say, what to think. I followed him into the
               living room and I sat down weakly on the bid davenport, hoping he would sit beside
               me; but he remained standing by the fireplace, his face averted. After a moment I
               said tremulously:</p>
            <p><q>Whatever is the matter, Jerry. You are acting so strangely</q>.</p>
            <p>At that he looked at me from under his knotted brows.</p>
            <p><q>I’m sorry, Ethel</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Sorry—for what?</q></p>
            <p>I was a prey to a horrid premonition. I was afraid to hear him speak.</p>
            <p>His chin set in an almost dogged line and he said, <q>Sorry to be obliged to tell you
                  that it is all over between us</q>.</p>
            <p>A dead silence fell. I was trying to take that in, to comprehend the full import of
               his words. I did not know my own voice, and my throat felt dry.</p>
            <p><q>Over? What do you mean?</q></p>
            <p>He spoke slowly, almost as if he were choosing his words.</p>
            <p><q>I don’t want to hurt you: but it is better to tell you the truth. I am not going
                  to marry you. I did not get a divorce</q>.</p>
            <p>I half stated up, and he said roughly, <q>Stay where you are. I’ll try to explain. My
                  wife and I have become reconciled</q>.</p>
        
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>Again that long, long, silence. Then I began to sob, to beg, to implore, to threaten,
               to taunt him. I accused him of baseness, of deceit, of brutality. I said I’d kill
               myself; I’d kill him; I’d kill her. Ah, you all know what a <q>scorned woman</q> says
               at such a time.</p>
            <p>He merely stared down at me, his jaw squared, and in a pause in my outcry, he said
               firmly, <q>It’s true, I have done you a wrong. But I would be doing you a greater
                  wrong if I married you or continued relations with you when I love another
                  woman</q>.</p>
            <p>At that I screamed.</p>
            <p><q>It’s a lie! It’s a lie! You love <emph>me! </emph>I have been in your
               arms, and you have told me you loved me!</q></p>
            <p>His voice was firm as fate.</p>
            <p><q>No—I never told you that, Ethel. I never lied to you. I will not say I was
                  indifferent to you—you attracted me immensely, but your attraction was mainly
                  sexual, and no woman can hold a man purely through sex</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Hell hath no fury like a woman scorned</q>, says the poet. How true that is! I
               felt all hell raging inside me. I don’t know what I said. I talked like a wild woman.
               I fought like a tigress to hold him—he, who had never been really mine!</p>
            <p>Then I pleaded, <q>Oh, please, please think it all over. Don’t cast me off—don’t
                  discard me. Wait a bit—wait—wait—</q></p>
            <p><q>But my wife is coming—she will arrive within a few days</q>.</p>
            <p><q>No—no! You can’t bring her here. she can’t come to this town</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Certainly she is coming here</q>.</p>
         <pb n="96"/>
            <p><q>But don’t you see? Can’t you understand what that will mean? The whole town knows
                  of our engagement. How can I face the ridicule, the talk, the curiosity? I’ll be
                  ostracized, but! Everybody in town will be talking about us. Oh, can’t you see
                  them at the teas and bridges? Oh, don’t, don’t bring her here!</q></p>
            <p>After a moment he said, <q>Of course, we’ll have to face the music. There’s bound to
                  be a lot of talk; but if my wife is willing to face it, we should be too. What’s
                  more, I am willing to send you on an extended trip abroad. How would you like
                  that?</q></p>
            <p><q>I don’t intend to leave this city</q>, I shouted at him. <q>It’s my town—not hers.
                  She’s been living in California. She hates Council City. Why should I get out for
                  her? Answer me that! I won’t fo, I tell you. I won’t go!</q></p>
            <p><q>Very well. Stay then and take your medicine</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I’ll make things hot for her—I’ll—</q></p>
            <p>His face hardened; his eyes had almost a look of hate in them. His eyes held mine,
               and were dead cold.</p>
            <p><q>Look here, Ethel. I want to do the fair thing by you, but I warn you if you do one
                  single thing to injure my wife, you’ll suffer for it</q>.</p>
            <p>At that I began to laugh hysterically.</p>
            <p><q>Make me suffer, will you? Well, what do you think I’m doing now? You can’t make me
               suffer <emph>more!</emph></q></p>

         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            
            <p><q>You went into this affair with your eyes wide open</q>. he said, speaking coldly
               and incisively. <q>You knew from the first that I was a married man, you broadcast an
                  engagement that could not exist. None the less, I was willing to play your game, I
                  went to Reno, fully intending to divorce my wife, and to marry you. I did this as
                  a gentleman; but I could not carry my plan through. It was humanly impossible, for
                  the moment I saw my wife I knew that I still loved her; that I had never stopped
                  loving her; that I had fallen in love with her all over again</q>.</p>
            <p>His eyes were gleaming. He seemed almost to have forgotten he was speaking to me. I
               could see he was reliving that meeting with his wife after their separation of over
               three years. His voice grew husky. </p>
            <p><q>The moment I looked at her, my arms ached to hold her. I had one desire—to take my
                  wife in my arms!</q></p>
            <p>I couldn’t bear it any longer. No woman could have. I flung myself at him. I tried to
               claw him. He held my hands down at my sides, and forcibly thrust me back on the
               davenport. </p>
            <p><q>Try to compose yourself</q>, he said. <q>Nothing you can say or do now can alter
                  things</q>.</p>
            <p>But the touch of his hands aroused a fire within me. Something broke all up inside
               me. I wanted to feel his dear arms around me once again, if only for the last time. I
               was mad for the pressure of his lips on mine. </p>
            <p><q>Oh, Jerry</q>, I implored, <q>take me in your arms again. Kiss me for the last
                  time</q>.</p>
            <p>He stared at me, not unkindly, but strangely unmoved. His words cut me to the
               soul.</p>
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
               <p><q>No! apart from the fact that it would not be fair to my wife, it would be
                     odious to me</q>.</p>
               <p>This is my story. Imagine, if you can, what my life now is. I live in the same
                  town with Gerald Wallace and his wife. We belong to the same social set, though
                  now I am not invited to people’s homes as I was. I am being cold-shouldered,
                  ostracized, cut by some people. Others, pitying me, come to my house to console
                  me. But even they tire of me as there is only one subject I can talk about.</p>
               <p>From being one of the most sought-after women in our town, I know I have become
                  the very laughing-stock of Council City, I know that I am the subject of whisper
                  and joke at every tea and bridge. I know that the worst is believed of me.</p>
               <p>Mrs. Wallace’s arrival created a sensation. Society was not slow in showing which
                  they their favor turned. Morbidly, avidly I read the society personals. They are
                  giving teas, dinners, receptions, parties for her—Mrs. Gerald Wallace! As for me—I
                  am paying the penalty—the price exacted of a woman who breaks the Seventh
                  Commandment! </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>