<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesBookweek1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books, Literary Notes, Etc</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Eaton Reeve, Winnifred</name></author>.
                           <title level="a">Books, Literary Notes, Etc</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-11-13">November 13,
                           1923</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                        18</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">[Begins to talk about Bookweek and Salverson]</note>--></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="readyForProof">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-12" status="readyForProof">Ready for proof.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesBookweek1">
      <body>
         <head>BOOKS, LITERARY NOTES, ETC.</head>
         <opener><byline>(By <name ref="pers:LW1">WINNIFRED EATON REEVE</name>)</byline></opener>
         <div>
            <p>An important event in the impending Book Week, is the coming to Calgary of the
               distinguished Canadian poet, <name ref="pers:WM1">Wilson McDonald</name>, who will
               give a recital in the Public Library on Nov. 19, under the auspices of the Canadian
               clubs, the Press and Literary clubs and the Canadian Authors’ association.</p>
            <p>Practically unknown until the last year, <name ref="pers:WM1">Mr. McDonald</name>’s
               poetry attracted the attention of the critical and literary world by its beauty and
               power. There are scores of would-be poets, rhymsters, poetasters and writers of
               various sorts of verse, but there are in the Dominion of Canada scarcely a dozen who
               may claim the title of poet. To this limited company, <name ref="pers:WM1">Wilson
                  McDonald</name> unquestionably belongs. There is a gentle wistfulness and
               melancholy pervades many of his lines, yet he possesses a dramatic gift which is
               reminiscent of Masefield.</p>
            <p>A volume of poetry may be likened to a casket of jewels. Some jewel cases, we knew,
               contian paste and tawdry imitations; but some there are that are full of rare and
               precious gems. A beautiful poem is a finer thing than a rare gem, for the jewel
               charms but the eye, while the poem reaches the heart. The poet is the sensitive
               medium through which the noblest and the loveliest thoughts of heaven and earth find
               expression.</p>
            <p>The birth of a great poet in any land is as important an event as the discovery of
               radium. The poet who is coming to Calgary has received high praise from the critics
               of the east and from English and American lovers of poetry and literature. The
               Toronto Saturday night says of him: <q>A new elemental force in poetry—perhaps the
                  first since Whitman</q>. The San Francisco Star declares his <q>Song of
                  Brotherhood</q> might well be read into the Hall of Conference at Versailles. From
               William Archer, dean of English critics, from <name ref="pers:BC2">Bliss
                  Carmen</name>, from the English poet Masefield, and from many others come
               enthusiastic appreciation of his poetry.</p>
            <p>Timid, delicate, fragile as his own poems, the Canadian poet is travelling, like a
               minstrel of old, from city to city in Canada, reading to appreciative audiences the
               poems that are certain to bring him sure fame. If Canada is cold to this native son
               of genius, other lands will not hesitate to acclaim him. But a few years ago there
               was in Canada a young artist, whose work was shown at various exhibitions in the
               west, and I believe in one of the cities of the east. His work, though receiving high
               praise from art critics was practically ignored in this country. He could not sell
               enough pictures to keep a roof over his head. He was driven almost to the perilous
               edge of starvation. Friends assisted him to leave his native country, which had
               failed to appreciate or even allow him the boon of a livelihood from his work. Today
               he is one of the most famous artists in Europe. His work created a furore in Paris.
               He is recognized in New York as one of the greatest of modern artists, but, and this
               to a lover of Canada, is surely a bitter ddrop—he is proclaimed and known not as a
               Canadian artist, but an American.</p>
            <p>Time will make of this city of the Foothills something more than an agricultural and
               business center. In a measure we have already our intellectual and our cultural life,
               but that side of us still is in the growing stage. Nevertheless there are many in
               this city who will appreciate and delight to honor the Canadian poet, of whom Rivert
               Norwood, M.A., D.C.L., has written:</p>
            <p><q>Do not stifle his genius by indifference. Honor him. Let him feel your pride in
                  him. He is one of the greatest poets of the Anglo-Saxon race</q>. And he is a
               Canadian!</p>
            <p>If I were asked to name the most significant, the most important work of fiction by a
               Canadian author published during the past year, I should be inclined to say, <q>The
                  Viking Heart</q>. This is the work of <name ref="pers:LS1">Laura Goodman
                  Salversen</name>. It is a first novel, though a volume of poems from her pen was
               accepted by American and Canadian publishers prior to the publication of this
               work.</p>
            <p>The word <q>epic</q> has been used so often lately that I hesitate to pronounce this
               book to be <q>an epic of the soil</q>, which indeed it is. It is a great piece of
               work. The author conceived a canvas of no mean size on which to print what, in a way,
               may be accounted a masterpiece. She did not confine her plot to one or two
               characters. She set out to write the saga of a tribe—immigrants from Iceland who,
               rendered homeless, when the mountain under whose benevolent shadow their farms and
                  <unclear reason="faded">hamlets</unclear> had sheltered, burst into violent
               volcanic eruption and drove them into enforced exile. I have never read a more
               graphic and at the same time simpler description of a flight of a terrified people as
                  <name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> pictures in the first few chapters of
               her book. Almost one sees the flames and feels the heat of the storming lava and
               fire. Almost one hears the voice of that Rachel, who could not be comforted, when her
               glorious young son turned back to succor the sheep trapped in those walls of fire and
               perished beneath the ashes and molten flames. Even as the exiles from the land of
               Evangeline, so down unending the rivers and over strange, forbidding, desolate lands,
               wandered the Icelanders seeking what they fondly believed would prove to be the land
               of promise—Manitoba, at that time almost a barren wilderness, where substance was for
               him only the strength, courage and the heart of a Viking. There is in this narrative
               such a ring of sincerity and truth that we feel as if we were reading not a work of
               art and fiction, but the human life story of Canadian pioneers. One has a sense also
               of shame and wrath at the callous treatment of these pitiful exiles by the then
               immigration authorities, who separated families from each other, assigned parents to
               bare, unbroken lands in immigration settlements and put the growing young sons and
               daughters out to service with strangers 50 to 100 miles apart.</p>
            <p>Of the family, whose life story <name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> records,
               but one survived the ravages of hunger, cold and the fearful scourge of smallpox
               which devastated the unsanitary camps of those bitter days.</p>
            <p><q>The Viking Heart</q> has been compared with the work of such master writers as
               Tolstoy. It possesses something of the slow gathering force of de Maupassant’s <q>Une
                  Vie</q>, but is more than the life story of an individual. It is the tragic saga
               of a race.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> was born in the city of Winnipeg,
               Manitoba, but her parents were Icelanders. She writes with authority, information and
               first-hand knowledge. Her uncle is the present governor-general of Iceland. Of
               interest to Calgary is the fact that she is now a resident here, her husband, in the
               employ of the C.N.R., having recently been transferred from Edmonton to Calgary.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
