<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesHale1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books by Onoto Watanna: Canadian Cities of Romance by Katharine Hale</title>
            <title>Literary Notes [Hale]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna, Onoto</name></author>. <title
                           level="a">Books by Onoto Watanna: Canadian Cities of Romance by Katharine
                           Hale</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                              Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-07-09">July 9,
                           1923</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                        13</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">[The series shifts in name and Eaton goes solely by Watanna here]</note>-->.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-30" status="published">Complete.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-27" status="inProgress">Missing some pers
            ref.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesHale1">
      <body>
         <head>BOOKS</head>
         <opener><byline>By <name ref="pers:LW1">ONOTO WATANNA</name></byline></opener>
         <div type="section">
            <head>CANADIAN CITIES OF ROMANCE BY <name ref="pers:KH1">KATHARINE HALE</name></head>

            <p>I first heard of <name ref="pers:KH1">Katharine Hale</name>’s <q>Canadian Cities of
                  Romance</q> through an English source. Mrs. Neville Chamberlain, wife of England’s
               postmaster-general, wrote me that she was reading <q>a most lovely book by a Canadian
                  poet</q> and a clipping from a discriminating review was sent me.</p>

            <p>Highly praised by the English critics in its fourth edition in the United States,
               this charming book, concerned with our <q>cities of romance</q> should be in every
               Canadian home.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:KH1">Katharine Hale</name> is the author of several books of poetry,
               and she is also a talented professional vocalist and dramatic teacher. The wife of
               one of Toronto’s big business men (<name ref="pers:JG3">John Garvin</name>) she finds
               time each year to make a tour through Canada and the United States, singing and
               reciting old Canadian folk songs, tribal melodies, Canadian chansons, songs of the
               modern composers and poets, and original lyrics and poems from her own pen.</p>

            <p>She is possessed of a vivid, sensitive personality, which is revealed in her poetry.
               Of this latest book, <name ref="pers:CR3">Charles D. Roberts</name> has said: <q>Only
                  a poet could have written it</q>, and <name ref="pers:BK1">Basil King</name>: <q>A
                  Canadian compelled to live outside his own country, must find that this book takes
                  him home again</q>. <name ref="pers:KH1">Katharine Hale</name> belongs to that
               limited country of whom <name ref="pers:TG1">Theophile Gautier</name> has said:
                     <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Pour qui le monde visible existe</foreign></q>.
               Nothing of charm or interest has escaped her in her pilgrimmages through our cities.
               With the vision of an artist, and the pen of a poet, she has set down an imperishable
               record of the lovely remainders of our Canadian cities of romance.</p>

            <p>It is quite possible that this book will never be listed among the <q>best
                  sellers</q>, but book lovers will find a permanent place for it on the shelf with
               the classics.</p>

            <p>Many friends of the late <name ref="pers:JW4">Jean Webster</name>, author of Daddy
               Long Legs and the Patty books, and niece of Mark Twain, have remarked upon the
               resemblance between <name ref="pers:KH1">Miss Hale</name> and <name ref="pers:JW4"
                  >Miss Webster</name>. There is the same charming irregularity of feature,
               quaintness of expression, a quality of sensitive animation that seems to pervade
               personality both fine and fragile. As strange as the physical resemblance is the
               similarity of their handwriting, and many believe that the living poetess and singer
               is possessed also with that lovely human nature that distinguished and endeared <name
                  ref="pers:JW4">Jean Webster</name> to all who were fortunate enough to know
               her.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <head>CANADIAN COPYRIGHT BILL</head>

            <p>The passing month of the Canadian copyright bill has made a profound impression upon
               authors in Canada. Several are preparing to leave Canada and take up residence in the
               United States, where they declare laws are not especially leveled at their craft. The
               Canadian Bookman, commenting upon the act, says:</p>

            <p><q>It is felt by the authors that not only have their interests been scarified, but
                  in failing to adhere in full measure to the Berne convention, the Dominion
                  parliament has exhibited a restricted national sense, and surrendered
                  ignominiously to the self interested demands of the printed trade interests. . . .
                  . . It gives authors of union countries, other than natives, absolute control over
                  publications of their works in Canada. There in that provision is the rub. Authors
                  of other countries get protection not vouchsafed to authors of our own land. The
                  authors of Canada are wondering why they are thus discriminated against, and are
                  convinced that the ‘nigger<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SL1">This is an
                     offensive racial slur. Please see our <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note
                        on language</ref>.</note> in the woodpile’ is the fact as expressed in the
                  senate when the bill received its third reading, that there are more printers than
                  authors in Canada, and that the desires of the former must take precedence in the
                  eyes of legislators, in utter disregard of the principle at stake</q>.</p>

            <p>It is true enough as maintained by Senator Lougheed, who was one of the sponsors of
               this act, that there are more printers than authors in Canada. It is also true that
               such an act will tend to further reduce the number of authors in Canada. In
                  <q>protecting</q> the printers and publishers at the expense and sacrifice of
               Canada’s authors it is possible that the legislators ignored the fact that the
               printer is safeguarded by regular employment and steady salaries. He has his union
               hours and his union pay, but the author is largely dependent upon his inspiration,
               and seldom has a steady market for his work. The publisher on the other hand,
                  <q>holds the purse</q> as it were. Nevertheless both publisher and printer have
               their dependence upon the original product of the author, and by author I use the
               term in the larger sense, meaning all types of writers, whose product must pass
               through the printing press. Without the author, in fact, the publisher and the
               printer cannot exist. This act is a severe and serious blow to the Canadian author,
               and will have detrimental effects upon our future literature. Such an act should be
               exposed. The sponsors of it may find themselves pilloried in print by the pens of the
               very men and women they have injured. It would seem as if no statesman of a wide
               vision, no real well-wisher of Canada would desire to see a decrease in our literary
               production. Nevertheless it is a fact, that while other countries are conserving and
               cultivating and encouraging their talent, by this act Canada <choice>
                  <sic>cooly</sic>
                  <corr>coolly</corr>
               </choice> opens the gate which leads to expatriation for the author or the
               alternative fate of a starvation livelihood in his own country.</p>

            <p>Can anyone wonder why such authors as <name ref="pers:AS2">Arthur Stringer</name>,
                  <name ref="pers:BK1">Basil King</name>, <name ref="pers:AR1">Agnes Repplier</name>
               and many others live in the United States in preference to the country they love. It
               is simply a matter of self protection, which the adage assures us is the first law of
               nature. If laws were made discriminating against the lawyer, the doctor, the
               tradesman, in Canada, I have my doubts whether they would continue to function in
               Canada.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:AS2">Arthur Stringer</name> passed through Calgary last week, looking
               as big and wholesome as ever. He is living now in a lovely part of New Jersey,
               Mountain Lakes, which he tells me has become quite a center for the artist and
               writers of New York. He is writing a new novel of our prairie and ranching life.
               Though forced, for financial reasons, to live outside of Canada, <name ref="pers:AS2"
                  >Arthur</name> is still wholeheartedly Canadian, and he told me that all of his
               future novels would be of this country. That is good news, because <name
                  ref="pers:AS2">Arthur Stringer</name> is one of our foremost Canadian authors and
               poets.</p>

            <p>The Calgary branch of the Canadian Authors’ association loses in <name ref="pers:AM1"
                  >Dr. MacRae</name> one of its most valued members and its vice-president. Author
               of the History of Alberta, though not author of the Who’s Who Gallery, which against
               his will was injected into his work by commercial interests, he is an outstanding
               figure in the literary and educational life of this city. The association recently
               honored Dr. MacRae at a banquet, where eulogistic speeches were made by such notables
               as his worship Mayor Webster, Consul S. C. Reat, Dr. Johnston, Dr. Scott, W. M.
               Davison, Father Cameron, P. Harcourt O’Reilley and Mrs. Marshall Witty and gay as
               were the speeches, an undernote of sadness at the though of the parting from one so
               honored and loved was discernible, and <foreign xml:lang="sco">Auld Lang
                  Syne</foreign> was sung by all standing with considerable emotion.</p>



         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
