<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesLauriston1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books, Literary Notes, etc [Lauriston]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl299"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Eaton Reeve,
                     Winnifred</name></author>. <title level="a">Books, Literary Notes, etc</title>.
                     <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">Morning
                     Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1924-02-05">5 Feb 1924</date>, p.
                     <biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from the University of Calgary archives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-07" status="published">Added person references for Douglas Durkin.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="published">Added person
            references for Victor Lauriston and Bliss Carman.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="published">Proofed and set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="inProgress">Transcribed. Downloaded
            document from Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-24" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesLauriston1">
      <body>
         <head>Books, Literary Notes, Etc.</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Eaton Reeve</name></byline>
         </opener>

         <div>
            <p>In a recent number of the Top-Notch Magazine there appeared a <q>Canadian</q> story
               by an American author. The story is entitled <q>The Terror of the North</q>. The
               following description will amaze and amuse Canadians, and give some idea of how
               Canada is described in American fiction.</p>
            <p><q>The man who carried the mall from Regina to Saskatoon cracked his whip over the
                  shaggy backs of his six huskies and peered into the encompassing blackness. It was
                  somewhere near midday, but almost as dark as midnight, for masses of blue-black
                  clouds hid the sun, and a storm was raging in the heights of the north</q>.</p>
            <p>Not to be outdone in description of Canada, another American author, one who writes
               with skill, pictures a baseball match at Guelph, Ontario, watched by a stolid
               audience of Indians and squaws in blankets and feather headdresses.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:VL1">Victor Lauriston</name>, the Canadian author of <q>The
                  Twenty-first Burr</q>, draws attention to the fact that Indians of that sort in
               Guelph would draw a bigger crowd than a baseball match, for <q>the baseball germ in
                  the Royal City is so old a resident that the place is pretty well immunised. The
                  Guelph ‘Maple Leafs’ toured the States in the days when the great American pastime
                  was still young</q>.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:VL1">Mr. Lauriston</name>, in a recent letter, tells of a personal
               experience with an American editor in New York to whom he was trying to sell some
               stories whose locale was Chatham, Ontario.</p>
            <p><q>A neighbor of yours writes for us quite a bit</q>, said the editor.</p>
            <p><q>A neighbor! Who is he?</q></p>
            <p><q><name ref="pers:DD1">Douglas Durkin</name>. You’re from Chatham, aren’t you? Well,
                  he lives right near you</q>.</p>
            <p><q><name ref="pers:DD1">Durkin</name> lives in the west — near Winnipeg</q>.</p>
            <p><q>That’s not far from Chatham, is it?</q>
               <q>Oh, no. Only about a thousand miles</q>.</p>
            <p>On February 8 Calgary will have an opportunity of seeing Canada’s poet laureate in
               recital at the Central Methodist church. This may be the last time that an
               opportunity will be afforded Calgarians of seeing Canada’s best loved poet, <name ref="pers:BC2">Bliss Carman</name>, for his health has been poor of late years,
               and the traveling exacts a heavy toll from a man of Mr. Carman’s age.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, did you once see Shelley!</q> Those words still throb with the eager hero
               worship of the poet that wrote them. The time may come when others will ask us
               whether we had actually seen Canada’s Carman.</p>
            <p>It is said that the Normal school, from which a large attendance had been expected,
               have invited the Normal school of Carbon to come to Calgary for a dance on the night
               of the poet’s recital. An effort is to be made to induce the Normal school to change
               their invitation to read <q>recital</q> instead of dance, or to bring their friends
               to hear the Canadian poet prior to the dance.</p>
            <p>Mrs. McClung, in her address before the local council of women at their recent
               banquet, pointed out that the coming of the Canadian poet to Calgary was an event
               that should be noted by all who are lovers of poetry and are patriotic.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:WM1">Wilson McDonald</name>, the Canadian poet, was a recent visitor
               for a couple of days in Calgary. While here he attended the Gladys Attree special
               performance of exhibition dancing, and expressed a deep interest in the Little
               Theater movement in Calgary. <name ref="pers:WM1">Mr. McDonald</name> is the author
               of an opera entitled <q>In Sunny France</q>. It was put on in Toronto by Hart House,
               the <q>Little Theater</q> of that city, and ran continuously for a couple of weeks,
               playing to capacity audiences. It has also been put on by other Little Theaters, and
               is now being rehearsed in Moose Jaw, under the auspices of the local council of
               women,</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:WM1">Mr. McDonald</name>, as soon as he learned of the Little Theater
               movement in Calgary, immediately offered his opera for an initial vehicle for the
               association. Besides giving his opera ot the newly formed association, <name ref="pers:WM1">Mr. McDonald</name> is willing to come to Calgary and personally
               rehearse the piece, as he has done in other cities. Besides writing the libretto and
               lyrics, he is also the author of the music, and composed the dances, and he plays one
               of the parts himself.</p>
            <p>This generous offer may well appeal to the association which is to be formed some day
               this week at an open meeting to which the public is urged to come.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>