<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesMacdonald1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Wilson Macdonald</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a">Wilson
                           Macdonald</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The
                              Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1924-04-05">April 5,
                           1924</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>. </bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-08-23" status="published">Encoded. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesMacdonald1">
      <body>
         <head>Wilson MacDonald</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By</byline>
            <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto
                  Watanna</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>One of the greatest of Canadian poets is in our city. He came here at the invitation
               of the Tan-nis-uk chapter of the I.O.D.E. For a couple of weeks he has been
               rehearsing his opera, <q>In Sunny France</q>, which was produced last night at the
               Grand theater. Wherever this opera has appeared and incidentally it has been produced
               in Toronto, Vancouver, Victoria and numerous other well known cities, praise has been
               bestowed upon it. - Hector Charlesworth, musical critic of the Toronto Saturday
               night, and generally conceded to be one of the foremost critics in Canada, in a
               review of the opera wrote as follows:</p>
            <p>‘‘The solid merits of Mr. MacDonald as a writer of tuneful and amusing lyrics need
               little advertisement for his fellow-Canadians. It is these lyrics which are superior
               in quality to those of most recent musical comedies emanating from Broadway that give
                  <q>In Sunny France</q> its claim to critical attention and public support. The
               framework of the play seems to have been devised to give it a most effective
               background. The tale is fantastic and fresh, melodious music and the facile and
               felicitous verses carry the show.</p>
            <p><q>Mr. MacDonald shows excellent gifts as a light comedian in the role of a London
                  Johnny and his three songs <q>Johnny from London Town</q>, <q>The Taxi Girl</q>
                  and <q>Legerdemain</q> are capital, especially the latter which enables him to
                  show his unique gifts in parlor magic</q>.</p>
            <p>It is at best a nerve wracking and thankless task to rehearse amateurs, for the
               reason that only the most talented among them are punctilious in keeping their
               engagements and coming regularly to rehearsals. There are always some who flout rules
               and regulations that in a professional show are stiffly enforced. In the case of
               amateurs a girl comes one day to rehearsal; she is not there the next. At the
               eleventh hour she throws down a role in which she has been trained and drilled for
               days. It is folly to expect an amateur production to be of the finished quality of
               the professional. Far be it from me to criticize the actors in a play of this sort;
               on the other hand, I would not condemn the play—which, after all represents the
               sincere and arduous labor of the author—while unctuously flattering those who will be
               here after the poet is gone.</p>
            <p>And concerning poets, I will quote from what Dr. Robert Norwood, M.A., Litt. D.,
               wrote about Wilson MacDonald in the Philadelphia Record:</p>
            <p>‘‘It is not easy to measure the genius of Wilson MacDonald. As an artist he is beyond
               reproach.</p>
            <p><q>For one week MacDonald has been our guest. Philadelphia gave him instant welcome.
                  Before an audience that crowded the auditorium of the Parish House, he read his
                  unforgetable poems. It was a distinguished audience, too</q>.</p>
            <p>‘‘MacDonald has a profile not unlike Dante’s, and like Dante, he has known hell. It
               would be impossible for such a finely strung instrument as McDonald’s personality to
               escape the throb of pain. His delicate perceptions have set him forever aside for the
               height of joy and the deep of sorrow. Out of these agitations spring the poet’s music
               and message. The mark of destiny is on him.</p>
            <p>‘‘His audiences were brilliant and representative of the best thought in this city,
               of widespread love of the arts.</p>
            <p>‘‘We return him to Canada and say to our neighbors across the border:</p>
            <p>‘‘Be kind to MacDonald. He is one of the greatest poets of the Anglo-Saxon race. In
               technique, in style, in creative magic, he is the equal of any of your poets.</p>
            <p>‘‘Do not stifle his genius by indifference. Honor him. Let him feel your pride in
               him. A poet is of greater value to you, Canada, than a Wilfred Laurier, a John A.
               MacDonald. A poet more represents your glory of soul and mind than a notable banker,
               a successful stock broker, a rich farmer.</p>
            <p>A poet is your greatest asset—greater than your mines, your farms, your fisheries,
               your markets.</p>
            <p>‘‘The lad with the coat of many colors—the dreamer of many dreams—is the portent of
               your destiny, O Canada! And to him shall your sons, one day come at his enthronement
               above the seats of the money changers and of those who buy and sell.</p>
            <p><q>We give you back Wilson MacDonald in gratitude for a week of inspiration from the
                  holiness of beauty</q>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
<!-- ‘ ’ curly quote, — em dash -->
