<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesCalgary1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>News, Notes and Views about Books [Calgary Authors]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a">News,
                           Notes and Views about Books [Calgary Authors]</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1922-12-14">December 14,
                           1922</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-08" status="published">Completed. Set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-03" status="inProgress">Transcribing.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesCalgary1">
      <body>
         <head>News, Notes and Views About</head>
         <head>BOOKS</head>
         <opener><byline>BY <name ref="pers:LW1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name></byline>
            <byline>(<name ref="pers:LW1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</byline></opener>

         <div>
            <p><unclear reason="faded">It is possible that few people in Calgary are aware that the
                  oldest and one of the greatest of Canadian poets is a resident of this
                  city.</unclear></p>
            <p><unclear reason="faded"><name ref="pers:CM2">Charles Mair</name>, author of
                     <q>Tecumseh</q> and <q>Dreamland</q>, a volume of thirty-five poems, and many
                  articles and stories, is 84 years old, but his mind is as keen and his eyes as
                  bright as in the stirring days of his youth. One of our finest old timers of the
                  west, his life’s history reads like a romance. He was educated at King’s college,
                  Kingston, and it was originally intended that he should be a doctor. He came out
                  to the northwest with a construction party to open communication from the Lake of
                  the Woods to the Red River.</unclear></p>
            <p>Shortly after his marriage to Miss Eliza MacKenney, a niece of <name ref="pers:JS3"
                  >Sir John Schultz</name>, lieutenant-governor of Manitoba, he and his wife were
               taken prisoners by <name ref="pers:LR1">Riel</name>. His wife, in fact, with her
               aunt, Lady Schultz, figures in history as one of the heroines of that adventure.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:CM2">Mr. Mair</name>, in spite of his greaet age, is a delightful
               person to meet. His memory appears to be unimpaired. As he graphically traced some of
               his extraordinary experiences and adventure to me, it seemed increditable that this
               fine, gentle, old poet, had passed through such wild scenes. His escape from <name
                  ref="pers:LR1">Riel</name> in itself is as thrilling an episode as could well be
               imagined. On a stormy bitter night, he crawled through the window of his prison,
               slipped by the sentry at the gate and escaped to Portage la Prairie, travelling four
               hundred miles on snowshoes to St. Paul and on to Ontario. He still speaks with
               evident grief of the great loss he experienced at that time, when all of his precious
               manuscripts, the work of many years, were burned by <name ref="pers:LR1"
               >Riel</name>.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:CM2">Mr. Mair</name> takes an active interest in Canadian literary
               matters of today, and asked me questions concerning the Canadian Authors association,
               and the authors. In spite of his years, he by no means considers his work ended. On
               the contrary he contemplates writing his memoirs. To give some idea of this
               remarkable old man’s tenacious interest in life, and the strength and virility of
               mind and body it is only two years since he made the long trip to New Zealand for the
               purpose of visiting a married daughter, resident there, and he told me, with a smile,
               that he was none the worse for the long trip and hoped to make it again.</p>
            <p>Early last summer a manuscript was brought to me by another old-timer, who was one of
               the scouts who captured <name ref="pers:LR1">Riel</name>. His somewhat ragged
               manuscript proved to be a human document of the most intense and throbbing interest.
               True, it made no attempt at literary grace or style; the expressions were rude and
               sometimes coarse; the grammar could bear doctoring; but nevertheless it was a
               singularly interesting script, and if published should be of some historical value. I
               spoke about this man to <name ref="pers:CM2">Mr. Mair</name>, and mentioned his
               connection with the capture of <name ref="pers:LR1">Riel</name>. Instantly the poet’s
               face brightened:</p>
            <p><q>Why, I remember him well. You don’t mean to say that he is living in Calgary also?
                  Well, well! I remember when he made the capture. I was right there. <name
                     ref="pers:LR1">Riel</name> was hidden in an old shack . . . . ?</q></p>
            <p>He went into the details of that famous capture of so long ago. I could see that to
               him, at least, the happenings appeared to be as if they were but yesterday.</p>
            <p>It is strange that these two find old figures from the stirring days of the past
               should now both be residents of our city Calgary.</p>
            <p>It is becoming quite a custom for visiting authors and editors, to call upon and pay
               their respects to the veteran poet. When Professor Allison was here and, with his
               charming wife, came to see me, one of the first things he said was that they had to
               make their visit short, for they were going to call upon Canada’s oldest poet, and it
               was like visiting at a shrine. Mr. McKenzie, editor of MacLean’s, also sought out the
               poet.</p>
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            <p>The <q>best seller</q> among the authors in Calgary is not a writer of novels. He is
                  <name ref="pers:JW2">John M. Williams</name>, better known as a musician. <name
                  ref="pers:JW2">Mr. Williams</name>’ first book, <q>The Child’s First Music
                  Book</q>, has run into no less than four large editions. It is used generally in
               the cities of the United States, and even in Australia and England the book has
               considerable circulation. He has also had the fortune of having his book used in
               Germany, which, in music, is considered extremely flattering. Besides this book, he
               is the author of <q>Adventures of Ten Little Fingers in Mother Goose Land</q>. Both
               of these books are published by Schirmer Music Publishing company of New York. His
               new book <q>First Lessons in Piano Playing</q>, will be published at an early date.
               Besides these books on music <name ref="pers:JW2">Mr. Williams</name> has written
               articles and stories for several of the magazines, among them the Ladies’ Home
               Journal and other well known journals, and has had critical articles in the well
               known music magazines, The Etude and The Musician. He has also written several motion
               picture scenarios, and, though it is hard to get him to talk about it, <name
                  ref="pers:JW2">Mr. Williams</name> has under way a musical play which it is
               possible Calgary will be the first to see.</p>
            <p>In Calgary alone 600 copies of his <q>Child’s First Music Book</q> have been sold.
                  <name ref="pers:JW2">Mr. Williams</name> is a member of both the Canadian Authors’
               association and the Authors’ League of America. The recitals and concerts of his
               pupils are an annual event of social and artistic importance in Calgary.</p>
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            <p>Beginning with the new year, the Canadian club of Calgary contemplate a course of
                  <unclear reason="faded">reading and study of the work of Canadian authors. This is
                  a most laudable and patriotic intention. If the other Canadian clubs throughout
                  Canada follow the lead of our Calgary club, it will not be long before our authors
                  will be as well known in Canada as the American and English writers now are. I do
                  not advocate buying Canadian books just because they are Canadian but a
                  discriminating inquiry into our literary productions will result in an
                  acquaintance with the work of Canada’s own writers. In the States, and in a
                  measure, in England, the old proverb of a prophet, etc., scarcely applies today,
                  so well do these countries <gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="illegible"/> and
                  encourage their talent.</unclear></p>
            <p>While on the subject of the Canadian Women’s club of Calgary, the work done by this
               organization Authors’ book week was one of the most notable achievements of the week
               in Canada. The short articles concerning eminent literary Canadians that appeared
               daily in both of our newspapers were written by members of the club, and despite the
               fact that the authors of these minute size biographies were not professional writers
               they were extremely well written and in some cases showed the technique and craft of
               the experienced writer.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
