<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesWharton1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books, Literary Notes, etc: Edith Wharton</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>17.3</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl34"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Eaton Reeve,
                     Winnifred</name></author>. <title level="a">Books, Literary Notes, etc</title>.
                     <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">Morning
                     Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1924-05-28">28 May 1924</date>
                  <distributor ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>
                  <idno>17.3</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <!--Add information about previous citations or bibliographies using the source element-->
                     <!--
                        <recordHist>
                           <source target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        </recordHist>
                     -->
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from the University of Calgary archives</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                  <!--
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                     </listBibl>
                  -->
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-20" status="published">Gaps re-encoded..</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-29" status="published">Gaps encoded. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-29" status="inProgress">Proofed but gaps not yet
            encoded.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-29" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-06-30">Wrote note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2019-08-29">directed facsimile.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl34 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesWharton1">
      <body>
         <head>Books, Literary Notes, etc.</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By Winnifred Reeve</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>A new book by <name ref="pers:EW1">Edith Wharton</name> is always a distinguished
               event in the literary world. <q>Old New York</q> comes in four volumes, <q>False
                  Dawn</q>, <q>The Old Maid</q>, <q>The Spark</q> and <q>New Year’s Day</q>.</p>
            <p>The New York Times, in reviewing <q>The Old Maid</q>, says that she has <q>written a
                  story as universally significant and as enduringly beautiful as ‘Ethan Frome,’ a
                  story which exercises the inevitable authority of great art</q>.</p>
            <p>I should not call <q>Ethan Frome</q> beautiful, but great it is, probably one of the
               greatest stories ever written. Though it is several years since I read it, the
               characters still stand out clear cut in their stark realism.</p>
            <p><q>Ethan Frome</q> was different from anything <name ref="pers:EW1">Edith
                  Wharton</name> had previously written. <q>The House of Mirth</q>, <q>The Fruit of
                  the Tree</q>, even <q>Summer</q> gave no inkling of the fact that she was capable
               of depicting the bare, sordid life of the poverty stricken farmer of an isolated
               region with such vivid verisimilitude. <q>Summer</q>, it is true, was laid in a
               country region. It was a study of beauty, adolescent youth and betrayal in the
               environment of a small town near the mountains.</p>
            <p><q>Ethan Frome</q>, on the other hand, was a haunting study of a strong man’s love
               for his wife’s niece, whose beauty, youth, goodness and gaiety of heart contrasted
               with the narrow, dull, mean and hard nature of the wife who was several years his
               senior. The drama unfolds in an isolated farmhouse, with a background of penetrating
               poverty and work, and there is something terrific in the way in which the story
               sweeps along its course to the immense climax.</p>
            <p><q>The Old Maid</q> was, I believe, published some time ago as a serial in an
               American <choice>
                  <sic>magaine</sic>
                  <corr>magazine</corr>
               </choice>. It is slightly reminiscent of <q>Ethan Frome</q>, inasmuch as there is the
               same tense situation of drama with the overhanging and threatening tragedy.</p>
            <p>In her youth <q>the old maid</q> had made one false step. She is the mother of a
               child, adopted by the woman the <q>old maid</q> had wronged. The story is mainly
               concerned with the conflict between the real and the foster mother in the upbringing
               of this child. The futile, reaching out mother love of the <q>old maid</q> for the
               child who regards her with careless interest, makes a poignant situation.</p>
            <p>Variations of this plot will probably be attempted by less skilled writers than Edith
               Wharton.</p>
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>A Canadian writer whose work is coming to the fore is Mrs. M. L Strange of Fenn,
               Alberta, wife of <gap extent="1 word" reason="damage"/> Strange of champion wheat
                  <gap extent="1 word" reason="damage"/> Mrs. Strange is writing stories <gap extent="approx. 2 words" reason="damage"/> concerned with farming
               in <gap extent="half line" reason="damage"/> have been bought for <gap extent="half line" reason="damage"/> known <gap extent="2 lines" reason="damage"/> has recently <gap extent="1 line" reason="damage"/>
               <unclear reason="faded">public</unclear>
               <gap extent="several lines" reason="damage"/></p>

            <p>her farm stories are running at the present time in the Grain Growers’ Guide, and are
               attracting very favorable notice. Prior to coming to this country from England, Mrs.
               Strange was already well known as a writer of short stories. Despite the distractions
               of a large farm and the growing fame as a scientific agriculturist of her husband,
               her inclinations have never been weaned from her former occupation as a writer.
               Young, attractive and full of energy and interest, Mrs. Strange has taken up her
               writing again with renewed enthusiasm, and we may look for some good results from her
               effort.</p>
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <p>MacLean’s Magazine is unique this month (May), inasmuch as it publishes a spended
               article by M. D. Geddes of this city, who has recently been sojourning in the east.
               Mr. Geddes’ article, <q>Canada’s Mountain Play-</q></p>
            <p>(Continued on Page Twelve) </p>
            <p><gap extent="several lines" reason="missing"/></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>