<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesGrahame2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books by Winnifred Reeve [Review of The Bond Triumphant]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name></author>. <title
                           level="a">Books by Winnifred Reeve [Review of The Bond
                           Triumphant]</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The
                              Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-10-05">October
                           5, 1923</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>. </bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="readyForProof">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-09-30" status="readyForProof">Transcribed. Needs proof
            and name tags.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesGrahame2">
      <body>
         <head>BOOKS</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name></byline>
         </opener>

         <div>
            <p>The publishers of <q>The Bond Triumphant</q> are showing far more courage and
               confidence in Mr. Gordon Hill Grahame’s novel, which took the first prize in the
               all-Canadian contest, than did McLean’s Magazine. It may be recalled that following a
               scathing editorial in the Catholic Register, McLean’s withdrew the serial from the
               pages and tendered a humble <q>explanation</q>. It is hard to understand the
               psychology of the editors of this magazine. They ahd ample time to read and judge the
               book in question. Months before its appearance in their publication they proclaimed
               it in their advertisements. Stress was laid upon the fact that out of the many
               manuscripts submitted in the contest, <q>The Bond Triumphant</q> was awarded the
               first prize — $2500, $2000 of which was contributed by the publishers, Hodder and
               Stoughton, and $500 by the magazine.</p>

            <p>At all events, this highly denounced novel now makes its bow between covers, and is
               the author’s and the publisher’s silent, though eloquent, proof of Mr. Grahame’s
               contention that his story in no way libels the Catholic religion. There is no
               denying, however, that certain individual Catholics are painted in odious colors. The
               author wields a bold and darling pen in description of Monsignor Francois Xavier de
               Laval. He is not exactly painted in villainous colors, but is shown as an ascetic,
               fanatical, bigotted, hard-hearted, cruel and callous, hesitating not to sacrifice
               those he lovedi n the interest of his prejudices.</p>

            <p><q>The Bond Triumphant</q> is fiction; not history. The young author has as precedent
               several of the most famous world novelists, themselves Catholic, who have not
               hesitated to paint members of the Catholic priesthood in forbidding colors. Dumas,
               Victor Hugo, Balzac, de Maupossant, Flaubert. However, such characters were not drawn
               from historical personages, and it is a dangerous matter to pillory even the dead. It
               is to be hoped, therefore, that Mr. Grahame’s authorities are reliable. If they are
               not—well—we may recall the fact that his story is—fiction, and a first novel.</p>

            <p>As for the story itself. It is a thrilling, vivid, exciting, romantic, colorful story
               of Old Quebec. It is a livign, movign photograph of Canadain <choice>
                  <sic>Seigreurial</sic>
                  <corr>Seigneurial</corr>
               </choice> days. Before us pass all of the fascinating figures of those early days of
               wild romance, high adventure, daring and torture. The French habitant and pleasant,
               the seigneurs, the gentlemen adventurers, the trader, the Indian, the soldiers and
               governors, and dominating, governing all, the priests and the nuns and the sisters of
               mercy who had come out to the unknown wilds of the new country, and faced with
               intrepid heroism and bravery the perils and danger of those times. In this company we
               pass along through the <choice>
                  <sic>strets</sic>
                  <corr>streets</corr>
               </choice> of <choice>
                  <sic>old</sic>
                  <corr>Old</corr>
               </choice> Quebec, or we crouch behind stockades and are driven through the terrors of
               an Indian massacre. We are in the old Hotel Dieu, leaning, with the sweet-faced
               sisters, above the cots of the plague-stricken. It is a graphic hot pen that this new
               author wields. He <unclear>has</unclear> a tremendous gift. If the prize contest did
               nothing else than discover a Canadian writer of genuine power, it was well worth
               while.</p>

            <p>The plot is simplicity itself. It is the back-ground and the moving figures in this
               living drama that make <q>The Bond Triumphant</q> an unusual tale. The Seigneur
               Etienne St. Dennis, master of Crevecoeur, loved little Sister Jacqueline, the pretty
               young novice of the Hotel <choice>
                  <sic>Diev</sic>
                  <corr>Dieu</corr>
               </choice>. Her uncle, the great Monsignor Laval, is determined that his niece, the
               only human being he truly loves, shall be a bride of the church. How youth and love
               outwit the keeneset of brains, villainy and even prison bars and the wide rolling
               waves of the sea is told in a ringing, gripping style of this latest Canadian novel.
               A writer of talent and power is revealed. The book has the faults of a first novel.
               It is not good technique in fiction to lead down from a climax at so early a stage in
               a story. Taken all in all, however, it is a capital piece of work. Its publishers
               claim that McLean’s defection and the editorials denouncing the story in no way
               affected the sale of the book and that it has started off with a splended rush. In a
               letter which the Catholic Register describes as <q>manly</q>, the author disavows all
               intent to cast reflection upon the Catholic church, and it is averred by his
               publishers that he is, if anything, pro Catholic.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
