<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesCarman1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books, Literary Notes, etc [Bliss Carman]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SH1">Shaun Hunter</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from the University of Calgary archives</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:298"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNFInterview"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="published">Proofed, person references added, and set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="inProgress">Transcribed document. Uploaded
            transcription. Downloaded document from Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2021-09-02" status="empty">Added gap to signal no
            transcription.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-10-13" status="empty">removed transcription.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-10-11" status="inProgress">Added transcription.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-24" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesCarman1">
      <body>
         <head>Books, Literary Notes, Etc.</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Eaton Reeve</name></byline>
         </opener>

         <div>
            <head>Bliss Carman</head>
            <p><q>Poets are reputed to walk with their heads in the clouds</q>, says the Canadian
               Bookman, <q>and <name ref="pers:BC2">Mr. Carman</name> actually comes near to this
                  description. He is over six feet two. His fine head is crowned with proper ‘poet’s
                  hair.’ He has noble features, a mobile mouth, a characteristic nose and chin and
                  dreamy eyes that seem to see into the far distance…Eyes that seek and find a wide
                  horizon: that break into laughter…quicksilver eyes</q>.</p>
            <p>That the poet is not altogether a dreamer, however, is shown in his significant
               remarks anent the Canadian copyright law.</p>
            <p><q>That the peculiar species</q>, says <name ref="pers:BC2">Carman</name>, <q>known
                  as the Canadian authors will become extinct shortly, because of the effect of this
                  law, and therefore I advise you to patronize your writers at once while they are
                  still in the land of the living</q>.</p>
            <p>When an interviewer from the Bookman recently called upon the poet, after exclaiming
                  <q>God help you!</q>
               <name ref="pers:BC2">Mr. Carman</name> said:</p>
            <p><q>The only thing on which I can fire off an opinion as if it were a gun is in regard
                  to the Canadian copyright act. Unless we can have one that is decent and honest,
                  Canada will have no literature; only printers and publishers. However, as we,
                  people or nations, get what we want and what we deserve we certainly won’t get
                  literature. Judging by the copyright act, Canadianas don’t want
               literature</q>.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:BC2">Bliss Carman</name> comes of a family of scholars and
               litterateurs. On his mother’s side he is a lineal descendant of Daniel Bliss, of
               Concord, one of the most famous and powerful ministers of his time, and
               great-grandfather of Ralph Waldo Emerson. He is a cousin of Charles G. D. Roberts,
               and in the recent book by Lloyd Roberts on the Roberts family, some illuminating and
               humorous stories are told of <q>Uncle Bliss</q>, who talked with the children man to
               man as if they were of his own age, and addressed each one as <q>old man</q>.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:BC2">Carman</name>’s sense of humor has always been a delight to his
               friends, and numerous stories are told to illustrate this. Especially characteristic
               is the following story:</p>
            <p>It seems that <name ref="pers:BC2">Mr. Carman</name> lost a poem in the great
               Pennsylavnian station in New York city, and failing to find it he appealed to a
               policeman to assist him. That burly representative of the law surveyed him with
               amazement, not unmixed with tolerant humor.</p>
            <p><q>A poem, is it! Sure ‘tis no great loss. Can’t you be writing another one
               thin?</q></p>
            <p><name ref="pers:BC2">Bliss Carman</name> lowered his voice confidentially, and
               plucking the policeman by the sleeve, he whispered in his ear:</p>
            <p><q>Certainly, but you see, that poem was wrapped around a perfectly good
                  sandwich!</q></p>
            <p><name ref="pers:BC2">Mr. Carman</name> is due in Calgary on February 8, when he will
               be heard in recital at the Central Methodist church.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
