<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryMatters1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books and Current Literary Matters</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a">Books
                           and Current Literary Matters</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"
                              ><title level="j">The Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date
                           when="1923-03-28">March 28, 1923</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                           10</biblScope>. </bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="readyForProof">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-24" status="readyForProof">.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryMatters1">
      <body>
         <head>Books and Current Literary Matters</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto
                  Watanna</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>If M. L. Menken, the American editor and writer upon political and sociological
               subjects, were a non-entity in a literary way, Canadians might very well ignore the
               latest product of his pen. When he undertakes callously and with brutal disregard for
               the friendly feeling existing between the United States and Canada, to set down in
               cold type a categorical statement and prophesy touching upon the annexation of Canada
               by the United States by force of arms, it gives one pause. That such an article
               should be permitted publication in an American magazine is in itself amazing.
               Certainly no reputable Canadian <choice>
                  <sic>journel</sic>
                  <corr>journal</corr>
               </choice> or magazine or newspaper would print an article of such an offensive nature
               concerning a friendly neighbor.</p>
<!-- proofed -->
            <p>The first part of Mr. Menken’s article has to do with the <q>engulfing</q> of Mexico
               an <q>all the little republics down to the Panama canal, not to mention the West
                  Indies</q>. With a few fatuous and possible facetious paragraphs upon the subject
               of this easy walkover for the United States, the author comes to Canada.</p>

            <p><q>Destiny</q>, writes Mr. Menken, ‘‘will eventually shove us northward. That is to
               say, we will grab Canada some day, just as we grabbed Oregon in 1818. So far we have
               not done so simply because the pressure behind the natural impulse has been more than
               counterbalanced by contrary pressures, chiefly of a cautionary nature. Moreover, the
               value of Canada, until very lately, was not very evident; it seemed to be chiefly a
               snow waste, inhabited by scattered bands of half-civilized French Canadians. But
               during the past two or three decades it has been developed in so brilliant a manner
               that its possibilities are patent to anyone. In the east it now has large and
               prosperous cities; in the far west and prairies have been converted into farms.</p>

            <p>‘‘The conquest of Canada, as things stand in the world today, would be enormously
               difficult and expensive, and so no one advocates it as a practical enterprise. But
               the fundamental impediments, realistically examined, reduce themselves to two, and
               neither allows any sign of permanence. The first, obviously, is England . . . The
               second the Canadians themselves. . . . Neither need detain us once the time comes. No
               sane person believes that we’ll tackle Canada so long as we remain at peace with
               England, but who will argue that the present peace is likely to last? Certainly no
               one who understands the competitions which lie at the bottom of international
               relations. We are moving rapidly and <choice>
                  <sic>ineviably</sic>
                  <corr>inevitably</corr>
               </choice> into the position occupied by Germany before 1914—that of chief competitor
               for the sea-borne commerce of the world. Soon or late that rivalry will take on a
               violent and implacable character. England will have to try to cripple us in order to
               save herself and the moment the combat is joined Canada will become a convenient club
               for belaboring the motherland. More, it will instantly attract our elder statesmen as
               a club that will be charmingly edible and nourishing after its use in war is
               over.</p>


            <p>‘‘The military problems presented by an invasion of Canada are considerably less
               serious than those presented by an invasion of Mexico. The territory to be conquered
               is much larger, but getting into it will be easier and it will not be necessary to
               seize so large a part of it. Once a few towns are taken and the chief railroads are
               in our hands, Canada will be quite unable to make any further resistance. These towns
               and railroads, as a glance at the map will show, are so conveniently located that
               they almost seem to have been laid out by the strategists of the general staff at
               Washington. Even a militia colonel, given troops enough, could take them in ten
               days—and in the second or third month of the next war there will be troops enough in
               our northern tier of states alone to beat any conceivable army that Canada can
               muster. To cut off Manitoba, Saskatchewan, Alberta, and British Columbia from Ontario
               and Quebec will be a job for a sergeant and twenty men. To reduce Ontario and Quebec
               themselves and with them the maritime provinces will be a matter for the
               landwehr.</p>

            <p>‘‘Moreover, there is little reason to believe that the Canadian army will make any
               serious resistance. In the first place the futility of it will be manifest from the
               start. In the second place the reliability of at least a part of the troops will be
               seriously open to question. This part will be made up not of native and patriotic
               Canadians, but of Americans settled in Canada. During the late war it was easy to
               enlist such pioneering and adventurous men in the army, and they performed valiant
               deeds for England and the empire of Northern France. It would not be unreasonable to
               argue that they saved England and the empire, at least in the first year of the war.
               . . .</p>

            <p>‘‘The number of such Americans in Canada is usually greatly underestimated. Not only
               do they constitute a large minority of the recent settlers in the western provinces,
               but they are also very numerous in Ontario, and particularly in the big cities. Their
               presence, in fact, is partly responsible for the bitter anti-American feeling which
               rages among the native Canadian loyalists. These loyalists see their country
               gradually succumbing to peaceful penetration. Such towns as Toronto, Hamilton and
               London are now quite as American as Scranton, Pa., or Joliet, Ill., and so are
               Vancouver, Winnipeg, Calgary and even Regina and Edmonton. The four western
               provinces, in fact, have been settled by the same wave of immigration which settled
               Minnesota, Wisconsin and the Dakotas. The international boundary grows more frail and
               academic every day. Even if there is no war the whole of Canada west of the Soo will
               be thoroughly American within twenty-five years.</p>

            <p>‘‘To obliterate the boundary will be a good job. Its existence simply dooms Canada to
               an incurable second-rateness. It can never hope to be anything more than a puerile
               and unconvincing imitation of the United States. It lacks the variety of resources,
               the geographical compactness, the military power that are necessary to a nation of
               the first rank. Its politicians are a trashy and tricky lot, bent only upon
               attracting the condescending notice of their English overlords by a fawning loyalty.
               Like all colonies, it constantly hoses its best men to the motherland. Worse, it is
               in the position of a colony with two motherlands. Both England and the United States
               drain it. Its provinces would be immeasurably better off as American states. They
               would help to augment the power and dignity of the United States and they would share
               in that power and dignity. Their development would proceed more rapidly; more
               first-class men would settle in them; they would become richer and more secure.</p>

            <p><q>What stands in the way of that upward step is simply sentimentality. It will be
                  disposed of by force of arms. To attempt to halt the inevitable expansion of so
                  vast and powerful an organism as the United States by appeals to principles and
                  ideas is as childish as to attempt to overcome gravity by prayer</q>.</p>

            <p>We might, of course, ignore and treat with contempt this vain outpouring; but that
               would be like the <choice>
                  <sic>astrich</sic>
                  <corr>ostrich</corr>
               </choice> who sticks his head in the sand and imagines that no one sees him. On our <choice>
                  <sic>newstands</sic>
                  <corr>newsstands</corr>
               </choice>, in our homes, spread upon the tables of the libraries, lies the magazine
               containing this flammatory and extraordinary article in it. It cannot be allowed to
               pass unchallenged, lest we be charged with indeed being <q>puerile</q>. Puerile,
               Canadians are not, as the war demonstrated, but painfully slow to resent an affront;
               nay! a gross libel and insult, it would seem we must be, for so far as I know there
               has not been a single movement to stop the entry into this country of this magazine,
               and the circulation has gone on without interruption.</p>

            <p>It is not my intention to attempt to refute the vain-glorious boasts or diagnose the
               military program outlined by this <q>prophet</q>. That is a task for an abler
               editorial pen than mine, or possibly for a military ex-expert. What I would like
               especially to point out is that thought there is no denying that the article is most
               cleverly and plausibly written, the author reveals that amassing ignorance concerning
               Canada and Canadians so common in the United States and other parts of the world, and
               it should bring home to Canadians the fact that it is high time that this erroneous
               opinion should be corrected and proven to be false. We have been misrepresented and
               grossly libelled by writers who have used our country for literary exploitation.</p>

            <p><q>Until lately chiefly a snow waste, inhabited by scattered bands of half civilized
                  French Canadians!</q></p>

            <p>It is then, indeed, only lately, that the <q>towns</q> of Toronto, Montreal,
               Winnipeg, Vancouver were snow wastes? Are the cities of Toronto, Hamilton, London,
               Edmonton, Vancouver, Winnipeg, Calgary, Regina and Edmonton American as this editor
               claims?</p>

            <p>His ignorance concerning these cities is almost as ridiculous as the delusion that
               during the late war our army had so many Americans in it in the first year that
                  <q>they saved England and the empire!</q></p>

            <p>It would be interesting if statistics will be published giving the exact percentage
               of Americans in the Canadian army at that period. Once and for all then that inflated
               bubble, which is blown by so many across the line would be pricked and dissolved into
               thin air.</p>

            <p>As a matter of fact, the Canadian army in the first year had far more Englishmen in
               it than Americans.</p>

            <p>It is well to <q>see our sels’ as <choice>
                     <sic>ithers</sic>
                     <corr>others</corr>
                  </choice> see us</q>. As regards our conquest, it might be well to remind Mr.
               Menken that Canadians are no duller, nor less valiant than during the war of 1812,
               when the matter of the conquest of Canada was not considered such an easy task.</p>

            <p>Stephen Leacocks’ recent speech anent the matter of our population of three or four
               and our government railroads (this was not one of Stephen’s humorous speeches, or was
               not meant as one, but an attempt—and failure—at serious speech), aroused far more
               wrath than mirth among his fellow-countrymen, but pallid and innocuous appear his
               words beside these sinister ones of the American.</p>


         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
