<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesChildren1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Books and Literary Notes</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a">Books and Literary Notes</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-03-26">March 26, 1923</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">[About children’s book with Calgary connections]</note>--></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2025-05-06" status="published"></change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesChildren1">
      <body>
         <head>Books and Literary Notes</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>Another large edition of <q>Ten Little Fingers in Mother Goose Land</q> comes from the press of G. Schirmer, Inc., of New York City.</p>
            
            <p>This original picture-music book is selling in the States like the proverbial <q>hot cake</q>, and bids fair to outsell all other music books for children. Besides being deliciously quaint and funny in illustration and text, it reveals a practical and unique method of teaching children the piano and gives a simple medium by which a mother, without previous isntruction herself, can teach the smaller tots the rudiments of the piano.</p>
            
            <p>This book has attracted so much favorable attention that it is being taken from the regular music book stands and placed with picture books and other publications for children.</p>
            
            <p>Of especial interest to Calgary is the fact that both the author and illustrator of this unique publication are both residents of this city and it is gratifying to know that the book is also having an excellent sale here. The author is <name ref="pers:JW2">John M. Williams</name>, who invented the simple method expounded in the book, wrote the text and transposed the music of the Mother Goose rhymes selectd, while the delectable illsutrations are the work of <name ref="pers:NW2">Miss Nina V. Wright</name>, whose delicate and charming paintings have been on annual exhibit at the Christmas season in the Hudson’s Bay art department.</p>            
         </div>
         
         
         <div>
            <head>Ten Little Fingers</head>
            
            <p>In <q>The Adventures of Ten Little Fingers</q>, <name ref="pers:NW2">Miss Wright</name> reveals an undoubted talent for illustrating. Some of the odd little figures she has drawn are as original and cunning as the best of the kewpies, and far more real and human. We may look for some especially fine work in the future from the brush of this talented artist-author of Calgary.</p>
           
            <p>The new executive of the Calgary branch of the Canadian Authors’ association is an especially interesting and happy one. It consists of <name ref="pers:MG2">M. D. Geddes</name>, publisher of the Farm and Ranch Magazine and also of Alpine club and poetry fame; <name ref="pers:SR1">Consul S. C. Reat</name>, whose wit and wisdom would gild the dullest prospect; Admiral Como, whom an editor recently declared was one of the most polished writers and cultured gentlemen in Canada; <name ref="pers:CG2">Charlotte Gordon</name>, noted not only for her stories and articles that are appearing almost daily in numerous newspapers and publications all over Canada and the States, but for her executive ability (she is literary secretary of the Woman’s Canadian club and the Calgary Literary club); <name ref="pers:FW1">Flos Jewel Williams</name>, the latest star in the Canadian literary firmament; the much beloved Mrs. Newhall and Mrs. Catley, whose charming poems and lyrics appear from time to time in our papers and journals. Then there is Dr. Kerby, who was our last year’s president. This makes up an executive that promises well for the coming year.</p>
            
            <p>Besides the executive, the association is fortunate in having as its secretary-treasurer <name ref="pers:PHO1">P. Harcourt O’Reilly</name>, who appeared very much amazed and dazed when the office descended upon him by acclamation. His amazement changed to unholy joy, when <name ref="pers:SR1">Mr. Reat</name> arose and solemnly moved that in view of the fact of the disappearance of the first secretary of the Authors’ association, and as we had $19.02 left in our treasury that the incoming secretary-treasurer of the Calgary branch of the Canadian Author’ association should be bonded.</p>
            
            <p>I think it was then that <name ref="pers:PHO1">P. Harcourt</name> decided to accept office. At all events the protests that were emanating from his direction suddenly ceased and he gazed in the direction of the American consul with a glance that expressed plainer than mere words his wholesome English-Irish admiration for this specimen of typically American humor. The meeting broke up at this juncture, amid gales and chuckels of laughter. <name ref="pers:AM2">Dr. O. A. Macrae</name>, president of Western Canada college, was unanimously elected as vice-president of the association, while I attained to the office of president. I am not especially equipped for a presidency, lacking what is said to be the necessary qualities of tact and diplomacy. However, one can at least do their darndest, which I realize is an inelegant word for a president to use.</p>
         </div>
            
            
          <div>
             <head>New Calgary Authors</head>
               <p>New authors in Calgary are turning up from most unexpected quarters with every day. This winter I read no less than nine full sized novels and one book of verse, to say nothing of numerous short stories, articles, poems, and essays, all the work of Calgary writers.</p>
            
             <p>The first of the novels was a 40,000 or 50,000 word manuscript, the work of a girl of eighteen. It was in the form of a diary and though it showed considerable acuteness for a girl of that age, still was not a remarkable performance. The same girl has written many poems and short stories that show a definite promsie. The second manuscript was the product of a boy of 14, and was nothing more nor less than the journal of a prizefighter. I pass over this bloody yarn of exciting physical contests and amazing profanity with the simple statement that any boy who could achieve such a torment of language and conceive a plot of such torturing twists, is doomed, sooner or later to be what is most evidently his passionate ambition, an author. The third was an excellent story of ranching in Alberta in the pioneer days, and should make an exciting and gripping motion picture play. The fourth was a <q>human document</q>, the life story of the scout who captured <name ref="pers:LR1">Riel</name>. I found the last paragraph of a manuscript that teemed with exciting, bloodcurdling and murderous adventures, where the rule was <q>a man before breakfast</q>. Edifying, for, wrote the scout, <q>I often look back with pleasure upon those days, and in these upsetting times, I tell myself that the old days were the safest and the best!</q> The fifth was a story of Ontario farm life, and here was revealed a novelist of no mean skill, and of powerful promise, the sixth was a 70,000 word story concerned with the wheat gamble. It was a well written, thoughtful, almost scholarly, narrative. The seventh was a passionate tale, that revised and rewritten, might, if published, attain the notoriety and fame of <q>The Sheik</q>. Apart from its love story, its technique and dialogue, the character drawing and description are good, but the tale is unevely written and still has the mark fo the amateur upon it. The literary gift of its author, however, is unquestionable. The eighth was read to me off and on over the year as the author proceeded with the writing of it. It is a beautifully written story of the Okanagan valley, permeated with a certain charm and felicity of expression, and concerned with gentlefolk of the ranching district. Possibly a novel could give a more lifelike photograph of a country region than does novel from the pen of the Calgary author. I should be much surprised should this manuscript not see publication and attain a distinguished success. The author is a well known writer of special articles and stories, and is very much admired and loved in Calgary, so that any success that may come to her will be a matter of special delight and pride to her host of friends here. The ninth was a volume of poems—or rather material for such a volume. It had flashes of real warmth and charm.</p>
          </div>
         
         
         <div>
            <head><name ref="pers:PG1">Sir Philip</name>’s Opinion</head>
            <p>When <name>Sir Philip Gibbs</name> was here he stated that this country had all the elements that went to  making an inspiration of writers and poets, and he prophesied that within a few years Alberta would produce men and women of distinct talent in this line of work. His prophesy is very likely to be fulfilled sooner than he expected. Calgary may sit up and take notice and prepare ot be proud of men and women who are surely destined to make their mark in the world of letters.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
