<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesHale2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Literary Notes [Hale]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name></author>. <title
                           level="a">Literary Notes [Hale]</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"
                              ><title level="j">The Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date
                           when="1923-10-09">October 9, 1923</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                           12</biblScope>. </bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-01" status="published">Completed. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesHale2">
      <body>
         <head>LITERARY NOTES</head>
         <opener><byline>(By <name ref="pers:LW1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name>)</byline></opener>
         <div>
            <p>Calgary will have on Monday distinguished and talented visitors in the persons of Mr.
               and Mrs. <name ref="pers:JG3">John Garvin</name> (<name ref="pers:AG1">Katharyn
                  Hale</name>) of Toronto, and <name ref="pers:AW1">Miss Anne Elizabeth
                  Wilson</name>, literary adviser for the Hodder &amp; Stoughton Publishing
               company.</p>
            <p>During her stay in Calgary, <name ref="pers:AG1">Katharyn Hale</name> will give one
               of her unique recitals, for which she is rapidly becoming famous. A fragile little
               woman, weighing seldom more than ninety pounds, there is something both radiant and
               spiritual about her personality. <q>Her spirit and ambition are often too much for
                  her physical strength</q>, wrote her husband in a recent letter.</p>
            <p>As a young girl, <name ref="pers:AG1">Katharyn Hale</name>’s tastes and aspirations
               all turned toward music. For five years—in fact <choice>
                  <sic>nutil</sic>
                  <corr>until</corr>
               </choice> her father’s death—she sang professionally. Then, deeply disappointed at
               being unable to continue her singing elssons abroad, and forced into earning her
               livelihood, she turned to newspaper work. For nine years she had the book review page
               of the Toronto Mail and during that period poems and stories from her pen appeared at
               frequent intervals in various publications.</p>
            <p><q>When I was married</q><choice>
                  <sic>.</sic>
                  <corr>,</corr>
               </choice> she writes, in a particularly charming and revealing letter, <q>my husband
                  insisted on my giving up the grind of the Mail page</q>. Rest, however, for <name
                  ref="pers:AG1">Katharyn Hale</name>, meant work, now of an especially fascinating
               sort. Her music, which despite the long years of newspaper work, had nevertheless
               always stayed with her <q>like a friend or a dear child</q>, and now pushed its way
               to the foremost once again, but to her gift of music she brought the fruit of her
               years of literary work. Her programs were unique combinations of folk songs, French
               Canadian chansons, tribal melodies and original poems and prose from her own pen. And
               as she traveled from city to city, everything that was interesting and fine, that was
               typical of the especial part of the country where she was sojourning was noted by her
               within the result that <q>Canadian Cities of Romance</q>, which has been described as
                  <q>prose etchings delicate as those of Whistler</q>, came into being.</p>
            <p>Equally distinguished in a literary way, <name ref="pers:JG3">John Garvin</name>,
               something more than the mere husband of <name ref="pers:AG1">Katharyn Hale</name>,
               is, off the written page <q>banker and broker of Toronto</q>.</p>
            <p>To an expression of surprise at his affiliation with literature though engaged in the
               prosaic if profitable undertaking of banker, <name ref="pers:JG3">John Garvin</name>
               wrote: <q>It is not unusual for eastern business men of some prominence to have a
                  hobby or two on the side. <name ref="pers:BW1">Sir Byron Walker</name>, president
                  of the Canadian Bank of Commerce, is president of the Champlain society that has
                  published twenty or thirty substantial volumes and he is chairman of the Canadian
                  Art commission. <name ref="pers:VM1">Vincent Massey</name>, president of the
                  Massey-Harris Co., Ltd., is deeply interested in art, literature and education,
                  and so on</q>.</p>
            <p>In a whimsical letter from <name ref="pers:AG1">Katharyn Hale</name>, anent her <choice>
                  <sic>husban’s</sic>
                  <corr>husband’s</corr>
               </choice> literary proclivities, she writes <q>He is a broker and when he plunges
                  into literature on the side, we go broke, but he has done some wonderful things
                  for Canada</q>. And so he has. Candian literature has been his especial hobby and
               delight for more than a quarter of a century, and his spare hours are devoted to
               reading books by Canadian authors, <q>eliminating, selecting, editing and
                  publishing</q>. <q>Masterpieces of Canadian Literature</q>, in twenty-five
               volumes, represents his work as editor and publisher.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:AW1">Anne Elizabeth Wilson</name> is an example of how far an
               especially clever girl may go in her chosen profession. For one as physically
               attractive as <name ref="pers:AW1">Miss Wilson</name>—for her bone-ribbed glasses
               fail to hide the fact that she is extremely pretty—it is unusual to find a girl far
               more interested in others than in herself. And yet her career has demonstrated that
               she is an extraordinary young woman. She had the fortune to be associated since
               childhood with literary peple of eminence. Mr. Alden and William Dean of Howels—Mark
               Twain and others—these men <name ref="pers:AW1">Miss Wilson</name> knew as a child.
               At an early stage in her career she entered the employ of the old publishing house of
               Harper &amp; Bros. From the’ literary staff of Harpers she pursued and interesting
               climb, <unclear>still</unclear> at the present time she carries on her young
               shoulders the important position of literary adviser of Hodder &amp; Stoughton. Upon
               her judgement depends the fate of many a manuscript and upon her advice and revised
               and changed. Besides liteary advice and reading and judging of manuscripts, <name
                  ref="pers:AW1">Miss Wilson</name> does an immense amount of publicity work, and I
               believe, personally superintends the exacting business of syndicating material and
               placing prospective novels as serials. She is a stout little champion and
                  <q>rooter</q> for the books from her firm puts out and her spirited defence of the
               new prize novel by <name ref="pers:GG2">Gordon Grahame Hill</name>, <q>The Bond
                  Triumphant</q>, is almost enough to engage one on the side of the novel before one
               has read it. Pity it is so far as <name ref="pers:GG2">Mr. Grahame</name> concerned,
               that <name ref="pers:AW1">Miss Wilson</name> was not the editor of MacLeans, which
               panically withdrew the serial from its pages, after publishign one instalment,
               following the criticism leveled at the story because of its supposed reflections upon
               Catholics.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
