<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesGibbons1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><q>Pagan Love</q>: Murray Gibbon’s New Novel</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a"
                              ><q>Pagan Love</q>: Murray Gibbon’s New Novel</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1922-12-02">December 2,
                           1922</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>. </bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-24" status="published">Published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesGibbons1">
      <body>
         <head>News, Notes and Views About</head>
         <head>BOOKS</head>
         <opener>
            <byline><q>Pagan Love</q></byline>
            <byline><name ref="pers:JG2">Murray Gibbon</name>’s New Novel</byline>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name></byline>
            <byline>(<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>The first thought that occurred to me when I picked up <q>Pagan Love</q> was, <q>I
                  wonder when he found the time to write it?</q></p>

            <p>It is remarkable that a man of <name ref="pers:JG2">Mr. Gibbon</name>’s singularly
               modest and retiring nature should hold the position of chief publicity agent of one
               of the greatest organizations in the world. He is always travelling—from one end of
               Canada to the other to say nothing of repeated trips into the United States and when
               in Montreal it is said that he puts in as many hours as his <unclear reason="faded"
                  >resk</unclear> as a day laborer.</p>

            <p>Since the inception of the Canadian Authors’ association, of which he is founder and
               president, an enormous correspondence has been precipitated upon him, to say nothing
               of the thousand and one calls and demands upon his time. I venture to say that he
               finds himself in the unique position of oracle, father confessor, champion, agent and
               general pacifier of the whole tribe of Canadian writers—no enviable job, when we
               consider the artistic temperament.</p>

            <p>When, besides the above duties he produces a novel such as <q>Pagan Love</q>, we
               begin to realize that <name ref="pers:JG2">Mr. Gibbon</name> is a man possessed of
               that rarest and strangest of all qualities—genius!</p>

            <p>It seems a pity that he does not concentrate purely upon writing, for we are sorely
               in need of just such authors as <name ref="pers:JG2">Murray Gibbon</name>. Besides
               writing beautiful English, he possesses the gift of being able to interest, charm,
               excite and thrill his readers. Endowed with the natural God-given talent of the
               writer, he has also the advantages of education, culture and experience. Sceptics
               assert that there is no such thing as a typically Canadian story. Nothing
               distinctive, nothing unusual stands out in our literature from that of contemporary
               productions of other countries. Canadians, they say, will continue to be the <q>side
                  men</q> in the American and English literary shows.</p>

            <p>Of course, we know that no one country has secured a corner on greatness. Each land
               produces its giants, mentally and physically, our best talent it is very true, has
               been absorbed into the United States. That is our misfortune and our fault. Now there
               is a national movement, that seems to be growing like a rolling snowball, to preserve
               and to cultivate Canada’s natural resources and among the natural resources of a
               country, our native talent unquestionably stands first. No country can arise to
               greatness without its dreamers. Just as long as we force them across the border into
               the hospitable arms of the United States, or starve them if they persist upon staying
               here, Canada will become but <choice>
                  <sic>nonenity</sic>
                  <corr>nonentity</corr>
               </choice> as a nation. Yet Canada is a literary gold mine. Its surface is barely
               scratched. In mining, we must not mistake a streak of gold or gilt for the mother
               lode. It is good to have a man like <name ref="pers:JG2">Murray Gibbon</name> to
               direct and shepherd Canada’s literary talent, but it would be better if he used his
               splendid gifts as a writer to demonstrate to the world that in Canada we can produce
               a real literature.</p>
            <p>His novel, <q>The Conquering Hero</q> was mainly of Canada, a diverting story of a
               packhorse outfit in the Rocky mountains and an exquisitely funny picture of the
               tenderfoot Englishman in the B.C. ranching country, I wish that <q>Pagan Love</q>
               could also have been of Canada, for it is a much superior work. <q>Pagan Love</q>,
               however, is of no particular country. We move from France and England to Canada and
               the United States. We are in Czecho-Slovak, Russia, Austria, Poland. Figures from
               nearly all the countries arise throughout the book, make their peculiarly national
               mark upon the pages and are absorbed into the general melting pot of the tale, but
               into this story is woven the thoughts and the aspirations of the great common peoples
               of the world. At times it is a fascinating, grim narrative, in which the author sues
               unsparingly the surgeon’s knife.</p>

            <p>From the beginning of the story, when the starving, Scotch young derelict pauses upon
               the edge of the river, prepared to make his despairing exit from life, and reaching
               out a hand saves, instead, his own life, in saving another’s—One already in the dark
               waters before him—we are entrapped in the web of an intriguing and fascinating
               romance.</p>

            <p><q>Pagan Love</q> is cleverly conceived and brilliantly written. In spite of its
               title, however, <q>Pagan Love</q> is rather a sane, philosophical, almost scientific
               chronicle. Only toward the end we are suddenly surprised by the introduction of a
               seductive and passionate <q>Pagan</q> element. An American millionaire, the
               cool-headed business genius who has exasperated and fascinated us becomes as by the
               flash of a magician’s wand, transformed into a modern Cleopatra. This curious
               personality, with his cynical and searching observations upon life and people and his
               strangely emotional reactions, proves to be a masquerader. Behind his hard mask he
               has concealed the tremulous wildly beating heart of a passionate woman.</p>

            <p>Some day <name ref="pers:JG2">Murray Gibbon</name> will <unclear reason="faded"
                  >write</unclear> an exquisite story, lyrical with the charm and beauty of which we
               have flashing glimpses in his own poetry. A scholar and critic, no doubt he has found
               the psychology of the peoples of the world, which he knows so well tempting to his
               own pen. Nevertheless it may be that that fount of emotion and poetry which is
               certainly penned up within him, behind the intellectual front, will find expression.
               The medium of poetry will not suffice. He has more than the equipment of a poet,
               though poetry he can write most charmingly. As an instance the following taken from
                  <q>Pagan Love</q>, and concerning camp life in Canada’s Rocky Mountains gives one
               an inkling of the type of imagery of which he is capable:</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <lg>
               <l>Between the acres of wheat</l>
               <l>Are the wide streets of the West,</l>
               <l>And worn with moccasin’d feet</l>
               <l>Are the ways that I love best.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg>
               <l>The shadowy trail through the maze,</l>
               <l>Where the cedar and tamarack grow</l>
               <l>And the portage follows the blaze,</l>
               <l>From the lake to the river below.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg>
               <l>Where the moose and deer slip by,</l>
               <l>As the fisherman finds the pool,</l>
               <l>And the trout swirls up to the fly</l>
               <l>From the caverns deep and cool.</l>
            </lg>

            <lg>
               <l>And then, while the light allows,</l>
               <l>The trail that can never tire,</l>
               <l>To the bed of cedar boughs</l>
               <l>And the snug tent by the fire.</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
