<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesMisc1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>News, Notes and Views About Books</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a">News,
                           Notes and Views About Books</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title
                              level="j">The Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date
                           when="1922-12-16">December 16, 1922</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                           17</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-04" status="published">Completed. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-03" status="inProgress">Transcribing.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesMisc1">
      <body>
         <head>News, Notes and Views About</head>
         <head>BOOKS</head>
         <opener><byline>BY <name ref="pers:LW1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name></byline>
            <byline>(<name ref="pers:LW1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</byline></opener>
         <div>
            <p><unclear reason="faded">Fashions change in books, even as they do in dress. Time was
                  when we wept and thrilled over the loves of the painfully innocent heroine of
                     <q>sweet 17</q>. The villain that pursued her was anathema to us. She ran into
                  hundreds of editions and her grandchildren still survive, but the <q>sweet 17</q>
                  heroine of today is a sophisticated flapper, who knows more than her grandmother
                  does.</unclear></p>
            <p><unclear reason="faded">We’ve been <q>fed up</q> on wild western stories; business
                  stories, with the stenographer-boss theme worked overtime; pathological and
                  psychological tales elbow their way in with the spooks and psychic literature;
                  Canada has been exploited on screen and in story, and we learn through the medium
                  of a certain popular type of alleged Canadian story, that Canada is a country
                  whose main products are the snow, polar bears, especially <gap quantity="1"
                     unit="char" reason="illegible"/> sleigh dogs, igloos, noble mounted police and
                  French Canucks, who address each other not in the French language, but in pidgin
                  English <foreign xml:lang="fr">a la habitant</foreign>. The geography of our
                  country is no less remarkable, and the airships have nothing on some of these
                  heroes who sprint lightly from Ontario to the vicinity of the North Pole in record
                  dashes.</unclear></p>
            <p><unclear reason="faded">Glad Books came in on an uplift and <gap quantity="1"
                     unit="char" reason="illegible"/> wave. Of them we have had a <gap quantity="1"
                     unit="char" reason="illegible"/>. The Sunny Jims and Sunshine Marys are the
                  bane of our lives in stories and <gap reason="illegible"/>.</unclear></p>
            <p><unclear reason="faded">Contemporary with Pollyanna stories, oddly enough, possibly
                  as an antidote an overwhelming plague of what is known as <q>sex stories</q>. Some
                  call it <q>realism</q>. If such things are really real, we prefer illusion. Sex
                  stories, of course, have been written from time immemorial, and when they are done
                  by the master hands of the foreign authors, we have something worth while and
                  truly great but the <q>sex</q> stories that are selling by the hundred thousands
                  and are sprawled abroad in the popular magazines do not belong to the same family.
                  Though it is some years since <q>Three Weeks</q> set the world gasping, there has
                  been no let up to this type of story, and the epidemic reached its peak within the
                  last year. <q>The Sheik</q> ran into edition after edition, and <q>Three Weeks</q>
                  sells like a standard work <gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="illegible"/>.
                  Badly written a hodgepodge of <gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="illegible"/>
                  and <gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="illegible"/> one ponders upon the type
                  of mind that conceived them.</unclear></p>
            <p><unclear reason="faded"><q>Cytherea</q> by <name ref="pers:JH2">Joseph
                     Hergesheimer</name> is diabolically clever as are all the novels of this
                  author. <q>Java Head</q> by the same author was his best work. <q>Cytherea</q> is
                  a study of a woman of 45, who, though the author does not name her so, is
                  nevertheless apparently a nymphomaniac. The man in the case, a few years older,
                  apparently normal, with a meek, commonplace, faithful wife and several charming
                  children, is in reality a subtle sensualist, who has spent himself in dreams,
                  while seemingly devoted to his wife, and well satisfied with his comfortable home.
                  The two above characters come together with a bang, and at their first meeting
                  abandon themselves to their strange love, if such it may be called. No alienist or
                  mental specialist being at hand to control or confine them, they leave their
                  respective wife and husband, children and homes, and fare forth</unclear> to the
               inevitable rocks, where the woman perishes as a result of her abnormal passions, and
               the man is left to mourn her in baffled dreams and hectic phrases.</p>
            <p><q>The Beautiful and the Damned</q>, another sex story, is a brilliant torrent of
               language expended upon a certain fast American type and set. It is <choice>
                  <sic>extraordinary</sic>
                  <corr>extraordinarily</corr>
               </choice> well written and succeeds in almost hypnotizing the reader into what wild,
               jazzy, whirling mob of booze fighters and money slingers. Its author is hailed as one
               of the great coming novelists of the U. S. A.</p>
            <p>So much for sex stories. I have not room to touch upon more in this article, and one
               or two of such a diet is surely enough.</p>
            <p>Family <q>life stories</q>, that dip into every detail and thought and event of the
               particular type portrayed, are quite in the vogue today. I should say that <q>Spoon
                  River Anthology</q> was the forerunner and inspiration for this type of story.
                  <q>Main Street</q>, in a way, was a prose <q>Spoon River</q>.</p>
            <p><q>The Forsythe Saga</q>, by <name ref="pers:JG4">John Galsworthy</name>, towers head
               and shoulders over all of the family sotires published during the last year. Three or
               four generations of a single middle class family are portrayed in this remarkable
               book.</p>
            <p><q>His Children’s Children</q>, by <name ref="pers:AT1">Arthur Train</name>, concerns
               the carryings on and the love affairs of a family of nouveau riche. It is a well
               written, glittering tale, that will probably have a big sale.</p>
            <p><q>Certain People of Importance</q>, by <name ref="pers:KN1">Kathleen Norris</name>,
               has been praised out of all proportion to its merits, and is being proclaimed by its
               publishers as an <q>epic</q>. An epic it is not. An epic is a heroic narrative, a
               poem. <q>Certain People of Importance</q>, though a meritorious production, is
               neither heroic nor poetic. It is a detailed chronocle of the life and works of three
               generations of a middle-class American family, possessed of the average amount of
               virtues and vices. It is, in a way, a composite of the <q>Forsythe Saga</q> and
                  <q>Main Street</q>, but it lacks the noble structure and technique of the former
               story, and it possesses not the grim, gripping power of the sordid story of <q>Main
                  Street</q>. Nevertheless, it is excellently written; its types are photographic.
               We learn in detail of the daily life and thoughts of the thirty or forty members of
               the Crabtree family, and even witness the pains and struggles of their birth.</p>
            <p>A book that stands by itself is <q>The Key of Dreams</q>, by <name ref="pers:LB2">L.
                  Adam Beck</name>. It is a prose poem, full of mystical charm and beauty. It is a
               song, for it vibrates with melody and gragrance. The author has, I understand, had
               only one other book published, <q>The Ninth Vibration</q>, and he has had several
               short stories in the Atlantic Monthly. I learn that he is a Canadian, though he is
               cutting his way to sure fame in the United States. There is no Canadian writer who
               can touch him in sheer lyrical charm of expression. His work has been compared with
                  <name ref="pers:PL1">Pierre Loti</name>’s, and there is something of the elusive,
               almost ghostly, charm of <name ref="pers:LH1">Lafcadio Hearn</name>.</p>
            <p>It is pleasant, it is refreshing, after reading a score of new novels, few of which
               left one with a satisfying sense to come upon a rare piece of literature like this.
               It is also highly gratifying to learn that its author is Canadian.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
