<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="BooksLiteraryNotesPringle1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>News, Notes and Views about Books [Review of George C. F. Pringle’s <title
                  level="m">Tillicums of the Trail</title>]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a">News,
                           Notes and Views about Books [Review of George C. F. Pringle’s <title
                              level="m">Tillicums of the Trail</title>]</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1922-12-30">December 30,
                           1922</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4, 18</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-01" status="published">Completed. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:BooksLiteraryNotesPringle1">
      <body>
         <head>New, Notes and views About</head>
         <head>BOOKS</head>

         <opener>
            <byline>BY <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name></byline>
            <byline>(<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</byline>
         </opener>

         <div>
            <p>I did not like the title, <q>Tillicums on the Trail</q>. It sounded like
               Tiddledewinks and Tweedledumdee, and I thought <q>here is one of those hopeless
                  tickle-me-books</q>. then I read the brief foreword and learned that the author
               had been chaplain in the field of the Cameron Highlanders of Canada and that he had
               also been a <q>sourdough Padre</q> in the Klondike. At the present time, the <name
                  ref="pers:GP1">Rev. George F. Pringle</name> is in charge of the Presbyterian
               coast mission which takes care ofthe loggers, settlers and fishermen in camps and
               small settlements along the B.C. Coast. In 1899, he went to the Atlin gold camp. From
               1901 to 1910 his home was a <q>small cabin back in the mountains of the Klondike
                  creek district</q>. He ministered to men over a radius of 250 miles.</p>
            <p>All this was revealing and refreshing. The author was a real man. However, real men
               are not always good authors.</p>
            <p>I was not half way through the first chapter, when I realized that I was going to
               have a good time reading this book. It is an unconscious human document, a
               straightforward, fine narrative of a sky pilot in the Klondike, told by said sky
               pilot after he had become the chaplain of the Cameron Highlanders, and searching his
               wits for means to divert his men in the trenches with other matters than prayer and
               song, he stumbled upon this absorbing means of entertainment. The stories were told
               to the boys in all sorts of places, under fire, and out of fire; after service and in
               hospitals; while the guns were thundering; when each day thinned their ranks. They
               are rough stories of adventure, and concern strong and brave men. They must have
               quickened the pulse and warmed the hearts of those Canadian soldiers.</p>
            <p><q>Tillicums on the Trail</q> is peculiarly written and without much regard for the
               usual form of story writing. Each chapter is a story or an incident in itself. Each
               chapter starts in France, with a description of the place where the tale is being
               told to them, of the action that is going on about the narrator, of the comments of
               the men, etc. Then the tale drifts off to Klondike. Graphically, swiftly, it is
               narrated as it was told to the boys at the front.</p>
            <p>Some of the types are as clearly drawn as if photographed. We can literally see them.
               And the author himself, he is very much alive and near us, whether in the Klondike
               plugging along, lost in a blizzard while en route to a Christmas celebration, or when
               he first donned his kilts near Lens in France. <choice>
                  <sic>Me</sic>
                  <corr>He</corr>
               </choice> describes himself as of the greyhound type, built for speed, not beauty.
               His major advised him not to go out in his kilts, as <q>the police might arrest you
                  for having no visible means of support</q>. His blushes and exquisite
               embarrassment over his pipestem bare legs as two pretty French girls came in sight,
               are things to chuckle over.</p>
            <p>The book abounds in humorous as well as adventurous incidents. Scarcely a skirt
               flutters through the pages. It is a book about men, and evidently written chiefly for
               men; but we are given a glimpse of the few women in the Klondike, and the incident of
               the marriage of one of them, at which the author officiated, in one of the funniest
               chapters in the book.</p>
            <p>The bride was a cook in one of the camps, and in a country where women were scarce,
               she has many suitors. The two, however, whom she especially favored were named
               respectively Archie and Tweet. While concerned over which to accept, a little bird
               alighted on her window sill, and sang: <q>Tweet, tweet</q>. The bird’s chirrup
               settled it. She married Tweet.</p>
            <p>At another wedding the chattering of the false teeth of the agitated groom, caused
               explosive gurgles of laughter from the highly delighted miners, and all but lost the
               minister himself his dignity.</p>
            <p><q>Tillicums on the Trail</q> is a fine, clean, splended book, full of the tang of
               the out of doors and with that element of appeal that grips the imagintion, and makes
               us pause in our own hasty career through life, to observe the life and work of better
               men than ourselves. It is packed full of information, both of the war and of the
               Klondike. I don’t know when I’ve read a book I like better.</p>
            <p>Of the humorous stories in this season’s budge of books, the two that have the
               laughter splitting qualities in them Stewart, author of <q>A Parody Outline of
                  Etiquette</q>, by <name ref="pers:DS1">Donald Ogden Stewart</name>, author of <q>A <choice>
                     <sic>Paradoy</sic>
                     <corr>Parody</corr>
                  </choice> Outline of History</q>, which deserves a column of notice in itself, and
                  <q>Over ’ere and Back ’ome Again</q>, by P. O’D. This latter volume is made up of
               whimsical sketches on the humorous side of English and Canadian everyday life. They
               concern the adventures of a Canadian <q>innocent abroad</q>. The description of
                  <q>our</q> attempt to uplift the morals of pigdom, the wild gallop across country
               and the scorekeeping in golf are particularly funny. The use made of the editorial
                  <q>We</q> incrases the amusing effect not a little.</p>
            <p><q>The Timber Pirate</q>, by Charles Christopher Jenkins is full of thrills, and
               concerns the pulp and paper makers of Lake Superior.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
