<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CanadianAuthorsSalverson1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canadian Authors (Mrs. Laura Goodman Salversen)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name> (<name
                              ref="pers:WE1">Onota Watanna</name>)</author>. <title level="a"
                           >Canadian Authors (Mrs. Laura Goodman Salversen)</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-11-19">November 19,
                           1923</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">6, 14</biblScope>. </bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-01" status="published">Completed. Set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:CanadianAuthorsSalverson1">
      <body>
         <head>CANADIAN AUTHORS</head>
         <head>(Mrs. Laura Goodman Salversen</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>(By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onota
                  Watanna</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p><name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Laura Goodman Salversen</name>, author of <q>The Viking
                  Heart</q>, was born in the city of Winnipeg. Her parents fled from Iceland, about
               fifty years before, when the country was devastated by a fearful volcanic eruption.
               They put to sea in one of the old-fashioned vessels then in use, and suffered
               harrowing experiences. The ship was lost for weeks, and a pestilence broke out
               aboard. Two of <name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name>’s brothers and a sister
               died from the pest and were buried at sea. After long wanderings, her parents reached
               Quebec, and started, with other Icelandic exiles, on the journey west, entering
               Manitoba on the second train that went in that province. Here they were among the
               early pioneers and lived to see Winnipeg grow from practically a barren wilderness
               into a thriving city.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name>’s father is a literary man, and has for
               many years written critical book and art reviews for the Icelandic papers of Canada.
               One of her brothers is a well known cellist in the United States. <name
                  ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> likes to explain that the Icelanders are
               different from other Scandinavian people, inasmuch as they are of Irish as well as
               Norse descent, and she says that this explains the Icelander’s sense of humor, a
               quality notably lacking in other Scandinavian people. She comes from one of the
               oldest families in Iceland, who were noted for their relation to art, literature and
               education. Her cousin is the present governor-general of Iceland, now in his second
               term.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>Wrote Short Stories</head>
            <p>Prior to the publication of <q>The Viking Heart</q>, <name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs.
                  Salversen</name> had had a number of short stories and poems from time to time in
               Canadian and American magazines and journals. She gathered her poems together and
                  <q>with a quaking heart</q> sent them forth to American and Canadian publishers.
               While the poems were under consideration <name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name>
               wrote her novel, taking a period of only six weeks in which to actually write the
               story, though she had been gathering the materials for years, and had mapped out the
               scheme and the characters for her tale. She had barely finished the story when she
               received word of the acceptance by the publishers of her book of poems.</p>
            <p>At their request for the privilege of examining anything else she may have written,
               she immediately despatched her novel manuscript. It created something of a sensation
               in the publisher’s office, the reader’s verdict being that it would <q>prove to be a
                  Canadian classic</q>. Professor Allison who also read the novel while in
               manuscript, pronounced it <q>a valuable chapter on Canadian history</q>.<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Missing closing quotation mark in
                  original.</note> Meanwhile the American publishers declared <q>The Viking
                  Heart</q> to be <q>The best Canadian book we have ever handled</q>. High praise,
               indeed, from an American publisher for a Canadian book. The novel was rushed in ahead
               of the volume of poems.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>Has Penned New Novel</head>
            <p><name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> has already planned out her new novel to
               follow <q>The Viking Heart</q>. Iceland has always appealed to her a great subject
               for romance. She purposes now a story of so large a scope that one marvels at her
               courage in attempting so ambitious a piece of work. Her new novel will be concerned
               with the migration of the Irish to Iceland in the early days; of the intermarriage of
               these pioneers with the descendants of the Norse chiefs who were already there, and
               who had broken away from King Harold Fair Head of Norway. She will follow the race
               down through successive generations to the present hardy people who still survive the
               incredible hardships of a volcanic ridden island. One volcano steadily erupted
               without cessation for an entire year. It is her ambition to reveal to the world this
               little know, yet most romantic country, mis-named Icland, for, says <name
                  ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> the climate of Iceland is the mildest of any
               of the Scandinavian countries. In fact, it closely resembles that of Scotland, to
               which country geologists decalres it once was joined, some asserting it still is
               joined under the water.</p>
            <p><name ref="pers:LS1">Mrs. Salversen</name> has recently become a resident of Calgary,
               and is a member of the Authors’ <choice>
                  <sic>association</sic>
                  <corr>Association</corr>
               </choice> here. She was formerly on the executive of the Edmonton branch.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
