<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CanadianAuthorsAssociation1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Canadian Authors’ Association</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:JT1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Eaton Reeve, Winnifred</name></author>.
                           <title level="a">The Canadian Authors’ Association</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1924-05-22">May 22,
                        1924</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                        16</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">[This one is really fascinating — she’s ousted just a week or two earlier due to the Salverson scandal, more-or-less]</note>--></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-09-30" status="published">Proofed and published. Encoded
            name references.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="readyForProof">Transcribed and changed
            status.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:CanadianAuthorsAssociation1">
      <pb n="4"/>
      <body>

         <head>The Canadian Authors’ Association</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>(By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Eaton Reeve</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>The Canadian Authors’ Association is about to hold its fourth annual convention. It
               is now of an age where it may be said to have found its sea legs, and to have
               demonstrated its valuable staying qualities. It has become, indeed, a permanent
               institution, and although it has sailed at times through troubled seas of criticism,
               it seems to be making port.</p>
            <p>Let us survey, therefore, neither too harshly nor too leniently the work of this
               organization. Many reproaches and criticisms have been laid at its doors, possibly
               the chiefest of which may be said to be its tendency to proclaim too loudly the
               talent of its members, which, it is claimed, has lowered the ethics and the tone of
               the literary profession. Some have gone so far as to maintain that the Authors’
               association is nothing but a huge publicity medium for the Canadian author. That may
               be as it may be. Why should not the Canadian author have a publicity organ? This is
               the day of publicity, when unless one makes a noise in the land he is not heard above
               the great clamor with which the world today proclaims even the slightest of its
               achievements. Perhaps, also, the association has been too rigidly held to account,
               and chiefly by its own members, whose profession it is to analyze and weigh even a
               straw or a hair. The claim has been made that there is too indiscriminate
               exploitation of the Canadian author, that mediocrities have been hoisted to
               undeserved notice, and the trusting public’s attention been focussed upon unworthy
               productions. In the general effort to bring its splendid writers to the attention of
               the Canadian public it is a pity that we did not find it always possible to separate
               the chaff from the wheat. Our critics were only too ready to pounce upon the excuse
               of declaring that in fact our dish was nearly all of chaff. <choice>
                  <sic>Scarecly</sic>
                  <corr>Scarcely</corr>
               </choice> an utterance, hardly an action, every single movement of the association
               has been watched by its critics and unsparingly analysed and often savagely
               condemned.</p>
            <p>Utterances of such men as <name ref="pers:RS1">Robert Stead</name>, the national
               president of the association, who suggested that our libraries should made up of 50
               percent Canadian literature, met with unmeasured condemnation from authors as well as
               from laymen. On the other hand, <name ref="pers:RS1">Mr. Stead</name> was supported
               by many who earnestly and stubbornly upheld his views and who pointed to him as the
               patriotic leader of the craft.</p>
            <p>That the association has been of value to the author cannot be doubted. That it has
               been the means of acquainting an incredibly indifferent public with their own
               literary sons and daughters cannot be denied. Once since the Authors’ association
               into being did the average Canadian know that such writes as <name ref="pers:CR3"
                  >Charles G. D. Roberts</name>, <name ref="pers:MS1">Marshall Saunders</name>,
                  <name ref="pers:BK1">Basil King</name>, <name ref="pers:AS2">Arthur
                  Stringer</name>, <name ref="pers:VL1">Victoria Lauriston</name>, <name
                  ref="pers:LB2">L. Adams Beck</name>, <name ref="pers:MP2"/>Marjorie Pickthall,
                  <name ref="pers:MR1">Mazo de la Roche</name>, <name ref="pers:MM2">Marjory
                  MacMurchy</name> and others too numerous to mention here were Canadians. It was
               the Authors’ association, in fact, that acquainted us with the extent of our literary
               wealth and aroused in us a pride in our past and hope for our literary future. With a
               romantic literary history that went back as far as 1604, when our bibliography opened
               with a book of poems by <name ref="pers:ML1">Marc Lescarbots</name>, inspired by and
               dedicated to the then new colony of Port Royal—Annapolis, in Nova Scotia, with no
               less than 16 of our Canadian writers crowned by that supreme literary tribunal, the
               French academy, since 1880, when <name ref="pers:LF2">Louis Frechette</name> won the
               Montyon prize of 19,000 francs, had we not every reason to believe that our authors
               of the most present generation would also most nobly and splendidly do Canada honor?
               These were the things upon which the Canadian Authors’ association laid stress, and,
               in fact, forced a sort of awakening in the Canadian mind of a realization that Canada
               possesses authors of great genius, whose posterity was assured. This, then, was the
               great work of the association.</p>
            <p>Second in importance to this was the bringing together of the authors themselves. I
               do not mean physically, through conventions or public meetings, for I made the
               discovery that the conventions are not always visited by the best of our authors. I
               was told that last year barely a handful of Canada’s really big authors were present.
               This is the case, also, with the local branches, where the author is obliged to give
               but sparingly of his time and thought. When I speak, therefore, of the bringing
               together of the authors, I mean in that sense where through the medium of articles
               and speeches or correspondence we have become acquainted with each other. We now know
               and hail each other. We are in league, as it were, to give each other a helping hand,
               and to guide those who are essaying the uncertain pathway which we fondly believe
               leads to the great gates of Fame.</p>
            <p>Of the social and public service rendered by the Authors’ association I need not
               touch upon here. It is certain, however, that in every city where they have a branch
               of the association its influence has begun to be felt upon the cultural life of the
               community, and that is something.</p>
            <p>Nor shall I enter into the details of the large work entailed in the oversight of the
               laws that been framed most injustly in the past against the literary craft. The
               existence of an organization numbering more than 1,500 members, many of whom are men
               and women occupying the highest kind of positions, gives the association a power that
               cannot be disregarded when so serious a question as the copyright comes up before our
               senate.</p>
         </div>
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
         <div>
            <p>We might scrutinize now some of the matters condemned by the critics of the
               association. If our publicity methods have been somewhat blatant, this might be
               excused on the ground of our youth, and also because of the almost incredible
               indifference and even ignorance of the great majority of our people, as regards the
               Canadian author. It was necessary to dynamite the public conscience; to quick it to a
               realization of the importance to the country of its authors and to reveal the
               conditions of the Canadian author.</p>
            <p>I do not agree with <name ref="pers:RS1">Robert Stead</name> that 50 percent of our
               literature in the public libraries should be Canadian. I respect and admire <name
                  ref="pers:RS1">Robert Stead</name>, but I no more agree with that dictum of his
               than I do with another statement voiced by him in his inaugural speech last year,
               when he adjured the Canadian author to cultivate contentment with his lot and to be
                  <q>satisfied to be in the Ford class</q>. I am of those who passionately believe
               that we should attach our wagon to the very farthermost star. <q>Build high Master
                  Builder!</q>—and whether, as <name ref="pers:RS1">Mr. Stead</name> seemed to
               infer, our place in the sun be of but limited dimensions, beyond which we dare not
               go, yet the aspiration to attain the heights, the divine discontent and the fret
               under the chains that gall and hold us back, are the spurs and the hope that will
               speed us along the way. I for one would sooner snap all my pencils in twain and cut
               to bits the paper upon which I write my stories if I had no better hope before me
               than to achieve the Ford class.</p>
            <p>It would be a deplorable thing, moreover, if 50 percent of the books in our libraries
               should be Canadian. It would indeed be a literary tragedy. I am inclined to believe
               that <name ref="pers:RS1">Mr. Stead</name> has been misquoted.</p>
         </div>
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
         <div>
            <p>If anyone were to ask me what I considered the greatest defect of the association, of
               which I am a member, <fw type="continued">Continued on Page Sixteen</fw>
               <pb n="16"/> I would be inclined to say its apparent inability to keep out of its
               membership a certain class of writers who are not truly authors. Shot into being like
               a mushroom overnight, it was inevitable that numerous parasites of the pen swiftly
               slipped under the wing of the association, and they have stuck with the tenacity of
               bloodsuckers.</p>
            <p>When I was east a couple of years ago, even then there was considerable discussion
               among the authors as to this, and dissatisfaction was felt that the association had
               not confined membership purely to authors. When <name ref="pers:WM2">Wilson
                  MacDonald</name> was here, he told me of a group of authors in the east who were
               getting ready to form a new Authors’ League, which would be made up wholly and
               entirely of authors, and to which no one would be admitted without proved
               credentials.</p>
         </div>
         <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
         <div>
            <p>In some of the branches the busiest of bodies and the loudest voices heard emanate
               from those who by the widest stretch of imagination cannot be described as authors,
               and it is no secret how some of them became members. Many of us recall the time when
                  <name ref="pers:JG2">Murray Gibbon</name>, accompanied by <name ref="pers:AS2"
                  >Arthur Stringer</name> and other authors, made his famous trip over the country,
               forming branches of the organization in every city of any size or importance. A local
               club would give a function of some kind or other for the visiting authors, and at
               that function, after <name ref="pers:JG2">Mr. Gibbon</name> had explained the objects
               and purposes of the association, then and there membership was enrolled. It was an
               easy matter for one to leap up, nominate a friend, and, presto! he was a member, for,
               naturally, in our <choice>
                  <sic>eagenrness</sic>
                  <corr>eagerness</corr>
               </choice> to obtain a membership there was a disposition to be extremely kind in our
               scrutiny of the applications, and more than one went through as a regular member who
               was nearer to being a waiter than an author.</p>
            <p>The association was in the way, therefore, of being exploited by the hangers-on upon
               the skirts of the literary profession—people whose relationship to literature was of
               the vaguest.</p>
            <p>In a way the association, even in the beginning of its life, appreciated the
               possibility of something like this, and for that reason they made the laws governing
               the associate members extremely elastic and admitted to associate membership writers
               of any kind or sort and those associated with literature in various capacities. This
               was as it should be, and one could find no complaint were even the type of members
               referred to above content to remain in the associate ranks. But no they pushed and
               shouldered themselves in among the authors who had won their right to regular
               membership through years of arduous literary work. Indeed, there were occasions when
               the author was shoved unceremoniously out of the way with a barefaced <choice>
                  <sic>brazenzness</sic>
                  <corr>brazenness</corr>
               </choice> and lack of pride and sensitiveness almost unbelievable.</p>
            <p>The Canadian Press club, a dignified and splendid organization, already existed for
               members of the newspaper profession, and it is notable that the average bona fide
               newspaper man and woman made no effort to come into the Authors’ association, save
               where they properly should. They recognized the fact that was a place for both
               organizations, and they gave a generous and hearty support to the new association.
               More ambitious, however, were certain slush-mush scribblers, who intrigued and pulled
               wires and insinuated themselves into the newly formed and unsuspecting Authors’
               association. An Authors’ association should be what its name implies—an Authors’
               association.</p>
            <p>In our desire to proclaim our sons of talent, our effort to help the young
                  <unclear>and</unclear> potential literary genius of Canada, <unclear>it</unclear>
               may be that we have unconsciously been also cultivating weeds, and we know that weeds
               will outgrow the strongest of plants and in time choke and destroy them.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
