<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CanadianAuthorsDennison1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canadian Authors [Dennison]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl297"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Eaton Reeve,
                     Winnifred</name></author>. <title level="a">Canadian Authors</title>.
                     <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">Morning
                     Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1924-01-09">9 Jan 1924</date>, p.
                     <biblScope unit="page">4, 14</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNFInterview"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2024-01-14" status="published">Found better scan and replaced facs. Completed transcription. Proofed and set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="inProgress">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="inProgress">Added gaps for illegible word,
            proofreading complete for page one.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="inProgress">Transcribed first page of
            document. NOTE: Second page mostly illegible; Line 129, there is an end quote coded, but
            that is technically incorrect. The quote continues into the next page which is
            illegible, so the curly quotations should be in the second page. Downloaded document
            from Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-24" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:CanadianAuthorsDennison1">
      <pb n="4"/>
      <body>
         <head>Canadian Authors</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Eaton Reeve</name>, Author of <q>Cattle</q>,
               Etc.</byline>
         </opener>

         <div>
            <head>Merrill Dennison</head>
            <p>With the possible exception of Harvey J. O’Higgins and Willard Mack, both of whom
               have achieved international reputations, Canada has produced no dramatist or
               playwright of especial note. During the past year, however, the work of a young
               Canadian author, Merrill Dennison of Toronto, has made the literary and theatrical
               world of the east <q>sit up and take notice</q> of the fact that a new star is rapidly arising.</p>
            <p>Mr Dennison has produced a book of plays of singular originality and power, entitled
                  <q>The Unheroic North</q>. In a former article I briefly mentioned this book and
               it was my intention later to give an extended review.</p>
            <p>Plays are not, as a general rule, as easy or as interesting to read as are stories.
               The playwright is intent upon working out the dramatic technique of his play, or
               getting his values and effects across the footlights, rather than to charm the reader
               with literary sentences.</p>
            <p>Two of the one-act plays in this volume have been put on with great success by
               university and community players in the east, and there is a likelihood that <q>Marsh
                  Hay</q>, a play in three acts, will be put on this season by the Provincetown
               Players of New York City. It is said that the plays in <q>The Unheroic North</q> act
               much better than they read, when the characterizations have been ably done. This has
               not always been the case, as on a couple of occasions the plays were produced with
               actors who had been trained in the English diction, and the result was absurd, since
               the characters in Dennison’s plays are of the type peculiar to the small town, the
               back woods and the poor farm regions of Ontario.</p>
            <p><q>The literary quality of my plays mean less than nothing to me</q>, writes Merill
               Dennison. <q>The only important thing about them is—how they act</q>.</p>
            <p>This is, of course, a good point of view for one who intends to write plays.
               Nevertheless these plays have not only an acting value, but a literary flavor. They
               are piercing, photographic studies, done with a sharpened pen and the keenest kind of
               a gift for getting under the skin of things. Mr. Dennison possesses an uncanny and
               intuitive knowledge of human nature. He shows us weak, strong, erring, loving, hating
               men and women, all more or less affected by their environment.</p>
            <p>The lines brim over with wit; a strain of ironic humor runs throughout, and always we
               are conscious of the eternal pathos of life in a small, drab, shut-in community.
               Often this immense pathos trembles upon the verge of dire tragedy. <q>The Weather
                  Breeder</q> is, in a way, a masterpiece. <q>Brothers in Arms</q>, a humorous
               sketch with remarkable characterization; but the best of the plays is the last, and
               the longest in the book, <q>Marsh Hay</q>. Here we have a study of shiftless, lazy
               adolescent youth which finds its outlet in seduction and perjury. Dispassionately,
               yet dramatically, the sordid drama is unfolded. Strangely enough though the scene is
               laid in a backwoods community, we all know and have met the types.</p>
            <p>The action is swift, the climaxes come at the right time, and there are tensely drawn
               moments of real drama.</p> 
            <p>When Wilson MacDonald was in Calgary, I told him that I had
                  <q>discovered</q> a Canadian dramatist of great talent. I had never heard of him
               before. When I mentioned the name, MacDonald looked up in surprise and said
               instantly:</p>
            <p><q>Merrill Dennison! The most original genius in Toronto</q>.</p>
            <p>I was pleased to have my judgement confirmed, and also pleased to learn more about
               this clever writer, who is a friend of Mr. MacDonald. Mr. Dennison is 30 years of
               age. He was educated at Toronto public and high schools and the universities of
               Toronto, Pennsylvania and in Paris, as an architect. After the war, in which he
               served in three armies, at one time or another, he became associated with Roy
               Mitchell of the Hart theater, Toronto, as art director. They had advertised a bill of
               three Canadian plays, and could only find two tragedies. (This gives an idea of the
               shortage of original dramatic material in Canada) There were no comedies available,
               and the exigencies of the situation demanded that they should find one or write one.
               It had to be Canadian, played inside two other sets, cast three men and women, last
               10 minutes and be funny. It was up to the <q>art director</q>, and he accordingly sat
               down and wrote <q>Brothers in Arms</q>. The play went across with a whoop, much to
               the astonishment of the author, who thereupon decided that his forte was writing and
               not art <q>directing</q> or architecture.</p>
            <p>Mr. Dennison writes swiftly. His <q>Marah Hay</q>, a play in three acts, was written
               in 17 hours. He finds playwriting much easier than novel writing, though at the
               present time he is engaged upon the writing of a novel in collaboration with Arthur
               Heming, another Canadian writer of deserve fame. The two authors are
                  <q>hibernating</q> as they call it, at Bon Echo, where Mr. Dennison owns a large
               estate and inn.</p>
            <p>The author of <q>The Unheroic North</q> declares that his mother has been the
                  <q>stimulating influence</q> in his life. <q>A brilliant and forceful woman with a
                  fine intelligence and the soul of a crusading radical. She belonged to the
                  pioneers of the feminist movement and fought a valiant battle in Canada at a time
                  when it was the stagnant backwater of the world’s ideas—although it is no Niagara
                  even yet. It was she who bought Bon Echo, and dedicated its tremendous rock as a
                  monument to Walt Whitman, and it was during the 20 summers I spent</q></p>
            <p>(Continued on Back Page)</p>
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>(Continued from Page Four)</p>
            <p><q>here, that I came to know the back countrymen</q>.</p>
            <p>This is the tribute Merrill Dennison pays to his mother. If fame comes to him, he wishes her to have a share in the credit.</p>
            <p>During the last few weeks, we have been contemplating the possibility of beginning the little theater movement here in Calgary, and I have been asking to undertake something in that direction. We may in the not for distant future find ourselves started with a company of community players. There is undoubtedly dramatic talent in this city, and we should be able to produce sufficient original plays by Canadian authors to make the thing interesting and worth while. The one act plays of Merrill Dennison offer a fascinating opportunity for the community players to put on something new and of typically Canadian interest. Perhaps we shall see them done yet in Calgary--by Calgary players.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>