<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CarnivalBanff1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Carnival Spirit in Full Swing at Banff; Lack of Snow no Deterrent to Fun</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna, Onota</name></author>. <title
                           level="a">Carnival Spirit in Full Swing at Banff; Lack of Snow no
                           Deterrent to Fun</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j"
                              >The Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-03-03"
                           >March 3, 1923</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page"
                        >7</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">[An odd piece of reporting…but was <title level="a">Written Specially for The Morning Albertan by Onota Watann</title>.]</note>--></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-08-24" status="published">Encoded. Set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:CarnivalBanff1">
      <body>
         <head>Carnival Spirit in Full Swing at Banff; Lack of Snow no Deterrent to Fun</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>Sport Clothes of Fur and Blanket Cloth Rival Paris Creations; Weather Amazes
               Outsiders</byline>
            <byline>(Written Specially for The Morning Albertan by <name ref="pers:WE1">Onota
                  Watanna</name>).</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>The carnival spirit in Banff is undaunted by the fact that the country is practically
               snowless, and the temperature wavers around 50 to 70 degrees. The crowds pouring into
               the famous mountain resort are taking advantage of the extraordinary chinook weather
               to disport themselves in the sulphur baths (said, by the way, to have the added
               curative properties of radium) and to find such fun around the town as a place like
               Banff is sure to offer.</p>
            <p>The hotels are crowded and the streets, gaily decorated, are thronged with tourists,
               local residents, and people from the various cities of Alberta. Besides these there
               are the visiting teams that have come from all parts of Canada to compete in the
               sports.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Sport Clothes Rival Paris Creations</head>
               <p>Possibly nowhere else can be found such an assortment of varied costumes. The
                  latest styles from Paris, London and New York in sport clothes are outshone by the
                  carnival clothes and the brightly colored blanket overcoats, with their sash,
                  caperschaun, and toque. These look extremely fetching on the pretty bob-haired
                  flappers. Indeed the blanket overcoat, or the bright sweater or sport coat, worn
                  with breeks and puttees seem to be the favorite mode at the Banff carnivals.
                  Colors outvie the gaudiest ones dear to the heart of the Indian—magentas, flaming
                  yellows and oranges, screaming reds, paddiest of greens and the flashiest of
                  blues.</p>
               <p>If there is one thing that is purely, and it might be said typically Canadian, it
                  is the blanket overcoat. It’s rather a pity that this pictureque, warm and
                  exceedingly comfortable and practical garment seems to be used only upon carnival
                  occasions. Time was when in certain parts of our country, the blanket overcoat was
                  the every day practical coat. I wore it, as a child, in Montreal.</p>
               <p>The tourists in their fashionable clothes look with both admiration and envy at
                  the blanket clad Canadians, and they are to be found exploring in the stores for
                  similar coats and gloves and caps.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Wonderful Fur Suits</head>
               <p>More interesting even than the blanket overcoat are some of the furs that have
                  come down from the north. Fancy chappes made of beaver, edged with ermine, or an
                  unplucked otter coat with a collar of real seal. Sumptuous and handsome is a huge
                  coat of baby cariboo, which looks like grey-brown squirrel. This coat has a lining
                  of Shepherd’s plaid woollen goods, and is edged all around with bright scarlet
                  flannel. A sash of the same color and material finishes off what is certainly a
                  most picturesque and beautiful garment. Perhaps its attractiveness was enhanced by
                  the fact that it had been lent to and was being worn by Fern Brewster, queen of
                  the carnival, a stunning looking girl in her early twenties.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Queen Is Real Banffite</head>
               <p>Banff’s choice of a queen reveals excellent judgement. Fern Brewster is the type
                  of girl one would like to plant into a story of just such a coutnry as Banff. She
                  is typical of this mountain country. Intensely dark-eyed, with a straight, frank,
                  rather serious expression, Fern has a certain free and fine look about her, and a
                  grace of poise that one insensibly associates with an outdoor girl. Horses and
                  dogs and small boys—incidentally all the big boys also that can get a
                     <q>look-in</q>—seem naturally to gravitate in the direction of this girl of the
                  mountains. She will tell you, with her slightly reluctant smile that she <q>just
                     belongs</q> to Banff. She was born here. Her <q>dad</q> and her mother and all
                  her folks are of Banff, and—<q>Well, I just belong</q>.</p>
               <p>The name of <q>Brewster</q> of course is as often seen in the pleasure resort as
                  Banff itself, and it is indeed quite fitting that the carnival queen should bear
                  that name. So much then for Fern Brewster, queen of the Banff carnival.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Many Celebrities at Carnival</head>
               <p>Banff just now is full of celebrities or near celebrities, and more are expected
                  with every day. Lionel Barrymore is scheduled to appear for the derby. Ince, the
                  famous motion picture producer, is on his way. C.D. Gibson, of Life,
                  brother-in-law of Lady Astor and the most famous of American illustrators, is due
                  to arrive.</p>
               <p>The Trimble-Murfin motion picture outfit are in evidence everywhere. They seem, in
                  fact, to be a part of the scenery, and they are <q>on location</q> at every
                  corner.</p>
               <p>It is possible that few realize the value of <name ref="pers:LT1">Mr
                     Trimble</name>’s co-operation, or the importance of his presence in Banff. He
                  is filming several important plays in the Rockies, and he believes that there is a
                  great future for the motion picture industry in this part of the country. It is
                  true that the pictures he is now talking are all <q>snow</q> pictures, but they
                  are not of the desolate type which previous producers have loved to show of
                  Canada. His snow is connected with our sports and carnivals, and reveals it not
                  from the forbidding point of view, but from the aspect of sports.</p>
               <p>The outfit possesses in the person of Mrs. Barrel, whose husband is one of the
                  leading players, not only a clever actress, but a scenario writer of no small fame
                  or ability. Some of her plays have been of the most successful put on by the
                  Goldwyn and other big firms. She is attractive enough to be the heroine of one of
                  her own stories, but a few minutes’ talk with her reveals a mature and thoughtful
                  nature, gilded with the fine gift of imaginary and creative ability.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Pretty Girls Galore</head>
               <p>There are several visiting teams of hockey players, curlers and skaters. Winnipeg
                  has a dozen representative girls from their C.P.R. telegraph offices. Edmonton has
                  half a dozen young challengers, while Vancouver girls would take a beauty prize.
                  They make an especially good-looking exhibit, and are the cynosure of all male
                  eyes at Banff.</p>
               <p>Most of the visitors who have come from outside Canada go about with widened eyes,
                  and exclaim upon the ever-lasting subject of the weather. The Canadian who knows
                  his Banff feels both a sense of pride and chagrin over the failure of the snow to
                  descend and the uncanny condition of the thermometer. He now seizes this
                  opportunity to demonstrate a previously doubting world what manner of climate is
                  this we produce in Alberta. Sunny skies overhead, the thermometer at 60 degrees, a
                  balmy, ozoney feel and nip in the air that makes you walk on tip-top, and skaters
                  on the ice sans coats and hats. <q>Can you beat it?</q> they proudly demand. This
                  is one breath, and in the next they deplore and try to explain the fact that the
                  snow God is merely <choice>
                     <sic>witholding</sic>
                     <corr>withholding</corr>
                  </choice> for a little while his annual shower of white. For what is a carnival
                  without snow, and how may the ski jumpers and racers, the tobogganers, the dog
                  sleds run without snow? It’s all very well to import carloads from the north.
                     <q>Hang it all</q>, says the Banff showman—and every Banffite is at carnival
                  time a showman—<q>it’s not the real cheese. Not Banff snow</q>. All eyes therefore
                  are turned with real anxiety to the ever-smiling skies.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Hopeful of Snow</head>
               <p>As I write, flurries that bear resemblance of flying confetti is blowing lightly
                  in the air. The signs are hopeful, though the old-timers of Banff shake their
                  heads sadly and declare in all the 15 or 30 years that they have lived in Banff
                  they have never seen the like of this winter. Chinooks and warm spells they
                  know—they come with every winter, but this is a February apart from all others
                  that have gone before in this temperamental land.</p>
               <p>However, the flags are flying gaily, bunting is strung lavishly above the streets
                  and draped over buildings, at every corner some <choice>
                     <sic>jiggamaree</sic>
                     <corr>jigamaree</corr>
                  </choice> is whirling around, the ice palace glitters and glistens under the
                  melting rays of the too ardent sun, and along the streets go the merry crowd of
                  happy revellers.</p>
               <p>Someone is hi-yiing like an Indian <unclear>on</unclear> the street. I look out
                  and behold a phenomenon that has occurred in the short interval in which I have
                  been writing this yarn. A bright sun above still shines. The sky is golden, and
                  the rugged peaks of the beautiful mountains are traced in splendor on all sides,
                  but becoming steadily thicker and denser, blowing and whirling and dancing in the
                  air at last the long desired and looked for snow is coming. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
