<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CarnivalBanff2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Banff Masked Ball Is Fun Festival; Carnival Ends With Crowning of Queen</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna, Onoto</name></author>. <title
                           level="a">Banff Masked Ball Is Fun Festival; Carnival Ends With Crowning
                           of Queen</title>. <publisher ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The
                              Morning Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-03-06">March 6,
                           1923</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page"
                        >7</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> [Another odd piece <title level="a">written specially</title>. — spelling of name also fixed — definitely something SL would be interested given the costumed parade of <title level="a">war dancing</title>.]</note>--></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-08-24" status="published">Encoded. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:CarnivalBanff2">
      <body>
         <head>Banff Masked Ball Is Fun Festival; Carnival Ends With Crowning of Queen</head>
         <head type="subtitle">Mrs. Frank Patrick of Vancouver Chosen Queen; Old-timers Dance Indian War Dance</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>(Written Specially for The Morning Albertan by <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto
                  Watanna</name>).</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>The Dog Derby was, of course, the supreme event of the Banff carnival; but the
               masquerade ball was a whirling success.</p>
            <p><q>For sheer originality and inventiveness, for downright sporting, mischievous
                  fun</q>, declared Mr. Peters, artist and illustrator of <q>Life</q>, <q>I have
                  never seen anything beat the Banff masquerade ball</q>.</p>
            <p>Mr. Peters, who himself has taken part in the many costume balls given by the
               illustrators and artists of New York, declared that considering the limitations and
               facilities of the country, the giddy, gaudy costumes achieved at this dance excelled
               in ingenuity and originality any he had seen elsewhere. Nor was Mr. Peters alone in
               his praise. A bewildering variety of clever costumes, dependent not so much upon
               their costliness of material, as the oddity and uniqueness of the characters
               represented, paraded amid uproarious applause and cheers over the ball room floor.
               The first prize went to Miss Rich, who was a dazzling dragon-fly. Old men and women
               came dressed as <q>kids</q>, while the young folk staggered in, arrayed in the <choice>
                  <sic>habilaments</sic>
                  <corr>habiliments</corr>
               </choice> of age.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Old Timers’ Dance</head>
               <p>What brought the most applause was in itself a whole vaudeville act. Ten old
                  timers of Banff, dressed as Stoney Indian chiefs and braves, formed into a circle,
                  and beginning slowly and deliberately, the war dance of the tribe grew steadily in
                  speed and fervour till presently, going round and round, the <q>Indians</q>
                  whirled with something of the fierce freedom and fire of the Indian war dance. I
                  saw this dance done at Lake Windermere last summer, when the Thomson Memorial
                  exercises were celebrated, and the Old Timers of Banff gave almost as vivid a
                  performance as the Indians at Lake Windermere. Such men as Norman Luxton, James
                  Brewster and Mr. Sibbald were among the dancers. Another novelty at the ball was a
                  hockey game played on the florr by the masqueraders. This brought gales of
                  laughter and excited applause and cheers. A Cannibal Chief won the second prize.
                  Arrayed mainly in his ebony skin, and a few feathers he achieved a barbaric and
                  bloodcurdling appearance.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Dog Derby Starts</head>
               <p>The snow and the zero weather that had come overnight, followed by a brilliant
                  sun, made ideal carnival conditions for Saturday, and although the masquerade ball
                  lasted till the small hours, at eight in the morning the revellers were on hand to
                  see the start of the Dog Derby.</p>
               <p>The end of the carnival was celebrated by a ball Saturday evening. Those who had
                  danced all of the previous night at the masquerade ball and had gone out to Lake
                  Minnewanka to see the start of the derby, now were on hand for the crowning of the
                  new queen of the carnival, and stayed again till the dance was done.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Carnival Queen Crowned</head>
               <p>The crown which had been worn with such distinction and grace by the beautiful
                  young queen of the previous year, Miss Fern Brewster, of Banff, now rested upon
                  the head of Mrs. Frank Patrick, of Vancouver, one of the visiting hockey team, and
                  a contestant for the crown of the previous year. Her majority was overwhelming,
                  and overwhelming was the entusiasm and cheering when her name was announced. Miss
                  Rich, of the Trimble-Murfin motion picture outfit, came second. There was a
                  general feeling of gratification that the carnival queen of this year should be a
                  Canadian girl, and that the return of the Vancouver team for next year was
                  assured.</p>
               <p>What followed the crowning brought the last touch of wild hilarity to a night that
                  was packed full of fun.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Adopted Into O. O. D.</head>
               <p>The queen was adopted into the Order of Dog, and the ceremony of initiation
                  followed. The head of this order was helped to the platform by several pushing
                  hands and took an unsteady stand before an audience that indulged in gales of
                  laughter as his rich oratory poured forth. The speech was delivered with fire and
                  fervor and emotion and ran on and on up splended heights and flights, to the
                  accompaniment of roars of laughter. The orator explained, with emotion, that he
                  had had a little drink or two, and that he was feeling in prime shape.</p>
               <p>Presently the Vancouver hockey team, which had been jubilantly cheering and
                  yipping like Indians ever since their candidate was elected, formed into a knot
                  and let out yells indicative of anything but jubilation at the attitude of the
                  still spieling orator. The queen seized the moment to make her final escape and a
                  dozen hands were laid upon the still talking happy orator, and he was led, still
                  talking away. The dance was over.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
