<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="HerLoveSin2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Her Love Sin (Part 2)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno type="UofC">CU111976229</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl47"><author>Anonymous</author>. <title level="a">Her Love
                           Sin: The Story of a Fallen Woman [Part 2]</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:IConfess"><title level="j">I Confess</title></publisher>, <date
                           when="1925-02-06">6 Feb. 1925</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page"
                           >28-35</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at University of
                           Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-09" status="published">Completed. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-08" status="readyForProof"/>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-01-05" status="empty">Adding document from 2023 Calgary
            Transcribe-a-thon.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-31">Numbered instalment.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and
            exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl47 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:HerLoveSin2">
      <pb n="28"/>
      <body>
         <head>Her Love Sin</head>
         <head type="subtitle">An Amazing Human Document</head>

         <div type="paratext">
            <p>She had made a woman’s supreme sacrifice for the man she loved. Yet, when his eyes
               were opened to her astounding act, he turned silently away. Was she punished too
               much?</p>
         </div>

         <div type="content">
            <p>Can love survive poverty, hard work and the deprivation sometimes of the necessities
               of life? We were both so much in love—George and I that we marreid even though he was
               only a clerk in a department store and I a stenographer in a film corporation.</p>
            <p>But George some day would be famous, and with fame would come fortune—we were both so
               sure—for George was a writer. True he had had only rejections so far, but he was full
               of hope that some day, very soon, he would come through!</p>
            <p>All day long he measured dress goods and at night he would sit over his desk until
               three and four in the morning writing. From sheer exhaustion he would fall asleep on
               his arms and my day started with heartbreak—the tragedy of having to awaken him. This
               I did gradually, preparing his bath, starting the coffee to boil in our tiny
               kitchenette and then I would awaken him.</p>
            <p>But you cannot burn the candle at two ends without reaching the point where there is
               no more substance. It was a terrible winter that winter, the worst we’ve had for
               years. Our dismal combination living room, bedroom-alcove flat was none too warm, and
               frequently George would have to stop writing to thaw out his benumbed fingeres.</p>
            <p>At the end of March—a cold, blustery March, George came down <pb n="29"/> with a
               terrible cold. Influenza, the doctor said. I was nearly distracted with worry.
               George’s salary, of course, stopped while he was away from the store and my salary of
               twenty-five dollars a week could not be stretched another inch. Then to add to all my
               worries, I was up against another problem at my office.</p>
            <p>There was a Mr. Multinnez, one of our important directors, who kept pushing himself
               into my consciousness. I hated him. He emanated prosperity and sensuousness.</p>
            <p>He was pudgy, with black hair, thick lips, a braod nose and lead-colored eyes.
               Ordinarily I would have insulted him but I thought of George—George whose eyes had a
               feverish, hunted look; George who was so knocked out of his illness that he could
               hardly work. So I smiled when I wanted to scream; <pb n="30"/>laughed when I wanted
               to sob. . . .</p>
            <p>One day he asked me to take a letter. I got out my notebook.</p>
            <p><q>Just say</q>, he dictated, <q>that any time you say the word, Nathan Multinnez is
                  yours for the having</q>.</p>
            <p>I never answered a word but I burned with anger. Little did I realize the part Nathan
               Multinnez was to play in my life.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>George’s stories—he had written a number of short stories as well as his novel—came
               back with painful regularity. About the end of April he lost his position. He tried
               hard to get another place, and as he was able to sleep later in the mornings now, his
               health bucked up a bit. But there was so much unemployment that year. You can’t
               imagine the number of men who answer the advertisements in the paper. Poor old George
               was one of hundreds and hundreds of men after that most elusive of things in New
               York—a good job. And then too, he really was unfitted for most employment. He tried
               to get on the newspapers. Couldn’t get a look in. There were a score of live, husky,
               swift-stepping young college youths ahead of George.</p>
            <p>My husband was thin—almost cadaverous looking at that time and he looked older than
               he was. He didn’t sleep enough. He didn’t eat enough. He wasn’t well enough dressed
               and he hand’t a pinch of, I suppose you might call it <q>pep</q>. Some men were
                  <q>go-getters</q>. They can land anything they go after. George, in spite of his
               talent—no, genius—was diffident, slow and painfully shy. I daresay he’d let every man
               go ahead of him if there were a crowd waiting to get a position.</p>
            <p>As I said, he did his best to get another position, but his efforts were fruitless.
               So then he said he’d work much harder at his writing. He felt sure it would <q>pan
                  out</q>. The return of his manuscripts never daunted him. He never had the
               slightest doubt but <choice>
                  <sic>what</sic>
                  <corr>that</corr>
               </choice> ultimately he would succeed.</p>
            <p>Of course, my salary—I was getting twenty-five dollars a week—did not afford us many
               luxuries, but by careful economy it sufficed at least for our needs. Love and hope
               are meager meals, but they are the food of the gods, and with my salary George and I
               might have continued indefinitely.</p>
            <p>I forgot to mention too that even though his stories were being rejected at this
               time, we took it as a promising sign that he never received printed rejection slips.
               On the contrary, he had most encouraging letters from editors and publishers, but
               there was always some little reason why this or that story was refused.</p>
            <p>I’m not clever. George once said I had <q>flashes</q>. That is, there were times when
               I would come out with some observation that he would say was searching, penetrating.
               However, he was the brains of our little family. But it was my strength and optimism
               that kept us afloat, for in spite of his fine mind, George was subject to fits of
               depression.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I had a great crying spell last night. It came on me all of a sudden just like a
               raging storm. It tore through my whole being. It seemed to well up from somewhere
               deep down within and I could no more control or hold it back than I could dam up the
               ocean with my hand.</p>
            <p>Most people think women like I am now never cry. They think we are so hardened and
               calloused that we are impervious to feelings; our <pb n="31"/>hearts are petrified.
               There’s osmething to that too. For three years I never shed a tear. All human
               emotions perished within me. There was not a spark of fire left. And I cannot explain
               the tears of last night.</p>
            <p>I suppose it’s the going over of all this old stuff—like reliving it. I come alive
               again—out of my living tomb.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I can’t remember where I left off. I have to tell you some things about Multinnez.
               You see, all this time he was after me at the office. From that first time when he
               slipped his cards all over my desk he never let me alone. He was crazy about
               me—wanted me, and he went about trying to get me in his coarse way. I knew the value
               of his friendship and I masked my feelings. I knew that it was desirable for me to
               stand well in his eyes. I had a feeling that I would need him some day and I had not
               the slightest compunction about using him if necessary.</p>
            <p>I suppose you think that sordid. So it is. But then, after all, I was sordid for
               another. Had I only myself to consider, I would have snapped my fingers in
               Multinnez’s face and told him to go to the devil. But I had George back of my mind
               all the time. So I smiled at him instead, laughed even at his off color jokes, and
               when his thick fingers would hover over mine I would manage to keep mine flying at
               the type.</p>
            <p>But you can’t keep a man like that at arms length for long. I was playing a dangerous
               game. Through Multinnez’s influence my salary went up ten dollars a week. He was
               always giving me presents of flowers and candy and finally jewellery. Do you know
               what I did with a diamond ring he gave me? Well, I pawned it and then, to deceive
               him, I wore a good imitation.</p>
            <p>With the money I got for pawning that ring, we were able to take a larger flat on the
               top floor, and that gave us a sort of roof garden, where George used to write. It was
               quite pretty up there, and I bought one of those swinging couches with an awning top,
               and when George felt like it he could lie down and rest.</p>
            <p>But even these precautions were not enough, and with the first chill of the new fall,
               George came down critically ill. He had influenza in an aggravated form and the
               doctors feared pneumonia. I was nearly distracted with worry. You see, the doctors—I
               called in three in my desperation—said that he could not have the proper care in our
               rooms, and they said he’d stand a better chance, if I could arrange to have him at
               the hospital. Hospitals, I learned then, are only for the rich or the desperately
               poor. Anyone who has been sick knows what it costs today to go to a hospital. One can
               hardly afford to die in these days.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I remember after the doctors left to arrange for George to be taken to the hospital,
               I walked round and round in a circle, wringing my hands and not knowing what I was
               doing, with just one thought cracking away in my brain—the thought that I must
               somewhere, somehow, get the money to give George proper treatment at the hospital.
               And as I ran like a crazed thing around in that circle suddenly the fog cleared up
               from my mind. I saw the way clear cut before me. It was an ugly, a terrible way—but I
               knew that I would have to tread it!</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <pb n="32"/>
            <p>I daresay you already know from whom I obtained the money to pay for George’s
               illness. Most stories bring the heroine just to the verge of ruin and then save her,
               leaving her virginal and pure. That’s how you write stories, isn’t it? But that’s not
               how things go in life. Everything has its price, and I, no different from hundreds of
               other women before me, had my market value. Multinnez, I beleive, would have paid
               five times the price I exacted for the moments I spent with him. Even though he drove
               a hard bargain with me the first time I went to him. Not only that he played a dirty
               trick on me.</p>
            <p>I went directly to his apartment. I asked him outright for one thousand dollars. He
               replied:</p>
            <p><q>What do I get for it?</q></p>
            <p><q>Anything I have to give</q>.</p>
            <p>That brought a gulping chuckle from him, and he said huskily, as his arms closed
               about me:</p>
            <p><q>I’ll take the first installment now then</q>.</p>
            <p>I want to say to you that no matter what I did at that time, I never once lost my
               head. A chant was gonig on inside me. I was crying—shouting within me:</p>
            <p><q>This is for George! For George! For George!</q></p>
            <p>When he put the check in my hand, he folded it up. Something made me look at it and I
               saw he had made it not for a thousand dollars but for one hundred. He said, with his
               lead-colored eyes fixed upon me:</p>
            <p><q>First installment, baby. Nine more coming</q>.</p>
            <p>All the way home I kept repeating over and over again:</p>
            <p><q>Ten times one hundred is a thousand! Ten times!</q></p>
            <p>I am not insensitive—or rather I should say, I was not insensitive in those days. I
               was able to commit that act without the usual self-condemnation or even shame,
               because my whole mind was saturated with one thought—George. I wasted no time on
               self-analysis. Nevertheless I never left Multinnez save with a sense of being
                  <emph>unclean</emph>. I had a sort of dim comprehension that all the waters of the
               world could never make me whole or clean again.</p>
            <p>By the time George left the hospital, I had received all of the thousand dollars and
               I had been ten times to his apartment. I meant never again to go there or to have
               anything further to do with him. But when George came home, he was so painfully weak
               that the doctors ordered him to be sent <q>south</q>. They suggested that his lungs
               were affected.</p>
            <p>It costs money to go south. Everyone knows that. After the doctors had left us alone
               together, we sat for a long time hand in hand, looking at each other. He tried to
               pooh-pooh their warnings. Said he was as sound as a whistle, and in a few days he
               would be himself again. He said everyone was weak after the flu. As for going
               south—When he said <q>South</q>, a far away look came into George’s eyes, and I knew
               he was thinking of some sweet, warm land, where he could rest and sleep and write.
               Oh, I knew his thoughts before he uttered them. That’s how close I was to him, then.
               As we sat in our little dingy room on that murky, humid-chill day, I knew that the
               doctors were right, and that George could not continue to live in such a climate.</p>
            <p>I think we are all affected by the weather. There are depressing days when it seems
               almost as if some clammy heavy hand was clutched upon our poor souls. That was the
                  <pb n="33"/>kind of day it was when George sat dreaming of the south and my mind
               went stealing back like a thief to the place where I knew were a thousand
               dollars—waiting to be taken by me.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I don’t know what my face revealed, but George sat up suddenly and he puckered up his
               brows in that boyish way characteristic of him.</p>
            <p><q>Look here, Joss, dear old girl, you don’t look yourself. Your face is—is—changed
                  somehow. What’s the matter dear? You mustn’t worry so much about me. I’m first
                  rate now</q>.</p>
            <p>Do you know how I felt then? Just like a captured, surprised criminal. I thought that
               my sin was marked upon my face. And why shouldn’t it be? We register happiness and
               joy in our faces; we register sorrow and grief. One’s face is a mirror for our
               emotions. Does not crime and sin then also put its implacable print upon us? I’ve
               wondered about that.</p>
            <p>Look at me now. Would you believe that I am only twenty-six years of age? Oh, I know
               what you are thinking. It’s not the one sin only; it’s the attendant train that
               always follows when one goes wrong. Drink—drugs—what not? They all drag us down to
               the hell that is on this earth itself.</p>
            <pb n="34"/>
            <p>I’m not going into the details of my return to Multinnez.</p>
            <p>Our misdeeds follow us like our shadows. Our actions are inevitably followed by their
               consequences. You cannot cheat destiny. I believe in predestination. I beleive I was
               born under some unlucky star. Most women of my class are superstitious, you know.
               It’s queer, too, for when one descends to the very dregs of life, what is there left
               to look for? The sky is blotted out. We cannot see the sun. We are down in dark, deep
               waters, sluggish quicksands, and we rise only to the top when we are dead.</p>
            <p>I think whoever first used that expression <q>Primrose Path</q> must have meant it as
               bitter satire. Primrose! Why—Primrose? Where is the Primrose coloring? I never saw
               it. There was no light—no rosy shades in my degraded affair. It was just a
               cold-blooded business transaction. For so many dollars and cents I sold my body. You
               will say: <q>And your soul</q>. I don’t believe that.</p>
            <p>I like to think that no matter how my body was involved, the real Me—the soul of
               me—soared above my sin. I tell you, though I went over and over again to Multinnez, I
               had only one single purpose in mind. I surrendered myself to a man I hated for a man
               I loved. I closed my eyes; I gritted my teeth; I closed my mind as it were. I leaped
               down blindfolded, and I sank into heavy darkness like one who is drugged.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I don’t think I mentioned the fact that George did not go south after all. He refused
               to go. Said he had been too much of an expense to me already. He said he was going to
               buckle down to work and I’d soon <q>see</q>.</p>
            <p>Strange I never suspected the cause of his cheer in those days. For he was cheerful.
               He used to whistle and hum about our rooms, and when I would come home he would give
               me the most mighty hugs and call me all kinds of pet names. I didn’t even suspect
               anything when he lifted my face one day, looked deeply into my eyes, and said in a
               voice that vibrated with emotion:</p>
            <p><q>Dearest, dearest, dearest—only a day or two more and then—then, sweetest of little
                  women, I am going to give you</q>—he lowered his voice to a joyous whisper—<q>the
                  surprise of your life</q>.</p>
            <p>You see my mind at that time was obsessed with so many cares and alarms. Even with
               the money I was getting from Multinnez I had my hands full making both ends meet.</p>
            <p>The doctors’ bills were terrifically high. Then there were all kinds of things it was
               necessary for George to have at that time. Eggs—one dollar a dozen that
               year—quantities of milk, cod liver oil. . . . Oh! I can’t begin to enumerate the
               things the doctors said he had to have. He had no idea how much they cost. George was
               singularly innocent and guileless. Anyone could deceive him, and I had no trouble in
               making him believe that I had had several raises in my pay and that at night I worked
               overtime. So I did! Is that not a ghastly joke?</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>Of course, it was written in the book of Fate that George should find me out. A woman
               told my fortune by cards once, and she said that I was <q>living a double life</q>,
               but that I should soon be discovered. It’s remarkable the things they are able to
               tell from cards.</p>
            <p>As I said, it was inevitable that George should find me out. I wouldn’t have believed
               it possible the coincidence of his going down to my office that night, in order to
                  <pb n="35"/>break to me the wonderful news of the sale of his first book—to show
               me the contracts and the check that had arrived—then to find me not there. The office
               closed. Dark. The elevator boy told him I was never there at night. I always went out
               with my <q>fellow</q>—Mr. Multinnez, the president of the company.</p>
            <p>I can imagine how George took that in slowly, blinking his eyes and his brows
               congested. It probably didn’t sink in at once, and then perhaps the boy said
               something else, cementing the thing, and way back in George’s mind the slow rise of a
               terrible suspicion. . . . Of how he went over the pages of the telephone directory,
               his finger going down the list of M’s. Of the <q>Multinnez</q> in the telephone book.
               The address—written shakily on a piece of paper. . . . I found it later, or rather
               Multinnez did, and, in fact, he supplied these details.</p>
            <p>I can’t go on!</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I’ve been lying here for three days trying coherently to follow the train of events.
               My mind wanders at times. They say I talk to myself. I know I do. I dare say that’s
               what I’m doing now. I resurrect the past and live in a world of my dreams. I am back
               again in our apartment—George is asleep over his desk. I awaken him with a kiss. I go
               to touch him. Oh, God! he is not there! It is only a dream. . . .</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>There are moments in our lives that stand out in our memories like electrical flashes
               of fire branded on our conscience.</p>
            <p>If I lived to be a hundred thousand years, I could never forget that single moment of
               my life when I looked over the shoulder of Multinnez and saw my husband’s face.</p>
            <p>If he had struck me! If he had sprung upon me with animal, primitive fury! If he had
               whipped and lashed me—shot me through the heart or head! But no! George stood like
               one turned to stone and just looked at me. He said no word. His face had that
               bewildered, blighted look of a child caught in some ghastly trap. I saw his head come
               right down between his shoulders. He drooped like an old, old man. Then backward,
               step by step, my George faded through the doorway and into the darkness of the hall.
               Thus he passed from my life forever.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>They say the wages of sin is death. One would think Death was the worst of all
               punishments. Living seems to me more terrible than death. Death even has something
               beautiful about it.</p>
            <p>Death liberates us from rude worldly cares; death wreaths us about in veils of
               oblivion. Death is the fragrant balm from heaven which wipes away all the rust from
               our souls.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>I suppose sick people are prone to morbid fancies. I have a hatred of life. Remote
               things seem to me the most precious. I live in the fragrance of memories. There are
               times even when I am almost happy. I lie back here and my mind soars away from me. I
               am carried away on wings, as it were. I am near to George again! I feel his presence,
               the soft, sympathetic touch of his hand upon mine, his cheek pressed against my own.
               I close my eyes and I seem to see before me a beautiful conflagration, mysterious and
               subtle, and there I warm my shivering hands. I am lifted out of myself, as I said—on
               wings—on wings!</p>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
