<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="HollywoodMelody1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hollywood Melody</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve
                  Fonds</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl255"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Anonymous</name></author>. <title level="a">Hollywood Melody</title>. ms., <date when="1931">1931</date>,
                     <distributor ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve
                  Fonds</distributor>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <!--Add information about previous citations or bibliographies using the source element-->
                     <!--
                        <recordHist>
                           <source target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        </recordHist>
                     -->
                     <availability>
                        <p>
               <q>Hollywood Melody or Star Bright</q>, c. 1931, (CU2337783) by Eaton, Winnifred.
               Courtesy of Libraries and Cultural Resources Digital Collections, University of
               Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                  <!--
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                     </listBibl>
                  -->
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreFilm"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-23" status="inProgress">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-09-01" status="inProgress">Set back to inProgress. Already proofed and coded, but some code has to be edited to reflect script formatting.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-31" status="published">Proofed and encoded. Set to published. This is a test for formatting.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-31" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info and
            facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:HollywoodMelody1">
      <pb n="0"/>

      <body>
         <head>Hollywood Melody</head>
         <opener>by <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>   -- <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name></opener>

         <div type="content">
            <p>SYNOPSIS OF NOVEL                                              READ BY* * *</p>
            <p>SUBMITTED BY                                                   Sherill Tyler</p>
            <p>WINNEFRED REEVE                                                September 10th</p>
            <p/>
            <p> Copied by SC</p>
            <p> September 14th</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>HOLLYWOOD MELODY</head>
            <byline>or</byline>
            <head>STAR BRIGHT</head>
            <opener>- by -</opener>
            <opener><name ref="pers:WE1">Winnefred Reeve</name></opener>

            <note place="inline" style="display:flex; align-items:baseline; justify-content:space-between;">
            <label style="text-align:right; text-decoration:underline;">SYNOPSIS:</label></note>
            <p style="width:40%">Though Mavis Lee is a gay, clever, gorgeous-looking girl, she is
               one of hundreds in Hollywood who has parked the old companionate toothbrush in a
               folding apartment and is waiting for the big break. She can act. She would be a
               knockout at pantomime on the screen, if only she could have a screen test.
               Hollywood’s full of people waiting for screen tests.</p>
            <p>In the apartment across from hers lives Daavid Pivar, a serious young chap with the
               soul of a poet and a musician. He loves Mavis, but will not speak to her of love
               because he knows she’s destined to become a star, and would only impede her progress.
               He doesn’t like studio life. He has no desire to become a great screen figure. He’s a
               composer. He has done some beautiful things, the true worth of which Mavis realizes,
               but his nature is not in the least aggressive, and he doesn’t even try to put himself
               over.</p>
            <p>One day on the set, Mavis succeeds in attracting the attention of Victor Blanton, a
               producer whose word in Hollywood was law. He is married, has several mistresses, is
               keeping no end of young girls who want to get on and are willing to play the game,
               but he forgets them all when he meets Mavis. He rushes her for weeks, gives her a
               lead, dines and wines her every night but still she remains true to David. Of course
               David is depressed by her good fortune because he realizes that she is being farther
               removed from him.</p>
            <p>The day that Victor Blanton gives Mavis her contract, calling for $2500 a week, she
               throws her arms about his neck and kisses him. As luck would have it, David sees this
               embrace. When she comes back drunk two nights later from a party at Blanton’s, David
               sees her, packs his effects, and moves out. While she was drunk, she had told Blanton
               of her love for David, and Blanton, being quite human, fires David from the studio
               the next day. He disappears and Mavis has no idea where to find him.</p>
            <p>So she buries herself in work, and as a safety-valve, starts going to Hollywood
               parties. At first they’re a recreation, but later become a habit. She goes completely
               Hollywood. She can’t live without liquor. It begins to tell on her and her work.
               Eventually she</p>
            <milestone unit="page"/>
            <p>HOLLYWOOD MELODY, Con’t.</p>
            <p>Page 2.</p>
            <p>collapses and is taken to a hospital.</p>
            <p>When she is convalescing, Balnton comes to see her. He is genuinely interested, not
               only in the girl, but in the artist. Together they plan a super, sound production,
               which will feature Mavis, and bring her back to the screen as the lovable comedienne
               which first won the hearts of her fans. Mavis shows Victor some of David’s music,
               which she has kept. The producer thinks it very unusual, and plans to incorporate it
               in Mavis’ new story. As soon as she can be up and about, she starts work on the
               picture.</p>
            <p>At the premiere of <q>Hollywood Melody</q>, Mavis who is with Blanton, sees David,
               for the first time in many months. The long agony of their separation is wiped out in
               a long, burning glance, and each has the feeling that now that they have found
               another, they will never lose each other again. The Picture is a sensation. Davids’
               music is a sensation. Mavis is a sensation. But, Blanton gets screen credit for
               David’s music. As Mavis leaves the  theater, she sees David, crushed, and his angry
               eyes seem to call her a cheat. She is furious at Blanton.</p>
            <p>He has gone on to his home to entertain some friends. Mavis drives far into the
               night, until she imagines that Blanton’s guests have gone. Then she goes to his
               house. She enters his bedroom off the patio, in the dark stumbles over something on
               the floor. It is Blanton’s body. She screams and faints.</p>
            <p>Police find her in rather a compromising position when they are summoned by the
               servants the following morning. No one will believe but what Mavis murdered Blanton.
               Her fame becomes notoriety overnight, and she is completely crushed. Everywhere she
               goes for work, producers give her the cold shoulder -- though its rather baffling how
               she could look for work when she’s the chief suspect in a sensational murder case. -
               - - - Exhibitors withdraw all pictures starring Mavis Lee, and she’s just a
               professional outcast, who has to sell her house, cars and clothes to eat.</p>
            <p>Blanton’s death remains a mystery, but he made on beau geste before he died. He wrote
               a note swearing that the music used in <q>Hollywood Melody</q> was written by David
               Pivar. As a consequence, David, becomes a musical director at one of the larger sound
               studios.</p>
            <p>A year later, in a projection room, David is sitting with a group of <choice>
                  <sic>official</sic>
                  <corr>officials</corr>
               </choice> listening to voice double tests. He recognizes one of them as Mavis’. He
               asks who owns the voice and is directed to an extra, a little old woman. There’s
               something familiar about the little hunched figure. David follows her into traffic,
               and onto a bus. Flinging himself into a seat beside her, he murmurs her name. It is
               Mavis, made up as an old woman so that she <gap extent="1 word" reason="illegible"/>
               be recognized in none of the studios. The gray wig, the artificial wrinkles, the dark
               glasses all conceal the same dear Mavis whom David had known in the dingy little
               side-street apartment, and they both go home together.</p>
            <milestone unit="page"/>
            <p>HOLLYWOOD MELODY, Con’t.</p>
            <p>Page 3</p>
            <div/>
            <div>
               <p>COMMENT: Hollywood’s looseness has been widely publicized in both celluloid and
                  print, and I do not think it necessary to deliberately draw attention to the
                  well-known lax ways to the film colony by endorsing this story for a picture. A
                  big star is believed to murder her lover, the man who made her in pictures, and
                  that sort of thing is rather bad form on the screen. The plot is most
                  synthetically worked out, and the characters are frightfully <choice>
                     <sic>sterotyped</sic>
                     <corr>stereotyped</corr>
                  </choice>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <pb n="1"/>
               <p>Synopsis outline:</p>
               <p style="text-decoration:underline">HOLLYWOOD MELODY</p>
               <p>or</p>
               <p style="text-decoration:underline">STAR BRIGHT</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>A novel of 80,000 words, now in revision.</p>
               <label>Author:</label>
               <p style="text-decoration:underline">ONOTO WTANNA</p>
               <p>-- Winnifred Reeve</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head type="subtitle">HOLLYWOOD MELODY</head>
               <p style="text-decoration:underline">Theme:</p>
               <p>This is a story of Hollywood--the Hollywood of multihued lights and hungry
                  shadows. The Hollywood of tinsel joys and transient triumphs; of tender, prodigal,
                  passionate hearts.</p>
               <p>It is the story of a Movie Butterfly, who became a Bright Star, the Darling of the
                  World, and who at the peak of her fame was pilloried by the press and public
                  opinion.</p>
               <p>It is the story of a youth, whose dreams rose above the miniature piano he played
                  on a Movie set, and who dreamed of embracing in a musical composition the spirit
                  and the soul---the heart---the MELODY OF HOLLYWOOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>The novel opens in a typical Hollywood bungalow court--a second rate cheap affair.
                  All of the tenants were in the Movies, or in some way or another connected to
                  them.</p>
               <p>In one of the bungalows three girls eked out a living, by working as extras--when
                  they could get work.</p>
               <p>There was Adeline, a slangy, thin girl, who turned a hard boiled front to a hard
                  boiled world, to conceal the real mother heart within her.</p>
               <p>There was Anita, a constitutional liar---the sort that <pb n="2"/> lies about
                  small and large things, who was pretty as a kitten and who sexed her way through
                  life.</p>
               <p>Then there was MAVIS LEE.</p>
               <p>Mavis was a wild hearted, loveable, immensely <choice>
                     <sic>talentdd</sic>
                     <corr>talented</corr>
                  </choice> girl. A Mabel Normand type. A champagne personality. Passing through
                  life laughing, clowning dancing, throwing herself away. Excitement and movement
                  were the breath of life to Mavis. A child of nature. A quicksilver
                  personality.</p>
               <p>Across the court in a tiny bungalow was David Pivar, a musician on a Movie lot.
                  David was the antithesis in type to Mavis. He was a dreamer, and as moody as she
                  was gay. Yet these two loved each other. David held back telling Mavis of his
                  love, much as she tried to entrap him into speaking, for he wanted to do something
                  that would make him worthy of the girl. So he poured out his heart in his musical
                  compositions---lyrics for the most part.</p>
               <p>These two youngsters found their pleasures in walks about Hollywood, or in David’s
                  antique Ford. They would be part of the great throng behind the ropes on the night
                  of a premiere. Mavis even hung <choice>
                     <sic>outsidethe</sic>
                     <corr>outside the</corr>
                  </choice> Montmartre Cafe, to watch the stars go in and out.</p>
               <p>She had a natural gift for comedy. An irrepressible talent for clowning, and her
                  antics were often so funny that people laughed at her against their will---laughed
                  and loved her.</p>
               <p>Then one day Victor Blanton, a Producer, saw Mavis on a set when a certain super
                  picture was being shot. Mavis had gotten into trouble by knocking over a prop, and
                  now <pb n="3"/> she was trying to wheedle her way into the good graces of the
                  irate assistant director who was bawling her out. The somewhat edified Blanton
                  strolled over, and Mavis gave him a beautifully candid wink. He interceded for
                  Mavis. They had a little talk, Blanton appraising and against his will intrigued
                  by the girl. The result was a test on the following day for Mavis.</p>
               <p>The days that followed were thrilling ones for Mavis. With the favor of Blanton,
                  and her own inimitable gift, she rose rapidly. During this time she had several
                  quarrels with David. She tried to coax him to propose to her, and finally
                  deliberately asked him. <q><choice><sic>Lets</sic>
                        <corr>Let’s</corr>
                     </choice> you and I get married</q>. His reply was rough. He didn’t intend to
                  be</p><p style="text-decoration:underline">Mr.</p><p>Mavis Lee.</p>
               <p>Mavis had little enough time for him, but she never failed to rush in to tell him
                  the gorgeous news of the day, for events were leaping along for her in the Movie
                  world. And with her climb, David crept more and more into his shell. Meanwhile,
                  Mavis secured an important part--the lead in fact in a picture, and with $200. A
                  week, she thought she was a millionaire. She flew out to the stores, bought
                  everything <choice>
                     <sic>ing</sic>
                     <corr>in</corr>
                  </choice> sight, flung her money right and left and opened accounts in several
                  stores.</p>
               <p>David told himself he was glad to see her succeed, but he began to realize that
                  she was soaring beyond him.</p>
               <p>With the showing in the projection room, of the picture, it was immediately
                  perceived that Mavis was a great find. Blanton, who in spire of his numerous
                  affairs with women, <pb n="4"/> a wife somewhere or other, a mistress &amp;c. and
                  girls he was <choice>
                     <sic>keepi g</sic>
                     <corr>keeping</corr>
                  </choice> either from <choice>
                     <sic>kindnessof</sic>
                     <corr>kindness of</corr>
                  </choice> heart or a transient passion, was in love with Mavis---the first real
                  love of his <choice>
                     <sic>liefe</sic>
                     <corr>life</corr>
                  </choice>. But Mavis thought only of David---David, pig headed and stubborn---now
                  always so remote and withdrawn from her. However, the days were too full to bother
                  much over the sulky David, and Mavis was lightheaded and a natural joy-child.</p>
               <p>Everything her little heart could desire, Blanton saw to it that she had. They
                  went rounds. Parties, dances, drinking-----so forth and so on. Mavis was a Wampas
                  baby star. She made her personal appearances she acquired a fan following
                  &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then came the glorious day, when Blanton held above <choice>
                     <sic>herhead</sic>
                     <corr>her head</corr>
                  </choice> just beyond her reach her first contract--a very big contract. He told
                  her he had a <q>price</q> for it. This was just a joking matter. O.K. She would
                  pay the price. The price was a kiss. She <choice>
                     <sic>wasin</sic>
                     <corr>was in</corr>
                  </choice> his arms.</p>
               <p>There was a bang down of a piano top. David passed, unseen by them.</p>
               <p>Mavis flew home, literally on air, rushed into David’s bungalow, waving her
                  contract. He stared at her. She cried:</p>
               <p><q>Look! Look! David----my contract</q>.</p>
               <p>He glared at her with hatred.</p>
               <p><q>I know the price you paid for that</q> he said.</p>
               <p><q>Whattt!</q></p>
               <pb n="5"/>
               <p><q>Oh yes. Don’t try and pull any of that baby stuff to me. I saw you in Blanton’s
                     arms---saw him kiss you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Well what of it? You know as well as I do a kiss means nothing in this game.
                     Everybody does it. You know very well----</q></p>
               <p><q>I know very well we speak a different language</q>.</p>
               <p>The quarrel grew in bitterness. Mavis flung out, saying she hated him. Then a
                  moment later she thrust in her head to say:</p>
               <p><q>Don’t believe a word I say. I’m an awful liar</q>.</p>
               <p>But she went off that night for another party with Blanton. David sat up all
                  night. He saw her come in toward dawn. Mavis was drunk.</p>
               <p>Mavis had confided in Blanton her feelings for david. The latter masked his
                  feelings, and promised to help David get some good berth at the Filmo. Company.
                  But he managed the following day to have the boy let out. When Mavis tapped on
                  David’s door, on a repentant quest, she found it empty. David and his old piano
                  were gone. Adeline gave her a bundle David had left. It was his music---<choice>
                     <sic>aongs</sic>
                     <corr>songs</corr>
                  </choice> composed by David. Movie Moths and Butterflies; The World is Mine,
                  Hollywood Melody and so forth. Consumed with longing for him, Mavis went to the
                  studio and was told he had quit.</p>
               <p>For a time she was inconsolable, but her work <pb n="6"/> took so much of her time
                  and thought. She embarked moreover upon a dissipated, reckless career.</p>
               <p>She bought expensive cars, and from Paradise Court she went first to a gaudy
                  little apartment, with its cheap futuristic flashy furnishings, and from <choice>
                     <sic>ther</sic>
                     <corr>there</corr>
                  </choice> to a very ornate and elegant house of polyglot architecture bathing
                  pools &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here she lived on the crest of the wave. She was becoming more careless and
                  wilder. Her friends were the hosts of parasites that seem to flutter always around
                  a movie celebrity. Her black maid called her a Honey Child because people came
                  around her like flies to the honey pot; but when the honey would be gone, then the
                  flies too would go.</p>
               <p>Meanwhile her fame grew. She was considered the best comedienne in the country. A
                  real star, in every sense of the word.</p>
               <p>No matter how much money she made, she spent more. With a salary of $2500. a week,
                  she bought a $75,000. <choice>
                     <sic>h use</sic>
                     <corr>house</corr>
                  </choice> and a Rolls Royce car. She was always in debt, always giving her money
                  to others. Her hordes of dependents preyed upon her &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Meanwhile the drink habit was fastening upon her. She began to break. Her hands
                  would tremble. She would break into hysterical laughter. One night she saw
                  things.</p>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <p>Meanwhile also a whispering campaign of slander was circulating through the Movie
                  City, and stealing out of New York and over the country. Her name became a byword.
                  In spite of her fame, people thought of her as one addicted to wild parties and
                  dissipations, and the stories grew like a rolling snowball.</p>
               <p>Note: I realize that all this is not for picture use. Nevertheless it is in the</p>
                  <p style="text-decoration:underline">novel.</p> <p>An important and integral part of my story.</p>
               <p><choice>
                     <sic>Mav s</sic>
                     <corr>Mavis</corr>
                  </choice> goes to see a famous alienist. He tells her that she is somewhat
                  psychopathic. She did not know the meaning of the word. Found it in the
                  dictionary. And was furious. She threw another party. The alienist had <choice>
                     <sic>advisedher</sic>
                     <corr>advised her</corr>
                  </choice> to run away from her environment. Mavis retorted that you cannot run
                  away from yourself. She went to her little bungalow at <choice>
                     <sic>Malibou</sic>
                     <corr>Malibu</corr>
                  </choice> Beach---but the stillness and quiet of the place got upon her nerves. At
                  night she imagined things were following her, and one day she struck a dog, who
                  wailed at her door. A collapse followed, and she was taken to the hospital.</p>
               <p>(I have some immense chapters on this phase, but it is not Movie material, though
                  great for my novel)</p>
               <p>While sick, Blanton comes to see her. She tells him that if she only knew where
                  David was--if she could but see him, she would be a changed girl. David was always
                  back of her mind. Blanton, who is at bottom a good sort promises to do what he can
                  to locate David, and Mavis tells him of David’s music.</p>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <p>She has the music with her. Blanton, who is himself somewhat of a <choice>
                     <sic>connoiseur</sic>
                     <corr>connoisseur</corr>
                  </choice> on music, looks it over. He tells Mavis he believes they can use it in a
                  picture they are about to produce. Sound pictures have now come in. Music is more
                  and more in demand.</p>
               <p>Mavis feels new life and ambition. After leaving the hospital, she retires to <choice>
                     <sic>Malibou</sic>
                     <corr>Malibu</corr>
                  </choice>, and there she and Blanton whip David’s music into shape. She <choice>
                     <sic>thr ws</sic>
                     <corr>throws</corr>
                  </choice> herself heart and soul into the work. No more booze--no more parties<choice>
                     <sic>no ending punctuation</sic>
                     <corr>.</corr>
                  </choice> She lives for but one thing-----to see David’s music put across.</p>
               <p>The picture goes into production. Mavis is great and big enough to be satisfied to
                  subordinate her own talent for the good of the picture. She wants everything to
                  depend on David’s music.</p>
               <p>The Premiere of Hollywood Melody.</p>
               <p>This time Mavis is not behind the ropes---we see the celebrities pouring in,
                  beautifully dressed &amp;c. and Mavis the star of them all. As she goes in on the
                  arm of Blanton thinking the throng are all admiring her, we catch bits of their
                  excited talk. Though they admit her beauty and talent, everyone is whispering how
                  fast she is &amp;c &amp;c.</p>
               <p>(I’ve the dialogue in the novel)</p>
               <p>Mavis is the center of attraction. She is <choice>
                     <sic>raduiantly</sic>
                     <corr>radiantly</corr>
                  </choice> happy---blissfully so, when suddenly she sees across the aisle David.
                  She stands up---wants to go to him, and he <pb n="9"/> smiles gravely across at
                  her.</p>
               <p>But music is now flooding the theatre---David’s music. The dreamy eyes of the <choice>
                     <sic>musica</sic>
                     <corr>musician</corr>
                  </choice> looks across at Mavis. He begins to realize what she is doing for <choice>
                     <sic>himm</sic>
                     <corr>him</corr>
                  </choice> and his heart is full to overflowing.</p>
               <p>Then the theatre is darkened, and the picture is begun. Millions of butterflies
                  seem fluttering over the screen. These come flying toward the <choice>
                     <sic>camers</sic>
                     <corr>cameras</corr>
                  </choice> and as they come they turn into the faces of girls---Movie Butterflies--
                  till there is finally the one girl Mavis------ This is just a bit of imagery,
                  preceding the title sheets.</p>
               <p>And now the title sheet is being shown, and Mavis receives the shock of her life,
                  for the credit for the music and lyrics is given not to David but to Blanton.</p>
               <p>She is nearly distracted. Blanton tries to reassure her. Tells her it is some
                  error at the studio, but Mavis insists she must go to David---David----and in the
                  intermission she tries to reach him----but all she can see is the boy’s shoulders
                  drooped and <choice>
                     <sic>hunchedlike</sic>
                     <corr>hunched like</corr>
                  </choice> an old man’s, David’s dropped head, as though he had received a death
                  thrust.</p>
               <p>Then with the outpouring of the throngs, and people crushing <choice>
                     <sic>t</sic>
                     <corr>to</corr>
                  </choice> congratulate her <choice>
                     <sic>no ending punctuation</sic>
                     <corr>.</corr>
                  </choice> Mavis makes the motions with her arms of a swimmer, as she tries to make
                  way through the crowd.</p>
               <p><q>David! David!</q> she cries, and plucks his sleeve.</p>
               <p>He gives her a deep, dark look, and says the one <pb n="10"/> word:</p>
               <p>Thief!</p>
               <p>He pushes his way out.</p>
               <p>Blindly Mavis turns back. Someone has her arm--is guiding her. She realizes it is
                  Blanton. She turns on him in a fury, and regardless of who hears her, of the
                  sensation she is making she cries:</p>
               <p><q>Don’t touch me! I hate you! I hate you! I wish you were dead!</q></p>
               <p> She breaks away, and pushes through the throng, and on to the door.</p>
               <p><q>Get <choice>
                        <sic>mea</sic>
                        <corr>me a</corr>
                     </choice> taxi</q> she says to man at door.</p>
               <p>To Taxi man she says:</p>
               <p><q>Drive me anywhere---keep on driving</q>.</p>
               <p>All that night she drives, till about four in the morning, when the clouds begin
                  to clear a bit from her mind. She <choice>
                     <sic>decidew</sic>
                     <corr>decides</corr>
                  </choice> to go to Blanton--to have it out with him-- to <choice>
                     <sic>d mand</sic>
                     <corr>demand</corr>
                  </choice> the rest of David’s music.</p>
               <p>At Blanton’s Villa, in a place somewhat like Garden of Alla, she receives no
                  answer to her knocking. Going to the patio, she finds the window to his bedroom
                  open--a curtain blowing <choice>
                     <sic>ou</sic>
                     <corr>out</corr>
                  </choice>. She climbs in. Feeling for the light, her foot touches something soft
                  on floor. A horror sweeps over her. She tries to get back to window, trips on the
                  rug, and falls over a body. She screams like one gone mad. Then faints over the
                  body.</p>
               <pb n="11"/>
               <p>Her screams have aroused people in the court. There is a rush from every
                  direction---and the chauffeur who had waited for her outside, hammers on door.
                  Finally the door is broken down. A search of the villa, and in the man’s bed room,
                  Mavis is discovered in a swoon, over the body of Blanton.</p>
               <p>The following day, from one end of the country to the other, the sensational story
                  of Mavis Lee appears in the newspapers. She is pilloried. Regardless of whether
                  she had murdered Blanton or not, before she has been tried, <choice>
                     <sic>ornthe</sic>
                     <corr>or the</corr>
                  </choice> circumstances sifted, she is cruelly adjudged by public opinon.
                  Overnight her fame has become notoriety. No one recalls her beautiful hobbledehoy
                  ways on the screen; her loveable personality the hours of laughter and
                  entertainment she has given them. She is a bad woman. A woman found in a man’s
                  room &amp;c. Blanton was a married man and so forth.</p>
               <p><choice>
                     <sic>Appisoner</sic>
                     <corr>A prisoner</corr>
                  </choice> in her own house, held as a witness, for the Coroner’s Inquest, her
                  place surrounded by reporters and curious she crouches in her bed.</p>
               <p>An enterprising young reporter gets into the place over the roof, and via a little
                  balcony. There Mavis cries:</p>
               <p><q>What do you want?</q></p>
               <p>He says he is a friend who has come to help her.</p>
               <p>No one ever needed help more than she. He explains that he represents millions of
                  people who wish to hear her <pb n="12"/> story. In her rage at discovering he is
                  just a reporter she leaps out of bed, flinging anything and everything within
                  reach at him. He flees. <choice>
                     <sic>Comesout</sic>
                     <corr>Comes out</corr>
                  </choice> front door. Intimates he has had exclusive interview. Next day a
                  fantastic story of a <choice>
                     <sic>socalled</sic>
                     <corr>so called</corr>
                  </choice> personal and exclusive interview with the <choice>
                     <sic>allgged</sic>
                     <corr>alleged</corr>
                  </choice> murderess.</p>
               <p>There is a Coroner’s Inquest, into which I will not go here. The testimony of the
                  chauffeur and a woman tenant give Mavis an alibi. Incontestable.</p>
               <p>The ordeal has been a frightful one. Mobs besiege the place. Outside they cannot
                  get through hardly. She is nearly frantic with fear. Her lawyer gets her away
                  somehow, advises her to go to Malibu. At Malibu, <choice>
                     <sic>er</sic>
                     <corr>her</corr>
                  </choice> car speeds by, for she sees reporters waiting there for her. It is now
                  night. Farther up the beach she bids her chauffeur let her out. He is to return to
                  the city. She will telephone later.</p>
               <p>She <choice>
                     <sic>goesout</sic>
                     <corr>goes out</corr>
                  </choice> on the beach, lies on the sand. At five o’clock in the morning she wakes
                  with the seagulls and the clamoring wild geese. Seems as if earth and sky are
                  merged one. She feels part, of the great all <choice>
                     <sic>encompassibuniverse</sic>
                     <corr>encompassing universe</corr>
                  </choice>. She takes off her shoes---walks across the sands--and thus she arrives
                  at her home, unseen by the reporters, and slipping in at back with a latchkey.</p>
               <p>Her star now is in the complete descendant. The company she had worked for tell
                  her the demand of the exhibitors is such that her picture be withdrawn that they
                  dare not release <pb n="13"/> it. They point out the morals clause in her contract
                  &amp;c. In a flame of resentment she scoffs at them---repudiates the contract.
                  Declares all the companies are after her &amp;c.</p>
               <p>(omitted to mention <choice>
                     <sic>and</sic>
                     <corr>an</corr>
                  </choice> important detail <choice>
                     <sic>hwre</sic>
                     <corr>here</corr>
                  </choice>. It was discovered after Blanton’s death, that his last act on earth was
                  a note he had written, stressing the mistake made by someone at the studio, and
                  giving full credit to David Pivar)</p>
               <p>Mavis is astonished to find that the attitude of other companies is adverse to
                  her. No one can take a chance on her. She is taboo. This is not the fault of the
                  producers, but the demand and condemnation of the public itself, who have stamped
                  upon their former idol.</p>
               <p>Gradually she disposes of everything she has to pay her debts. She is right up
                  against it. She does finally sign a contract to play in a picture, the producer
                  being new to Hollywood. Three days after it goes into production she discover-it
                  is one of those hideous pathological things, of the sort where cards <choice>
                     <sic>mustgo</sic>
                     <corr>must go</corr>
                  </choice> up: <q>For men only</q> or <choice>
                     <sic>no beginning quotation mark</sic>
                     <corr>‛‛</corr>
                  </choice>For women only’’.</p>
               <p>She refuses to go on. The suave producer puts a double in her place, but the
                  disgusting picture is released as if Mavis were the star. This is the last straw,
                  and Mavis disappears.</p>
               <p>Time heals all our wounds it is said. The mystery of Blanton’s death is not
                  cleared. Mavis’s story occasionally peters out in the newspapers, but in a year or
                  so it is a dead <pb n="14"/> issue. Then one day there came to Hollywood a famous
                  psychologist and writer. He is doing a series of articles for a national magazine
                  on the subject of Famous Murders and Mysteries. This man lives very quietly, but
                  he is on the scientific systematic trial of the history of Mavis Lee.</p>
               <p>In due time there appears in the magazine an article with the title:</p>
               <p style="width:40%">WHERE IS MAVIS LEE?</p>
               <p>What has become of that bright spirit &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Public conscience is a peculiar thing. This article somehow strikes home. Club
                  women and others over the country, fans &amp;c. begin writing to the papers,
                  demanding the return of Mavis. This article had turned a magnifying searchlight
                  upon the little formerly radiant star, and revealed her not as the hardened
                  dissipated notorious person, but as a loveable, beautiful prodigal soul and
                  moreover it had cleared up her innocent connection with Blanton.</p>
               <p>This man also has <choice>
                     <sic>approa ched</sic>
                     <corr>approached</corr>
                  </choice> David Pivar now musical director for a big company. David tells him he
                  has searched everywhere for Mavis.</p>
               <p>One day, in a projection room, David sits with a group of officials listening to
                  several voices that are to double for some star. Suddenly he sits up erectly. A
                  low, <pb n="15"/> throaty, husky <choice>
                     <sic>co tralto</sic>
                     <corr>contralto</corr>
                  </choice> is stealing through the room. Only one person could sing like
                  that--Mavis! He demands to know whose voice that is. One of the men answers: <q>A
                     little woman- ---just an extra</q>.</p>
               <p>Later the saem man points <q>the little old woman</q> out to him as she is passing
                  through the gates. Something about the way she lifted her head recalled Mavis to
                  him. He becomes electrified, and rushes after her. Unmindful of trucks and cars on
                  all sides, he barely reaches the bus into which she has climbed and which is now
                  moving. He sits down beside her. He sees that grey hair is a wig. Mavis had been
                  earning her living as an old <choice>
                     <sic>womab</sic>
                     <corr>woman</corr>
                  </choice>. He speaks her name. She trembles. Shakes her head---declares he is
                  making a mistake. He pleads--begs--They get off the bus. She tries to hurry ahead
                  of him. He lets her think she <choice>
                     <sic>haseluded</sic>
                     <corr>has eluded</corr>
                  </choice> him; but presently he sees her---she is turning in to Paradise
                  Court---the court where first they had met. Just as she pauses at the stoop of her
                  house, David steps up. Again he calls her-------she shakes her head. Her face
                  turns against the door. She begins to sob. David puts his arms around her---lifts
                  the wig from her head--the dark glasses from her eyes---wipes the artificial
                  wrinkles--the makeup. Then he kisses her. She relaxes in his arms.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>