<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="IAmAWhite1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>I am a White N[---]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from original at University of Calgary, Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</note></notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:57"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
         <abstract resp="pers:ST1">
            <p>This incomplete typescript explores a common topic in Eaton’s oeuvre: the lived experience of mixed-race people. Rather than presenting this figure as a spectacle, however, <q>I am a White N[---]</q> highlights the precarity of racial passing in the US, where a single drop of Black blood disqualified one from whiteness and full citizenship. In this regard, it recalls contemporary narratives such as James Weldon Johnson’s <title level="j">Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</title> (1912) and Nella Larsen’s <title level="j">Passing</title> (1929). Though the use of a slur in the story’s title indicates the protagonist’s bitterness at American racism, her eventual rejection of Black identity illustrates Eaton’s sensitivity to the lure of white privilege despite economic hardships that cut across the color line. Eaton’s use of the terms <q>Creole</q> and <q>quadroon</q> showcases this period’s attention to minute degrees of racial and cultural distinction. The phrase <q>white n*****</q> entered English usage as early as the late 1820s. The US antebellum period witnessed a shift in racial ideology from nativism to white supremacism (i.e. a shift in attention from one’s origins to one’s skin color), during which Northern politicians and union organizers often made invidious comparisons between white wage labor and slavery. In 1836, a story with a similar title (<q>The White N*****</q>) was published by the (then) well-known Nova Scotian humorist Thomas Chandler Haliburton. His usage, in a tale about the auctioning off of white orphans and elderly folk, suggests <q>a white person likened to or treated like a black slave</q> (<title level="j">Oxford English Dictionary</title>). Notably, in Eaton’s nonfiction article <ref target="doc:TheHalfCaste1"><q>The Half Caste</q></ref> (1898), she observes that the word <q>n*****</q> was sometimes applied to mixed-race people of Japanese and European descent.</p>
         </abstract>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="empty">
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2021-06-16">Added headnote.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2020-08-12">Square brackets.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2020-07-30">Changed title. Need to add note.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2020-06-30">Added note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl57 using XSLT</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs= "facs:IAmAWhite">
      <body>
         <div>
            <gap reason="noTranscriptionAvailable"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
