<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="InTheCastle1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>In the Castle of Hikone</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:ST1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SG1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>5.7</idno>
                  <idno type="UofC">CU111913101</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl275"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Anonymous</name></author>.
                           <title level="a">In the Castle of Hikone</title>. ms., <date
                           notBefore="1917" notAfter="1935">1917-1935</date>, <distributor
                           ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>,
                           <idno>5.7</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at University of
                           Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-08-24" status="published">Encoded. Set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-01-05" status="empty">Adding document from 2023 Calgary
            Transcribe-a-thon.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:InTheCastle1">
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <head>IN THE CASTLE OF <choice>
               <sic>HIKONE’</sic>
               <corr>HIKONE</corr>
            </choice></head>
         <opener>
            <byline>by</byline>
            <byline><unclear reason="faded"><name ref="pers:WE1">ONOTO
               WATANNA</name></unclear></byline>
         </opener>
         <div type="content">
            <p><q>How lovely the little Princess Sado-Ko looks</q>, murmured the young Frenchman
               dreamily.</p>

            <p><q>If I were you</q>, gruffly responded his companion, in an undertone, <q>I should
                  not look at her so much</q>.</p>

            <p>The young Frenchman sighed, but his inconstant gaze wandered back to that great
               Chamber of Honor, which was separated from the one in which they were only by one
               deep step.</p>

            <p><q>There is something about her appealing and gentle</q>, said the young Frenchman.
                  <q>I am sure her voice is sweet, though I have never heard her speak. Have you,
                  Von Bernheim?</q></p>

            <p><q>Certainly not. No foreigner, or for that matter, no ordinary Japanese, can
                  approach the ladies of the Premier’s household</q>.</p>

            <p>The young Frenchman did not seem to hear his friend. He leaned farther forward, the
               better to see the little figure by the half opened screen.</p>

            <p><q>How charmingly she bends her little neck</q>, he said. <q>It looks as white as
                  milk from here</q>.</p>

            <p>His companion’s hand closed angrily upon his arm, and he drew the young Frenchman
               forcibly about, so that he was now faced the colossal columns of the Castle.</p>

            <p><q>You may have reasons to think of your own neck, my friend!</q> he growled, <q>if
                  one of her kinsmen <pb n="2"/> suspect your folly. Look about you. On all sides,
                  what do you see? Here in the Castle, beneath their silken robes, these
                  soft-speaking Japanese carry the sword. Below, there in the vast courtyard, inside
                  and out of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yashiki</foreign> (fortified dwelling) there
                  are a thousand <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>, who are the servants of
                  this Premier Ii-Kamon-no-Kami. Their faces are blank, inscrutable, as they look at
                  us ever askance; but I will tell you of what they are thinking. They are thinking
                  of the day, when they can throw aside the mask. One word, one look, from this
                  Ii-Kamon-no-Kami, and our lives would not be worth that</q>, and he snapped his
               fingers together in an eloquent motion.</p>

            <p>The young Frenchman regarded the fierce old face of the German with an element of
               reproach.</p>

            <p><q>Why, Von Bernheim</q>, he protested gently, <q>every courtesy has been shown us
                  here. Let us not question the motives of His Excellency, while we are beneath his
                  roof. Are we not his especially honored guests?</q></p>

            <p><q>Guests!</q> repeated the German savagely, <q>Say rather -- prisoners! We did not
                  come here to be the guests of this Japanese</q>.</p>

            <p><q>But when he so graciously invited us to remain, we are delighted to
               accept</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Are you then obsessed?</q> demanded the older man, in rising exasperation. <q>What
                  can I say to you that will wake you up to the terrible realities of our situation.
                  Surely you know as well as I what our position in the Castle Hikone is</q>.</p>

            <pb n="2b"/>
            <!-- This page is an addition with no page #, so I have for now named it 2b -->

            <pb n="3"/>

            <p>The young Frenchman stirred uneasily.</p>

            <p><q>Since we are here</q>, he said, <q>why should we not endeavor to make our enforced
                  stay tolerable? It can do no harm to look at this little Princess Sado-Ko</q>. He
               spoke the last sentence with a certain wistfulness, and, again, almost unconsciously
               his sentimental glance strayed back to that charming upper chamber, which was
               elevated like a throne, whose screens were all of gold, through which the sunlight
               pierced, and whose floors shone like glass. The latticed wall at back had been pushed
               to either side, making of the chamber an opened pavilion, and revealing the garden
               without. Like an exquisite, impressionistic picture of some fairy scene, a grove of
               cherry trees blew all pink and white against a sky of purest blue.</p>

            <p>The air was soft and full of the essence of Spring. There was a faint fragrance in
               the atmosphere, a dim odor as of some subtle incense, which pervaded and made
               pleasant the place. It acted like a charm upon the senses, and to the romantic young
               Frenchman seemed the last touch to a scene that was perfect. He forgot the grumbling,
               warning old German at his side. His face flushed with emotion, his dark eyes humid,
               he gazed so ardently and compellingly at the little Princess Sado-Ko, that her head
               drooped like a flower and her own cheek grew warm. Under his breath, the young
               Frenchman murmured:</p>

            <p><q>One cannot help but look at her! It is impossible <pb n="4"/> to resist</q>.</p>

            <p><q>You are mad -- mad</q>, said the German, staring at him, with an enraged and
               indignant expression.</p>

            <p><q>Ah, good friend</q>, said the young Frenchman gently, <q>have not you in your time
                  loved? Look! She is turning this way now! How <emph>pretty</emph> she is! How
                  incredibly pretty! I did not think it was possible for a Japanese woman to be so
                  lovely. I never see her soft little cheek, but I long to touch it -- to press it.
                  I am sure it is as fragrant as a flower!</q></p>

            <p>Von Bernheim’s voice was hoarse.</p>

            <p><q>And while you are mooning over the cheek of this Japanese princess</q>, he said,
                  <q>you forget what may be happening to your fellow-countrymen in Japan!</q></p>

            <p>Slowly the young Frenchman turned, his long patrician face paling.</p>

            <p><q>No, no, good Von Bernheim, do not suggest anything horrible. The day is so lovely.
                  There is friendliness and kindness in the faces of all about us. I feel -- I feel
                  so strangely light and happy, like one who is being drawn up to some blissful
                  height. I am sure that everything is good and well with our people. Why do you
                  suggest something that is sinister and horrible?</q></p>

            <p><q>I do not suggest -- I assert! Our people are in dire peril. You yourself realized
                  that before we came to Castle Hikone. You know what our mission was here. Were we
                  not warned by our friends -- friends we could trust and believe, even though they
                  were Japanese --</q> He added the last with a fierce reluctance, <q>that a
                  massacre of the <pb n="5"/>White people in Japan is impending? We came here to
                  demand protection for our people. With flattering promises and assurances he has
                  kept us here --- as his honored guests! Why? That is the question I keep asking
                  myself</q>.</p>

            <p><q>It may be</q>, eagerly declared the young Frenchman, <q>that he wishes to
                  demonstrate his friendship. His liking for the white people is well known. It was
                  he who signed the Treaties that have made the trouble</q>.</p>

            <p><q>He dared not do otherwise, while the allied fleet was afloat in the waters of
                  Japan. Now he must placate the enraged Japanese. His is a dangerous position. It
                  is said he is the worst hated man in Japan. But whatever may be his reasons for
                  keeping us here, whether to protect us, or as hostages while demands are made upon
                  our people -- I cannot say -- let us, at least, do nothing that may arouse his
                  antagonism. Let us capitalize our time by guarding every word, every look every
                  thought. Ah, my young friend, I speak only for your good</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I know you do, Von Bernheim</q>, said the young Frenchman in a low voice.
                  <q>Pardon me that I have tried your patience</q>.</p>

            <p><q>This is what troubles me the most -- what gives me no rest, day or night --- the
                  thought of what may be happening to those we left. Oh my friend, with the passing
                  of each day -- each hour, I seem to feel a sense of terrible disaster rushing upon
                  us</q>.</p>

            <pb n="6"/>

            <p>Impulsively, the young Frenchman cried out at that:</p>

            <p><q>Let us go. Let us leave this place, Von Bernheim. We should not be here. You are
                  right. I did wrong to think of anything save those who trusted me. Let us go to
                  them now. Let us not stay another moment. Traitor that I am, I had lulled my
                  conscience to sleep with pretty dreams and fancies. I see now the danger that
                  encircles us</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Even if we could freely pass the countless doors of the Castle Hikone</q>, said
               the German, shaking his head gravely, <q>we would be simply throwing ourselves upon
                  the waiting swords without. It would be suicidal and useless. It might prove to be
                  a signal for a general attack upon those we wish to save. No -- we cannot leave.
                  Here is our place for the present. Yet, while we are here, I beg you do no single
                  act that may hurt us. Keep your young eyes from this Princess Sado-Ko. Lovely she
                  may be, but do not forget, she is Japanese, and hence our enemy</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Ah Von Bernheim</q>, pleaded the young Frenchman, <q>do not think too hardly of
                  these people. I am sure we have many friends among them. Let us not judge a race
                  by the acts of individuals</q>.</p>

            <p>Said the German doggedly and bitterly: <q>I know these people well. I have studied
                  them as under a microscope. Beneath their silken veneer of smiles and purring
                  flattery, they are a race of savages! You will see! You have seen already! How
                  many of our good friends, who blindly trusted them, as you are doing, have paid
                  for their trust with their lives. Not in open fights -- as we white <pb n="7"/>
                  men meet our foes -- as man to man, in the square light of day! We’ve been cut
                  down in the dark -- stabbed in the back by unseen assassins!</q></p>

            <p>The young Frenchman was silent. He stood with his slender hand cupping his chin, in
               some troubled thought. Half protestingly, half conciliating, at last he spoke:</p>

            <p><q>It is pleasant to think of the men of our race who have died in Japan as martyrs;
                  yet, we foreigners should be honest, at least, with ourselves. We know that moat
                  of these acts of violence were cruelly provoked. Have we not acted here as
                  disdainful conquerors, rather than friends? Have we not arrogantly usurped to
                  ourselves insolent authorities? There is a Japanese proverb peculiarly applicable,
                  Von Bernheim, in our case: ’Our actions are followed by their consequences as
                  surely as a body by its shadow’</q>.</p>

            <p>The old German diplomat had removed his glasses and polished them fiercely. Now he
               shook them in the face of the young Frenchman.</p>

            <p><q>Men like you should remain at home. We white men must be served by our partisans,
                  not dreamers. It does not matter whether we have done right or wrong, whether our
                  desserts should be good or bad. That is not the problem we face now, and we cannot
                  give a thought to the causes that have precipitated the trouble. All that we can
                  think of now, is that these Japanese contemplate an assault upon our people. What
                  are we to do? How prevent this horrible calamity?</q></p>

            <pb n="8"/>

            <p><q>Let us go -- to our friends</q>, said the young Frenchman, with emotion.</p>

            <p><q>No -- this is the only place of safety for us at least</q>, declared the
               other.</p>

            <p><q>Ah, but I do not wish to be safe when our friends are in peril</q>, said the
               Frenchman.</p>

            <p>Von Bernheim made a hopeless motion with his hands, and then cautiously signalled for
               the other to be silent. A group of young courtiers, their silken robes of many colors
               trailing in the ancient style from their shoulders, and their fans fluttering like
               butterflies, came from out the quarters of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kuge</foreign>
               (Nobles) of the Castle Hikone, paused to bow with deep respect before the elevated
               room of the Princens Sado-Ko and passed the white men with flattering bows and
               hissing intakes of breath, ere they descended, whispering behind their fans, down
               into the Court yard below.</p>

            <p>The ladies of the Princess Sado-Ko craned their little necks at the passing nobles,
               peeped from behind their fans, and fell to chattering among themselves, laughing and
               teasing each other like a lot of playful children. Their merry, musical voices,
               floated down to the two men by the balustrade, and the young Frenchman turned slowly
               about, as if reluctantly charmed. Even as he turned, the Princeaa Sado-Ko looked up
               suddenly from her work, and for the space of a long moment, her bright dark eyes
               rested upon his own. It seemed to the young Frenchman at that moment as if he stood
               under some gloriously hued rainbow, that all the world had turned once more fair and
               charming, and that above all<pb n="9"/> else eyes that were full of a sweet mystery
               dumbly spoke across a great abyss to him a story that was like the passionate song of
               Lorelei. He scarcely heard the words of the German in his ear. He was conscious only
               of a ruthless, stabbing pain, as mechanically, true to his promise to his friend, he
               tore his gaze from the face of the Princess Sado-Ko, and as if forever to emphasize
               his heroic resolve, turned his back harshly upon her.</p>

            <p>And she? She had wondered much lately over this strange, exquisite tumult that had
               come floodingly to her heart. All through the golden days of this Season of Clear
               Weather, she had been warmly conscious of those long, yearning glances of the young
               Frenchman. She knew not why, as she sat among her maidens, her mind had ever wandered
               from her work to question with gentle wonder this blissful radiance that quivered
               within her. and now, it seemed to her at this moment, a calamity had suddenly
               befallen. Her eyes very wide and dark turned not away from that averted face. A
               strangely piteous look crept across her sensitive features. Abstractedly, she leaned
               forward. The ball of silk fell from her knee and the needle stuck idly in the <choice>
                  <sic>emboridery</sic>
                  <corr>embroidery</corr>
               </choice> frame. As still, stiffly, rigidly, sternly, the young Frenchman’s face
               remained turned from her, a sigh that was very long and <choice>
                  <sic>woful</sic>
                  <corr>woeful</corr>
               </choice> came from the lips of the Princess Sado-Ko. Her little world of sun and
               glitter seemed to swim about her. Something came welling up to her sweet long eyes
               and dropped upon the head of her little handmaiden kneeling at her feet. The child
               looked up, startled, an unuttered question upon <pb n="10"/> her lips.</p>

            <p><q>Alas!</q> said the Princess Sado-Ko, <q>the honorable needle was sharp. It had
                  pricked me!</q></p>

            <p><q>Where is it your graciousness has wounded her celestial self?</q> queried the
               anxious little maid, seizing the hands of her mistress and eagerly examining
               them.</p>

            <p><q>Ah, nay!</q> said the Princess Sado-Ko, arising and standing very straight and
               white among her maidens, her gaze still upon the young Frenchman, <q>it is not my
                  miserable hands I have hurt, my ladies!</q></p>

            <p>With fluttering murmurs of sympathy they came about her, asking solicitously what
               especial part of her most august anatomy the sacriligious needle had dared to pierce.
               But the Princess Sado-Ko did not answer her maidens. She had drawn her little white
               hands --- they were soft and fragrant as sweet slender lilies --- from the grasp of
               the kneeling child at her feet, and now she laid them crushingly upon her heart.</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>There was a festival in the streets below that night. They called it: <q>A Festival
                  of the Lanterns</q>, but to the two men, looking over the ballustrade, those
               dancing flames seemed something more than the friendly light of lanterns. Why did
               they run so fleetly, those brown, whispering people, and what gave to their voices
               that exultant snarl, as of fanatic madmen bent upon some conquering course? How
               horribly menacing seemed their savage faces under the threatening light of the angry,
               waving torches. A crowd had <pb n="11"/> gathered directly under the gates of the
               Castle Hikone, and suddenly a crier’s voice, shrill and sweet as a woman’s, but with
               a throbbing note of wild defiance, rang out upon the air, drowning the rumbling
               murmurs of the throng.</p>

            <p><q>Ii-Kamon-no-Kami!</q> cried the shrill, fierce voice, <q>friend of the white
                  barbarians, make your peace with the Eternal Gods!</q></p>

            <p>The cry was caught up by a hundred throats, till it seemed to come thundering against
               the iron gates of the Castle and to sweep beyong them into the fortified Yaskiki of
               the Premier Prince of Japan. A file of <foreign xml:lang="ja">Samurai</foreign>
               passed along the walls of the courtyard and slipped out of the gates into the street.
               A hubub arose without -- angry, defiant outcries, strangling shrieks, and the savage
               clatter of sword meeting sword; then the clacking patter of a hundred clogs beating
               in hurried retreat upon the pavement. The light of the angry torches died away. A
               silence fell all about the Castle Hikone.</p>

            <p>To the two white men, looking with haggard faces and straining eyes off over the
               marble balustrade of the second enciente of tho Castle, that silence was more
               appaling than the menacing cries of before. Waiting for they knew not what terror,
               scarcely breathing, they tried to pierce the thick darkness. Suddenly the older man
               gripped the arm of the younger and pointed off toward the west. Like a snake, against
               the blackness of the sky, a flame had suddenly leaped. It spread like forked
               lightning, licking its zigzag way across <pb n="12"/> the darkness, and joined in one
               dark blur of smoke and flame.</p>



            <p><q>My God!</q> cried the young Frenchman stranglingly, <q>the legations are
                  afire!</q></p>

            <p>Like some, wild, enraged beast, prodded and beaten beyound hurt, up leaped the old
               German, ran with his great head lowered almost as a battering ram before him, blindly
               along the parapet, till he reached the forbidden stairs. Darkness was beneath him,
               but he plunged down, down, into that mad pandemonium of hoarsely shouting, moving
               shapes that were pouring out through the now wide open gates of the Castle
               Hikone.</p>

            <p>For a moment only the young Frenchman hesitated. Then with a cry: <q>Von Bernheim, my
                  friend!</q> he started to follow. Something seemed to blow like a fluttering bird
               across his path, holding and staying his progress.</p>

            <p>Under the reflected light of that fearful flame in the west, he saw her face, white
               and wild, close to his own. Her little hands had somehow found their way to his
               shoulders. He tried to shake them off but there they clung resiatlessly.</p>

            <p><q>Outside country-man!</q> she whisperingly cried, <q>go not outside the Castle
                  Hikone tonight!</q></p>

            <p>He tried to speak, to turn his head back toward that flaming west, but the little
               frantic hands, clutching at his shoulders, drew him ever along, farther and farther
               back toward that golden room, where always she had sat among her maidens. Her face
               was so close to his own. Her soft, black hair came blowing against his lips. Like the
               wings of a bird, her long, silken sleeves seemed to reach out and <pb n="13"/> enwrap
               him to her. Dazed and charmed he moved along with her, but ever as he moved, he
               murmured hoarsely, like one who speaks in distress.</p>

            <p><q>Ah -- my people! my people! I must go to them!</q></p>

            <p><q>No, no</q> she said, <q>it is here you shall remain</q>.</p>

            <p><q>If I could -- if I dared -- how gladly would I stay</q> he stammered, like one in
               a sweet bewilderment, <q>but my people---my people---</q>.<note type="editorial"
                  >Period in original.</note></p>

            <p><q>They shall be saved</q> she said. <q>In my father’s name I promise it. He himself
                  will personally go to them. Rest you in confidence and safety, outside
                  country-man. I and my maidens will guard you from all harm!</q></p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>He awoke with a start. The dim, grey light of dawn had fallen. A robin twittered and
               called. A dull, slow rain fell sounctlessly. Everywhere he was enclosed by screens
               that were so freighted with gold and lacquer that they shone even in the dark. For a
               long time he stared before him, like one struggling to awaken from a trance. Then
               gradually there crept across his mobile features a strangely startled look -- the
               look of one mortally afraid. Blotting out all memory of that strange, sweet night of
               ecstacy, there came up suddenly to his mind with scorching vividness that flaming sky
               of the West.</p>

            <p>What was he doing here, resting among those silken futons, like a child soothed to
               sleep by a song? He reached out a hand and cautiously shoves aside a screen. Without,
               still asleep, those she had set to guard and care for him lay, like a <choice>
                  <sic>barriacade</sic>
                  <corr>barricade</corr>
               </choice> in his path. He stepped across them, <pb n="14"/> holding his breath,
               fearing with every move to awaken them. He came to a latticed <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >shoji</foreign>, and pushed it along its groove. It was still dark without, and
               the rain fell sullenly. All about him was silence, save for the twittering robin.
               Along the wide verandah that stretched without the apartments of the Princess
               Sado-Ko, he felt his way, till he came to the rampart of the Castle and crept along
               the ballustrade to the stairs.</p>

            <p>The Courtyard was strangely still and empty. Not a guard patrolled the inner walls,
               and the gates gaped wide open, unguarded. He stayed not to question this strange
               dereliction of the servants of his host, but, glancing upward suddenly, his agonized
               gaze fell upon something that sent him for a moment staggering back. Swinging on a
               line drawn from post to post of the great gates of the Castle Hikone, hung by his
               long, damp hair, was the head of the Baron Ii-Kamon-no-Kami, the friend of the white
               men!</p>

            <p>For a moment the young Frenchman stared up at this ghastly object, and then, his head
               dropping, as Von Bernheim’s had done, he dashed out of those terrible gates.</p>

            <p><del>Out into</del> the dark and silent streets sped the Frenchman. As the Castle
               Hikone had been, so seemed this whole city, enwrapped in a stillness and silence that
               was not merely of the dawn.</p>

            <p>On and on, through the deserted streets, blindly ran the young Frenchman.</p>

            <p>The sun came up in the eastern sky, and showed a dim questioning face through the
               mist. Far off in the hills <pb n="15"/> came the dull booming of a Temple bell, but
               its mellow chant found no response from the temples of this haggard city which dared
               not to awake.</p>

            <p>On and on, over miles of streets and bare stretches of land, up endless hills and
               down through dales and valleys, and again through streets that never seemed to end,
               until at last (but not, alas! like one who has run a great race -- home!) he dashed
               into the debris and the smouldering ruins of <q>The Street of White Devils</q>, as
               they had named it in Japan.</p>

            <p><q>My God, My God, My God!</q> he cried like one gone mad.</p>

            <p>There as a great dismantled litter in the center of the street, once doubtless, the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimon</foreign> of some personage of high rank. In his
               distraction, the young Frenchman neither saw nor recognized that luxurious equipage,
               that had so often pleased and interested his fancy. His glance went wildly from one
               stricken form to another. Here was a white woman, her bare arms and shoulders still
               gleaming like white ivory above her beautiful gown, lying with her tortured face all
               torn, Here was a man he had known well -- one of Japan’s truest friends -- and here
               was a child -- a little boy, whose small, chubby hand still grasped a toy -- an
               American warboa!? How many times the young Frenchman had held the little fellow upon
               his knee and played with him! And here -- and here was one he had knowm better than
               all -- Von Bernheim!</p>

            <p>So he had come in time, in time to die with those he loved. Never again would the
               young Frenchroan hear his biting voice or laugh at his quaint accent. How gallant he
               looked, even in <pb n="16"/> death? How clean -- and strong!</p>

            <p> How clean -- and strong? The yound Frenchman burst into frantic tears, crying with
               the unbounded grief of one who never again may be comforted, and calling upon his
               friend to speak to him but once -- to forgive him!</p>

            <p>And as he wept, one crept from under that dismantled <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >norimon</foreign>, paused a moment to look at the young Frenchman with a
               brooding, passionate gaze, and then with her hand to her cheek, her dark eyes wide
               and sunken in her withered little face, the Princess Sado-Ko crept on her knees to
               his feet. </p>

            <p>It seemed not strange to him that she should be there, in this place of horror, she
               who had saved him at the expense of his honor. He covered his face with his hands,
               lest he should see hers, which he knew to be too fair. Her voice was like a thin
               thread of melody that comes from very far away.</p>

            <p><q>Outside countryman</q>, she said, <q>do not lose faith in our Japan. We are not
                  all base. See, here are the native servants and body guard of the foreigners, who
                  have fought and died for them. Japan stands at the dawn of a new era! We are going
                  to be born again. Do not forget that at the time of the rebirth of a nation, there
                  are always madmen who seek to destroy where our leaders strive to uplift
               us</q>.</p>

            <p>Against his will, he had permitted her to draw him close to that wrecked <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">norimon</foreign>, and now, very calmly, she drew aside the
               curtains, and showed him what was within.</p>

            <p><q>See---here is my father, the Premier of the <pb n="17"/>
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>, lying headless in his own blood. He came
                  here to help your countrymen. He was a friend of the white men, and of the
                  Japanese; but there he lies, a great martyr, a far-seeing patriot! May his journey
                  to the Lotus Land be one of bliss!</q></p>

            <p>He turned with a sick shudder from that fearful sight. He was conscious of a heavy
               sense of lassitude and despair. The charming sunny world had turned all black to him.
               Never again would his heart beat with with ambition and desire. In a single night
               Youth had leaped away from him.</p>

            <p>Now the day had fully dawned. The rain was quenched, and a bright red Run sailed out
               across the sky. Under its light, the pallid, steaming ruins showed in all their
               hideous nakedness. The young Frenchman threw up his arm, and cowered against it, then
               staggering, swaying, looking back not once at that desolate figure there alone among
               the ruins, he found his way through the deserted streets down to the harbor, where
               the ships of the white nations were vengefully pulling in to the shore.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
