<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="JapaneseNightingale6">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Japanese Nightingale</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1">Sijia Cheng</name>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1">Sijia Cheng</name>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1">Sijia Cheng</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:18"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovel"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-07-29">Added transcription</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2020-07-24">Changed title.</change><change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl18 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:JapaneseNightingale6">
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <div>
            
               <head>Japanese Nightingale</head>
            <opener>
               <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>
               <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:GY1">Genjiro Yeto</name></byline>
            </opener>
            <div>
               <head>I</head>
               <head type="subtitle">The Storm Dance</head>
               
               <p>The last rays of sunset were tingeing the land, lingering in splendor above the
                  bay. The waters had caught the golden glow, and, miser-like, seemingly made effort
                  to keep it with them; but, inexorably, the lowering sun drew away its gilding
                  light, leaving the waters a dark green. The shadows began to darken, faint stars
                  peeped out of the heavens, and slowly the day’s last ray followed the sunken sun
                  to rest; and with its vanishment a pale moon stole overhead and threw a seraphic
                  light over all things.</p>
               <pb n="2"/>
               <p>Out in the bay that the sun had left was a tiny island, and on this a Japanese
                  business man, who must also have been an artist, had built a tea-house and laid
                  out a garden. Such an island! In the sorcerous moonlight one might easily believe
                  it the witch-work of an Oriental Merlin. Running in every direction through the
                  island were narrow little <foreign xml:lang="ja">jinrikisha</foreign> roads, which
                  crossed bewildering little creeks, spanned by entrancing bridges. These were round
                  and high, and curved in the centre, and clinging vines and creeping, nameless
                  flowers crawled up the sides and twined about the tiny steps which ascendeded to
                  the bridges. After crossing a bridge shaped thus, a straight bridge is ofrever an
                  outrage to the eye and sense. And all along the beach of this island was pure
                  white sand, which looked weirdly whiter where the moonbeams loitered and played
                  hide-and-seek under the tree-shadows. </p>
               
               
               <p>The seekers of pleasure who made <pb n="3"/>their way out to the little island on
                  this night moored their boats here in the shadows beneath the trees, and drove in
                  fairy vehicles pulled by picturesque runners, clear around the island, under the
                  pine-trees, over miniature brooks, into the mysterious dark of a forest. Suddenly
                  they were in a blaze of swinging, dazzling lights, laughter and music, chatter,
                  the clattering of dishes, the twang of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samisen</foreign>, the ron-ton-ton of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >biwa</foreign>. They had reached the garden and the tea-house. </p>
               <p>Some pleasure-loving Japanese were giving a banquet in honor of the full moon, and
                  the moon, just over their heads, clothed in glorious raiment, and sitting on a
                  sky-throne of luminous silver, was attending the banquet in person, surrounded my
                  myriad twinkling stars, who played at being her courtiers. Each of the guests had
                  his own little mat, table and waitress. They sat in a semicircle, and <pb n="4"
                  />drank the <foreign xml:lang="ja">sake</foreign> hot, in tiny cups that went
                  thirty or more to the pint; or the Kyoto beer that had been ordered for the
                  foreigners who were the chief guests this evening. This is the toast the Japanese
                  made to the moon: <q>May she with us drink a cup of immortality!</q> and then each
                  wished the one nearest him ten thousand years of joy.</p>
               <p>Now the moon-path widened on the bay, and the moon itself expanded and grew more
                  luminous as though in proud sympathy and understanding of the thousand banquets
                  held in her honor that night. All the music and noise and clatter and revel had
                  gradually ceased, and for a time an eloquent silence was everywhere. Huge glowing
                  fire-flies, flitting back and forth like tiny twinkling stars, seemed to be the
                  only things stirring. </p>
               <p>Some one snuffed the candles in the lanterns, and threw a large mat in the center
                  of the garden, and dusted it ex-<pb n="5"/>travagantly with rice flour. Then a
                  shaft of light, that might have been the combination of a thousand moonbeams, was
                  flashed on the mat from an opening in the upper part of the house, and out of the
                  shadows sprang onto the mat a wild, vivid little figure, clad in scintillating
                  robes that reflected every ray of the light thrown on them; and with her coming
                  the air was filled with the weird, wholly fascinating music of the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">koto</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ja">samisen</foreign>.</p>
               
           
               <p>She pirouetted around on the tips of the toes of one little foot, clapped her
                  hands, and curtsied to the four corners of the earth. Her dance was one of the
                  body rather than of the feet, as back and forth she swerved. There was a patter,
                  patter, patter. Her garments seemed endowed with life, and took on a sorrowing
                  appearance; the lights changed to accompany her; the music sobbed and quivered. It
                  had begun to rain! <emph>She</emph> was raining! It seemed almost as if the
                  pitter-patter of <pb n="6"/>her feet were the falling of tiny rain-drops; the sadness of her
                  garments had increased, and now they seemed to be weeping, at first gradually,
                  then faster and still faster, until finally she was a storm––a dark, blowing,
                  lightning storm. From above the light shot down in quick, sharp flashes, the drums
                  clashed madly, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">koto</foreign> wept on and the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">samisen</foreign> shrieked vindictively.</p>
               <p>Suddenly the storm quieted down and ceased. A blue light flung itself against the
                  now slightly swaying figure; then the seven colors of the spectrum flashed on her
                  at once. She spread her garments wide; they fluttered above her in a large
                  half-circle, and, underneath the rainbow of the gown, a girl’s face, of exquisite
                  beauty smiled and drooped. Then the extinction of light––and she was gone.</p>
               <p>A common cry of admiration and wonder broke out from Japanese and foreigners
                  alike. They called for her, clapped, stamped, whistled, cheered. <pb n="7"/>One
                  man’s voice rose above the clatter of noises that had broken loose all over the
                  gardens. He was demanding excitedly of the proprietor to tell him who she was. </p>
               <p>The proprietor, smiling and bowing and cringing, neverthelss would not tell.</p>
               <p>The American theatrical manager lost his head for a moment. He could make that
                  girl’s fortune in America! He understood it was possible to purchase a geisha for
                  a certain term of years. He stood ready on the spot to do this. He was ready to
                  offer a good price for her. Who was she, and where did she live?</p>
               <p>Meanwhile the nerve-scraping dzin, dzin, dzin of a samisen was disturbing the
                  air with teasing persistence. There is something provoking and still alluring in
                  the music of the sami- sen. It startles the chills in the blood like the maddening
                  scraping of a piece of metal against stone, and still there <pb n="8"/>is an
                  indescribable fascination and beauty about it. Now as it scratched and squealed
                  intermittently and gradually twittered down to a zoom, zoom, zoom, a voice rose
                  softly, and gently, insinuatingly, it entered into the music of the samisen. Only
                  one long note had broken loose, which neither trem- blednorwavered. Whenithadended
                  none could say, only that it had passed into other notes as strangely beautiful,
                  and a girl was singing.</p>
               <p>Again the light flashed down and showed her standing on the same mat on which she
                  had danced, her hands clasped, her face raised. She was ethereal, divinely so. Her
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">kimono</foreign> was all white, save where the shaft of
                  moonbeams touched the silk to silvery brilliance. And her voice! All the notes
                  were minors, piercing, sweet, melancholy—terribly beautiful. She was singing music
                  unheard in any land save the Oirent, and now for the first time, perhaps,
                  appreciated by the for-<pb n="9"/>eigners, because of that voice—a voice meant for
                  just such a medley of melody. And when she had ceased, the last note had not died
                  out, did not fall, but remained raised, unfinished, giving to the Occidental ears
                  a sense of incompleteness. Her audience leaned forward, peering into the darkness,
                  waiting for the end.</p>
               <p>The American theatrical manager stalked toward the light, which lingered a moment,
                  and died out, as if by magic, as he reached it. But the girl was gone.</p>
               <p><q>By Jove! She’s great!</q> he cried out, enthusiastically. Then he turned to the
                  proprietor. <q>Where is she? Where can I find her?</q></p>
               <p>That man shook his head.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, come, now</q>, the American demanded, impatiently, <q>I’ll pay you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>I don’t know. She is gone</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But you know where she lives?</q></p>
               <p>The proprietor again answered in the negative.</p>
               <pb n="10"/>
               <p><q>Now wouldn’t this make one of this country’s squatty little gods groan?</q> the exasperated manager demanded of a younger man who had followed him forward.</p>
               <p><q>She’d be a great card in vaudeville</q>, the young man contented himself with
                  saying.</p>
               <p><q>There’s a fortune in her! I’m going to find her if she’s on this island. Come
                     on with me, will you?</q></p>
               <p>Nothing loath, Jack Bigelow fared forth behind the theatrical man, whom he had
                  never seen before that afternoon, and whom he never expected to see again. They
                  hurried down one of the narrow, shadowy roads that almost made a labyrinth of the
                  island. But fortune was with them. A turn in the road, which showed the waters of
                  the bay not fifty yards ahead, re- vealed just in front of them two figures—two
                  women—both small, but one a trifle taller than her companion. </p>
               <p><q>Hi, there! You!</q> shouted the <pb n="11"/>manager, who, though among a people
                  whose civilization was older than his own, considered them but heathen, and gave
                  them scant courtesy deserved by all so benighted in matters theatrical. The two
                  figures suddenly stopped.</p>
               <p><q>Are you the girl who sang?</q></p>
               <p><q>Yes</q>, came the answer in a clear voice from the taller figure.</p>
               <p>The manager was not slow in coming to the point. <q>Would you like to be rich?</q></p>
               <p>Again the positive monosyllable, uttered with much eagerness.</p>
               
          
               
               <p><q>Good!</q> The manager’s face could not be seen, but his satisfaction was
                  revealed in his voice. <q>Just come with me to America, and your fortune’s
                     made</q>.</p>
               <p>She stood silent, her head down, so that the manager prompted her impatiently,
                     <q>Well?</q></p>
               <p><q>I stay ad Japan</q>, she said.</p>
               <p><q>Stay at Japan!</q> The manager <pb n="12"/>barely controlled himself. <q>Why,
                     you can never get rich in this land. Now look-a-here— I’ll call and see you
                     tomorrow. Where do you live?</q></p>
               <p><q>I don’ want you call. I stay ad Japan</q>. </p>
               <p>This time the manager, seeing a possible fortune escaping him, and having in mind
                  the courtesy due the heathen, delivered himself of a large Christian oath. <q>If
                     you stay here, you’re a fool. You’ll never––</q></p>
               <p>The young man named Bigelow, who had watched the attempted bargaining in silence,
                  broke in with some indignation. <q>Oh, let her go! She’s got a right to do as she
                     pleases, you know. Don’t try to bully her into going to America if she’d rather
                     stay here</q>.</p>
               
               <p><q>Well, I suppose I can’t use force to make her take a good thing</q>, said the
                  manager, ungraciously. He drew out his card-case and handed the girl his card.
                     <q>Perhaps you’ll change <pb n="13"/>your mind after you think about this a
                     bit. If you do, my name and Tokyo address are on that card; just come round and
                     see me. I’m going down to Bombay to look out for some Indian jugglers. I’ll be
                     gone about five months, and will be back in Tokyo before I start out on another
                     trip to China, Corea, and the Philippines, and then off for home</q>.</p>
               <p>The girl took the card and listened in silence; when he finished, she courtesied,
                  slipped a hand into that of her companion, and hurried down the narrow road.</p>
               <p>After the two Americans had made their way back to the tea-garden, the older one
                  at once sought out the proprietor. </p>
               <p><q>You know something about the girl. Come, tell us</q>, he said, imperiously.</p>
               <p>The proprietor was profusely courteous, but hesitated to speak of the one who had
                  danced and sung. Fi-<pb n="14"/>nally he unbent grudgingly. He told the theatrical
                  man and his companion that he knew next to nothing about her. She had come to him
                  a stran- ger, and had offered her services. She refused to enter into the usual
                  contract demanded of most geishas, and in view of her talents he could not afford
                  to lose her. She was attracting large crowds to his gardens by her strange dances.
                  Still he disliked and mis- trusted her. She came only when it suited her whim, and
                  on fetes and oc- casions of this kind he had no means of knowing where she was. It
                  was only by accident she had happened in this evening. Once he had attempted to
                  follow her, but she had discovered him, and made him promise never to do such a
                  thing again, threatening to stay away altogether if he did so. He spoke
                  disparagingly of her:</p>
               <p><q>Beautiful, excellencies! Phow! You cannot see properly in the deceitful light
                     of this honorable moon. A <pb n="15"/>cheap girl of Tokyo, with the blue- glass
                     eyes of the barbarian, the yellow skin of the lower Japanese, the hair of mixed
                     color, black and red, the form of a Japanese courtesan, and the heart and
                     nature of those honorably unre- liable creatures, alien at this coun- try,
                     alien at your honorable country, augustly despicable—a half-caste!</q></p>
             
            </div>
            <pb n="16"/>
            <div>
               <head>II</head>
               <head type="subtitle">In Which Woman Proposes and Man Disposes</head>
               
               <p>Jack Bigelow was beset by the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakodas</foreign>
                  (professional match-makers). He was known to be one of the richest foreigners in
                  the city, and the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakodas</foreign> gave him no rest.
                  Though he found them interesting, with the little comedies and tragedies to relate
                  of the matches they had made and unmade, he had remained impregnable to their
                  arts. He naturally shrank from such a union, and in this position he was
                  strengthened by a promise he had made to a college chum, before leaving America to
                  aq college chum, his most intimate friend, a young English-Japanese student, named
                  Taro Burton, that during his <pb n="17"/> stay in Japan he would not append his
                  name to the long list of foreigners who for a short, happy, and convenient season
                  cheerfully take unto themselves Japanese wives, and with the same cheerfulness
                  desert them.</p>
               <p>Taro Burton was almost a monomaniac on this subject, and denounced both the
                  foreigners who took to themselves and deserted Japanese wives, and the native
                  Japanese, who made such a practice possible. He himself was a half-caste, being
                  the product of a marriage between an Englishman and a Japanese woman. In this
                  case, however, the husband had proved faithful to his wife and children up to
                  death; but then he had married a daughter of the nobility, a descendant of the
                  proud Jokichi family, and the ceremony had been performed by an English
                  missionary. Despite the happiness of this marriage, Taro held that the Eurasian
                  was born to a sorrowful lot, and was bitterly <pb n="18"/>opposed to the union of
                  the women of his country with men of other lands, particularly as he was
                  Westernized enough to appreciate how lightly such marriages were held by the
                  foreigners. It was true, of course, that after the desertion the wife was
                  divorced, according to the law, but that, in Taro’s mind, only made the matter
                  more detestable.</p>
            
           
               <p>For five years, up to their graduation four months before this, the young American
                  and the young half-Japanese had been associated as closely together as it is
                  possible for two young men to be, and a strong and deep affection existed between
                  them. </p>
               <p>It had been originally decided that the friends would make this trip together,
                  which in Taro Burton’s case was to be his return to the home he had left, and,
                  with Jack bigelow, was to be the beginning of a year’s travel preliminary to
                  entering the business of his father, who was a rich ship-<pb n="19"/>builder. But
                  for some reason, which he never clearly set forth to his friend, Taro had backed
                  out at almost the last minute; yet he had urged Jack to undertake the trip alone,
                  and, under promise to follow shortly, finally had prevailed. So Jack Bigelow had
                  made the long voyage to Japan, and had taken a pretty house of his own a short
                  distance from Tokyo. </p>
               <p>It was unfortunate that Taro could not accompany his friend, for, while the latter
                  was not a weak character, he was easy-going, good-natured, and easily manipulated
                  through his feelings. </p>
               <p>The young Japanese, had he done nothing else, at least would have kept the
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakodas</foreign> and their offerings of matrimonial
                  happiness on the outer side of the American’s door. As it was, one of them in
                  particular was so picturesque in appearance, quaint in speech, and persistent in
                  his calls, that the young man had encouraged his<pb n="20"/>visits, until a
                  certain jocular intimacy put their relations with each other on a pleasant and
                  familiar footing.</p>
               <p>It was this <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> (Ido was his name, as he had
                  told Jack) who brought an applicant for a husband to his house, one day, and
                  besought him at least to hold a look-at meeting with her. </p>
                  <p><q>She is beautiful like unto the sun goddess</q>, he declared, with the
                  extravagance of his class. </p>
               <p><q>The last was like the moon</q>, said the young man, laughing. <q>Have you any stars to
                  trot out?</q></p>
               <p><q>Stars!</q> echoed the other, for a moment puzzled, and then, beaming with
                  delighted enlightenment, <q>Ah, yes—her eyes, her feet, hair, hands, twinkling
                     like unto them same stars! She prays for just a look-at meeting with your
                     excellency</q>. </p>
               <p><q>Well, for the fun of the thing, then</q>, said the other, laughing, <q>I’m sure
                     I don’t mind having a look-at meeting with a pretty girl. Show <pb n="21"/> her
                     into the <foreign xml:lang="ja">zashishi</foreign> (guest-room) and I’ll be
                     along in a moment. But, look here</q>, he continued, <q>you’d better understand
                     that I’m only going through this ceremony for the fun of the thing, mind you. I
                     don’t intend to marry any one—at all events, not a girl of that class</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Nod for a leetle while whicheven?</q> persuaded the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >nakoda</foreign>.</p>
               <p><q>Nod for a leetle while whicheven</q>, echoed the young man, but the agent had
                  disappeared. </p>
               <p>When Jack, curious to know what she was like, she who was seeking him for a
                  husband, entered the <foreign xml:lang="ja">zashishi</foreign>, he found the
                  blinds high up and the sunshine pouring into the room. His eyes fell upon her at
                  once, for the <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign> at the back of the room was
                  parted, and she stood in the opening, her head drooping bewitchingly. He could not
                  see her face. She was quite small, though not so small as the average Japanese
                  woman, and the two little <pb n="22"/>hands, clasped before her were the whitest,
                  most irresistible and perfect hands he had ever seen. He had heard of the beauty
                  of the hands of Japanese women, and was not surprised to find even a girl of this
                  class—she was a <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign>, of course, he told
                  himself—with such exquisite, delicate hands. He knew she was holding them so that
                  they could be seen to advantage, and her little affected pose amused and pleased
                  him.</p>
               
             
               
               <p>After he had looked at her a moment, she subsided to the mats and made her
                  prostration. She was dressed very gayly in a red craêpe <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >kimono</foreign>, tied about with a purple <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >obi</foreign>. Her hair was dressed after the fashion of the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign>, with a flower ornament at top and long, pointed
                  daggers at either side; but as she bowed her head to the mats, some pin in her
                  hair escaped and slipped, and then a tawny, rebellious mass of hair, which was
                  never meant to be worn smoothly, had fallen all about <pb n="23"/>her, tumbled
                  into her eyes and over her ears, and literally covered her little crouching form.
                  She shivered in shame at the mishap, and then knelt very still at his feet. </p>
               <p>Bigelow was speechless. Never before in his life had he seen such hair. It was
                  dark, though not densely so, for all over it, even where it had been darkened with
                  oil, there was a rich red tinge; and it was luxuriously thick and long and
                  wavy.</p>
               <p><q>Good heavens!</q> he said, after the little figure had remained absolutely
                  motionless for a full minute; <q>she’ll hurt or cramp herself in that
                     position</q>.</p>
               <p>The girl did not rise at the sound of his voice, but crept nearer to him, her hair
                  still enshrouding her. It made him feel creepy, and annoyed and pleased and amused
                  him altogether. </p>
               
               <p><q>Don’t do that</q>, he said. <q>Please stand up. Do!</q></p>
               <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> told him to lift her to <pb n="24"
                  />her feet, and the young man did so, entangling his hands in her hair. When she
                  stood up, he saw her face, which was oval and rosy, the lips very red. She still
                  drooped her eyes, so that her face was incomplete.</p>
               <p><q>What’s your name?</q> he asked her, gently. <q>What do you want with me?</q></p>
               <p>Now she raised her head and he saw her eyes. They startled him. They were large,
                  though narrow, and intensely, vividly blue. Before, with her hair neatly smoothed
                  and dressed, he had noticed nothing extraordinary about her; now, with that rich
                  red-black hair enshrouding her, and the long, blue eyes looking at him mistily,
                  she was an eerie little creature that made him marvel. A Japanese girl with such
                  hair and eyes! And yet the more he looked at her the more he saw that her clothes
                  became her; that she was Japanese despite the hair and eyes. He did not try to
                  explain <pb n="25"/> the anomaly to himself, but he could not doubt her
                  nationality. There was no other country she could belong to. </p>
               <p><q>You are Japanese?</q> he finally asked, to make sure. </p>
               <p>She nodded.</p>
               <p><q>I thought so; and yet–</q></p>
               <p>She smiled, and her eyes closed a trifle as she did so. She was all Japanese in a
                  moment and prettier than ever.</p>
               <p><q>You see–your eyes and hair–</q> he began again. She nodded and dimpled, and he
                  knew she understood.</p>
               <p><q>What is it you want with me?</q> he asked, desiring rather to hear her speak
                  than to learn her object, for this he knew. </p>
               
              
               
               <p>She was solemn now. She flushed, and her eyes went down. To explain to him why she
                  had come to him in this wise was a painful task. He could guess that, but she
                  forced the words past her lips.</p>
               <p><q>To be your wife, my lord</q>, she <pb n="26"/>said in English, and the queer
                  quality of her voice thrilled him strangely.</p>
               <p>This was the answer he knew was coming; nevertheless it stirred him in a way he
                  had not expected. To have this wonderfully pretty girl before him, beseeching him
                  to marry her–he who had as yet never dreamed of marriage for himself–was
                  disturbing to his balance of mind. Nay, more–it was revolting. He shrank back
                  involuntarily, wondering why she had come to him, and this wonder he put into
                  words.</p>
               <p><q>But why do you want to marry me?</q> he asked.</p>
               <p>The expression of her face was enigmatical now. She had ceased to blush and smile,
                  and had become quite white. Suddenly she commenced to laugh–thrilling, elfish
                  laughter, that rang out through the room, startling the echoes of the house.</p>
               <p><q>Why?</q> he repeated, fascinated.</p>
               <p>She shrugged her shoulders. <q>I mus’ make money</q>, she said.</p>
               <pb n="27"/>
               <p>Of course this was her reason; he knew that before she spoke; but hearing her say
                  so gave him pain. She was such a dainty little body.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, you need not sell yourself for that</q>, he said, earnestly. <q>Why, I’ll
                     give you some–all you want. You’re awfully young, aren’t you? Just a little
                     girl. <emph>I</emph> can’t marry you. It wouldn’t be fair to you</q>.</p>
               <p>Again she shrugged her shoulders, and spoke in Japanese to the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign>. </p>
               <p><q>She says some one else will, then</q>, he interpreted.</p>
               <p><q>All right</q>, said the young man, almost bitterly.</p>
               
               
               
               <p>She pretended to go slowly toward the door, and then came back towards
                  Bigelow.</p>
               <p><q>I seen you before</q>, she announced, ingenuously.</p>
               <p><q>Where?</q> He was curiously interested. He fancied her face familiar.</p>
               <p><q>Ad tea-house</q>.</p>
               <pb n="28"/>
               <p><q>What tea-house?</q></p>
               <p><q>On liddle island. You ’member? I dance like this-a-way</q>. She performed a few
                  steps.</p>
               <p><q>What! you that girl?</q> He knew her in an instant now. <q>How could you
                     remember me?</q></p>
               <p><q>You following me after dance with ’nudder American gent, and before thad some
                     one point ad you–ole wooman thad always accompanying me</q>.</p>
               <p><q>How did <emph>she</emph> know me?</q></p>
               <p><q>She din know you to speag ad, bud–she saying you mos’ reech barbarian ad all
                     Japan</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, I see</q>, he said, coldly.</p>
               <p><q>She tell me I bedder git married with you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Indeed! Why?</q></p>
               <p>She hung her head a moment.<q>Because she know I luffing with you</q>, she
                  said.</p>
               <p><q>You loving with <emph>me!</emph></q> He laughed outright. Her ingenuousness was entrancing.</p>
               <pb n="29"/>
               <p><q>Yes</q>, she said, and he, with masculine conceit, half believed her.</p>
               <p><q>But wouldn’t you rather stay at the tea-house than get married?</q> he asked.</p>
               <p><q>Not nuff money that business</q>, she returned.</p>
               <p><q>Do you do everything for money?</q></p>
               <p><q>How I goin’ live?</q>
               </p>
               <p>This question, answering a question, brought her back to the purpose of her visit.
                  She held her little hands out to him. </p>
               <p><q>Ah, excellency, <emph>pray</emph> marry with me</q>, she begged.</p>
               <p>He took her hands quickly in his own. They were soft and so small. He could
                  enclose them with one of his. They were delightful. He knew they were daintily
                  perfumed, like everything else about her. He did not let them go.</p>
               <p><q>You ought not to marry, you know</q>, he said to her, almost boyishly. <q>How
                     old are you, anyhow?</q></p>
               <pb n="30"/>
               <p>She ignored his question.</p>
               <p><q>I will be true, good wife to you forever</q>, she said, and then swiftly
                  corrected herself, as though frightened by her own words. <q>No, no, I make
                     ridigulous mistage—not forever—jus’ for liddle bit while—as you desire,
                     augustness!</q></p>
               <p><q>But I don’t desire</q>, he laughed nervously. <q>I don’t want to get married. I
                     won’t be over a few months at most in Japan</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, jus’ for liddle bit while marry with me</q>, she breathed,
                     entreatingly—<q>Pl-ease!</q></p>
               <p>It hurt him strangely to have her plead so. She looked delicate and refined and
                  gentle. He put her hands quickly from him. She held them out and put them back
                  again into his. Her eyes clouded, and he thought she was going to cry. </p>
               <p>He was seized with a desire to keep her from weeping, if he could, this little
                  creature, who seemed made for <pb n="31"/>anything but tears. He spoke from this
                  impulse, without giving so much as a second’s thought to the seriousness of his
                  words.</p>
               <p><q>Don’t cry. I’ll marry you, of course, if you want me to</q>.</p>
               <p>He felt the hands in his own tremble. </p>
               <p><q>Thangs, excellency</q>, she said, in a voice that was barely above a whisper,
                  but it was a voice which had in it no note of joy.</p>
               
              
               
               <p>There was pleasure, however, in the eyes of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >nakoda</foreign>. He had done a good piece of business, a most excellent piece
                  of business, for the American gentleman was reputed to be able to buy hundreds and
                  hundreds of rice-fields if he so cared to do. The <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >nakoda</foreign> came forward with a benignant smile to arrange the terms.</p>
               <p><q>She will cost only three hundred yen per down and fifteen yen each end per
                     week. Soach a cheap price for a wife!</q>
               </p>
               <p>It was the grinning face of this <pb n="32"/>matrimonial middleman that brought
                  Bigelow back to his senses. He had said he would marry this little creature, whose
                  limp hands he was holding. He dropped them as though they were the hands of one
                  dead, and drew back.</p>
               <p><q>I won’t do it!</q> he almost shouted. <q>Never!</q> Then he thought what must
                  be the feelings of the little girl whose yoke of marriage he was refusing, and
                  softened. <q>I wasn’t thinking when I said I would. I wouldn’t be doing right, and
                     it wouldn’t be fair to you</q>. He paused, and then added, lamely, <q>I think
                     I’d like you awfully, though, if I only knew you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But––</q> spoke up the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign>, anxiously, who found his dream of a large fee fading into thin air.</p>
               <p>Jack turned upon him quickly and gave him a sharp look, whereat he retired
                  hurriedly.</p>
               <p>A look of relief had come over the <pb n="33"/>girl’s face when Jack had cried out
                  that he would not marry her, and at this he wondered much. This relief in her
                  face, however, was succeeded almost instantly by disappointment. But she spoke no
                  further word. She gave him a single hurried glance from beneath fluttering
                  eyelashes, curtsied until her head was almost on a level with his knees, and left
                  him.</p>
         </div>
            <div>
               
               <head>III</head>
               <head type="subtitle">An Appointment</head>
               
               
               <p>Jack Bigelow regarded the attempt of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign>
                  and the little Miss——(he had not even thought to ask her name) as an incident
                  closed by the retirement of the one aspiring to wifehood from his sight. But in
                  passing from his house she had not passed from his mind. This she occupied in
                  spite of him, though it must be said that Jack made no effort to eject her.</p>
               <p>He had been approached by other <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakodas</foreign> who had the disposal of some most excellent wives, so they had told him, but never before had he consented to see one of their offerings, so the sensation of being asked in marriage by a girl whom he had never seen before was altogether new.That he, Laurin Reynolds, A.B.––he was very proud of that A.B.––should be so sought out was not at all displeasing to his vanity, a thing that he prided himself on not possessing; this notwithstanding the fact that he knew he had been approached because he had money. He chuckled at the event several times during the day. He would keep this incident in mind with all its detail, and make use of it now and then after he had returned home, when he was called upon to talk of his experiences in other lands. Of course, he would exaggerate a bit here and tone down a bit there, and would make the girl much prettier--no, the girl was pretty enough. This part of the incident could not be improved upon in the least.</p>
               
               
               
               <p>Laurin mused about the episode the entire day, and twice he exploded into such laughter at the idea of his being sought in marriage that his little man hurried in to see if the gray-eyed barbarian was taking leave of his senses. In the evening he grew restless, and having nothing else to do—-so he told himself––he went out to the tea-garden on the little island which he had visited a few nights before. For an hour he waited for something––for something that did not appear. Finally, when the proprietor chanced to pass him, he asked, in the manner of one casually interested: <q>The girl who danced and sang the other night––is she here?</q></p>
               <p>She was not, for which the proprietor humbly asked pardon. She had not visited his poor place since the night the American had seen her.</p>
               <p>For some reason not very well known to himself Laurin suddenly lost interest in the house and garden and returned to his home. But the next night––again because he had nothing else to do––found him once more a guest at the tea-garden. This time he did not leave at the end of an hour; possibly because a weird dance was performed and the weird songs were sung by a girl with vivid blue eyes. He could not see their color from where he sat, of course, but he knew they were blue.</p>
               
              
               
               <p>After that he fell into the habit of visiting the garden every night. These were dull times in Tokyo––never anything to do. Most of the evenings so spent were intensely wearisome, but some few were not. It may have been only a series of incidents, but it so happened that on the enjoyable evenings there was a weird dance and weird songs, and on the others there were none of the graceful swayings of a lithe body nor the wonderful music of a wonderful voice. One evening, immediately after the song had been ended, he found himself striding down the same road he had taken with the enthused theatrical manager, and this without consciously having decided upon such a course. But he came down to the beach without seeing man or woman, and though he would not acknowledge to himself that he was seeking any one, he carried away with him a very strong and keen sense of disappointment.</p>
               
               
               
               <p>For two months the dullness of Tokyo remained unabated, so that the only thing to do was to spend the evenings in the tea-garden. At the end of that time Laurin, becoming honest with himself, admitted that there was nothing else to do because there was nothing else he wanted to do. And while in this frank mood he let it become known to himself that there was nothing in all the Land of the Rising Sun that held so much of interest for him as did the girl who had offered herself to him as a wife; nothing, indeed, in all the other lands of the earth. Why this was he did not know, not being given to searching his own soul or the souls of others. While he reclined at his ease one afternoon in the little room in which he lounged and smoked he began to place her, in his imagination, here and there in his house to try the effect. He set her in one of his largest chairs, notwithstanding she would have been much more comfortable on the floor in this same room, and she added wonderfully to the appearance of things. He stood her passively at the <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign> in the <foreign xml:lang="ja">zashishi</foreign>; he nodded his head––very good. He placed her out beneath a cherry-tree in his garden; again he nodded approvingly. And a breakfast with her sitting opposite him!––that, he told himself, would be like unto the breakfast eaten by the angels in heaven--if angels partake of other than spiritual nourishment. Yes, she would be wonderfully effective in this little house––would harmonize with it exactly. But what an odd figure she would make in an American dress! He thought of her in a golfing costume, and smiled at his fancy. Nevertheless even in the gowns worn by the women of his own country she would be quaint and charming. She would be awkward, of course, but would be graceful even in her awkwardness. And she would transgress every polite convention, and would make herself all the more delightful by so doing. He compared her to the wives of some of the men he knew, to many of the girls he had met since girls had begun to have an interest for him, and his admiration for her grew apace. He would be proud of her, he knew, for she was pretty and would attract attention, and men like their wives to be looked at. She was unlike the wife of any of his countrymen he was likely to meet, and this was much.</p>
               <p>What would his parents think? They would be angry at first, of course, but they would give in; they loved him and could not resist her––no one could resist her. Anyhow, this prospective trouble was so far ahead that there was no use in wasting thought upon it now.</p>
               <p>Why hadn’t he learned her name? It was very unsatisfactory––this being compelled to think of her only as <q>she</q> and <q>her</q>.</p>
               <p>But why had she come to him asking that he marry her? He shook his head at that; he didn’t just like it. But––oh, well, you know these Japs have no end of queer customs. This incident just illustrated one of them. She was already a superior kind of girl––not an ordinary <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign>, as he had thought when his eyes first fell upon her. He had seen enough of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">geishas</foreign> at the tea-houses to know that she was of a different kind, and to his Occidental eyes these were most pleasing little creatures.</p>
               <p>Just then his man straggled through the room and brought a climax to his musings. Marry her! He sat up straight. What had he been thinking about? The idea was absurd; it was absurd for him to think about marrying any one. He got to his feet, called his man, ordered a <foreign xml:lang="ja">jinrikisha</foreign> brought him, and then rode off to Tokyo to forget all about it.</p>
               
               
               
               <p>But it would not be forgotten. After he had left the <foreign xml:lang="ja">jinrikisha</foreign> he caught sight of her on the opposite side of the street turning a corner. He hurried after her, but when he reached the corner she was nowhere to be seen. He looked into all the shops on either side of the street for a distance of a hundred yards, but saw no one that in the least resembled her. Then he tramped about the immediate vicinity, his sense of loss deepening with each minute, until he noticed that the shopkeepers were eyeing him with suspicion. He gave up the search and started back to his <foreign xml:lang="ja">jinrikisha</foreign>.</p>
               <p>As he was swinging disconsolately along his eyes lighted upon another person whom he knew––Ido, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign>––and him Laurin did not let escape. He pounced down upon him and clapped a hand upon his shoulder.</p>
               <p><q>Hello, there!</q> he called out.</p>
               <p>Ido started back as if he had been set upon by an enemy; he was unused to such emphatic greetings. But when he saw who his assailant was he slipped a smile upon his face, bowed, and hoped that the august American’s days were filled with joy.</p>
               <p><q>They’ll do</q>, Laurin answered. <q>And how’re things with you? Business good? Making any matches?</q></p>
               
               
               
               <p>Ido had introduced four persons to incomparable happiness, which was to say that he had brought about two marriages. Had his lordship come into like happiness?</p>
               <p>No, his lordship had not.</p>
               <p><q>You mek mistake</q>, Ido gravely informed him. <q>You nod yet seen Japanese woman thad please you for wife? No? I know nudder girl your excellency nod seen––mos‘ beautiful in Japan. You lig’ see her?</q></p>
               <p><q>No; I’ve seen enough. By the way, Ido, what became of the girl you brought around to my house? Married yet?</q> Laurin put on a look of indifference as he asked this.</p>
               <p><q>No, excellency</q>.</p>
               <p>For one entirely uninterested Laurin found very much relief indeed in this simple answer.</p>
               
               <p><q>But I think she going be</q>, Ido went on, calmly. <q>Two odder gents—-what you say? consider? yes?––consider her</q>.</p>
               <p>These words drove relief from Laurin’s heart and instantly set up in its place a raging jealousy. But he compelled himself to remark quite easily, <q>You don’t say!</q></p>
               <p>Ido confirmed his statement with a nod that was almost a bow.</p>
               <p><q>I think I’ll go around to see her and congratulate her</q>, Laurin went on. <q>Where does she live, Ido?</q></p>
               <p><q>She nod lig’ thad you come ad her house</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Ah, well, let it go, then. But say, I really would like to see her again before she’s married. Rather took a fancy to her, you know. Couldn’t you bring her out to call on me to-morrow morning?</q></p>
               <p><q>I going be very busy to-morrow</q>. He saw no chance to make a marriage fee, so saw no reason for his taking the trip.</p>
               <p><q>I’ll pay you for your trouble--needn’t worry about that</q>.</p>
               <p>Perhaps Ido could arrange it so that he could come: yes, now that he thought again, he felt absolutely sure he could come. So it was settled that he and the girl should visit Laurin at ten o’clock the next day.</p>
               
               
            </div>
            
            <div>           
               <head>Chapter IV.</head>
               <head type="subtitle">In Which the East and the West Are United</head>
               
               <p>The announcement of his man that Ido and his charge had arrived contained no news for Laurin, for he had been watching the road from Tokyo since nine o’clock, and had seen them while they were yet far off. Nevertheless he did not enter the <foreign xml:lang="ja">zashishi</foreign> until his man came to him with the word that guests from the city were awaiting him, and then he had no definite idea of what he intended doing.</p>
               <p>She was dressed exactly as she had been on her previous visit, and just as she had then done she made obeisance almost to the floor in greeting him. He hastened her recovery from the deep curtsy by taking her hands and raising her to an upright posture.</p>
               <p><q>You have come to see me again. I am very glad to see you</q>, he said.</p>
               <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> say you lig’ see me; tha’s why I coming</q>. There was not a trace of her former coquetry in her manner.</p>
               <p><q>Yes. I had to send Ido after you. I suppose you would never have let me see you again if I had not</q>.</p>
               <p><q>You nod want thad I marry with you. You send me ‘way. I thing you nod care seeing me again</q>.</p>
               <p><q>We could be friends even if we didn’t care to marry, couldn’t we?</q></p>
               <p><q>Frien’? I nod thing I want frien’</q>.</p>
               <p><q>I’d like to have you for a friend, all the same. But I’m afraid I’ll not get to. Ido</q>––he hesitated––<q>Ido says you’re going to be––be married, you know</q>.</p>
               <p>She inclined her head.</p>
               <p><q>You’re not married yet, are you?</q> he asked, in alarm, forgetting that he had put this same question to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> the day before.</p>
               <p><q>Nod yet</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Do you––um––like him?</q></p>
               <p><q>Which one, my lord?</q> She looked up at him innocently.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, both of them!</q> He was beginning to get angry. He would find pleasure in laying violent hands upon the two––one at a time.</p>
               <p><q>Jus’ liddle bid, augustness</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Better than you do me?</q> he asked, hesitatingly.</p>
               <p>She shook her head decisively. <q>You nod so old, and nod so––all hairy-lig’!</q> She rubbed her little hands over her face, by which he understood that the two wore beards.</p>
               <p>He hardly knew what to say next, and the silence grew embarrassing to him. She broke it by remarking, quietly: <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> say thad you lig’ mek liddle talk with me</q>.</p>
               
            
               
               <p>He turned to the match-maker, who was pretending deep interest in a framed drawing on the wall. <q>Say, Ido, just step into the next room a minute, will you?</q></p>
               <p><q>You have never even told me your name</q>, he said, after the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> had withdrawn.</p>
               <p><q>Yuki</q>.</p>
               <p><q>I like it. Well, now, Yuki, mayn’t I visit you at your home––before you are married?</q> He was anxious to see what her parents were like and how she lived.</p>
               <p><q>Mos’ poor house––so liddle house. Augustness nod lig’ come</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But I don’t care if it is. I want to come, anyhow. Besides, I want to see you, not the house. Won’t you tell me where you live?</q></p>
               <p><q>I nod want thad you come</q>, she answered, with simple directness.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, that’s it, is it!</q> he said, somewhat taken aback.</p>
               <p>Her words gave him offense, but a glance at her and it was gone. She seemed such a simple little body, yet he knew he did not understand her. Her eyes, which she had kept turned downward, slowly raised and looked questioningly into his own. Such wonderful eyes! Such a simple, exquisite face! He was suddenly suffused with a great wave of tenderness, and he bent low and gently made prisoners of her hands. However indefinite his purpose had been up to this time it was definite enough now.</p>
               <p><q>Do you remember, Yuki, what you asked me when you were here the other day?</q></p>
               <p><q>Yes</q>. She still gazed at him questioningly.</p>
               <p><q>Would you like to––would you rather marry me than one of those other men?</q> he said, softly.</p>
               <p><q>Yes</q>, again.</p>
               <p>He hesitated, and she asked, <q>You want thad I marry with you, augustness?</q></p>
               <p><q>That’s just what I want, Yuki, dear</q>, he whispered, drawing her hands up to his lips.</p>
               <p><q>All ride</q>. She trembled--perhaps shivered is the word that expresses it more accurately as she said this, but gave no other sign that she felt any emotion whatever.</p>
               
              
               
               <p>Before Laurin could so much as touch his lips to her forehead Ido entered, smiling his professional blessing. It was evident that in the other room he had found no drawing to distract his attention, so was giving all his eyes and ears to what was going on in this, and could wait no longer to press his claim. Laurin, seeing an unpleasant duty before him, and desiring to have done with it at once, told Yuki that he would be back in a minute, and led Ido into the room out of which he had just come. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> began to make terms. This part was loathsome to the young man.</p>
               <p><q>Why</q>, he said, hotly, <q>if we’re to be married she can have all she wants and needs</q>.</p>
               <p>That wouldn’t do, the wary <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> told him; there would have to be a marriage settlement and a stated allowance agreed upon. He would have to pay more, also, as she was a maid and not a widow. Laurin made no effort to conceal his disgust, and to have the bargaining over with at once agreed to the sums the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> mentioned. Ido was to have two hundred dollars, and the girl was to receive a weekly allowance of fifteen dollars.</p>
               <p>When the ugly terms of the agreement were completed the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign> bowed himself out and Laurin went back to Yuki. He found her changed; her simplicity had left her and her coquetry had returned. She stood off from him, and he felt constrained and awkward.</p>
               <p>After a time she asked him, with a shrewd inflection in her voice, <q>You going to lig’ me, excellency?</q></p>
               <p><q>No question of that</q>, he answered, promptly, smiling.</p>
               <p><q>No</q>, she repeated; <q>tha’s sure thing</q>. And then she laughed at her own assurance, and she was so pretty he wanted to kiss her, but she backed from him in mock alarm. <q>Tha’s nod ride</q>, she said, <q>till we marrying</q>.</p>
               <p><q>And you––do you think you will like me?</q></p>
               
             
               
               <p>She surveyed him critically. Then she nodded. They laughed together this time, but when he approached her she grew fearful. He did not want to frighten her.</p>
               <p><q>You god nod anudder wife?</q> she asked.</p>
               <p><q>No! What do you think I am?</q></p>
               <p><q>I god nod anudder husban’</q>, she informed him, complacently.</p>
               <p><q>I should hope not</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Perhaps</q>, she said, <q>you marrying with girl in Japan thad god married before? Me––I never</q>.</p>
               <p><q>No, of course not</q>. He didn’t quite know what she was driving at.</p>
               <p>Then she said, <q>You pay more moneys ad liddle girl lig’ me thad nod been marry before?</q></p>
               <p>He recoiled and frowned heavily at her.</p>
               <p><q>I settled that matter with the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign></q>, he said, coldly. Seeing he was displeased she tried to reassure him. She smiled at him engagingly, coaxingly.</p>
               <p><q>You nod liging me now?</q></p>
               <p>But his face did not clear up. She had hurt him deeply by her reference to money.</p>
               <p><q>I thing you nod want me. I go ‘way. You lig’ American girl better</q>.</p>
               <p>She turned and was making her way slowly out of the room when he sprang after her. <q>Don’t, Yuki!</q> he cried, and caught her eagerly into his arms. She yielded herself to his embrace, and for the first time he kissed her.</p>
               <p>After she had left him he stared with some wonder at the reflection of himself in a mirror. So he was to be married, was he? Yes, there was no getting out of it now. As for that, he didn’t want to get out of it––of this he was quite sure. He was very well content––nay, he was enthusiastically happy––with what the future promised.</p>
               <p>But his happiness might have been felt in lesser measure if his eyes, instead of staring at his mirrored likeness, could have been fixed on Yuki. She had borne herself with a joyous air to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">jinrikisha</foreign>, but once within it and practically secure from observation the life had seemingly gone out of her. The brown of her skin had paled to gray, and all the way to Tokyo her eyes shifted neither to the right nor to the left, but stared straight ahead with blank gaze into nothingness. And once when Ido looked down he found they were filled with tears.</p>
               
             
               
               <p>A few days later they were married. It was a very quiet little tea-drinking ceremony, with no one there save Yuki, Laurin and the <foreign xml:lang="ja">nakoda</foreign>, and Yuki herself sang the marriage song, <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Takasago</foreign></q>.</p>
               <p>Laurin Reynolds was fascinated and bewildered at the turn events had taken. He was very good and gentle to her, and for a couple of days after the ceremony she seemed quite happy and contented. Then she disappeared, and for a week he saw nothing of her. He greatly missed her, his little bride of three days. He wished ardently to have her back again, and her absence alarmed him. Her little arts and witcheries had grown on him even in this short period of their acquaintance. Toward the end of the week she slipped into the house quietly, and then went about her household duties as though nothing unusual had occurred. She did not offer to tell him where she had been, and he felt strangely unwilling to question her.</p>
               <p>Instead of becoming used to her each day found him more puzzled and less capable of knowing or understanding her. Now she was clinging, artless, confiding, and again shrewd and elfish. Now she was laughing and singing and dancing like a little child, and again he could have sworn she was weeping, though she would deny it stoutly and pooh-pooh and laugh away such an idea.</p>
               <p>Laurin asked her one day how she would like to be dressed in American clothes. She mimicked him. She mimicked everything and every one, from the warbling of the birds to the little man and maid who waited on them.</p>
               <p><q>I loog lig’ this</q>, she said, and humped a bustle under her ridiculously tight <foreign xml:lang="ja">kimono</foreign> and slipped a large sun hat over her face. Then she laughed out at him and flung her arms tightly about his neck.</p>
               <p><q>You lig’ me be American girl?</q></p>
               <p><q>You are a witch, Yuki-san</q>, he said.</p>
               <p><q>I want new dress</q>, she said, promptly, and held out a pink little palm. He frowned. He almost disliked her when she spoke of money. He filled her hand, however, with change from his pockets, and when she broke away from him, which she did as soon as she had the money, he wanted to take it back. Her pretty laughter sifted out to him through the shoji at the other side, and he knew she was mocking him again.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
