<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="JournalLetters1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Journal Letters</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno type="UofC">CU111850124</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <!--Include an msIdentifier if this text is from an archive-->
               <!--                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                        <idno>10.2</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>-->
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><title level="a">Journal Letters</title></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at University of
                           Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with
                                a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-09-10" status="published">Transcribed, encoded, proofed. Set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-01-05" status="empty">Adding document from 2023 Calgary
            Transcribe-a-thon.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:JournalLetters1">
      <pb n="3"/>
      <body>
         <div>
            <p>Later:</p>
            <p>Irvine telephones. (Lawyer).</p>
            <p>Gave me an awful scolding. I should have kept in touch with him and O’Connor he says.
               Do I realize I’ve burned my <choice>
                  <sic>bridge</sic>
                  <corr>bridge.</corr>
               </choice> Have I taken any precautions to make sure that Frank’s actions are not
               based on a desire to rid <choice>
                  <sic>himsxlf</sic>
                  <corr>himself</corr>
               </choice> of judgements, and beat it from Calgary?</p>
            <p>I resent his inferences. Tell him Frank and I are reconciled. I’m going to join him
               in a couple of weeks.</p>
            <p>Irvine says:</p>
            <p><q>Fine. But meanwhile protect yourself. Write to O’Connor, and tell him not to let
                  the <choice>
                     <sic>judgment</sic>
                     <corr>judgement</corr>
                  </choice> go until Frank has proven his good faith by sending for you</q>.</p>
            <p>I explain that Frank had to go back to retrieve certain properties. He replies
               sceptically:</p>
            <p><q>Oh ye-eh? Well <choice>
                     <sic>lets</sic>
                     <corr>let’s</corr>
                  </choice> see what we will see. Meanwhile write to O’Connor</q>.</p>

            <milestone unit="section"/>

            <p>I am terribly restless and unhappy. Frank ought to write to me. I should not be
               exposed to such a test. He has uprooted me---unsettled my whole life.</p>
            <p>I have a pain in my heart.</p>

            <milestone unit="section"/>

            <p>FRIDAY</p>
            <p>A beautiful letter from my Frank. I am so happy that I cry.</p>
            <p>He is at Spokane. The letter is dated Tuesday, and he is to reach Calgary Thursday.
               So he is there now! I am terribly excited!</p>
            <p>Then why <choice>
                  <sic>does’nt</sic>
                  <corr>doesn’t</corr>
               </choice> he wire me? He promised to. <choice>
                  <sic>Its</sic>
                  <corr>It’s</corr>
               </choice> Friday now-------well supposing something happened between Spokane and
               Calgary? If he’s there, he would wire.</p>

            <pb n="4"/>

            <p>Saturday A.M.</p>
            <p>Nervous. If Frank’s been in Calgary for two days why <choice>
                  <sic>has’nt</sic>
                  <corr>hasn’t</corr>
               </choice> he wired or written me? I wait in all morning, but not a word comes from
               him. I have all sorts of fears and apprehensions.</p>

            <milestone unit="section"/>

            <p><choice>
                  <sic>SAturday</sic>
                  <corr>Saturday</corr>
               </choice> P.M.</p>
            <p>Can’t stand it. Wired Frank at Empress hotel to let me know if he had arrived
               safely.</p>
            <p>No reply.</p>
            <p>I wire Mr. Makay.</p>
            <p>Late in P.M. I get a curious wire from Frank signed with his business name of F.
               Reeve. He has arrived safely and will write me that night.</p>
            <p>I am bewildered. My heart sinks down in my boots. I’m terribly afraid of
               something---I don’t know what.</p>
            <p>Why did he sign: F. Reeve. <choice>
                  <sic>Thats</sic>
                  <corr>That’s</corr>
               </choice> what he signed to that formal letter he and she composed when he was trying
               to break with me.</p>
            <p>In Calgary two days!</p>
            <p>I’ve only had one letter from him since Sacramento, and now this queer wire.</p>

            <milestone unit="section"/>

            <p><choice>
                  <sic>SAturday</sic>
                  <corr>Saturday</corr>
               </choice> Night</p>
            <p>I get Frank on Long Distance---after considerable delay and refusal to accept
               call.</p>
            <p>It is about ten o’clock here---<choice><sic>11.30</sic><corr>11:30</corr></choice> there. His voice sounds strange. I am all
               agitation, trembling from head to foot.</p>
            <p>I ask him if he still cares for me. He answers carelessly: <q>Sure</q>.</p>
            <p>His voice is guarded, strange.</p>
            <p><q>Anyone in your room?</q></p>
            <p><q>No, but people can listen on the telephone</q>.</p>

            <pb n="5"/>

            <p><q>Did you get your bonds back</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh yes</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Are you seeing her still?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes</q>.</p>
            <p>This is a shock.</p>
            <p><q>You <choice>
                     <sic>should’nt</sic>
                     <corr>shouldn’t</corr>
                  </choice>---you can’t do that</q>.</p>
            <p><q><choice><sic>Theres</sic>
                     <corr>There’s</corr>
                  </choice> still some stocks to be attended to</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Have you told her about me?</q> (You promised to)</p>
            <p><q>No</q>.</p>
            <p>I begin to sob---I am shaken and hysterical. I cry:</p>
            <p><q>I’ll tell her then---I’ll write her!</q></p>
            <p><q>If you do you’ll ruin everything</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Now I understand---now I understand why you <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> write--<choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> wire. You’ve been with her</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Be careful----give me a little time---a few days</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Why <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> you write to me?</q></p>
            <p><choice>
                  <sic>Did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>Didn’t</corr>
               </choice> you get my wire?</p>
            <p>The one signed F. Reeve---why did you sign it that?</p>
            <p>Laughing:</p>
            <p><q>Force of habit</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Tomorrow’s Sunday. You’ll spend the <choice>
                     <sic>week end</sic>
                     <corr>weekend</corr>
                  </choice> with her</q>.</p>
            <p>He <choice>
                  <sic>does’nt</sic>
                  <corr>doesn’t</corr>
               </choice> deny it. I am getting incoherent. I say savagely:</p>
            <p><q>You can’t resume intimate relations with her</q>.</p>
            <p>He answers swiftly:</p>
            <p><q>Nothing like that!</q></p>
            <p>I hang up. Just as if I <choice>
                  <sic>did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>didn’t</corr>
               </choice> know what happens between a man and a woman, who have for a year or more
               been on intimate terms. Just as if I <choice>
                  <sic>did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>didn’t</corr>
               </choice> know! I’m nearly beside myself. And he was laughing---seemed happy even---<choice>
                  <sic>thou</sic>
                  <corr>though</corr>
               </choice> queerly guarded in his talk. <choice>
                  <sic>Whats</sic>
                  <corr>What’s</corr>
               </choice> he got to be afraid of? I’m not afraid for people to know that we are
               reconciled. Is he ashamed of me?</p>

            <pb n="6"/>

            <p>I send a long, wild wire.</p>
            <p>He must tell her. Either he must sever all relations with her, or I am through.</p>

            <milestone unit="section"/>

            <p>After the wire goes I realize that he will have an excuse to be angry with me. I can
               just imagine what he will think --what say --what do. Oh he will punish me all right!
               I am always put in the wrong.</p>

            <milestone unit="section"/>

            <p>SUNDAY</p>
            <p>I am frightened. I fear your wrath. I write a remorseful letter, begging you to
               forgive me.</p>
            
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p><choice><sic>MONDay</sic><corr>Monday</corr></choice></p>
            <p>Working. Typing all morning.</p>
            <p>She’s not working. Maybe she’s riding around in my husband’s car. He promised not to keep the car at her place. If he is <choice><sic>seen</sic><corr>seen in</corr></choice> public places with her, or she is riding in his car, people will think they are together again---it will be humiliating for me to go up there afterwards. I suppose, even when she learns the truth, she will pretend he loves her but that I would not set him free. <choice><sic>Thats</sic><corr>That’s</corr></choice> all right by me. If it saves her face---<choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it’s</corr></choice> quite O.K. but she had better keep hands off now----or I’m going to do something that will just about slay her in that town.</p>
<p>He should tell her! <choice><sic>He s ould</sic><corr>He should</corr></choice> tell her!</p>
<p>He has sent me no money. I don’t think he will send me enough to go out there.</p>
<p>He said he would write and explain everything. I look for that letter by Wednesday.</p>

<milestone unit="section"/>

<p>TUESDAY</p>
            <p>Signed contract with Theo Lightner. She promises big things for me at the studios. What do I care for studios. <pb n="7"/> I can’t think of anything, but my husband and that woman! I visualize them: She is riding in his car, snuggled up against him, as I did.</p>
<p>Oh why did you ever come back into my life, only to hurt me so cruelly?</p>
<p>I re-read her letters. What a shallow, silly <choice><sic>soul.’</sic><corr>soul.</corr></choice> Yet she must have been clever and scheming, the way she manipulated you, poor dear. She made a sucker out of you! You gave her everything---or rather put all in her hands. <choice><sic>that</sic><corr>That</corr></choice> will! Drawn carefully in a lawyer’s office---leaving her <choice><sic>everythinb</sic><corr>everything</corr></choice> but the income from a mean third to your wife!</p>
<p>And she financially independent---and I, without a cent, save what I earn.</p>
<p>Verily it is true---that <choice><sic>To</sic><corr>to</corr></choice> him that hath, shall be given!<choice><sic>’’</sic><corr></corr></choice></p>
            <p>But Ah! it should not be given by the husband of another woman!</p>

<milestone unit="section"/>

<p>Well, darling, you did make another will in <emph>my</emph> favor. I won’t forget that, even if Irvine, the lawyer, says it <choice><sic>could’nt</sic><corr>couldn’t</corr></choice> be probated and is improperly drawn. He advised me to tell you to make a new one. I told him you were going to ask Mackay to give you the one you made in her favor. What a mess!</p>
<p>She told you not to see me alone--I might poison you. What a mind she must have!</p>

<milestone unit="section"/>

<p>WEDNESDAY</p>
<p>Your letter at last. A cold, cruel letter, without a word of love in it. Only resentment, injury--hurt.</p>
            <p>I deserve it maybe. Maybe my telegram did things to you. Oh maybe! <del>You</del> May be I should have trusted you---trusted <emph>my</emph> husband with another woman! The irony of it all---what a sardonic jest of all the gods in heaven!</p>
            <p>You have recovered your securities. Still you have not broken up with her!</p>
            <p>I still maintain she should be told. Lies and deceit are hateful things.</p>
            <p>How could you change so quickly. A week ago I was all the world to you. Can a man blow hot and cold. Did you feel differently once you were back with her? You could not be so weak and base to deceive us both. If so, you are playing a dangerous game--for women are more deadly and inflammable than dynamite.</p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>

<p>Wednesday P.M.</p>
            <p><choice><sic>Its</sic><corr>It’s</corr></choice> queer, but your letter makes me feel better. <choice><sic>Its</sic><corr>It’s</corr></choice> like a blow in the face---a dash of cold water that has <choice><sic>brough brought</sic><corr>brought</corr></choice> me to my senses---wakened me out of my deluded trance.</p>
<p>I shall not write to you again.</p>
            <p>I wonder what you’d say if I told you I feel suddenly as if I had been relieved of something---released even. <choice><sic>I Its</sic><corr>It’s</corr></choice> just as if I had become <choice><sic>suddebly</sic><corr>suddenly</corr></choice> sane <choice><sic>again</sic><corr>again.</corr></choice> Now for you and for her, I am conscious of a sense of real disgust.</p>
            <p><choice><sic>Disilusionment</sic><corr>Disillusionment</corr></choice> is creeping over me.</p>
            <p>To hell with you and your paramour!</p>
            
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p>THURSDAY</p>
            <p>Slept fine. Feel fine.</p>
            <p>No letter from you---but neither did I write to you.</p>
            
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p>Later:</p>
            <p>Out all day. Interested again in my work and people. Met some nice people in Theo’s office. A Mr. Berliner--big Mining engineer. We had a great talk. He is a Columbia man. We compared notes. We had both taken courses at Columbia at the same time. Before I knew it we were telling each other about our lives. I told him about my husband. He looked at me queerly and said:</p>
            <p><q>Going back to him?</q></p>
            <p><q>I don’t know</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Don’t. Your place is with someone who understands you</q>.</p>
            <p><q><choice><sic>Its</sic><corr>It’s</corr></choice> nice to have a husband</q>.</p>
            <p><q>A woman like you can have any husband she wants</q>.</p>
            <p>A darned pretty compliment and followed by an invitation to dinner at the Ambassador. I don’t accept, but I get a kick out of it anyway.</p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            
            <p><choice><sic>Did’nt</sic><corr>Didn’t</corr></choice> write to F----and <choice><sic>did’nt</sic><corr>didn’t</corr></choice> think about him much. Am I falling out of love? Might be a good idea. If I had gone on in the way I was going, I’d have been like a worm.</p>
            <p>My friends think well of me. In Calgary, I’m just one of the townies. Damned if I want to live there. Going over to McGuire’s office.</p>
            
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p>Later</p>
            <p>Saw <choice><sic>MCHire</sic><corr>McGuire</corr></choice>. He’s trying to swing a Fox contract for me. I’m quite excited.</p>
            <p>What will I do? Suppose I get an offer of a contract---<choice><sic>h how</sic><corr>how</corr></choice> can I sign it if I am to join Frank in Calgary?</p>
            <p>I wonder now, about that month in Banff. Might be an idyll, but he’d have to go back to Calgary (and her?) and where would I be.</p>
            <p>I’m not so sure I care about camping. I loved being with him of course, but camps are dusty, dirty places. I like baths and pretty clothes and decently set tables.</p>
            <p>He’s had all the fine and pretty things with her----I’ve had to rough it always with him.</p>
            <p>Perhaps I <choice><sic>could’nt</sic><corr>couldn’t</corr></choice> stand the altitude.</p>
         
         <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p>I <choice><sic>wo der</sic><corr>wonder</corr></choice> whether Mrs. Hill would be willing to do what I would have done------live simply on his income. If so, someone might test her out. Perhaps she’d give up her fortune and take him on with just what he has? Like fun she would! Life’s certainly a grim joke.</p>
            <p>I’ll write O’Connor tomorrow.</p>
            
<pb n="10"/>
         
         <p>Friday</p>
            <p>Typed most of the day. No letter from Frank and did not write to him.</p>
            <p>I’m rather thrilled by the <choice><sic>stpry</sic><corr>story</corr></choice> I am writing. <choice><sic>Its</sic><corr>It’s</corr></choice> about our own drama---Frank’s and mine! It makes a corking story and I’ve got a new twist to it.</p>     
            <p><choice><sic>Asn</sic><corr>As</corr></choice> I typed, I had a queer sort of thought. Is she with my husband now? Probably he took her and her sons on a trip somewhere---- I wonder what Calgary thinks of it all. Wonder what they think. His returning without a divorce. He can’t marry her in any event!</p>
            <p>When the first mail came and nothing from him----I just went on typing, back of my mind a vague hope that I would hear from you in the afternoon mail. One minute I say to myself<choice><sic>;</sic><corr>:</corr></choice> <q>It <choice><sic>does’nt</sic><corr>doesn’t</corr></choice> matter. If he <choice><sic>does’nt</sic><corr>doesn’t</corr></choice> think enough of me to write me even---why that is that and I will make the most of it</q>.</p>
            <p>Then a great longing surges over me. I stop work and stare about before me. I see you again, dearest! We are tramping along Tahoe beach----climbing the hill----motoring---I am snuggled up against you---- we are <choice><sic>bacm</sic><corr>back</corr></choice> in the cabin. You are holding me closely......... All night long, I feel your dear arms around me! I lie beside you awake, a sort of <choice><sic>ecstacy</sic><corr>ecstasy</corr></choice> running over me----sensuous, longing----you are asleep beside me. You wake and drowsily call me by her name!</p>
            <p>Christ is not the only one who was crucified. We all have our Calvary I suppose.</p>
            <p>Maybe I deserve mine. Maybe. Was I wholly to blame? True I was gone so long---but I wanted to go back, begged you to let me come back----but you had developed other interests---another love! In the days of your success and affluence, you forgot the poor little wife you had taken out of New York and plumped down on the rough farm. I had the rough years---she the years of plenty.</p>
            <p>Queer how she changed you. Say you did not really love her---that you realized that when you saw me again--that you had really always loved <emph>me</emph>! Yet she affected you so! How considerate you were of her! What sacrifices you made on her account.</p>
            
            <p>I am obsessed by the fear that perhaps you have made a mistake---perhaps it is not really love you feel for me now. When with me, it is sure that you did love me----Away from me? You could hurt me so? Could you be capable of such neglect? Could you punish me so cruelly?</p>
               <p>Do you remember my reading you from Wilde:</p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            
            <l>Yet each man kills the thing he loves</l>
            <l>By each let this be heard</l>
            <l>Some do it with a bitter look,</l>
            <l>Some with a flattering word.</l>
            <l>The coward does it with a kiss----</l>
            <l>The brave man with a sword!</l>
            
            <milestone unit="line"/>
            
            <p>I have stopped working. Can’t work. An uneasy feeling, a sense of unrest permeates me. I am intensely sad.</p>
            
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p>Friday P.M.</p>
            <p>The afternoon mail-----Nothing from you. I feel weak--sick. I thought I <choice><sic>did’nt</sic><corr>didn’t</corr></choice> care. I do. I do. I can’t stand it.</p>
            <p>Theo Lightner telephones Mr. McGuire has a check for <choice><sic>$100.</sic><corr>$100</corr></choice> for me. I will pick it up tomorrow. Wonder if it will be N.G.</p>
            <p>I am beginning to think over Kennedy’s proposition. I could get immediate cash from him and go directly to Calgary----have a showdown.</p>
            <p>I can’t stand this suspense.</p>
            
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            
            <p>I wire Frank. <q>No letters. Worried sick. Is anything the matter. Please wire</q>.</p>
            <p>I put in a request for a reply to this.</p>
            <p>At intervals during the evening Western Union calls me up with the sickening words:</p>
            <p><q>No reply to your telegram</q>.</p>
            <p>So you will not reply.</p>
            <p>Maybe you know there is a letter on the way. If I don’t hear from you tomorrow I will wire to Mackay.</p>
            <p>Could you have left the city.</p>
            <p>Irvine suggested something pretty rotten.</p>
            <p>You <choice><sic>would’nt</sic><corr>wouldn’t</corr></choice> do anything so base.</p>
            <p>You could not come and make love to me and induce me to sign away my rights----and then scheme to deceive me. If ever a man looked and acted honestly you did.</p>
            <p>Yola and Sue come in the evening for Bridge.</p>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
