<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KingsDaughter1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The King’s Daughter</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>5.5</idno>
                  <idno type="UofC">CU111913093</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl273"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Anonymous</name></author>.
                           <title level="a">King’s Daughter</title>. ms., <date notBefore="1917"
                           notAfter="1935">1917-1935</date>, <distributor ref="org:WERFonds"
                           >Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>, <idno>5.5</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at University of
                           Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="readyForProof">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-12" status="readyForProof">Ready for proof.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-01-05" status="empty">Adding document from 2023 Calgary
            Transcribe-a-thon.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:KingsDaughter1">
      <pb n="frontcover"/>
      <body>
         <head>THE KING’S DAUGHTER</head>
         <byline>by</byline>
         <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">ONOTO WATANNA</name></byline>
         <milestone unit="section"/>
         <p>Address:</p>
         <p>Mrs. <name ref="pers:WE1">Mrs. W. Reeve,</name></p>
         <p>Suite 19,</p>
         <p>Barnhart Apartments,</p>
         <p>Calgary, Alberta, Canada.</p>
         <div>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>THE KING’S DAUGHTER</head>
            <byline>by</byline>
            <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">ONOTO WATANNA</name></byline>
         </div>
         <div type="content">
            <p>The King’s daughter sat in a high place, and she <choice>
                  <sic>lookeddown</sic>
                  <corr>looked down</corr>
               </choice> from her tower, with unseeing eyes, upon the wide spreading lands over
               which her father, the Great King, ruled.</p>
            <p>From the Courtyard below, a fresh young voice, fine as a linnet’s, broke into chant
               and praise of Her who saw him not. For the King’s daughter was far away in dreams.
               Scarcely she stirred, nor seemed she even conscious of her little favorite
               handmaiden, pressed against her knee, and most earnestly and anxiously searching her
               face.</p>
            <p><q>Highness</q>---timidly the maid plucked at her long sleeve---<q>the musicians go
                  now to the music arbor and the dancers form upon the terrace. They turn their
                  faces humbly toward your highness. Pray you, condescend to wave your kerchief in
                  approval</q>.</p>
            <p>The King’s Daughter neither moved nor spoke. Her chin was sunk in the cup of her
               hands. She gazed far <pb n="2"/><fw type="pageNum">2</fw>off. The maiden pointed,
               dissembling her fears, and assuming a lightness of tone.</p>
            <p><q>The flower carts wend now their way through the castle gates. Every flower in the
                  Kingdom has been plucked to lend fragrance and beauty to your marriage fete. All
                  of the castle will be carpeted with flowers in your high honor. Your feet shall
                  tread upon flowers only. In the City, they build giant arches, and these are
                  studded with human flowers, that stand like radiant jewels, holding the royal
                  torches that shall light the way for your marriage train this night</q>.</p>
            <p>Said the King’s daughter, wrenching her slim hands:</p>
            <p><q>Speak not to me of marriage trains. Tonight, I keep a tryst with one who comes
                  from afar</q>.</p>
            <p><q>There lives no knight so bold</q> declared the hand maiden, <q>that he dare defy
                  the edict of the great King</q>,</p>
            <p>The shadows deepened. The skies were a sea of Mother of Pearl. In a deep, brooding
               silence the end of day closed in about them.</p>
            <p>The King’s daughter leaned farther over the parapet, as though she sought to pierce
               beyond the deepening veil of twilight. Her eyes are dark mysterious pools.</p>
            <p><q>Oh my beloved mistress</q> said the handmaiden, <q>But last night I myself heard
                  the words of the Great King. He has sworn a mighty oath, that should the stranger
                     <pb n="3"/><fw type="pageNum">3</fw>knight return to our land, he shall be put
                  to the torture and most surely die!</q></p>
            <p>Said the King’s daughter:</p>
            <p><q>I too heard the oath of the King, my father. His words affright me not. My love
                  and I fear not mere death. In life we stand on separate hills, a bottomless gulf
                  between us. Death comes a friendly, merciful Liberator, that places our hands in
                  each other, and seals us in a marriage that has no ending</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Highness, speak not of dark things. Death is horrible, old as time itself. Life is
                  bright and young--an animated bubble that the Master Lord has tossed to us to play
                  with for our little span of years. We do well to hold it close, for soon it must
                  escape us, and no man knows whether ever again it shall be lighted for our
                  desire</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Maiden, I bid you go before me. Say in the Hall that presently I shall come. Say
                  that I would meditate for the short hours are my maidenhood shall cease. Greet
                  with cheer and guile those you meet. Dissemble and play upon their credulity. Seem
                  not to hurry, yet go with flying feet. Stay not for any excuse, but hasten before
                  me to greet my Lord, and escort him to our trysting place</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh my beloved mistress. The great King, thy father----</q></p>
            <p><q>Serve you me only. Fail me now, and never again shall you enter my
               presence</q>.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">4</fw>
            <p>The handmaiden of the King’s Daughter has pressed her face to the hem of her
               mistress’s robe. She has humbly kissed the hand of the King’s Daughter, and with its
               aid, she is on her feet. From her eyes she has dashed the bright tears. Like a youth,
               humming a gay song, she goes forth, down the thirty three steps of the tower, and
               with laughter upon her lips, she bursts into the great hall. Jauntily she delivers
               the message of the King’s Daughter.</p>
            <p>She slipped from the retaining hands of the Maids of Honor. She has evaded the severe
               questioning of the royal chaperone. Now she is flirting and playing tricks on the
               elder pages. With the tip of her <choice>
                  <sic>lomg</sic>
                  <corr>long</corr>
               </choice> feather fan, which is made of the wings of a tropic wild bird, she tickled
               a gaunt man of war behind the ear and he has grudgingly given her passage that lies
               free now to the corridor. Side glances of mischief and coquetry she darts at the
               guard, drawn like bronze statues along the stone wall. A knight comes swiftly upon
               her steps. She turns a shoulder, tosses her head, which is crowned with curls gold as
               the sun of day.</p>
            <p><q>Lady Jasmine, whither do you go? Permit me to attend you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>No--I would go alone. I seek my little dog, who hides upon the terraces. Strange
                  faces affright him. I would go alone</q>.</p>
            <p>On the first <foreign xml:lang="fr"><choice>
                     <sic>enciente</sic>
                     <corr>enceinte</corr>
                  </choice></foreign> of the castle three guards patrol. Their eyes gleam. How fair
               the <pb n="5"/><fw type="pageNum">5</fw>little handmaiden of the King’s Daughter
               appears, as she puts her finger saucily to her lips, as though she would include them
               in some pretty, trifling secret.</p>
            <p>Now her feet press the greensward. She waves her hand, the fingers twinkling, to the
               deeply bowing musicians and the sloe eyed supple bodied dancers, who watch her
               worshipfully. To the Premiere dancer she speaks a few gracious charming words:</p>
            <p><q>My mistress, the King’s daughter, delights in your most lovely music and she has
                  pleasure in your dance. Grace itself is not more charming than you, Oh beautiful
                  Columbine!</q></p>
            <p>Flattered and deeply moved by the honied words, the premiere dancer smiles and lowly
               curtseys; for the hand maiden of the King’s daughter is herself a great lady and
               daughter of the King’s Chamberlain.</p>
            <p>Now she wanders lightly across the moss green lawn, calling softly to her little
               dogs. There are eighteen terraces. All of these she must traverse. There is another
               space of wide open lawn.</p>
            <p>The night falls unawares, but its dusky veil is gilded by the shimmering gleams of a
               golden moon. Under dense, arching boughs, the broad road slopes into the depths of
               the forest. It is a warm, <choice>
                  <sic>velvetty</sic>
                  <corr>velvety</corr>
               </choice> night. The maiden checks her headlong rush and stands, tensely waiting, as
               the Knight rides steadily toward her. Now the handmaiden of the King’s daughter
               stands at his stirrup. The moonlight on her uplifted face, reveals its white terror
                  <pb n="6"/><fw type="pageNum">6</fw>and despair. Her message is whispered through
               quivering lips.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>It is dark in the secret, sunken gardens of the King’s Daughter. On all side high and
               ancient box shrubs are banked against a thicker growth of camphor and pine trees.
               Here in this cool retreat, flowers that love shady glens thrive and grow with a
               brightness and luster as dazzling as those which turn their faces to the sun. Here
               are <unclear reason="illegible">aquilegia</unclear>, pansies, purple, yellow and
               white violets, bleeding hearts, irises, <choice>
                  <sic>wistaria</sic>
                  <corr>wisteria</corr>
               </choice>, ferns, the lotus and the lily.</p>
            <p>On the moss covered rim of the lotus pool sit the lovers and seek in the shadowed
               garden to see each others faces. The air is fresh and permeated with fragrance; it is
               full of the essence of life.</p>
            <p>Time runs like a hare; but they know it not. They know not that half the night has
               already passed into eternity. For them the world is blotted out.</p>
            <p>From out the mountains come the booming of the seven monster bells of the Royal
               monastery. One by one the temples in the neighboring hills answer the challenge of
               the royal bells. Music pours forth from far and near, awakening a thousand melodious
               echoes, and with the music of the swinging bells comes presently the strains of the
               Royal wedding chant and the national anthem of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>A thousand lights flash out in unison upon the <pb n="7"/><fw type="pageNum"
               >7</fw>sounding of the saluting royal guns. High up in the air burst the jubilant
               fire works, while strung from one end of the Kingdom to the other, the lighted
               torches blaze forth their flame of joy. As far as the eye can see, even to the top of
               the highest mountain show the ruddy fires lighted by the <choice>
                  <sic>peasntry</sic>
                  <corr>peasantry</corr>
               </choice> in honor of the marriage of the King’s Daughter.</p>
            <p>Streamers of beautiful maidens, bearing ropes and garlands of flowers encircle the
               walls of the ancient stronghold.</p>
            <p>The great hall of the castle is filled to overflowing. On either side of the winding
               stairs, that leads to the King’s own tower, his special guard stand at salute, while
               down the stairs, preceded, followed and flanked by the royal pages, in gala array,
               comes the great King’s himself.</p>
            <p>From the Court without resounds the tramp of the oncoming bridegroom’s train. The
               doors are thrown wide open. They enter to the clarion notes of the pipers. With pride
               and bold gallantry first of all comes the Proxy of the bridegroom Lord. He moves
               toward the great King, with all the assurance and gaiety of the conquering prince
               himself.</p>
            <p>Halfway across the hall the two advancing trains meet. The pages and the courtiers
               fall back, and the King looks with a proud smile at the deeply bowing Proxy of the
               bridegroom, who has swept from his head the white hat with its long plume.</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">8</fw>
            <p>The King wears a purple velvet cape, padded with scarlet silk, piped all of the train
               and pointed hood, with ermine. It is a costume of ancient days, donned <choice>
                  <sic>upo upon</sic>
                  <corr>upon</corr>
               </choice> state and ceremonial occasions. The Proxy of the bridegroom Prince, wears
               his Master’s robes. White as new fallen snow are the cape and plumed hat of the Proxy
               of the Prince who comes to wed the daughter of the great King.</p>
            <p>As the King advances, his face becomes wreathed in gracious smiles. One hand he <choice>
                  <sic>mwaves</sic>
                  <corr>waves</corr>
               </choice> in greeting to his guest--the other he extends backward, and as he proceeds
               this hand is shaken impatiently as though the King awaited its immediate <choice>
                  <sic>takingby</sic>
                  <corr>taking by</corr>
               </choice> his daughter.</p>
            <p>A hush has fallen upon the glittering assembly. The king’s outstretched hand
               clinched. The smiles fade from his face, and amazement and wrath encroach. Slowly he
               turns; his eye sweeps the circle of trembling maids of honor.</p>
            <p>A grey faced dame, guardian and mentor of the handmaidens of the King’s daughter,
               despatches one of her trembling charges to the tower of the King’s Daughter. In tense
               silence, they await her return. But she comes not back. Empty, she has found the
               chamber of the King’s daughter, and fearing the wrath of the great King, she has
               thrown herself from the gallery that encircles the tower.</p>
            <p>Another maiden follows upon her steps. With chattering teeth and terror stricken
               eyes, she seeks some <pb n="9a"/><fw type="pageNum">9</fw>hiding place within the
               tower.</p>
            <p>Another and still another maiden ascends. They return with lagging feet and eyes that
               glance in all directions save that of the King’s enraged face.</p>
            <p>Now the high voice of a herald page intones aloud the greetings of His Royal Master,
               as bowing profoundly he makes way for the affably smiling <choice>
                  <sic>equery</sic>
                  <corr>equerry</corr>
               </choice> and proxy of the Royal Bridegroom. The latter moistens his lips, casts a
               glance about the splendid assemblage, and addresses the great King:</p>
            <p><q>My master, the noble Prince of the South Moonlands sends me before him to greet
                  you in his name, and to beg your graciousness to accept the nuptial gifts tendered
                  to the exquisite Princess Eglantine. They are too humble things to express the
                  honor and admiration of my master; yet he prays you to accept them, as the
                  respectful homage of one whose most ardent wish is to win favor in the eyes of
                  your greatness and in those of his bride to be, the peerlessly lovely
                  Eglantine</q>.</p>
            <p>There is a long and pleasant pause. Way is made for the gift bearers. The first of
               the wedding gifts rests upon a velvet cushion and is so fine and small that it seems
               a single spark of livid fire, gleaming greenly. Like a living eye it glistens in the
               face of the bewildered and enraged King.</p>
            <p>Brusquely he turns from the astonished visitors. Down the line of now kneeling
               handmaidens the King passes. <pb n="9b"/><fw type="pageNum">9</fw>At the far end of
               the line, one seeks to slip through the guard that at the King’s command has closed
               about that tragic circle. The lady Jasmine, favorite handmaid of the King’s Daughter.
               Rough hands seize her, thrust her forward. They have bound her fragile little wrists,
               and forced her to her knees. Pale as death she meets the questioning glare of the
               great King.</p>
            <p>One whispers in his ear of that late sojourn in Castle grounds. Another notes the dew
               and grass stains upon her silken skirts. Another retails the story of er passage
               through the hall.</p>
            <p>In thundering tones, the King has commanded her to speak. Mutely her head shakes, the
               gilded curls trembling. A deathless fire finds its birth in the depths of her dark
               eyes. Her glance quails not. She speaks no word.</p>
            <p>The King has summoned him of whom all of <choice>
                  <sic>t e</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> Kingdom have most dread and loathing. The giant black torturer of the great
               King, looms now above the kneeling handmaid.</p>
            <p>The <choice>
                  <sic>Kingwill</sic>
                  <corr>King will</corr>
               </choice> strike three times upon the stone floor with his staff. At the third
               stroke, if she has spoken not, that little tongue that keeps so mute and still behind
               those child-like lips, shall be torn with iron pinchers from her throat.</p>
            <p>The evil instrument is swung before her. The first thud of the King’s staff resounds
               upon the stone.</p>
            <pb n="10"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">10</fw>
            <p>Strange dreams, warm memories, besiege her mind in flood. The little events of her
               short life! They run like dancing quicksilver before her. Life is so sweet----<q>An
                  animated bubble that the Master Lord has tossed to us for our little span of
                  years</q>. Thus she had wisely spoken to the King’s Daughter. She wanted not to
               lose even the fraction of a moment of this so precious thing called Life.</p>
            <p>But now the second thud of the King’s staff resounds upon the stone.</p>
            <p>Quite suddenly a strange new feeling flows over her. A psychic sense, as though one
               she loved intervened bodily there between her and the great King. She feels the soft
               pressure of a hand upon her head, and lifts her face to gaze appealingly up at that
               one that forms like a spirit before her vision. Her hair is the color of the warm
               earth. Her face is pale, but the lips are red as the rose berry. Her heavily lidded
               eyes are dark pools in which mysterious and lovely things are mirrored. The whisper
               of her voice is as the music of an unknown land.</p>
            <p><q>Death comes as a Liberator!</q> says the King’s Daughter.</p>
            <p>The last thud of the King’s staff resounds upon the stone.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="content">
            <p>The great hall is empty. The castle is in darkness. The drums and the bells and the
               saluting guns are silent. The dancers have <choice>
                  <sic>disapeared</sic>
                  <corr>disappeared</corr>
               </choice>, scattering like a <pb n="11"/><fw type="pageNum">11</fw>swarm of startled
               butterflies---away--away--from the grim castle.</p>
            <p>Dumbstruck as the now tongueless favorite of the King’s Daughter, her handmaidens
               hide in their chambers, or grouped together cling and huddle closely, daring not to
               even murmur or voice their dreadful fears.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="content">
            <p>The King tramps up and down his chamber. He mutters or he shouts, raising his
               clinched hands above his head in his uncurbed wrath. At intervals come his minions,
               with catlike tread to whisper their spies tale.</p>
            <p>Now the tortured handmaiden has returned to consciousness........ Now she leaves her
               couch....... She seeks a place of egress from her prison...... She is wrenching the
               iron bars, purposely loosened for this. She has climbed to the little gallery outside
               the window. She has found the rope that cunningly appears to hold the ancient vine.
               She is slipping down the rope...... She creeps along the rampart......the guards
               feign sleep. Like a wild hare, she is fleeing across the lawn and down the eighteen
               terraces.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="content">
            <p>The great King has solicited the presence of the Proxy of the Royal Bridegroom. In
               atonement for seeming slight, he begs him to <choice>
                  <sic>accompaby</sic>
                  <corr>accompany</corr>
               </choice> the King. The Proxy of the bridegroom is thorny mannered and outraged. In
               his master’s name, he likes not the manner of His reception. His eyes have rested not
               yet upon the prospective <pb n="12"/><fw type="pageNum">12</fw>bride of his superior
               lord. Vested with all of the royal authority and <choice>
                  <sic>preogative</sic>
                  <corr>prerogative</corr>
               </choice> of the Prince himself, the Proxy <choice>
                  <sic>assumesthe</sic>
                  <corr>assumes the</corr>
               </choice> right also to resent affront. As the King serves him, so shall his Master
               serve the King. Ungraciously, with ruffled demeanor, presently he agrees to accompany
               the King.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="content">
            <p>The fluttering sleeves of the fleeing hand maiden of the King’s Daughter, gleam in
               the moonlight like the wings of a living bird. She looks not back, for she is intent
               upon reaching the secret trusting place of the lovers and to warn them, as well as
               her dumb lips may, to flee from the terrible wrath of the great King.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="content">
            <p>The King holds his robe across his left arm. He <choice>
                  <sic>graspst</sic>
                  <corr>grasped</corr>
               </choice> his sword with his right hand. He tramps before his train and the sulky
               frowning Proxy. How they have reached the opening in the deep hedge, which leads down
               seven steps and discloses the sunken garden below.</p>
            <p>The moonbeams shine like searchlights, making a quivering, lighted path, to where,
               close clasped in each others arms, oblivious even to the maiden kneeling at their
               feet, the King now sees the lovers.</p>
            <p>He has leaped like an enraged bull over the box hedge that bars his way. With
               avenging, lightning speed, the King’s sword buries itself deep first <unclear
                  reason="illegible">into</unclear> that which comes between him and the mark he has
               sought, and then more deeply into the mark itself.</p>
            <pb n="13"/>
            <fw type="pageNum">13</fw>
            <p>Nothing now but deep blank silence in the darkened secret gardens of the King’s
               Daughter.</p>
            <p>The King stands like one entranced, his hand still rigidly clutching the sword, while
               over the sword’s point his inflamed gaze pins itself upon the white garb of him he
               has slain. He mutters:</p>
            <p><q>An accursed stranger, he came to our land! Would report not his name; his race;
                  his kindred! boldly he dared to woo the King’s Daughter!</q></p>
            <p>The Proxy hears him not. He is staring with distended eyes. An exclamation bursts
               from his lips. He drops upon his knees and bends above that silent form. Solemnly,
               reverently, the hat with its long white plume is swept from his head. His stern eyes
               fasten upon the amazed and anguished face of the great King. The Proxy’s voice is
               husky--full of a most solemn import:</p>
            <p><q>My master, the noble Prince of the South Moonlands is dead</q>, he says.</p>


         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
