<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LiteratureAsBusinessProposition1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Literature as a Business Proposition</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred</name></author>. <title
                           level="a">Literature as a Business Proposition</title>. <publisher
                           ref="org:Albertan"><title level="j">The Morning
                           Albertan</title></publisher>, <date when="1923-11-26">November 26,
                           1923</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">4,
                        14</biblScope>.<!--<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">[Full version of <title level="a">Literature as a Profession</title>. I think — but also great]</note>--></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Newspapers.com</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2025-05-04" status="published"></change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-08-19" status="empty">Created document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:LiteratureAsBusinessProposition1">
      <body>
         <head>LITERATURE AS A BUSINESS PROPOSITION</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>(By <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name>)</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>The average business man has only a hazy idea concerning the men and women who write,
               and of the value of their product. He looks upon writers as impractical folks engaged
               in an unrenumerative and uncertain employment. Sometimes he goes farther and
               desingates them as <q>nuts</q>.</p>

            <p>Nevertheless these <q>nuts</q> produce material that make immense fortunes and give
               employment to thousands of people. Without the writers there would be no publishing
               houses, no newspapers, no magazines; the gramophone would be silent—for composers are
               authors of music—advertising agencies and literary brokers would close up shop and
               the printing enterprises would be at a standstill. The motion picture industry, which
               is said to be the fourth great business in the United States today, could not carry
               on without the author. The theaters would close their doors, for the actor could not
               act without a play written by an author.</p>

            <p>Until recent years the author received but a minimum of the profits that accrue from
               his work. Though possessed with the power of making fortunes for others, he suffered
               through his own business inability and he was the prey and the victim of the very
               ones who became rich through his labor.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:BH1">Bret Harte</name>’s daughter died in the poorhouse. Yet <name>Bret
               Harte</name>’s publishers are in the millionaire class. <q>Ben Hur</q>, I
               am told, sold for the nominal sum of $1000. It is impossible to estimate the enormous
               returns that poured into the coffers of the publishers of that story and the
               producers of the play.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:GM3">Du Maurier</name> sold <q>Trillby</q> for $500 to the publishers and the novel
               ran into edition after edition, had an enormous success as a play and is running now
               to crowded houses in the movies. I could mention a score of instances of literary
               property that has made fortunes for its publishers and for which the author has
               received scarcely anything.</p>

            <p>But all that is of the past. The author today is no longer a long-haired, dreamy
               freak of nature. His house may not be as large as the financial magnate’s; few
               authors ride in Rolls-Royces, and some of them still have bank rolls as thin as their
               clothes, but this is the day when at all events in such countries as the United
               States and Englanad his interests are safeguarded and his country realizes his
               importance and his value. Someone—I think it was Mark Twain—started a
               campaign in the United States to organize the authors even as the labor unions were
               doing. Incidentally, Mark Twain himself died a millionaire.</p>

            <p>There came into being the Authors’ League of America. It set out to teach the authors
               the value of their product and to direct him into the way he should dispose of it. So
               strong did this league become that I believe there was scarcely an author in the
               United States who did not enrol. I was myself one of the charter members. The author
               now says in effect to the publisher: <q>Authors can live without publishers.
                  Publishers cannot live without authors, for authors can themselves become
                  publishers, but publishers cannot become authors, because the author is born—not
                  made</q>. He said practically the same thing to the theatrical manager and to the
               magazine editors. The author sent his emissaries to Washington and they said in effect
               to the legislators there: <q>You have been rooting long enough for the other
                  fellow—the fellow who is sitting on the back of the author. We are here to see
                  that you change the laws so that they will be made just and right, and if you do
                  not give us justice, every pen in this country will be used to expose and condemn
                  you</q>. <q>The pen is mightier than the sword</q>, goes the old adage, and few
               men in public life could withstand the onslaught of the united men and women who
               controlled the nation’s pen.</p>

            <p>The laws were changed. Literary brigandage became a dangerous and a criminal game
               that brought a heavy penalty. Copyright laws were framed to protect and not merely to
               exploit the author. His children’s rights in that property after his death were
               safeguarded. Piracy of the work of an American author is punishable with a heavy
               penalty under the law. This is only a small part of what the coming together of the
               authors brought to pass.</p>

            <p>Today the annual earnings of a popular and successful author compare with the salary
               of the president of the United States. I know personally several authors who are
               earning fifty or sixty thousand dollars a year, and some of them have cleared a cool
               million. I myself, when in New York seven years ago, made an average of ten thousand
               a year, and I made $60,000 from one book alone. I am speaking in terms of dollars and
               cents because I want to make clear the fact that literature represents one of the
               most profitable enterprises in the world.</p>

            <p>The point I wish especially to bring out is this: Canada might very well have a share
               in the profits as well as the prestige that accrues from the product of the authors.
               Such an enterprise—and I am calling it by a business term—should be cultivated and
               encouraged. It should grow and expand here in Canada as it has in the United States.
               Under present conditions, Canada’s authors who have not gone over to the States are
               driven to earn their living by other means than their pen. Our market is small and
               sometimes mean. We have few periodicals that pay well—and a snubishness exists which
               sometimes turns the Canadian editor’s eye greedily toward the work of authors in
               other countries. Our publishers are doing the best they can for the author, but we
               need the support and sympathy of the Canadian public. We need protection from men who
               frame laws that are levelled at our craft. The present copyright law is a disgrace to
               Canada. No self-respecting author could do otherwise than resent its terms. Our work
               is not only open to piracy, but we are discriminated against in favor of those who
               were born in other lands. Under the terms of the law, the Canadian, born in England
               or other lands is exempted while the native born Canadian author is ham-strung.</p>

            <p>I wrote and spoke to <name ref="pers:JL1">Sir James Lougheed</name> concerning this law. He denied
               that he had sponsored it. He said it was a government measure. He said that we had to
               have a copyright law and that this was the best they could do at that time. He stated
               that he realized it was not perfect, but they were beset by the labor unions at the
               time. Now no emergency, however pressing, is justification for a wrong. Kicking one
               man in order to make another laugh is not good work. I cannot see that even the labor
               unions would desire to profit at the expense of another craft.</p>

            <p>We know that this country is in sore need of both capital and immigration. It does us
               no good to hug to ourselves the secret that this country possesses immense mineral
               and agricultural resources; that its climate is unrivalled, and that this might
               become the real Land of Opportunity and Promise, if only we could bring to it the
               right sort of people. The only way in which we can do this is by the most intensive
               kind of publicity, and the greatest publicity conveyors that this country possesses
               are its authors. Professional advertising and publicity stuff cannot compete with the
               work that the author can do. <name ref="pers:HL1">Longfellow</name>’s <q>Evangeline</q> did more to
               show the world the lovely land of Nova Scotia than a ton of adveritising would have
               done.</p>

            <p>We all know what has happened to Canada through not having authors of her own to
               describe her to the world. Charlatans of the pen from other lands have come to this
               country for short visits and returned to exploit the country in books, magazines and
               upon the screen. None of us relish being depicted in the weird and wild fashion that
               Canadians are revealed in snow stories to the world. A young woman here in Calgary
               recently returned from abroad, and in London she was induced by friends to go to see
               a <q>Canadian</q> play in a local theater. They described it as <q>wonderful</q>, and
               it was written by an English dramatist who should have known better. She stayed but
               for the first act. It was a scene in Calgary. The curtain rose on a rough bar-room.
               (The dramatist by the way ignored the prohibition laws existing at the time). Upon
               the bar leaned a noble mounted policeman. He wore, of course, the red coat, but as he
               had just come in from riding in a wild storm, his legs were encased in chaps made of
               tiger skins. Dancing alternately on the bar, the chairs and tables and the floor was
               a young Calgary girl arrayed in pink skin tights and some <name ref="pers:MP4">Mary Pickford</name>
               curls. From the corner table a villainous looking French-Canuck snevgalied <choice>
                  <sic>har</sic>
                  <corr>her</corr>
               </choice>. Presently the door burst open, and a fearful blast of hail and wind and
               snow and icicles and everything that the Canadian climate alone produces rushed in
               through the door, bearing with it a pitiful young Indian girl, around whose head was
               a red ribbon in which was struck a turkey feather at the back, and who was dressed in
               a beaded skirt something like they use in the can-can ballet dances. With her white
               papoose hugged to her back she cast one anguished glance at the dancing girl in
               tights, and then her bold outraged eyes lighted upon the man in the corner, now
               shrinking back against the wall. A pause and the Indian girl leaped at the white girl.
               They struggled back and forth while crawling from beneath the bar came an aged Indian
               chief, father of the wronged girl. He wiggled his way in full sight of all, yet
               unseen by them, across that Calgary bar-room, till suddenly he was upon the neck of
               the <choice>
                  <sic>terrifeid</sic>
                  <corr>terrified</corr>
               </choice> French-Canuck, and a moment later he had scalped him neatly from neck to
               brow.</p>

            <p>Now, there’s a Canadian play for you. True, is it not? Do you imagine that anyone who
               sees it will pine to come to Canada? But think:</p>

            <p>Supposing a Canadian author should write a play or a story of this country.
               Supposing, instead of showing the land all garbed in snow and ice, he revealed the
               wide spreading fields of grain, the blue sungilt skies, the noble mountains rising
               like a miracle across the horizon. Supposing he showed something of the spirit, of
               the feeling of tip-topness which we all feel here—the feeling that makes a man hold
               his chest up and walking along with a spring to his feet. Supposing the Canadian
               author took his pen and with a loving full heart wrote a role that was redolent with
               color and romance, that fascinated and enthralled its readers, would not then this
               country seem not only a desirable place to visit, but the veritable land of promise.
               Only the Canadian author can tell the true Canadian story, and do not think that
               among our writers we have not the talent—aye, genius needed for such a work. The two
               most distinctive novels published in New York last year were the work of Canadians—I
               refer to Maria Chapdelaine and to <name ref="pers:MP2">Marjorie Pickthall</name>’s
                  <q>The Bridge</q>. Yet the author of Maria Chapdelaine was a hired man on an
               Ontario farm who was run over by a train and buried as a tramp. It is true he was
               born in France, but he was <choice>
                  <sic>saturateed</sic>
                  <corr>saturated</corr>
               </choice> with the lore and the love of his adopted Canada. <name ref="pers:MP2"
                  >Marjorie Pickthall</name> lived only a few years after she had achieved
               recognition and fame. There are many other Canadian authors, equally talented. They
               need only encouragement and a chance to make a livelihood in a country where laws are
               not enacted especially to discriminate against their craft.</p>


         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
