<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LittleTheatreMovement1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Little Theatre Movement Aims to Encourage Talent of Every Kind and Sort</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:KS1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:313"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySource"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-05" status="published">Provided further edits and
             low certainty footnote</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2021-11-29" status="readyForProof">Edited and added text to
            repository.</change>
         <change who="pers:KS1" when="2021-10-28" status="inProgress">Began Transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2021-10-12" status="empty">Added genre, exhibit, and doc type;
            assigned facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2021-10-12" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>

      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:LittleTheatreMovement">
      <body>
         <head>Little Theatre Movement Aims to Encourage Talent Of Every Kind and Sort</head>
         <head type="subtitle">
            <name ref="pers:WE1">Mrs. Winnifred Reeve</name> Gives Interesting Talk on Movement
            Started in Calgary--Speaker Points Out Success That Has Been Attained in Other Large
            Cities In United States and Canada </head>
         <div>
            <p><q>What does the little theatre movement mean</q>? This question was answered very
               clearly and fully by Mrs. Winnifred Reeve in an address given at the Gladys Attree
               studio on Thursday evening to a large audience. <choice>
                  <sic>Summping</sic>
                  <corr resp="pers:JT1">Summoning</corr>
               </choice> up her answer to the question, Mrs. Reeves explained that the movement is
               simply <q>drama of the people, by the people and for the people</q>.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Reeve commented her talk by expressing some little surprise that the question
               should be put by so many in a city the size and importance of Calgary, for, said she,
               nearly every city and town of any consequence in the United States and in Canada, to
               say nothing of Europe, today possesses its little theatre, or groups who make up
               community players.</p>
            <p>The objects of the little theatre, the speaker set forth as the promotion of the
               study of drama, the production of high-class plays--both foreign and Canadian, to
               develop and encourage the talent of the city--not merely dramatic talent--but talent
               of every kind and sort.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Must Be Wide Open</head>
            <p>Proceeding, Mrs. Reeve said in part: <q>Indeed I may say at the outset that the
                  closed shop idea would be fatal to such a movement. By that I mean small groups
                  who might gather together and run things for the benefit of their own limited
                  circle. We should not specialize on the talent of the west side the north side the
                  east side or the south side of the city. The little theatre should have no pets no
                  special man or woman to thrust repeatedly forward into the limelight unless he or
                  she is of prime importance to the special play being put on. Pull and money should
                  avail nothing. Talent alone should be the touchstone</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Field is Limited</head>
            <p>
               <q>The difference between the little theatre and amateur dramatic club is that the
                  amateur club confines itself to the work of its members. It is, therefore, narrowed
                  down to a limited field. Furthermore its intentions and ideals are widely
                  different from that of the little theatre</q>.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The difference between the little theatre and the professional theatre lies in the
                  fact that the one is a commercial proposition. Plays are put on with the main idea
                  of making money. On the other hand the little theatre is purely community work,
                  done for love of that work, without pay</q>.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It would draw under its wing all of the dramatic clubs or community players of the
                  city, and it would open its doors wide to the talent of the city. Here are some of
                  the assignments that would be given</q>:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Designing costumes or scenery, painting scenery, <gap reason="illegible"/>,
                  printing, dancing, electrical work, play reading, secretarial work, publicity,
                  dyeing, stencilling, typewriting, decorating, play producing, coaching, play
                  writing, acting, music, vocal or instrumental, carpentering work, clerical and
                  executive work, <supplied cert="low" resp="pers:LW1">orchestra, shopping</supplied>, 
                  reading of MSS</q>.</p>
            <p>
               <q>In some of the little theatres princes and millionaires have worked <gap
                     reason="illegible"/> wielded the broom that has cleaned the stage, while the
                  daughter of a scrub woman has played the star part</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Success Everywhere</head>
            <p>Mrs. Reeve then went on to tell of the success of the little theatre idea has met
               with in a large number of cities of the United States and Canada, and how it has
               succeeded in developing talent that would otherwise have lain dormant. Speaking of
               the effort in Toronto, the speaker said:</p>
            <p>
               <q>You probably have all heard of Hart House, the mecca of the talent of Toronto. And
                  you know, no doubt, also of the splendid work done by the universities. It is good
                  to record how the movement caught on at the universities. You see it was something
                  that appealed to the young. You can scarcely find a university today that has not
                  allied itself in some way with the little theatre movement</q>.</p>
            <p>Coming to the movement in Calgary, Mrs. Reeves said: <q>There is no question of the
                  fact that we possess all kind of talent in this city. Besides talent we have
                  beauty--hundreds of unusually pretty girls and some raving beauties</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Beauty is not an essential for an actress but is a mighty fine asset and will
                  carry a girl a long way. Talent will take her farther</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Much Musical Talent</head>
            <p>
               <q>We have musical talent, and a movement such as this will discover composers of
                  ability. We have literary talent and a movement such as this will bring out
                  playwrights and dramatists. We might have a contest in the schools. Put the young
                  people to dramatizing a short story of some kind and see what will result: for it
                  is the aim of the little theatre to put on as well as tried plays original ones
                  done by residents of the city</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Take Mrs. McClung’s <q>Bringing Up Danny</q>. Someone could make a corking little
                  play out of that and give opportunity for some comic and emotional acting of a
                  high order. Sergeant Kendall has material for a play</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Essentiality of Stage</head>
            <p>
               <q>Then there is dancing. Dancing has always been closely allied with the theatre.
                  Its proper setting is the stage</q>.</p>
            <p>
               <q>All this you see would come with the little theatre. This would <gap
                     reason="illegible"/> these things not for use in professional life but because
                  of love of them because of the culture to mind and body that they would
               impart</q>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
