<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LoveOfAzalea4">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Love of Azalea</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from Google Books from original at Harvard University </note></notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:166"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovel"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" when="2020-08-28" status="inProgress">Begin transcribing and proofreading</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-24" status="empty">Changed title.</change><change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-02" status="empty">Changed genre.</change><change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-01" status="empty">Added note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2019-08-23" status="empty">Addes facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl166 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:LoveOfAzalea">
     <pb n="1"/> 
      <body>
         <head>The Love of Azalea</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name> 
               Author of <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6">A Japanese Nightingale</ref>, <ref
                     target="doc:HeartOfHyacinth1">The Heart of Hyacinth</ref>, etc.
           </byline>   
         </opener>
         
           <pb n="5"/>
         <div type="content">
              
               <div type="chapter" n="1">
                  <head>Chapter I</head>
                  <p>It was drowsy in the little mission church, and the gentle mellifluous voice of the young preacher increased rather than dispelled the sleepy peacefulness. The church, if such it could be styled, was well filled. The people of Sanyo knew it for the coolest of retreats. They drifted aimlessly in and out of the church, making no pretense of either understanding or appreciating the proceedings. It was a curious congregation, one which, innocently enough, never <pb n="6"/>thought of assisting the pastor. They came to see the white priest, not to listen 
                     to the pleading message he brought, which as yet they could not understand. His Japanese was too correct. Spoken slowly and painfully in the unfamiliar accent of the Caucasian, it was often quite unintelligible. But, as was said, the church was cool, the villagers curious, and the minister an unending source of wonder to them. If some of the congregation waited patiently throughout the length of the sermon, it was not because they deemed this the proper thing to do, but because they knew they would be treated to another form of entertainment, which they childishly en-<pb n="7"/>joyed. For, after the sermon, the minister, closing the large black book before him and opening a small red one, would raise his voice, throw back his head, open his mouth, and sing aloud in a voice which had never lost its fascination for his hearers. He had done this from the first, leading an unresponsive congregation in hymns of praise; but singing to the end alone. No aiding voice took up the refrain with him nor was there even the music of an organ to bear his clear voice company. Through the opened windows the chirp of the birds floated. Sometimes a baby, grown restless, laughed and crowed aloud. </p>
                  <p>On this particular Sunday, however, the <pb n="8"/>minister, who appeared
                  unusually happy, had introduced an innovation. As its nature had been whispered
                  about the village, the service in consequence was well attended. Behind the
                  minister’s small sandal-wood pulpit a bench had been placed, upon which the people
                  saw seated five of the most disreputable waifs of the town. At first they were
                  hardly recognizable. From smudgy-faced, soiled and tattered bits of flotsam, they
                  were transformed in garments of white—miniature surplices they were. </p>
               <p>The minister beamed upon them. The boys looked stoically back at him. This day
                  those in the church forgot to look about <pb n="9"/>at the various objects of interest, forgot to drowse, for all eyes were intent upon that little row behind the priest. When the sermon was ended and the minister turned to the red hymn book, the boys arose to their feet, and as his baritone voice was raised, five piping and discordant minor voices joined with him. </p>
               <p>The result of the minister’s effort for a choir was immediate. It broke up the
                  apathy of the congregation. </p>
               <p>Groups lingered about the mission house after the service—groups of curious
                  child-women for the most part. The question discussed from every standpoint was
                  the seeming elevation of these most unsavory <pb n="10"/>and godless of town
                  waifs. How could these good people guess that the young minister, restless at the
                  seeming fruitlessness of his labors, had given of his own meagre salary to induce
                  the hungriest of the town, for so many sen, to be respectable for one day in the
                  week? What would not a Japanese vagabond do for a sen or a sweet potato? Submit to
                  a bath, a robe too clean to touch and the pleasure—sometimes pain—of mimicking the
                  voice of the white man. </p>
               <p>The mellow tinkling of temple bells disturbed the gossips. It was the hour of
                  noon, when the gods were good and for a little prayer would give them sweet food
                     <pb n="11"/>and excellent appetites. So straight from the temple of the white
                  priest they dispersed, through the valley to the opposite hill, where the Shinto
                  Temple, golden-tipped, beckoned them to the prayers they mechanically understood;
                  a moment only in the temple, nodding heads and prostrating bodies, and after that,
                  home and the noon-day meal. Thus every day. Only on the Sunday, since the coming
                  of the foreign priest, they had added to the routine this weekly pilgrimage of
                  curiosity to the white man’s temple. Strange indeed were the ways of the foreign
                  devils! </p>
                  <p><q>Let us wait a little while</q>, said a round-<pb n="12"/>faced, merry-eyed maid of fifteen, grasping the sleeves of girl friends.</p>
               <p>Azalea was departing slowly when recalled by the raised voice of her friend. At a
                  short distance from the other girls she paused and looked back inquiringly. </p>
               <p><q>Wait till they come out</q>, continued the speaker, Ume-san by name, <q>those
                     beggars, and we will have some fun</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, good!</q> agreed Koto, snapping her fan upon her hand; <q>we will find out
                     what the white beast says to them</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Perhaps</q>, suggested Fuji, stretching herself—she was fat and indolent and
                  the church seat was hard—<q>he pays them</q>.</p>
                     <pb n="13"/>
               <p>Azalea looked interested. </p>
               <p><q>I wish</q>, said she wistfully, <q>he would pay me something</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Perhaps he will</q>, said Fuji, nodding her head slowly; <q>my honorable father
                     says he is rich—very rich</q>.</p>
               <p><q>And my honorable father says so, too</q>, said Ume. </p>
               <p><q>Oh, all foreign devils are</q>, declared Koto conclusively. </p>
               <p><q>Well, but Matsuda Isami says he is not</q>, said Azalea. <q>And Matsuda knows
                     surely</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Matsuda is jealous</q>, said Koto. <q>He wants to be always the richest. The
                     gods despise avarice</q>.</p>
                  <pb n="14"/>
               <p>Azalea was fluttering her fan somewhat nervously. She regarded it thoughtfully,
                  then closed it sharply. </p>
               <p><q>I am avaricious</q>, she said, with the point of her fan touching her pretty
                  red underlip. </p>
               <p>Her friends laughed at her, and she blushed. </p>
               <p><q>Yes</q>, she said, <q>I am avaricious. The gods will despise me truly. I adore
                     money. I would like to have one hundred yen all to myself</q>.</p>
               <p><q>What would you do with it?</q> questioned Ume, the oldest of the four. </p>
               <p><q>I would leave my step-mother’s house</q>, said Azalea simply. </p>
                  <pb n="15"/>
               <p><q>Here they come!</q> cried Koto. The girls fell into an excited little line by
                  the church door, one behind the other. Out came the choir—their surplices doffed,
                  their washed faces wide with smiles and their little eyes shining. Five sen
                  rattled in the sleeve of each. The girls had drawn in hiding behind the church
                  portico in order to surprise them. Now they sprang out into view, and grasped the
                  boys by the sleeves. Thinking they were being set upon for their hard-earned sen,
                  a series of angry shrieks and snorts burst out. Their fears set at rest by the
                  merry laughter of the girls, they were finally induced to tell all they knew. The
                  minister, it seems, had <pb n="16"/>brought them to his house at various times, had fed them on sweet potatoes and rice cakes, and had taught them to sing just as he did. For this public effort in his temple, he had given them
                  each—well, they did not propose to tell any one how much he had given, but the intimation was that it was a sum sufficient to keep them in luxury for some time to come. Furthermore, they, the members of his choir, were to have this same sum given to them as a weekly income, for singing, just like the white priest, in his church, each Sunday. 
               </p>
               <p>Azalea sighed and, sitting on the church steps, looked at the fortunate boys with
                  envious and wistful eyes. </p>
                  <pb n="17"/>
               <p><q>And does not the white beast want females also to sing?</q> she asked. </p>
               <p><q>Females!</q> repeated one of the boys. <q>Did the gods ever favor
                  females?</q></p>
               <p><q>The foreign devil is not a god</q>, said Azalea thoughtfully. <q>Who knows,
                     perhaps he would pay me also to sing with him</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Time to go home</q>, said Koto, and she pulled Ume’s sleeve. <q>Are you not
                     hungry? Come, Azalea!</q></p>
               <p><q>She won’t give me to eat, my most honorable mother-in-law</q>, said Azalea.
                     <q>I need not go there</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>You will soon be a beggar, too, Azalea</q>, laughed Koto, <q>and the white man <pb n="18"/>will give you charity. But come, girls</q>.</p>
               <p>Clinging to each other’s hands and almost tripping over each other’s heels, the
                  three girls fluttered homeward down the hill, leaving Azalea sitting alone,
                  looking moodily and reflectively at the choir boys, now counting their money. She
                  knew that they, like her, were orphans. Unlike her, they had not an uncharitable
                  roof, called by her ungracious step-parent a home for her. Shelter beneath it was
                  only grudgingly accorded, because Azalea’s step-mother was vain and feared the
                  criticism of neighbors and the wrath of the gods should she turn Azalea out. As it
                  was, the young girl was only half fed and her clothes were those <pb n="19"
                  />half-worn ones thrown to her by arrogant and fortunate step-sisters, yet the
                  girl’s nimble fingers made those same threadbare garments objects of
                  attractiveness, which set off her own appealing beauty. But she was seventeen,
                  unmarried and unhappy. Something must be done soon, or she would become the bride
                  of the river. Her step-mother’s scoldings grew with the girl’s in- creasing beauty
                  and grace. She did not know this was the cause, only she knew life was becoming
                  unbearable. </p>
               <p>The choir boys had already shuffled a portion of the way down the hill slope, when
                  she sprang to her feet and ran after them. </p>
                  <pb n="20"/>
               <p><q>Gonji!</q> she called one of them by name. <q>Wait just a moment</q>.</p>
               <p>They stopped and she overtook them. She was breathless when she reached them. </p>
               <p><q>Is it because you are beggars</q>, she said, <q>that this priest favors
                     you?</q></p>
               <p>Gonji nodded. </p>
               <p><q>I</q>, said Azalea, spreading out her little hands, <q>am also a
                  beggar</q>.</p>
               <p>They laughed at her. Only the homeless were beggars in their eyes. In addition,
                  members of her sex were received among them only when they had reached the old
                  witch age. The country knew many old women beggars, who drifted, <pb n="21"/>whining, upon
                  their staffs from town to town. Often they were blind and clung to the rope about
                  the neck of a tailless cat, which led them. Who ever heard of a maiden beggar? So
                  Azalea’s statement was received in laughter. </p>
               <p><q>How much did the minister give?</q> she demanded, ignoring their jeers. </p>
               <p><q>Five—ten—maybe one hundred sen</q>, glibly lied Gonji. </p>
               <p>Her eyes widened and shone. </p>
               <p><q>Oh!</q> she said. </p>
               <p><q>That’s only for the singing</q>, said Gonji; <q>if we become convert to his
                     religion he will pay more</q>.</p>
               <p>He turned to his companions for verifi-<pb n="22"/>cation. They had moved on their
                  way and he made to join them. </p>
               <p><q>No, no, don’t go! Wait a little while, please!</q></p>
               <p><q>Well?</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>What is ‘convert?’</q></p>
               <p><q>Why</q>, the Japanese boy of sixteen racked his brain for an explanation of the
                  word, <q>why, that’s to—ah—that’s just abandoning the gods for a new one</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh!</q> His sleeve dropped from her grasp and she drew back, her face somewhat
                  blanched. </p>
               <p><q>Abandon the gods!</q> she repeated. </p>
               <p><q>But if we do that, then the gods will be angry with us</q>.</p>
                  <pb n="23"/>
         </div>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
