<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Marion8">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Marion (Part 7)</title>
            <title type="sub">The Story of an Artist’s Model</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from Hathi Trust: <ref
                  target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000542803"
                  >https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000542803</ref>.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:80"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovelSerial"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:NewYork"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-08-28" status="published">Proofed.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-07-16" status="published">Proofed and set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-06-01" status="readyForProof">Encoded foreign language
            and letters.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-25" status="readyForProof">Encoded milestones and
            pages. Set to readyForProof.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-25" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-15" status="empty">Removed primary source people from
               <gi>respStmt</gi> using XSLT.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-04">Added facs and readied for
            proof.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl80 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Marion7" prev="doc:Marion7" next="doc:Marion9">
      <pb n="231"/>
      <body>
         <head>Marion: The Story of an Artist’s Model</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">The Author of Me</name></byline>
            <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:HH1">Henry Hutt</name></byline>
         </opener>
         <div type="content">
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <div>
               <div type="paratext">
                  <p>Synopsis: Here we have the story, told at first-hand, of Marion Ascough, sister
                     of <q>Me</q>, a girl destined to eventually travel far—Montreal, Boston, New
                     York, and even to <q>Bohemia</q>, accumulating experiences by the way—clinging
                     to the highest ideals, as artist, model, friend of painters, and finally the
                     wife of an artist. She was born in the queer little French-Canadian village of
                     Hochelaga, a suburb of Montreal; her father was an English painter, her mother
                     a Frenchwoman. Here Monsieur de St. Vidal proposed to her in the snow, and she
                     ran home. Then she had a bent for the stage and made a hit in amateur
                     theatricals. Along came Mr. Reggie Bertie—call him Bartie, so English you
                     know—remittance-man, who is studying for the bar. It was a case of love at
                     first sight between handsome Reggie and pretty Marion Ascough. He took her to
                     the ice carnival and when he should have been watching the procession he was
                     looking down at her. Later, he refuses to take her into a flashy all-night
                     restaurant because Marion is <q>too nice and too sweet</q>. Very soon they
                      become engaged, but while Bertie is an ardent wooer he does not want the
                     marriage to take place; he’s afraid of <q>the governor</q> of England, so poor
                     Marion is in for a long wait, during which she must be self-supporting at
                     painting and other art work, besides helping at home. Then she hires a little
                     studio of her own—Reggie pays for it—in Montreal; Reggie still procrastinates.
                     At last she tells him that he has no right to monopolize her time and her
                     society unless he intends to fulfill his promise,—particularly as he objects to
                     her seeing any other men. She goes to Boston and there becomes a full-fledged
                     model, with some weird experiences and cruel privations. Then she falls ill,
                     owing to privation and anxiety.</p>
               </div>
               <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>The sun was shining, and the warm breath of summer felt good to me. I was up now;
                  but I felt impatient with my own weakness and I had a restless desire to move
                  about and do things. I realized my indebtedness to Lois, and I wondered if I would
                  ever be able to wipe it out.</p>
               <p>I had had very dreadful news from my people. Wallace, Ellen’s husband had died,
                  after a long illness. When I first heard that, I wanted to go at once to my
                  sister, and I was heartbroken because of my inability to comfort and help her.
                  Lois wrote to Ellen for me, telling her that I would join her in New York, just as
                  soon as I was strong enough to travel; but Ellen had written back that she was
                  going to England, with her little boy, to Wallace’s people.</p>
               <p>I thought of how close Ellen and I had been to each other as children, and of the
                  strangeness and cruelty of fate that cut sisters apart. It seemed to me that this
                  was a world of all pain. Yet, if we measured our griefs by those of others, mine
                  shrank into insignificance beside those of Ellen’s. Always there had been some way
                  out for me, but Ellen’s road had been walled up. Death had shut to her forever the
                  golden door of Hope. I knew that no one—not even her little son—could ever take to
                  Ellen the place of Wallace, her young hero and lover and husband. Poor Wallace!
                  Literary critics had said he was a genius, and I think he was. He was only
                  twenty-seven when he died, with his second book of essays but half written, and
                  his play still unproduced.</p>
               <p>Lois had a little gas-stove in the room, on which she boiled coffee and eggs. She
                  called to me to come now to breakfast. I said to her sadly:</p>
               <p><q>Lois, I’m awfully indebted to you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Not on your life</q>, said Lois; <q>you don’t owe me anything, and if you say
                     anything more about it, I’ll get real cross. You can’t imagine how nasty I am
                     when I’m cross</q>, she laughed. <q>I’ve had the time of my life nursing you,
                     and Dr. Squires says—</q></p>
               <p>A beautiful flush came over Lois’s face, and I said: <q>Oh, Lois, I do hope you’ll
                     get married and be ever and ever so happy</q>.</p>
               <p><q>I’ve got to go to England</q>, said she. <q>My parents are there now, and
                     there’s a lawsuit over some property left by a relative who died lately. You
                     see, I’m the real heir, they say. I’m really a Ward in Chancery</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Why, Lois, I thought you were a native American</q>.</p>
               <p><q>So I am. I was born in Massachusetts, but my mother was English, and now I’ve
                     got to go over there to see about this property they say I’m rightful heir to.
                     I’ll have to leave at the end of the month</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, how I’ll miss you!</q> I cried. <q>I don’t know how in the world I’ll ever
                     get on without you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>When you get your strength back</q>, said Lois, <q>you’ll not feel that way,
                     and you’re going to stay here and room with me till I go. So don’t worry,
                     whatever you do. Get to work now, and forget everything blue</q>.</p>
               <p>I had not told Lois I was a model. I had simply said at home I had been an
                  artist.</p>
               <p>She had brought down my paints and palette, and now, as I arranged my things, she
                  watched me with great interest. She had brought me a print of a basket of fruit
                  and a bowl of flowers, and asked me if I wouldn’t copy these for her. I  painted
                  them on two wooden plates she had, and she was delighted, and cried out
                  admiringly:</p>
               <p><q>Aren’t you the smartest girl, though!</q></p>
               <p>Tim O’Leary came in while I was painting, and the admiration of that big bartender
                  was pathetic. He actually walked on tiptoe to come nearer to take a look. Then he
                  said:</p>
               <p><q>I’ll be back in a second</q>.</p>
               <p>He left the room, and returned shortly with a parcel wrapped up in white tissue
                  paper, which he gently unfolded. He showed us a little piece of white satin with
                  some pink flowers painted in the center, and trimmed around with cream lace; also
                  two pieces of embroidery of a really fine quality. He handled these works of art,
                  as he called them, poor fellow, with an almost reverent tenderness, and Lois and I
                  loudly expressed our admiration of them.</p>
               <p><q>I’m keeping them</q>, said Tim, <q>for the little girl back home. She’ll be
                     coming to me before long, and I’ll have her little nest as elegant as the
                     finest of them</q>, he said shyly. <q>My Katy has eyes like this little girl
                     here, and it’s real smart you are to do such grand work, Miss Marion</q>.</p>
               <pb n="232"/>
               <p><q>Say, Mr. O’Leary</q>, I said, <q>I’m going to make you something to add to your
                     collection for your little girl</q>.</p>
               <p>I kept my word, and in a few days I had painted on a piece of blue satin that Lois
                  found among her things a bunch of roses, which poor Tim declared he could almost
                  smell. That same evening he brought me two enormous whisky jugs. They were about
                  three feet high—sample bottles. They were of course, empty. Tim made the
                  astonishing request of me that I should paint on them, and he offered to pay
                  me.</p>
               <p>So I painted a little seascape on one and a wreath of lilies-of-the-valley and
                  forget-me-nots on the other. Of course, I would not take pay from Tim for them.
                  The following day Tim came rushing in to tell me he had placed them on his bar,
                  and all of his friends and customers had thought them great, and one man offered
                  him five dollars apiece for them. He said that nothing would induce him to part
                  with them, but he was sending over to me all the big sample bottles he could get,
                  and also beer and wine and champagne bottles, and he said if I would paint on
                  these he would sell them for me. Well, the astonishing part is, that he did sell
                  them. I must have decorated at least twenty of those awful bottles, and Tim got me
                  about forty dollars for my work. So I was able to pay Miss Darling, and I went
                  over to the boarding-house where I still owed that bill and I paid it. To my
                  surprise the landlady tried to force two dollars back upon me.</p>
               <p><q>We all know how ill you’ve been</q>, she said, <q>and I said to my man: ‘We’ll
                     never see the color of that board money,’ and he says: ‘You’ll get it yet,’ and
                     you see he’s always right. So here, you can take two of it back, and may you
                     have the good luck your pretty face should bring you</q>.</p>
               <p>Lois sailed on one of the small merchant liners, and it left the pier at five in
                  the morning, so we had to get up very early to see her off. We had sat up very
                  late the night before, and Dr. Squires had spent the evening with us and promised
                  to be at the pier to see her off. The morning was foggy and chilly. I clung
                  tightly to Lois before I let her go, and the doctor said:</p>
               <p><q>Here, give another fellow a chance</q>.</p>
               <p>He, too, kissed Lois, and there were tears in both their eyes.</p>
               <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
               <p>It is conceivably hard for a girl without a definite trade or profession, and
                  possessed of no particular talent, to earn her own living. With Tim O’Leary’s help
                  I had made a little money that tided me over for a time, but I realized that it
                  was merely a temporary relief. The artists would not be returning for a couple of
                  months, and I was in a quandary what I should do. A letter from Lil Markey, the
                  girl who had posed for Count von Hatzfeldt in Montreal, made me consider the
                  advisability of joining her in New York. This is Lil’s letter:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dear Marion:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Here I am in little old New York. Been here two months now. I’m trying to
                           get a job on the stage, and I’ve almost landed one. You ought to come
                           here. There’s lots better opportunities, especially for a model. I have
                           all the work I can do just now posing for <q>The Banner</q>, a theatrical
                           paper.</p>
                        <p>Now, there’s a fellow here who is going to get a bunch of girls and put
                           us in living pictures. All one needs is looks.</p>
                        <p>Say, why don’t you come on and join me here? I’ve a little flat with a
                           couple of other girls, and we need another to squeeze in and help pay the
                           expenses. I’d prefer you to anyone I’ve seen here. Say, some of them are
                           tough!</p>
                        <p>I was awfully sorry to hear about the old Count dying. Ada told me how
                           cut up you were about it, too. I’ve a date now—my meal-ticket!</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>With love,</salute>
                           <signed>LIL.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Lil’s letter had started my thoughts on an old trail. The desire to act came
                  creeping back on me. It was like an old thirst that suddenly awoke and tugged at
                  one’s consciousness insisting on being satisfied.</p>
               <p>In Boston I had not thought to see theatrical managers. Reggie had long ago
                  successfully squelched my ambitions in that line. Now Lil’s letter and her
                  reference to Mr. Davis quickened a new hope within me.</p>
               <pb n="258"/>
               <p>Perhaps, as Lil wrote, conditions were better in New York. Certainly there should
                  be more work for a model, and perhaps I might in time really get on the stage. I
                  had enough money for my fare and a little over, and Boston appealed to me. Still,
                  I had not definitely decided to go until I had read the letter that came from
                  Reggie:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>’Dearest old girl:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I am so glad you are keeping well, and have quite recovered from your
                           recent indispotion. I have been up to my eyes and ears in important work.
                           I’m going to run for the next sections for the ninth ward. What do you
                           think of that for a young and rising barrister? I’ll bet you are proud of
                           your Reggie, now aren’t you, darling? As for me, now that the rush has
                           let up a bit, I am simply famising for the sight of my little Marion, and
                              <emph>now</emph> for the <emph>best</emph> news of all. I’m leaving
                           for Boston to-morrow evening, and I’ll be with you within a day! There
                           won’t be any more cross, stiff little letters coming to me from Boston,
                           from a strange Marion that’s not a bit like the loving little girl I
                           know. The States is no place for a girl like you, darling, and I’m going
                           there to fetch you home. Be at Grand Union Station at 8:15.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>Your</salute>
                           <signed> ’REGGIE.’</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Feverishly I packed my clothes. I would go to New York! Reggie should not again
                  find me here to hurt me further.</p>
               <p>My train would not leave till night and I had a few friends whom I wished to bid
                  good-by. When I was leaving the house I met Tim O’Leary, and he invited me to have
                  lunch with him. I smiled to myself as I sat opposite that bartender, thinking what
                  Reggie would say if he could see me, and I suddenly said to Tim:</p>
               <p><q>Tim, do you know, you are more of a real gentleman than the grandson of a duke
                     I know</q>. Tim’s broad red face shone.</p>
               <p>When I said good-by to Rose St. Denis she took me in her arms like a mother.</p>
               <p><q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Enfant</foreign></q>, she said, <q>you are so t’in from
                     ze seekness, I have for you ze pity in my ‘eart. I will not see you face never
                     again, but I will make me a prayer to <foreign xml:lang="fr">le bon
                        Dieu</foreign> to pitifully tek care of my <foreign xml:lang="fr">petite
                        soeur</foreign></q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, Rose</q>, I said, crying, <q>I’ll never, never forget <emph>you</emph>. I
                     think the thought of <emph>you</emph> will always keep me
                     <emph>good!</emph></q></p>
               <p>I was fortunate in finding Dr. Squires in, though it was not his office-hour. He
                  seemed glad to see me, and when I said:</p>
               <p><q>Doctor, I am off for New York</q>, he answered:</p>
               <p><q>What’s the matter with Boston, then?</q></p>
               <p>I explained that I thought that I could do better in New York, and he agreed that
                  my chances there were more promising. Then I said: <q>Doctor, I want to thank you
                     for all your kindness to me and will you please tell me how much your bill
                     is?</q></p>
               <p>He had not only come to see me two or three times a day during my illness, but he
                  had also supplied all the medicines. He looked at me very seriously when I asked
                  for his bill, and then he said in a deep, thrilling voice:</p>
               <p><q>You do not owe me a cent. It is <emph>I</emph> who is indebted to
                        <emph>you</emph></q>.</p>
               <p>I knew what he meant, and oh, it did thrill me to think that my illness had
                  brought those two beautiful people together, Lois and her doctor. When I was going
                  out I said:</p>
               <p><q>Doctor, I am going on the stage. Perhaps I’ll succeed. Wish me good
                  luck</q>.</p>
               <p><q>I wish you the best of luck in the world</q>, he said cordially, <q>and I
                     wouldn’t be a bit surprised to hear of your success. You look like Duse,
                     Bernhardt, Julia Marlowe, and at times like a composite of all the great
                     actresses</q>. He did not laugh when he said that, and he wrung my hand warmly
                  as if he actually meant it.</p>
               <p>Lil had a tiny little flat near Columbus Avenue. She was delighted to see me and
                  introduced me to the two other girls. They were both quite pretty, with bright
                  golden hair and wonderful complexions. Lil whispered to me that their hair was
                  bleached and she said that they got their complexions from the corner drug-store.
                  I suppose in the daytime I could have seen for myself, but I had arrived at night
                  and I was dead tired. The girls were all very friendly and later in the evening a
                  number of men friends called. I was too tired and sleepy to sit up with them and I
                  went to bed. The flat was so small that I could hear them talking and they seemed
                  to sit up all night. In spite of the noise of their chatter and laughter I went to
                  sleep.</p>
               <p>I stayed with Lil in that flat for a month and we all shared expenses. I got work
                  right away with some advertising photographers who paid me $5.00 for a single
                  sitting—but that would take a good part of the day. Lil and the other girls posed
                  for <q>The Banner</q>, a kind of theatrical magazine, that ran pictures of
                  chorus-girls, etc. I remember one picture which showed the girls tumbling out of a
                  toboggan and another where they all were supposed to have fallen out of a street
                  car. I could have done this work too, but it seemed tawdry and dirty work to me,
                  and so long as I could get the photographic work I much preferred it.</p>
               <p>In September we were all engaged to be living pictures by a man who was putting
                  them on in vaudeville houses. The subjects represented were strictly proper ones,
                  such as <q>Youth</q>, <q>Psyche</q>, <q>The Angelus</q>, <q>Rock of Ages</q>, etc.
                  We received fifteen dollars a week. As we lived cheaply and men were always taking
                  us out to dinners, our expenses were really small, and although Lil urged me to
                  get some new clothes, I paid off my debt to Lu Fraser.</p>
               <p>I suppose I ought to have been contented, but the work seemed stupid to me. I
                  tired of the everlasting talk of chorus-girls. They all seemed to have but one
                  interest, and that was the stage. Mind you, not <emph>acting</emph>, but the
                     <emph>stage</emph> and all the cheap shop-talk that goes with it. What is more,
                  I was weary of Lil and her girl friends and their men friends. They sat up in the
                  flittle flat so late that it was almost impossible to sleep; and there was too
                  much drink and crazy laughter. It worked upon my nerves and I began to long for
                  the atmosphere of the studio once more. I thought that posing for the artists was,
                  after all, preferable to this cheap <q>acting</q>. So when an offer came to me of
                  twenty-five dollars a week as a show-girl in a popular <q>musical show</q>, I
                  refused it, although Lil and the other girls exclaimed enviously over my
                     <q>luck</q>. They seemed to think that I was out of my senses and shrieked at
                  me:</p>
               <p><q>What on earth <emph>do</emph> you want then?</q> and I replied wearily:</p>
               <p><q>I don’t know myself. I guess I just want to be let alone</q>.</p>
               <p>How those girls did exclaim at that! Apparently, to them, I thought myself better
                  than they were; but indeed this was not the case. I just realized that our
                  interests were different. What seemed exciting and fine to them seemed to me just
                  stupid, and the miserable lot of little Willie boys who were always hovering about
                  us with their everlasting cigarets and silly short coats and foolish hats
                  disgusted me. The artists for whom I had worked in Boston were
                  <emph>men</emph>.</p>
               <p>Thus I decided to leave Lil. Anyway there was some talk of their all going out
                  with a road show and they expected to give up the flat soon.</p>
               <p>I had had a furious letter from Reggie the day after I arrived in New York, and we
                  had been quarreling by letter ever since. He accused me of deliberately leaving
                  Boston when I knew he was coming and he said: <q>It was a low-down trick and I
                     shall never forgive you</q>. In his anger he also wrote that perhaps the reason
                  for my leaving was that I knew he would find out the kind of life I had been
                  living there. He wrote:</p>
               <p><q>I met a few of your ‘friends’—a low down bartender and a store clerk</q> (poor
                  Billy Boyd’s room-mate, I suppose), <q>and let me compliment you on your choice of
                     associates. Your tastes certainly have not changed</q>.</p>
               <p>I did not answer that first letter; but he wrote me another, apologizing, and at
                  the same time insinuating things. To that second letter I did reply, hotly. And so
                  it went on between us.</p>
               <p>After leaving Lil’s, I found a little room on Fifteenth Street near Eighth Avenue.
                  It was cheap and fairly comfortable and I soon got settled down there. Then I
                  started out to look up some artists whose addresses had been sent to me by the
                  Boston men. Right away I secured several engagements. I found, moreover, that my
                  room was only a couple of blocks from what the artists called <q>Paresis Row</q>
                  on Fourteenth Street. Here many artists occupied the upper floors, which had been
                  turned into studios in these buildings, once the pretentious homes of mighty rich
                  people. On the lower floors various businesses were carried on.</p>
               <p>I was sent to a man who had a studio in Paresis Row. He was a friend of Mr. Sands,
                  and although he did not use models, he said he would try to help me get work. He
                  explained to me his own kind of painting as <q>old-master pot-boilers</q>.
                  Sometimes, he explained to me, he got a rush of orders for <q>old masters</q>, and
                  then a number of fellows would get busy working on them. He declared humorously
                  that he ran an <q>old masters</q> factory.</p>
               <p>As I looked at his work, I felt sure I could do that kind of painting, and I
                  said:</p>
               <p><q>Mr. Menna, would you let me try it, too?</q> and I told him about the work I
                  had done for the Count and about my father, and he exclaimed:</p>
               <p><q>Fine! you’re just the girl I’m looking for</q>.</p>
               <p>So I went to work for Mr. Menna, part of the day. I would paint in the most of the
                  start, and he would finish up the pictures. <q>Clean them up and draw them
                     together</q>, as he would say. We were able this way to turn out many <q>old
                     masters</q>. We worked for the dealers and frame-makers, who in order to sell a
                  frame put these hastily-made oil paintings in and sent them out as <q>genuine
                     imported paintings</q>.</p>
               <p>Mr. Menna and I became fast friends. He treated me just like any other
                     <q>fellow</q> and divided the profits with a generous hand. Besides helping him
                  to paint, I acted as his agent. I would go down-town and see the dealers, take
                  orders and sometimes sell to them the ones we made on speculation.</p>
               <p>I found out many things in the <q>picture business</q> that I had never dreamed
                  possible, but that is another story.</p>
               <p>At times, too, I posed for Mr. Menna. He would take spells when he became
                  disgusted with his <q>pot-boilers</q>, and would say he intended to do some
                     <q>real stuff</q>. These spells never lasted long, for he would run short of
                  money, and would start with renewed energy on the <q>painting business</q>, as he
                  disgustedly called it. He discovered that I was very good at copying, but he
                  discouraged my doing it. He said:</p>
               <p><q>There’s mighty little money in copying, unless you pass it off as the original,
                     and although the dealers do it, and I paint for them, I’m dashed if I’ll
                     actually sell them myself as original. It’s not honest</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But, Mr. Menna</q>, I argued, <q>isn’t it also dishonest for us to do the
                     copying and let the dealers pass it off and sell it as original?</q></p>
               <p><q>Maybe it is</q>, he admitted, <q>but we don’t see them selling them to the
                     ‘suckers’ who buy them, and confound it, we certainly don’t get the price, so
                     what the dickens—</q></p>
               <p>Mr. Menna had raised his voice, and immediately we heard a big noise from the
                  studio across the hall.</p>
               <p><q>It’s that bunch of fellows at Fisher’s</q>, said Menna grinning. <q>They get
                     together and all chip in to pay for a model. Say, how would you like to pose
                     for them? Most of them are illustrators, and they’d want you in street clothes
                     and things like that. You could make an extra dollar or two. Go up and see
                     Bonnat. He generally engages the model for the other fellows. You’ve met Fisher
                     here. He’s that little red-haired chap. Talk to him about it, too. Now I’m off
                     for lunch and a glass of beer. Come along if you like, Ascough</q>.</p>
               <p>I went along with Menna. We ate in a little restaurant at the back of a saloon
                  corner of Eighth Avenue and Fourteenth Street. The lunch cost twenty-five cents
                  each. Menna did not eat much, but he drank four glasses of beer, and he got cross
                  with me when I at first refused to drink. So to please him I had a glass. He
                  said:</p>
               <p><q>Now you’re a good sport, and the beer will make you fat</q>.</p>
               <p><q>It’s not my ambition to be fat</q>, I laughed back.</p>
               <p><q>Get out</q>, he answered. <q>Did you hear that German fellow who was in the
                     studio the other day, when Miss Fleming</q> (Miss Fleming was Mr. Menna’s girl)
                     <q>asked him how he liked the American ladies? He said with a sad shake of his
                     head: ‘They are too t’in. The German wimmens have the perportions,’ and he
                     curved his hands in front of his chest as he said, ‘It is one treat to look at
                     her.’</q> Menna laughed heartily. <q>You’re a German yourself</q>, I said.</p>
               <p><q>Not on your life, I’m not</q>, denied Menna vigorously. <q>I’m American. Even
                     my folks were born here. I studied in Muenchen. That’s the place!</q> He shook
                  his head and siged.</p>
               <p>We got up to go, and Menna told me to hustle down town and see a dealer.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>Jacobs, the dealer, was busy showing some customers the paintings. The place was
                  softly lighted, and the paintings were shown off to the best advantage by the
                  arrangement of the lights. There were a number of Orential rugs about, helping to
                  make the place look luxurious, and adding somehow to the value of the paintings.
                  Jacobs nodded to me, and I sad down to wait.</p>
               <p>As soon as the customers were gone, he called me over and, pointing to a couple
                  of paintings in elaborate gold frames, he said:</p>
               <p><q>Those people who were in are furnishing their new home on Riverside Drive, and
                     I expect to sell them quite a few paintings. They got stuck on those two, and I
                     made a price on them. Now, those two are already sold, and the party who bought
                     them wants them delivered next week. You have to come in time, Miss Ascough, as
                     I must have these copied right away. Can you get me an artist to do it?</q></p>
               <p>I looked at those paintings. They were about sixteen by twenty-eight inches, and
                  the subject of one was a Breton field of wheat and harvesters, and the other was
                  of a priest or cardinal in his red robes sitting reading in a richly furnished
                  library. Menna, I knew, could not possibly do the work that week, for he was
                  working out an order for another dealer, and I had come to Jacobs to collect for
                  old work. I thought, however, that I could easily do it myself. So I said to
                  Jacobs:</p>
               <p><q>I know a woman artist who’ll do it for you</q>.</p>
               <p><q>A woman! No, sir! I would not have a woman do any work for me</q>, said the
                  dealer. <q>I have had all I want to do with women artists. They do much inferior
                     work to the men, take twice as long, and get swelled heads about it. They whine
                     if they don’t make a fortune out of their daubs. No—nothing doing with the
                     women. Now I like Menna’s work. Take them to him. Don’t let anyone see them,
                     and I’ll very likely be able to have them copied again, as I think they’ll
                     prove good sellers</q>.</p>
               <p><q>All right</q>, I said, but I made up my mind to do them myself, and I went out
                  with those precious <q>imported</q> paintings under my arm.</p>
               <p>Mr. Menna was showing some of his <q>pot-boilers</q> to a man when I returned.
                  They were paintings of little ragged boys. The man did not care for them. As he
                  was going out he said:</p>
               <p><q>I’ll come again some day when you have other pictures. Those little-boy
                     pictures are nice, and I like them, but they are not <emph>parlor</emph>
                     pictures, and my customers want parlor pictures</q>.</p>
               <p>Menna was puffing angrily on a big cigar. I laughed as the man went out, but Menna
                  could not see the humor of it. He got angrier and angrier. He threw down his
                  palette and brush and let out a big anathema.</p>
               <p><q>I hope you feel better now, Mr. Menna</q>, I ventured.</p>
               <p><q>That’s the kind of thing one is up against</q>, he roared, <q>and that fool,
                     Bonnat, was in here a while ago and he told me he had refused to make some
                     alteration in the portrait he is painting of the wife of that rich Dr. Craig,
                     because the ass said he would not prostitute his art, and a lot of stuff like
                     that. It makes me sick. He also lost a good chance to had to make illustrations
                     for a magazine—best-paying magazine in New York. he had his own ideas about the
                     illustrations, and as they were paying for the job they told him how they
                     wanted them smooth cut. Bonnat belongs to the new school of painting, and he
                     actually refused to please them—missed a chance almost any artist would be glad
                     to get. He’s a chump</q>.</p>
               <p>I was getting excited. In a dim way I was beginning to see something else in Art
                  that <q>the picture business</q>. It reminded me of how poor Wallace, Ellen’s
                  husband, used to talk of literature. I secretly admired this Bonnat for his stand
                  and his courage.</p>
               <p><q>Is Mr. Bonnat a Frenchman?</q> I asked.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
