<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Marion7">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Marion (Part 6)</title>
            <title type="sub">The Story of an Artist’s Model</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from Hathi Trust: <ref
                  target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000542803"
                  >https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000542803</ref>.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:79"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovelSerial"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:NewYork"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="readyForProof">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-25" status="readyForProof">Status changed to readyForProof. Everything should be encoded.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-25" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-15" status="empty">Removed primary source people from
               <gi>respStmt</gi> using XSLT.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-04">Added facs and readied for
            proof.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl79 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Marion6" prev="doc:Marion6" next="doc:Marion8">
      <pb n="155"/>
      <body>
         <head>Marion: The Story of an Artist’s Model</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">The Author of Me</name></byline>
            <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:HH1">Henry Hutt</name></byline>
         </opener>
         <div type="content">
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <div>
               <div type="paratext">
                  <p>Synopsis: Here we have the story, told at first-hand, of Marion Ascough, sister
                     of <q>Me</q>, a girl destined to eventually travel far—Montreal, Boston, New
                     York, and even to <q>Bohemia</q>, accumulating experiences by the way—clinging
                     to the highest ideals, as artist, model, friend of painters, and finally the
                     wife of an artist. She was born in the queer little French-Canadian villageof
                     Hochelaga, a suburb of Montreal; her father was an English painter, her mother
                     a Frenchwoman. Here Monsieur de St. Vidal proposed to her in the snow, and she
                     ran home. Then she had a bent for the stage and made a hit in amateur
                     theatricals. Along came Mr. Reggie Bertie—call him Bartie, so English you
                     know—remittance-man, who is studying for the bar. It was a case of love at
                     first sight between handsome Reggie and pretty Marion Ascough. He took her to
                     the ice carnival and when he should have been watching the procession he was
                     looking down at her. Later, he refuses to take her into a flashy all-night
                     restaurant because Marion is <q>too nice and too sweet</q>. Very soon they
                      become engaged, but while Bertie is an ardent wooer he does not want the
                     marriage to take place; he’s afraid of <q>the governor</q> of England, so poor
                     Marion is in for a long wait, during which she must be self-supporting at
                     painting and other art work, besides helping at home. Then she hires a little
                     studio of her own—Reggie pays for it—in Montreal; Reggie still procrastinates.
                     At last she tells him that he has no right to monopolize her time and her
                     society unless he intends to fulfill his promise,—particularly as he objects to
                     her seeing any other men. She goes to Boston and there becomes a full-fledged
                     model, with some weird experiences.</p>
               </div>
               <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>Later in the evening Jimmy Boyd came. He was very quiet and queer for Jimmy, and
                  he sat down on my window-sill, and held his head in his hands. When I told him
                  about Benevenuto, he looked up and said: <q>The cheeky little rat. I’ll throw him
                     out the window</q>. After a moment he said: <q>Come over here, Marion, I want
                     to tell you something</q>. So I went and sat down on the opposite side of the
                  window-seat.</p>
               <p><q>Say, Marion, there’s a big row going on up at my house about you. Sis kicked up
                     an awful fuss, and they’re all on to my coming to see you. She declares I
                     insulted her friend, because I took you home instead, and mother is mad, too.
                     They make me sick. Mother asked me where your folks lived, and what you were
                     living alone like this for. I told them that you were a hard little worker, and
                     then they wanted to know what you did, and I told them you were a model, and
                     that I was proud of it, but gosh! You ought to have heard those women! When I
                     told them that, they almost burst themselves mouthing about it. I turned on ‘em
                     and told them not one of them could be a model. They didn’t have the looks. But
                     the long and short of it is that mother has telegraphed for dad, and she says
                     she won’t give me another cent unless I promise to give you up. As I needed a
                     ten-spot, I said I would, but you better believe I’m not going to do
                  it</q>.</p>
               <p>I stood up and put my hand on Jimmy’s shoulder. Somehow I felt older than Jimmy,
                  though we were about of an age. He seemed such a boy, so wayward and reckless, and
                  there was so much that was lovable about him, despite his <q>toughness</q>. <q>Jimmy
                  dear</q>, I said, <q>I guess your mother’s right. You’d better give me up. It’ll only
                     make trouble for you if you keep on coming to see me</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Tell you what I’ll do</q>, said Jimmy. <q>I’ll quit college, and get a job of
                     some sort. Then I’ll be independent, and I’ll come to see you all I please, and
                     I’m going to marry you whether they want me to or not</q>.</p>
               <p>I thought of Jimmy’s happy-go-lucky nature and his love for drink, and I
                  determined the poor fellow should not lose the help of his family if I could avoid
                  it. We took a little walk around the block, I urging Jimmy all the time to please
                  do what his people wished, and I even told him that while I was fond of him I did
                  not love him. He said savagely that he guessed I had left my heart in Montreal,
                  and then he pulled his cap down over his eyes, and didn’t say anything for a long
                  time. We just tramped around, and then Jimmy said suddenly:</p>
               <p><q>Say, Marion, why doesn’t he come on here and marry you if he loves you? Is it
                     lack of money prevents him?</q></p>
               <p>I said: <q><emph>I</emph> don’t want to marry <emph>him</emph>. That’s the reason
                     why</q>. how I wished that was the truth!</p>
               <p><q>Well, say, girlie, let’s you and I get married on the q. t. Then I’ll go West,
                     as they’re talking of shunting me out there, and as soon as I’ve made good you
                     can join me. How’s that for a scheme?</q></p>
               <p><q>It sounds pretty nice, Jimmy, but I’d rather do teh marrying <emph>after</emph>
                     you’ve made good</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, it’ll be dead easy</q>, declared Jimmy. <q>I’ve an uncle out there with a
                     ranch as big as a whole county. It’ll just be like dropping into a soft snap,
                     don’t you see?</q></p>
               <p>I sighed. <q>Making good isn’t merely dropping into soft snaps, Jimmy</q>, I said
                  sadly.</p>
               <p>Jimmy suddenly whistled under his breath, and I saw him looking at a couple of
                  women who were coming toward us. He raised his cap as they passed, but although
                  the younger one returned his bow, the older one <pb n="156"/> stared at him
                  indignantly, and then she gave me a very severe and condemning glance. All of a
                  sudden I knew who that woman was. I recognized her by her hat. She was Jimmy’s
                  mother!</p>
               <p>The following day I had a letter from her. She said I was ruining her son’s
                  future, and if I did not give him up he would soon be without even a home. She
                  said that he was in serious trouble with his father and that the latter intended
                  to send him out West, and that she hoped I would do nothing to prevent her son
                  from going. Finally she said that if her son were to marry a model the family
                  would never forgive him and that such a disgrace would break all of their hearts,
                  besides ruining him.</p>
               <p>I did not answer her letter.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <div>
               <p>I sat for a very long time thinking about my life. What was there wrong about
                  being a model that society should have cast the bar sinister upon it? Surely there
                  was no disgrace in one who had beauty having the beauty transferred to canvas. I
                  had long ago ceased to despise the profession myself. The more I posed the more I
                  felt even a sort of pride in my work, though I still felt one was <q>beyond the
                     pale</q> when one posed undraped.</p>
               <p>Miss Darling knocked at my door, and brought in a telegram. I thought at first it
                  was from Reggie—that he was at last coming, as he had been threatening in all of
                  his letters to do, and my hands were trembling when I broke the flap. But it was
                  from poor Jimmy—Jimmy <emph>en route</emph> to Colorado, entreating me to write to
                  him and assuring me that he would never forget his <q>own little Marion</q>, and
                  that he would <q>make good</q> and I’d be proud of him yet. I sat down to write an
                  impulsive answer to the boy, and then my eye fell upon his mother’s letter. No! I
                  would not ruin her son’s life. Jimmy should have his opportunity, but I said to
                  myself with a choking sob:</p>
               <p><q>And if Jimmy ever does make good, they’ll have <emph>me</emph> to thank for it,
                     even if I am an artist’s model!</q></p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
            <div>
               <p>June had come and I was filling the last of my engagements. There was not a single
                  other date in my calendar for the week, and it was Wednesday. I had filled only
                  two engagements the week before.</p>
               <p>I was posing for three women. The work was easy, as they were amateurs and liked
                  to meet together and use the same model, and paint and have a social time. I was
                  posing in a gipsy costume, and they talked to me occasionally in a patronizing
                  way, as if I were a little poodle. One of them asked me if I wouldn’t like to
                  paint. I knew I could paint better than she could, but pretended to simper and
                  said:</p>
               <p><q>Oh yes, indeed</q>.</p>
               <p>One of the women, with kind-looking eyes, smiled at me and asked if I managed to
                  make a living, and then the one who asked me if I would like to paint said:</p>
               <p><q>Oh, by the way, we won’t need you again, as we are all off the country</q>.</p>
               <p>She added that they might be able to use me the next season, and I wondered dully
                  to myself whether I would need them when the new season came. A feeling of despair
                  was stealing over me—despair and recklessness.</p>
               <p>The woman with the kind eyes who asked if I made a living I have since recognized
                  as the wife of one of our Presidents. I wish I had known her better.</p>
               <p>Though I had so little work to do, nevertheless I was feeling languid and tired in
                  these days, and when I reached my room that afternoon I threw myself bodily down
                  upon my bed. I felt that I did not want to get up even to go out for my dinner. I
                  was lying there with my face buried in the pillow when Miss Darling called up the
                  stairs:</p>
               <p><q>There’s a gentleman to see you, Miss Marion</q>.</p>
               <p>I jumped up and ran out into the hall. A short, dark man was mounting the stairs.
                  I thought at first he was a picture-dealer I had once seen at Mr. Sands’s studio.
                     <q>Miss Ascough?</q> he asked. I bowed, and led him to my room.</p>
               <p>He said he had obtained my name from Mr. Sands and that he wanted to engage me as
                  a model for some decorative work he was doing.</p>
               <p>He had seen me several times about the studio <pb n="157"/> buildings, and had
                  decided I was the type for this particular work. As he said the work would last
                  all summer I was delighted, and I thanked him fervently. Then he said:</p>
               <p><q>Suppose we have a little supper together somewhere</q>.</p>
               <p>I was awfully sorry, but I had promised to help Miss St. Denis fix a waist she was
                  making. So I told this man I could not disappoint my friend. He said: <q>As you
                     please, then</q>, and was going, when I asked for his address. He stopped and
                  thought a moment, and then wrote something on a slip of paper and handed it to me.
                  He told me to come to work at ten the following morning, and, bowing, went. The
                  address was in Brookline, and as it was some distance out I planned to start early
                  to be sure to be there in time. After the man had gone all my lassitude vanished.
                  I felt like dancing and screaming, I was so relieved and happy. Here I was engaged
                  for six hours’ work a day for all of the summer. I rushed to tell the good news to
                  Rose St. Denis. She said</p>
               <p><q>I tink it is too good to be true. It looks too easy. I tink he will want the
                     model to pose undrape’, ha! You will not do so yet?</q> as I shook my head, she
                  said with a nod: <q>You will make very poor living if you don’t do so, <foreign
                        xml:lang="fr">mon enfant</foreign>. The artists have not enough to keep one
                     model in work in ze costume, and then there is so many doing the same ting.
                     Every girl—even ze frien’ of ze artist, she will pose in costume. The model
                     cannot get enough work to keep her, unless she is a friend of some one or maybe
                     she is <foreign xml:lang="fr">complaisante</foreign> to ze artist—yes. Only
                     when she pose in ze schoolsse—e, she get ze work, so long as she have ze
                        <foreign xml:lang="fr">belle</foreign> figure. It is so. Now, which a model
                     prefer? Post that way, starve—or perhaps be <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                        >maîtresse</foreign> to somebody—which is same ting</q>, she added to the
                  shrug, <q>as <foreign xml:lang="fr">aller au diable!</foreign></q></p>
               <p><q>Which would you prefer?</q> I asked her.</p>
               <p><q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Mais oui!</foreign> Some funny question you ask</q>,
                  said the French girl. <q>It is because I love my Alfred</q> (Alfred was her
                  fiancé) <q>that I pose un-drape; for ze other mens; for bi-cause I pose <foreign
                        xml:lang="fr">comme ça</foreign> I can keep myself good and pure for only
                     him. It would be more easy if I were not good. Do you not see, <foreign
                        xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>? I pose and stand on my poor feet for three,
                     four and sometime nine <foreign xml:lang="fr">heures</foreign> a day—nine
                        <foreign xml:lang="fr">heures</foreign> when I do night work, and for zat I
                     get me fifty cent one <foreign xml:lang="fr">heure</foreign>. Ze bad girl she
                     get for very liddle time more moneys than I; but me? I keep me my reespect.
                     Yes—it is so. Soon my Alfred he will come from France and we will marry. Then,
                        <foreign xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>, ah! we will be happy like
                     cheeldren</q>.</p>
               <p>Someow, when she was speaking, this model who posed so freely looked like the
                  Virgin Mary, and I put my arms around her and kissed her. She said:</p>
               <p><q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Pauvre enfant</foreign>! Me? I know eet is hard for you!
                     I have ze pity for you; but dat will not put ze food in ze stomach! <foreign
                        xml:lang="fr">Non</foreign>! Soon you will see!</q></p>
               <p>I awoke happily next morning. I was going to start at good steady work. Now, I
                  thought, I would pay back Lu Frazer all I owed her, and I’d send mama money every
                  week, and Reggie’s letters should go unanswered. He had written me saying that he
                  was coming soon to Boston to bring me home, unless I returned myself. And I
                  thought I would buy myself a new hat and trim it with violets.</p>
               <p>I went into the basement dining-room to get my breakfast, and the landlady put a
                  bill at my plate. It was for three dollars for meals I had had. I told her I would
                  pay her in a few days.</p>
               <p>I had exactly five cents in my pocketbook when I started for Brookline, but I
                  intended to ask the artist to pay me a little in advance. They often did that, and
                  as I was to have steady work I was sure he would not object. I could not help
                  thinking of a remark of my father’s, that something always <q>turned up</q> and I
                  felt that my something had come in the nick of time.</p>
               <p>It was three-quarters of an hour’s ride to the street in Brookline he had marked
                  on the slip. I got off at last, and walked down the street looking at the numbers.
                  I went up and down twice, but I could find no such address. I went to nearly every
                  second house on the street, but no one knew the name I inquired for, and the clerk
                  at the drug-store where I also inquired said there was no such man in the
                  vicinity. Again and again I looked, and then a sick sense of apprehension stole
                  over me, and I began to realize that I was the victim of some cruel hoax.</p>
               <p>What in heaven’s name was I to do? I had no carfare even, and it was too far to
                     walk. I wandered about distractedly, and then I finally resolved to get on the
                     car, and when the conductor should ask for my fare, I would pretend I had lost
                     it. Then I thought, <q>even if he puts me off, I will be that much nearer home,
                     and I will try another car</q>.</p>
               <p>So I got on a car, but I suffered the shame of a cheat when the conductor finally
                  came up to see me, and I almost cried as I pretended to search through my empty
                  pocketbook. Then I heard the conductor’s voice. He was a big, red-faced Irishman,
                  with freckles on his face, and he grinned down at me:</p>
               <p><q>Aw, dat’s all right, kid!</q> he said, and taking a nickel from his own pocket,
                  he rang up my fare. When I was getting off, I said:</p>
               <p><q>Thank you! I’ll send it back to you, if you give me your name</q>.</p>
               <p>He laughed. <q>Dat’s all right, kid</q>, he said, and then leaning to my ear he
                  added: <q>Say, do you want another nickel, sissy?</q></p>
               <p>I borrowed the dollar from Evans, the student who was a friend of Jimmy’s. I
                  bought the morning papers, and scanned the <pb n="190"/> columns of
                  advertisements. I was determined to look for some other kind of work, yet I
                  realized that I was a <q>Jack-of-all-trades and master of none</q>, unless it be
                  that of the model. I found one advertisement that seemed to be pretty good:</p>
               <div>
                  <q>
                     <l>’Wanted: A smart, pretty young lady for light, easy work. Experience not
                        necessary.’</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p>I started down to answer that advertisement at once. The address was in the old
                     building on Washington Street and there seemed to be all kinds of businesses
                     carried on there. On the door of the place I was to apply was some name, and
                     the word <q>Massage</q>. I had a dim idea what massage meant. I associated it
                     in some way in my mind with illness. I pushed the bel, and the door was quickly
                     opened. A stout, matronly woman stood smiling at me.</p>
                  <p><q>Come in, dearie</q>, she said, as though she were expecting me.</p>
                  <p>I found myself in a room that looked like the average boarding-house parlor. It
                     was stuffy and dark. The woman sat herself down in a rocker, and she was still
                     smiling at me</p>
                  <p><q>I came in answer to the advertisement. What do you require me to do?</q></p>
                  <p>Patting me on the arm, she said:</p>
                  <p><q>Easy, easy, dear. Don’t talk so loud. It is massage work, dearie</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>I can’t do it</q>, I said, <q>but I might be able to learn</q>.</p>
                  <p>She kept on grinning and winking at me, and I don’t know why, I suddenly felt
                     terribly afraid of her. I said tremulously:</p>
                  <p><q>Will I have to wear aprons?</q></p>
                  <p>She got out of the rocking-chair and poked me in the side.</p>
                  <p><q>Now, dearie, if you are really a good girl, I don’t want you to come at all.
                        I’d rather have a young married lady. I had a sweet little married lady
                        before, but her husband got on to us and—</q></p>
                  <p>I had begun to back toward the door, and with my hand behind me I found the
                     knob. I ran out into the hall, and down those stairs as quickly as I could get.
                     Oh, how good the air did seem when I found myself at last on the street.</p>
                  <p>When I got to my room, I found a note on my table. It was from Miss Darling,
                     and was as follows:</p>
                  <div>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                        <l>’Dear Miss Marion:</l>
                        <l>‘I don’t want to press you, but could you let me have the rent? I would
                           not bother you, but I have expenses to meet, and even if you could let me
                           have a part if you cannot let me have it all, I would be obliged.</l>
                        <l>                                        ‘C. DARLING.’</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <p>There was a letter, too, from Reggie. I opened it with my hatpin and oh! I
                        think if I could have pierced Reggie instead of that letter, just then, I
                        would have liked to do it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div>
                    
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                        <l>’Darling Girlie:</l>
                        <l>‘I met your sister Ada on the street, and she tells me you are doing
                           awfully well in Boston with your painting. I hope, however, you are not
                           forgetting your old sweetheart. Ada tells me you are coming home this
                           summer. Darling, I shall try to arrange to go to Boston, and we will come
                           back to Montreal together. I am longing for the moment when I can hold my
                           own little Marion in my arms again, and tell her how much I love her.</l>
                        <l>‘Everything’s going my way lately, and you’ll see me a Q. C. before many
                           years have passed.         Your own,         REGGIE.’</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
             
                  </div>
                  <div>
                     <p>Somehow I blamed Reggie for all I had suffered, and as I stared out at the
                        darkening night descending upon the streets, I muttered to myself:</p>
                     <p><q>Now it is your fault that I am compelled to pose in the way I
                        hate!</q></p>
                     <p>It had come to this at last. There was nothing else for me to do, and Miss
                        Darling must be paid. She had been so good to me.</p>
                     <p>As I went out, I knocked at Miss Darling’s door. She put out her head and I
                        said:</p>
                     <p><q>Dear Miss Darling, it’s all right. I’m going to pay you in a few
                        days</q>.</p>
                     <p>She said: <q>All right, dear, I know you will keep your word</q>.</p>
                     <p>Yes, I would keep my word! I was on my way to Miss St. Denis to tell her
                        what I was now willing to do. I found her in, but she was not feeling well.
                        She had been posing at a class the previous night, she told me, and also
                        three hours in the afternoon.</p>
                     <p><q>See my feet</q>, she said, thrusting them out, <q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                              >Mon Dieu</foreign>! they are so sick. All ze night I have put me some
                           vaseline and it is no good. They are grown beeg again</q>.</p>
                     <p>Her poor bare feet were badly swollen. I begged her to let me bathe them in
                        hot water. Mama always bathed our feet in hot water when we had colds or our
                        feet hurt.</p>
                     <p><q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Bien</foreign>!</q> she said. <q>Do so, <foreign
                              xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>, if you wish, but it is so hard to get
                           hot water in zese boarding-house. Ah! very soon I will have dat little
                           house of all my own, and den, you will see, <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                              >enfant</foreign>, what it is to be <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                              >tres</foreign> happy!</q></p>
                     <p>She sighed, as if she were inexpressibly tired, and lay there with her dark
                        eyes closed, and her beautiful soft dark hair all about her lovely face, and
                        I thought to myself again: <q>She looks like a picture of the Virgin</q>,
                        and I felt sure that although she was just a poor model, she was pure and
                        good like the Virgin. She opened her eyes after a moment and smiled at me,
                         and she said:</p>
                     <p><q>When I have my little house, <foreign xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>,
                           then always ze water will be hot. There will be ze gas on ze stove, and
                           it will give beeg flame, and me? I will have plenty for heat my water.
                           Here, me, I stand and hold for eternity ze little pot to make some water
                           hot on ze little gas-jet. It is all stuff up full!</q> and she closed her
                        eyes again.</p>
                     <p><q>Wait a minute</q>, I said: <q>I’ll go and ask your landlady for hot
                           water</q>.</p>
                     <p>I found my way down to the basement, and very politely I said to the
                        landlady:</p>
                     <p><q>Miss St. Denis has a very bad foot. Will you be so kind as to let me have
                           a pitcher of hot water?</q> She snapped back at me: <q>I guess I give my
                           roomers more hot water than they pay for. Does she think she is paying
                           hotel prices?</q></p>
                     <p>In a begrudging manner she poured me out half a pitcher full from the kettle
                        on the range. Thanking her, I started to carry it up, but a loose piece of
                        carpet at the foot of the stairs caught my feet. I slipped and all my
                        precious hot water was lost. The landlady had picked up the pitcher, which
                        fortunately was not broken, and when she saw me crying she began to laugh
                        uproariously, and seemed to be suddenly good-natured, for she refilled the
                        pitcher.  </p>
                     <p>I bathed Rose St. Denis’ fet, and made her comfortable, and she thanked me
                        sweetly and seemed to be grateful. I sat beside her bed for awhile,
                        smoothing her forehead. She was not really ill, just tired out. Presently I
                        said:</p>
                     <p><q>Now the time has come for me to pose as you do, or as you say, starve or
                           go to the devil</q>.</p>
                     <p>She opened her eyes with a start, and she said: <q><foreign xml:lang="fr"
                              >Merci!</foreign> But you do say things so suddenly, <foreign
                              xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>. You are funniest girl. You say some
                           time ze ting I would not dare to speak, or if I did I would have to
                           confess to my priest/ and den you are afraid to do some tings zat is
                           nutting wrong, and you mek one beeg fuss for dat</q>.</p>
                     <p>She sat up in the bed, with her knees drawn up, and regarded me with the
                        benignant, tolerant glance of a young wise mother. She could understand my
                        viewpoint in regard to posign undraped, but she believed I was simply wrong
                        and my stubborness in teh matter had always puzzled her. She did not waste
                        any time on pitying me now. On the contrary she urged me to do the work.</p>
                     <p><q>Now you have come</q>, she said, <q>at a very good time for me. I am not
                           able to go to dat night class, and I have made engagement for all dis
                           week. You will take my place, <foreign xml:lang="fr">voilá!</foreign>
                           first you will tell him you have pose bi-fore, dat you have ze <foreign
                              xml:lang="fr">belle</foreign> figure—yes, you must say dat. If
                              <foreign xml:lang="fr">necessaire</foreign> you will show him</q>. As
                        I shook my head, she nodded at me and said: <q>Yes, yes, you will do dat, if
                              <foreign xml:lang="fr">necessaire</foreign>. Mebbe he will not
                           require. You must not tell him that you have not pose bi-fore in dat
                           altogedder. He will tink you you ‘greenhorn,’ as you say, den. Tell him
                           you are one professional model, and dat you are fren’ to Rose St. Denis,
                           and dat you will tek my place. I tink he will be satisfy. You look liddle
                           bit like me. Like you are liddle sister to me. Yes, dat is so</q>.</p>
                     <p>She patted my hand, smiling comfortingly at me. Then she went on with her
                        instructions. <pb n="191"/> It was only Tuesday, and I would have five
                        evenings’ work and earn seven dollars and fifty cents. I would probably also
                        be engaged for the following week, and for the day classes of the summer
                        school. A model as much in demand as was Rose St. Denis sometimes got steady
                        work for nine hours a day. Three in the morning, three in the afternoon, and
                        three at night. She assured me that I would be soon in demand as she was,
                        perhaps more so, since I was younger than she.</p>
                     <p>The seven dollars and fifty cents I felt would be a godsend at this time. I
                        would be able to pay the boarding-house woman. She had stopped me on the
                        street only that morning and said:</p>
                     <p><q>If you don’t pay me, Miss Ascough, you will have no good luck</q>.</p>
                     <p>Then there was Miss Darling. I must keep my word to her. Moreover, Ada had
                        been writing me urgent letters insisting that I should send something home,
                        for Wallace, Ellen’s husband, was very ill, and of course, no help was
                        coming from them now. As I looked at Miss St. Denis, I thought to myself
                        that after all it could not be such dreadful work or she would not do it.
                        She seemed to me the embodiment of sweetness and refinement, and I could not
                        imagine her doing anything that was gross or impure. I remembered the time I
                        saw her posign before the class, I had not felt revolted in the way I had
                        that time when Lil Markey had skipped about the Count’s studio. Teh amateur
                        model, Lil, had been brazen. The professional one was seriously doing her
                        honest duty.</p>
                     <p>Miss St. Denis was lying back among her pillows with her white hands—the
                        hands Mr. Sands had said were the most beautiful in America—clasped at the
                        back of her head. She was watching me, and I suppose she knew I was turning
                        the matter over in my mind, and I do not doubt but what she realized
                        somewhat of the struggle that was wrestling in my heart. After a while she
                        said:</p>
                     <p><q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Enfant</foreign>, pass me dat bottle on ze
                           dresser</q>. I did so, and she pressed it back into my hand.</p>
                     <p><q>See</q>, she said, <q>it is ze spirit that will give you courage. I will
                           give it back to you. The moment that you deesrobe, tek one good long
                           drink, and den, <foreign xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>, you will forget
                           dat you have no clothes on, and dat <foreign xml:lang="fr">tout le
                              monde</foreign>, he is look’ at you. It will be joost like little
                           dream. Dat firs’ time time, also, I am feel ze shame—but soon it pass—and
                           it is all forget. Courage, <foreign xml:lang="fr"
                        >enfant</foreign>!</q></p>
                     <p><q>No, no, Miss St. Denis. Oh, I can’t do it! I can’t!</q> I began to cry,
                        and then she seized hold of my hands fiercely and pulled herself up in
                        bed.</p>
                     <p><q>Ah, you are ze coward—renegade. You will not help me</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>Oh, Miss St. Denis, I might just as well go to the dogs completely. Oh, I
                           can never, never do it! Oh, if my people found out, I would be eternally
                           disgraced and REggie—he would never speak to me again. Then, surely, he
                           would <emph>never</emph>, never marry me, and there would go my last
                           hope</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>You are <foreign xml:lang="fr">hysterique</foreign></q>, she said gently.
                           <q>I tink you have not eat so much—yes?</q></p>
                     <p>I told her I had had my dinner, which was not true, and after awhile, when I
                        had dried my tears and was feeling more composed, she resumed, just as if I
                        had not said I would not do it.</p>
                     <p><q>It is not so hard as you tink. You will yourself undress behind the
                           screen that they provide, wiz one chair for you to rest upon. Nobody look
                           at you when you take off dose clothes. Dere also is one wrapper for you
                           to slip on, and when the monitor he call: ‘Pose!’ you will walk wiz ze
                           wrapper on to ze model stage, and only den you will drop ze wrapper.
                           Listen, <foreign xml:lang="fr">enfant</foreign>! If you have take dat
                           dreenk I am tell you ‘bout, you will forget dat it is you. You will say
                           to yourself: ‘Dis is not me. Dis is jus’ some statue—so many lines for
                           dem to draw and paint, to make some peecture. Ze real me, I am lef’ in my
                           clothes dat are behind dat screen. <foreign xml:lang="fr">Voilá,
                              enfant?</foreign></q></p>
                     <p>I was beginning to get her spirit, and I said:</p>
                     <p><q>Why, yes, I do see. It’s like acting, isn’t it? I <emph>will</emph>
                           forget it is I</q>. I tried to laugh and added: <q>I will say: ‘O Lord,
                           have mercy on me, this is none of me!’ That’s an old Mother Goose rime,
                           Miss St. Denis</q>. Because I could see she had fatigued herself on my
                        account, and it was my turn now to comfort and reassure her. I put my arms
                        around her and hugged and kissed her. Tears came into her eyes, and she
                        murmured:</p>
                     <p><q><foreign xml:lang="fr">Pauvre petite enfant</foreign>. You look like
                              <foreign xml:lang="fr">ma petite soeur</foreign>!</q></p>
                     <p>I went directly from Miss St. Denis to the school. I asked to speak to Mr.
                        Lawton, the master, and he came out to the little ante-room and looked at me
                        sharply while I spoke. I knew my voice was trembling, but I said as bravely
                        as I could:</p>
                     <p><q>I have come from Miss St. Denis. She is ill; but I will take her
                           place</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>You have posed before?</q> he asked, his eyes seeming to scan me from
                        head to foot.</p>
                     <p><q>I am a professional model</q>, I answered.</p>
                     <p><q>Hm! Yes, I think you will do</q>.</p>
                     <p>I was behind the screen. I had disrobed and I was wrapped up in the wrapper
                        which I found to be very dirty. I wondered how many girls had wrapped it
                        about them.</p>
                     <p>I could hear the students entering the class-room. I peeped out, and already
                        there were about fifteen men of various ages, and there were about thirty
                        easels and stools. More students were coming in. There was one elderly man
                        with white hair, and two young boys, one only about thirteen. He looked like
                        my little brother Randle. I began to redress. I could never go out before
                        those men and the little boy! Merciful heavens, no!</p>
                     <p>Then I remembered my promise to Miss Darling. I thought of my father, who
                        was ill, of Ada’s insistent demands. Of my empty pocketbook, and then I
                        thought of the bottle that Miss St. Denis had given me. I undressed again. I
                        heard a voice saying:</p>
                     <p><q>Where’s the model?</q></p>
                     <p>Then the voice of the monitor called sharply: <q>Pose! Pose, please!</q></p>
                     <p>I drained that bottle dry. I stepped from behind that screen. I walked up to
                        the platform, and I flung off the wrapper. I heard a voice saying, as from a
                        distance:</p>
                     <p><q>Take some poses</q>, said the voice. I obeyed.</p>
                     <p>I stood there immovable. I felt like a slave who was to be burned as an
                        offering by some savages. It seemed as if I were turning to stone. There was
                        a vague ringing in my ears, and then, as Miss St. Denis had foretold, I
                        forgot that class. I did not see it. I was back in Hochelaga, and Charles
                        was dragging me along on a sleigh. The snow was thick on our clothes. Mama
                        was brushing it off. Charles was pulling off his mittens and I heard him say
                        to mama: <q>Mama, I’ll never take that Marion with me again. When we pass
                           the Catholic store with all those images of saints she makes me so
                           ashamed. She will stop to look at the naked Jesuses. I couldn’t make her
                           come away</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>Rest! Rest!</q></p>
                     <p>The voice of the monitor! I awoke. Mechanically I pulled the wrapper over
                        me. Somebody said:</p>
                     <p><q>The model is crying</q>.</p>
                     <p>I walked behind the screen. My head still swam, and I still saw dim visions
                        of my home. I seemed to have been there only five seconds—it was five
                        minutes—when again came the command:</p>
                     <p><q>Pose!</q></p>
                     <p>Now I felt angry. I stepped on that stage, and once more I threw off the
                        wrapper. Somebody said:</p>
                     <p><q>Put the left foot further back</q>.</p>
                     <p>My anger was mounting. The dream had all vanished and I was conscious only
                        of a vague furry. I know not why, but I hated all of those men. They were
                        looking at me, I thought, like cruel tormentors. I wanted to hurt them all,
                        as they were hurting me. Their intent looks, some with their eyes narrowed
                        to see better, others measuring me with a plumb string, seemed to be mocking
                        at my pain. Somebody said:</p>
                     <p><q>She looks cross</q>.</p>
                     <p>I seized the wrapper, and savagely I wrapped it about me. I ran for the
                        screen, shouting:</p>
                     <p><q>Oh, you fiends! You beasts! You shall not torment me any more!</q></p>
                     <p>Again I was behind the screen, and with mad, hurrying, fumbling hands I was
                        dressing myself. Threw as the scraping of boots and stools, and several
                        whistles from the class-room, after the first silence.</p>
                     <p>Then the master came behind the screen:</p>
                     <p><q>What does this mean, Miss Ascough?</q> he demanded. I was crying
                        bitterly. <q>Did anyone say or do anything to offend you? If so, I’ll put
                           him out of the class</q>.</p>
                     <p>I said: <q>Oh, yes, they are not gentlemen. They all stared at me and talked
                           about me</q>.</p>
                     <p>There was an indignant murmur of denials from the students. Mr. Lawton put
                        his head over the screen and I saw him wink to the students. Then then he
                        turned to me an said in a coaxing voice:</p>
                     <p><q>Now, now, be a good girl. We want you to finish the pose. If anybody
                           dares to be rude to you, you just tell me about it, and I’ll put you
                           out</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>No, no</q>, I said. <q>I’ll not do it again</q>.</p>
                     <pb n="192"/>
                     <p><q>Now, please, won’t you for my sake? It’s instruction night, and I am here
                           to give criticisms. Please resume the pose, like a good girl. Yours is
                           just the kind of figure we need. Come, now</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>No—no—I am through forever!</q></p>
                     <p>I was all dressed. Oh, my beloved clothes! The teacher was now thoroughly
                        provoked.</p>
                     <p><q>What do you mean by taking an engagement and wasting our time like
                           this?</q></p>
                     <p><q>I don’t know</q>, I answered, and I ran out of the room.</p>
                     <p>I owe an apology to that class.</p>
                  </div>
                  <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
                  <div>
                     <p>We were all sitting around the big hall stove, and papa said:</p>
                     <p><q>Put your feet on the fender, Marion, and get them warm</q>.</p>
                     <p>Mama was feeding me with a big spoon of ice-cream, which Reggie tried to
                        snatch away, and then he would throw red-hot coals in my face.
                        Screaming:</p>
                     <p><q>Reggie! Reggie! Stop! Stop!</q> I woke up.</p>
                     <p>A man was sitting by the bed in my little room, and he was holding my wrist.
                        I recognized him as a young doctor who had attended Miss Darling was she had
                        the grippe. He had straight blond hair and a gentle expression. Standing by
                        him was the girl who had taken the big room on the first floor a few days
                        before. I had noticed her, because she dressed so well and had so many
                        visitors. Now she was holding some ice on my head, and I heard her say to
                        the doctor that she had just put a hot-water bag on my feet. She was not
                        beautiful like Rose St. Denis, for she was short and stout, but she had a
                        large, generous mouth, and when she laughed she showed the most beautiful
                        teeth, and she laughed a great deal, so that one could not help liking her.
                           <q>How is she, doctor?</q> she asked, and he replied:</p>
                     <p><q>She ought to stay in bed some time. Her temperature is a hundred and
                           five. I’m afraid of her being left alone. Has she no one to take are of
                           her?</q></p>
                     <p><q>No, no</q>, I moaned weakly. <q>I have nobody. They are all dead</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>Who was that ‘Reggie’ you were calling for?</q> asked the girl, and I
                        said:</p>
                     <p><q>He’s dead, too</q>.</p>
                     <p>My eyes felt very heavy, and I could not keep them open, I heard their
                        voices as if in a dream.</p>
                     <p><q>My! but she gave us a scare</q>, said the girl: <q>We were just going out
                           of the front door last night, to get a bite of supper over at the Plaza,
                           and as we opened the door she was coming up the front steps, and she
                           suddenly threw out her hands as if she were drowning, and would have
                           fallen down the stairs, had not Al caught her</q>.</p>
                     <p>There was a long silence, and then I heard her voice again—she was stroking
                        my hand.</p>
                     <p><q>Poor girl! What a <emph>pretty</emph> little thing she is</q>.</p>
                     <p>I put my cheek against her hand. Somehow it seemed to me natural that she
                        should be good and kind to me. Then the doctor said: <q>I will have her
                           moved to the hospital. This room is too small, and she will need the best
                           of care</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>Why can’t I care for her?</q> asked the girl suddenly. <q>I can do it!
                           Oh, you don’t believe me, eh?</q> I heard them both laugh, and she
                        said:</p>
                     <p><q>It’ll be lots of fun. To begin with, you carry her down to my
                        room</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>Do yo ureally mean that?</q> I heard him ask, and her reply: <q>Why, of
                           course I do</q>.</p>
                     <p>I did not say a word. I did not care much what they did to me, and there
                        seemed ot me no reason why I should not be cared for by this stranger. I
                        suppose it was my weakness, but perhaps it was the consciousness that I
                        would have done the same in her place. Poor girls instinctively depend upon
                        each other in crises like these. And then this girl—Lois Barrett was her
                        name—had a jolly way that made even the most trying service seem like a game
                        to her. She acted as if she really enoyed doing something that another
                        person would have considered a trial. She kept saying: <q>It’ll be all kinds
                           of fun. Come along, doctor, let’s get her right down now. Can you do
                           it?</q></p>
                     <p><q>Easily</q>, declared the doctor.</p>
                     <p><q>Ah!</q> said she, <q>It’s fine to have big broad shoulder. I wish I were
                           a man—like you</q>. She added the last two words softly, and the doctor
                        chuckled. They wrapped the blankets around me, and the doctor lifted me up
                        in his arms and carried me down the stairs. I was so weak that even this
                        slight movement affected me, and I fainted.</p>
                     <p>I must have been even worse than the doctor thought, for I did not know
                        anything more for a long time; then, one day, I opened my heavy eyes, to
                        find myself in a big sunny room, and dreamily I watched Lois Barret hovering
                        over me like a ministering angel. Then, in the evening, I have a dim
                        remembrance of the doctor standing in the window, and putting his arm around
                        Lois, and it seemed to me he was kissing her. I called:</p>
                     <p><q>Oh, I am not asleep. I can see you</q>.</p>
                     <p>They both laughed, and Lois came  over and gave me something to swallow, and
                        as I dropped asleep they seemed to grow into one person.</p>
                     <p><q>Lois, are you in love with Doctor Squires?</q></p>
                     <p>She burst out laughing.</p>
                     <p><q>I’m in love with everybody and everything. Here, lie back there</q>.</p>
                     <p>I was to sit up in bed that afternoon, and the following day in a chair. I
                        had been ill two weeks.</p>
                     <p><q>Now</q>, said Lois, <q>I have to go down-town on some business, and I’ll
                           be gone two hours. If you want anything just knock on the wall like
                           this</q>, giving me a brush, <q>and Billy Boyd in the next room will come
                           in, and if it’s something he can’t do himself he’ll call Miss
                        Darling</q>.</p>
                     <p>She kissed me, and looking fresh and radiant she went on out.</p>
                     <p>Billy Boyd roomed with a friend in the next room to Lois. his room-mate was
                        a clerk in a department-store, and Billy was a cable operator. He worked at
                        night. Reggie would have called these boys <q>common Yankees</q>. I knew how
                        much better and in every way superior they were to REggie, whose grandfather
                        was a duke or something like that. These boys would run errands for Lois if
                        she knocked on their wall for help, and when I was most sick and helpless
                        Billy even came in and helped Lois when it was necessary to lift me. Lois
                        treated them as if they were girls, and they treated her as if she was a
                        boy. It was a revelation to me, as in Canada and in Europe the simple
                        friendship between men and women is not known as in the United States.</p>
                     <p>Then there was big Tim O’Leary. He was a bartender in a nearby hotel. He had
                        a room in the basement of what had once been the dining-room. He used to
                        knock at the door and ask in his big voice, which sounded for all the world
                        like a foghorn:</p>
                     <p><q>How’s the little Canadian girl?</q></p>
                     <p>He would send over the waiters form the hotel where he worked with all sorts
                        of stuff that a sick person was not allowed to eat, big platters of lobster
                        salads, chicken salads, club sandwiches, wine and beer. Lois told him I
                        could only have a little broth, and then Tim sent over a big pitcher of rich
                        soup. Lois tasted it, and then fed a spoonful of it to the doctor, and they
                        both laughed. Then she went to the boys’ room and knocked, and they were
                        glad to get the good stuff.</p>
                     <p>Tim was a man of immense stature, and he would tell us all kinds of stories
                        of his experiences when he was a coalheaver in New York and the fights he
                        got into, and the times he was arrested, and always got off with a light
                        fine. Dr. Squires called him a <q>rough diamond</q>, and, much-sought-after
                        society man as Doctor Squires was, he liked to go off with Tim O’Leary, and
                        have a drink and <q>chin</q> together. I did admire the doctor for that, and
                        I remembered how Reggie had been ashamed and angry with me because I had
                        spoken to the conductor on the train.</p>
                     <p>There was a knock at the door, and when I called <q>Come in</q>, the door
                        was cautiously and softly opened, and Tim thrust in an inquiring face.</p>
                     <p><q>How’s yoursilf?</q> he inquired, in a big whisper.</p>
                     <p><q>I’m very well, thank you, Mr. O’Leary</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>And Miss Barrett, how’s hersilf?</q></p>
                     <p><q>Oh, she’s well too. She had to go out for a couple of hours</q>.</p>
                     <p><q>Sure, then, I’ll stay and take care of you mesilf</q>, said Tim. <q>i’m
                           dead tired. Standing behind a bar is hard on the feet; so if you don’t
                           mind, I’ll be taking off my shoes and stretch mesilf out for a
                        rest</q>.</p>
                     <p>I assured him I would be very glad to have him do it. The big man worked
                        sometimes ten and twelve hours at a stretch, and it was so quiet and
                        peaceful in this room I felt the rest would do him good, just as it was
                        doing me.</p>
                     <p>So Tim stretched himself out on the couch, with his shoes off, and fell
                        asleep.</p>
                  </div>
                  <milestone unit="sectionBreak"/>
                  <div>
                     <p>(New York is the Mecca of many an artist, and thence  Marion flits from
                        Boston, with better luck, as related in the October issue of Hearst’s.)</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
