<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Me4">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Me: A Book of Remembrance (Part 4)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from Hathi Trust</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:85"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovelSerial"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:NewYork"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-07-31" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-15" status="empty">Removed primary source people from
               <gi>respStmt</gi> using XSLT.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-08-02">Changed title.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-03">Added note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-05">Added facs and readied for
            proof.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl85 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Me4" prev="doc:Me3" next="doc:Me5">
      <pb n="408"/>
      <body>
         
            <head>Me: A Book of Remembrance</head>
            <opener>
               <byline>(Begun in the April Number)</byline>
               <byline><emph>This instalment includes themes of grooming as well as depictions of
                     sexual assault, sexual harrassment, and intimate partner
                  violence.</emph></byline>
            </opener>
         <div type="content">


            <head>XXI</head>
            <p>Fred was to leave for New York on the first of November, and that was only a week
               off. The firm had decided to retain me, after all, in the Chicago offices, but I was
               determined I would not remain there, and planned to go to New York as soon as
               possible, when Fred would immediately engage me. He said he’d <q>fire</q> any girl he
               had then for me.</p>
            <p>I had been saving from week to week for my fare and a set of furs. My suit, though
               only two months old, had already begun to show wear, and it was thin, as Mr. Hamilton
               had said. The girls at the yards were already wearing furs, but furs were beyond my
               purse for months to come. Lolly had beautiful furs, black, silky lynx, that some one
               had given her the previous Christmas.</p>
            <p>It was now five weeks since I had seen Mr. Hamilton, and two since Tom had gone. I
               had had a few letters from Tom. They were not exactly love-letters. Tom’s letters
               were more, as it were—well, written for publication. I don’t know why they seemed
               like that to me. I suppose he could not help writing for effect, for although he said
               tender things, and very brilliantly, too, somehow they did not ring true to me.</p>
            <p>I did not think very seriously of our engagement, though I liked my ring, and showed
               it to all the girls at the yards. My stories came back with unflattering regularity
               from the magazines to which I sent them. Lolly, however, gave two of my stories to
               her paper, and I was to be paid space rates (four dollars a column, I think it was)
               on publication. I was a long time waiting for publication.</p>
            <p>Dissatisfied, unhappy, and restless, as I now really was, I did not even feel like
               writing at night. I now no longer ran up-stairs to my room, with an eager, wishful
               heart, hoping that <emph>he</emph> might be there. Alas! I felt sure he had abandoned me
               forever. He had even ceased, I told myself, to be interested in me.</p>
            <p>Then one night he came. I had had a hard day at the yards. Not hard in the sense of
               work; but Fred was to leave the following day, and a Mr. Hopkins was to take his
               place. We had spent the day going over all the matters of our department, and it’s
               impossible for me to say how utterly wretched I felt at the thought of working under
               another <q>boss</q> than Fred.</p>
            <p>So I came home doleful enough, went out and ate my solitary dinner in a nearby
               restaurant, and then returned to the house.</p>
            <p>He called, <q>Hello, little girl!</q> while I was opening the door.</p>
            <p>I stood speechlessly staring at him for a moment, so glad was I to see him. It seemed
               an incredible and a joyous thing to me that he was really there, and that he appeared
               exactly the same—tall, with his odd, tired face and musing eyes.</p>
            <p><q>Well, aren’t you glad to see me?</q> he asked, smiling, and holding out his hand.
               I seized it and clung to it with both of mine, and I wouldn’t let it go. That made
               him laugh again, and then he said:</p>
            <p><q>Well, what has my wonderful girl been doing?</q></p>
            <p>That was nearly always his first question to me.</p>
            <pb n="409"/>
            <p><q>I wrote to you four times</q>, I said, <q>and you never answered me once</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I’m not much of a hand at letter-writing</q>, he said.</p>
            <p><q>I thought that you’d forgotten me</q>, I told him, <q>and that you were never
                  going to come and see me again</q>.</p>
            <p>He put his hand under my chin, raised my face, and looked at it searchingly.</p>
            <p><q>Would it have mattered so much, then?</q> he asked gently.</p>
            <p><q>You know very well I’m in love with you</q>, I told him desperately, and he said,
               as always:</p>
            <p><q>Nonsense!</q> though I know he liked to hear me say that.</p>
            <p>Then he wanted to inspect me, and he held me off at arm’s-length, and turned me
               around, too. I think it was my suit he was looking at, though he had seen it before.
               Then he made me sit down, and said we were going to have a <q>long talk</q>. Of
               course I had to tell him everything that had happened to me since I had seen him. I
               omitted all mention of Tom!</p>
            <p>I told him about Fred’s wanting me to join him in New York, and he remarked:</p>
            <p><q>Fred can jump up. You’re not going</q></p>
            <p>I did not argue that with him. Now I didn’t want to go. I was quite happy and
               contented now that he was here. I didn’t care whether he returned my love or not. I
               was contented as long as he was with me. That was much.</p>
            <p>He always made me tell him every little detail of my life, and when I said I found it
               difficult to write, because of so many men coming to see Lolly,—I didn’t mention that
               they were coming to see me, too!—he said:</p>
            <p><q>You ‘re going to move out of this place right away. We’ll look about for rooms
                  to-morrow</q>.</p>
            <p>So then I knew he was not going back that night, and I was so glad that I knelt down
               beside him and cuddled up against his knee. I wished that he would put his arm about
               me, but all he did was to push back the loose hair that slipped over my cheek, and
               after that he kept his hand on my head.</p>
            <p>He was much pleased with my description of the rooms at Mrs. Kingston’s. He said we’d
               go there the next day and have a look at them. He said I was to stay home from work
               the next day, but I protested that I couldn’t do that—Fred’s last day! Unless I did
               just what he told me, it exasperated him always, and he now said:</p>
            <p><q>Then go away from me. I don’t want anything to do with a girl who won’t do even a
                  trifling thing to please me</q>.</p>
            <p>I said that it wasn’t trifling, and that I might lose my position; for the new man
               was to take charge to-morrow, and I ought to be there.</p>
            <p><q>Damn the new man!</q> he said.</p>
            <p>He was a singularly unreasonable man, and he could sulk and scowl for all the world
               like a great boy. I told him so, and he unwillingly laughed, and said I was beyond
               him. To win him back to good humor, I got out some of my new stories, and, sitting on
               the floor at his feet, read them to him. I read two stories. When I was through, he
               got up and walked up and down, pulling at his lower lip in that way he had.</p>
            <p><q>Well</q>, I challenged, <q>can I write?</q></p>
            <p>He said:</p>
            <p><q>I’m afraid you can</q>. Then he took my manuscripts from me, and put them into his
               pocket.</p>
            <p>It was late now, for it had taken me some time to read my stories, but he did not
               show any signs of going. He was sitting in our one big chair, smoking, with his legs
               stretched out in front of him, and although his eyes were half closed, he was
               watching me constantly. I began to yawn, because I was becoming sleepy. He said he
               supposed I wanted him to get out. I said no, I didn’t; but my landlady probably did.
               She didn’t mind our having men callers as long as they went before midnight. It was
               nearly that now. He said:</p>
            <p><q>Damn that landlady!</q> just as he had said, <q>Damn the new man!</q> Then he
               added, <q>You’re not going to be run by every one, you know</q>.</p>
            <p>I said mischievously:</p>
            <pb n="410"/>
            <p><q>Just by you?</q></p>
            <p><q>Just by me</q>, he replied.</p>
            <p><q>But when you stay away so very, very long—</q></p>
            <p>It irritated him for me to refer to that. He said that there were certain matters I
               wouldn’t understand that had kept him in Richmond, and that he had come as soon as he
               could. He added that he was involved in some lawsuit, and that he was being watched,
               and had to be <q>careful</q>. I couldn’t see why he should be watched because of a
               lawsuit, and I asked:</p>
            <p><q>Would you be arrested?</q></p>
            <p>He threw back his head and laughed, and said I was a <q>queer little thing</q>, and
               then, after a while, he said very seriously:</p>
            <p><q>It’s just as well, anyway. We mustn’t get the habit of <emph>needing</emph> each other too
                  much</q>.</p>
            <p>I asked slyly:</p>
            <p><q>Do you think it possible <emph>you</emph> could ever need <emph>me?</emph></q> To which he replied
               very soberly:</p>
            <p><q>I need you more than you would believe</q>.</p>
            <p>Mr. Hamilton never made a remark like that, which revealed any sentiment for me,
               without seeming to regret it a moment later. Now he got up abruptly and asked me
               which room I slept in. I said generally in the inner one, because Lolly came in late
               from assignments and engagements.</p>
            <p><q>I want to see your room</q>, he said, <q>and I want to see what clothes you
                  need</q>.</p>
            <p>He knew much about women’s clothes. I felt ashamed to have him poking about among my
               poor things like that, and I grew very red; but he took no notice of me, and jotted
               down some things in his note-book. He said I would need this, that, and other
               things.</p>
            <p>I said weakly:</p>
            <p><q>You needn’t think I’m going to let you get me clothes. Honestly, I won’t wear them
                  if you do</q>.</p>
            <p>He tilted up my chin, and spoke down into my face:</p>
            <p><q>Now, Nora, listen to me. Either you are going to live and dress as I want you
                  ​​to, or I am positively not coming to see you again. Do you understand?</q></p>
            <p><q>Well, I can get my own clothes</q>, I said stubbornly.</p>
            <p><q>Not the kind I want you to have, not the kind I am going to get you</q>.</p>
            <p>He still had his hand under my chin, and I looked straight into his eyes.</p>
            <p><q>If you tell me just once</q>, I said, <q>that you care for me, I’ll—I’ll—take the
                  clothes then</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I’ll say anything you want me to</q>, he said, <q>if you’ll do what I tell
               you</q>.</p>
            <p>I took him up at that.</p>
            <p><q>All right, then. Say, ‘I love you,’ and you can buy pearls for me, if you want
                  to</q>.</p>
            <p>He gave me a deep look that made me thrill, and I drew back from his hand. He said in
               a low voice:</p>
            <p><q>You can have the pearls, anyway</q>.</p>
            <p><q>But I’d rather have the words</q>, I stammered, now ashamed of myself, and
               confused under his look.</p>
            <p><q>Consider them said, then</q>, he said, and he laughed. I couldn’t bear him to
               laugh at me, and I said:</p>
            <p><q>You don’t mean it. I made you say it, and therefore it has no meaning. I wish it
                  were true</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Perhaps it is</q>, he said.</p>
            <p><q>Is it?</q> I demanded eagerly.</p>
            <p><q>Who knows?</q> said he.</p>
            <p>Lolly came in then. She did not seem at all pleased to see Mr. Hamilton there, and he
               left soon after. When he was gone, she told me I was a very silly girl to have taken
               him into my room. I told her I hadn’t; that he had just walked in. Lolly asked me,
               virtuously, whether I had ever seen <emph>her</emph> let a man go in there, and I confessed I
               had not. She wanted to know whether I had told Mr. Hamilton about Tom. Indeed, I had
               not! The thought of telling him frightened me, and I besought Lolly not to betray me.
               Also I took off Tom’s ring. I intended to send it back to him. It was impossible for
               me to be engaged to him now.</p>
            <p>Lolly said if she were I, she wouldn’t let Mr. Hamilton buy clothes for her. She said
               once he started to do that, he <pb n="411"/> would expect to pay for everything for me, and
               then, said Lolly, the first thing I knew, people would be saying that he was
                  <q>keeping</q> me. She said that I could take dinners, flowers, even jewels from a
               man,— though in <q>high society</q> girls couldn’t even do that; but working-girls
               were freer,—and I could go to the theater and to other places with him; but it was a
               fatal step when a man began to pay for a girl’s room and clothes. Lolly added that
               once she had let a man do that for her, and—She blew out a long whiff of smoke from
               her lips, saying, <q>Never again!</q> with her hand held solemnly up.</p>
            <p>So then I decided I couldn’t let him do it, and I felt very sorry that I had even
               weakened a little bit in my original resolve not to let him spend money on me. I went
               to sleep troubled about the matter.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXII</head>
            <p>As soon as I got up next day I called him on the telephone. It was so early that I
               probably woke him up, but I had to tell him what was on my mind.</p>
            <p><q>It’s Nora</q>, I said.</p>
            <p>He replied:</p>
            <p><q>Last time you telephoned to me you were in trouble; do you remember? Are you in
                  trouble now, little girl?</q></p>
            <p>I said I wasn’t, but I just wanted to say I <emph>couldn’t</emph> and wouldn’t let him buy
               clothes for me.</p>
            <p>I knew just as well as if I could see him how he was looking when I said that. He was
               used to having his own way, and that I dared to set my will against his always made
               him angry. After a moment he said:</p>
            <p><q>Will you do something else to please me, then?</q></p>
            <p><q>What?</q></p>
            <p><q>Don’t go to work to-day</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I’ve <emph>got</emph> to; truly I have</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You only think that. Call up O’Brien and ask to be excused. If you don’t, I will.
                  Now I’ll be up at your place about ten. I’ve something special to give you,
                  anyway</q>.</p>
            <p><q>What?</q></p>
            <p><q>I can’t tell you on the ‘phone</q>.</p>
            <p><q>We-ell</q>, I weakened; <q>all right, then</q>.</p>
            <p>I was rewarded beautifully for that.</p>
            <p><q>That’s <emph>my</emph> little girl!</q> he said.</p>
            <p>Then he rang off. I never would have.</p>
            <p>So I stayed home from work, the first time since I had been at the yards—and Fred’s
               last day! Mr. Hamilton came over about ten. Lolly was still sleeping, so I had to see
               him down-stairs in the parlor. As soon as I saw him, I held out my hands and
               said:</p>
            <p><q>Where’s the special thing?</q></p>
            <p>He laughed. I could make him laugh easily now, though I don’t believe any one else
               could. He pinched my chin and said:</p>
            <p><q>Get your hat on. We’re going shopping</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Now, Mr. Hamilton, honestly, I am not going to let you buy things for me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Did I say I was going to do that?</q> he demanded.</p>
            <p><q>Well, then, how can we shop?</q></p>
            <p><q>You have some money of your own, haven’t you?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes, but I was saving it for furs and to go to New York</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, you can get the furs later, and you’re not going to New York. The main thing
                  is you need a decent suit and a—er—heavy coat to wear to work, since you <emph>will</emph>
                  work; and you need gloves and—let me see your shoes—</q> [I showed them] <q>and
                  shoes, a hat and—</q></p>
            <p><q>I haven’t the money for all those things</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Yes, you have. I know a place where you can get all kinds of bargains. Ever hear
                  of bargain-shops?</q></p>
            <p>No, I had never heard of bargain-shops, though I had of bargain-sales, I told him.
               Well, it was the same thing, he said, except that this particular shop made a
               specialty of selling nothing but bargains.</p>
            <p>That, of course, tempted me, and I went up to my room and put on my coat and hat. I
               had thirty dollars, and I borrowed ten from Lolly. So I was not so badly off. He was
               right, I really needed new things, and I might as well let him choose them for
               me.</p>
            <p>That was a happy morning for me! <pb n="412"/> There have been few happier in my life. All
               girls love to <q>shop</q>, and there was a joy in trying on lovely things, even if I
               couldn’t afford them. It was a small shop to which he took me, but the things there
               were really beautiful and astonishingly cheap. He made them try many things on me,
               not only suits, but negligées and evening gowns.</p>
            <p>Then he chose a soft dark-blue velvet suit, trimmed with the loveliest gray fur at
               the neck and sleeves. I thought it must be very expensive, but the saleswoman said it
               was only fifteen dollars. I had never <emph>heard</emph> of such a bargain, especially as a
               hat, trimmed with the fur, and a muff also went with the suit. I made up my mind I’d
               bring Lolly here. I told the lady who owned the store that I would bring a friend.
               That made her laugh, but she stopped, because Mr. Hamilton frowned and looked very
               angry. He liked to laugh at me himself, but he didn’t want others to do so, and I
               liked him for that.</p>
            <p>Still, I felt uncomfortable. The woman’s laugh had been peculiar, and the saleswomen
               were watching me. I bought, too, a heavy navy-blue coat, with a little cape, and
               belted, just the thing for every day, and gloves and two pairs of shoes. She said
               that, as I’d bought so much, she ‘d give me silk stockings to go with the shoes.</p>
            <p>Of course I know now that I was a blind fool; but then I was only seventeen, and nine
               months before I had never been outside my home city, Quebec. For that matter, I
               hardly knew Quebec, so limited and confined is the life of the poor. I thought my
               forty dollars paid for all; I <emph>did</emph> think that!</p>
            <p>Mr. Hamilton was in a fine humor now, and he made me wear the velvet suit and the hat
               to go to luncheon with him, and where do you suppose he took me? Right to his own
               hotel. There he introduced me to a man named Townsend who was waiting for him. I
               didn’t at all like the way Mr. Townsend looked at me; but Mr. Hamilton did not seem
               to mind it, though he was quick to notice such things. When I had dined with him
               before, if any man stared at me, he used to lean over and say, without the slightest
               suggestion of a smile:</p>
            <p><q>Well, what shall I do to him? Turn the seltzer on him or push his face in?</q></p>
            <p>Mr. Townsend, however, was not trying to flirt with me, as, for instance, Mr.
               Chambers always was. He studied me curiously and, I thought, suspiciously. He talked
               in an undertone to Mr. Hamilton, and I am sure they were talking about me. I did hope
               that Mr. Townsend had not noticed any mistakes I made about the knives and forks.</p>
            <p>I was glad when luncheon was over. We entered a cab again, and Mr. Hamilton directed
               the driver to take us to Mrs. Kingston’s. I asked him who Mr. Townsend was. He said
               his lawyer, and began to talk about something else. He wanted to know if I wasn’t
               curious to know what that special thing was he had to give me. I had forgotten about
               it. Now, of course, I wanted to know.</p>
            <p><q>Well</q>, he said, <q>‘open your mouth and shut your eyes, and in your mouth
                  you’ll find a prize.’</q></p>
            <p>I thought he was going to give me a candy, so I shut my eyes and opened my mouth,
               just like a foolish child; and then he kissed me. It wasn’t like a kiss at all,
               because my mouth was open; but he seemed to think it very funny, and when I opened my
               eyes, he was sitting back in the carriage, with his arms folded, laughing hard. I
               think he thought that a good joke on me, because I dare say he knew I wanted him to
               kiss me. I didn’t think it a good joke at all, and I wouldn’t speak or look at him,
               and my face grew hot and red, and at last he said teasingly:</p>
            <p><q>I’ll have to keep you angry all the time, Nora. you look your prettiest
               then</q>.</p>
            <p>I said with dignity:</p>
            <p><q>You know very well I’m not even a little bit pretty, and I wish you wouldn’t make
                  fun of me, Mr. Hamilton</q>.</p>
            <p>He was still laughing, and he said:</p>
            <p><q>You know very well you are pretty, you little fraud, and my name is Roger</q>.</p>
            <p>I never called him Mr. Hamilton again.</p>
            <pb n="413"/>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXIII</head>
            <p>When I introduced Mr. Hamilton to Mrs. Kingston, she put on her glasses and examined
               him curiously, and he said, with a rather formal smile, not at all as he smiled at
               me:</p>
            <p><q>I’ve heard quite a lot about you from Miss Ascough, and am glad to meet
               you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I’ve known all about you for some time</q>, she said, chuckling. And then she
               added, <q>I don’t know what I expected to see, but you don’t quite measure up to
                  Nora’s extravagant ideal</q>.</p>
            <p><q>No, I suppose not</q>, he said, his eyes twinkling. <q>I doubt if any man could
                  that</q>.</p>
            <p>We were all laughing, and I said:</p>
            <p><q>Oh, well, I know he’s not much to look at; but I’m crazy about him, anyhow, and he
                  wants to see the rooms</q>.</p>
            <p>He didn’t think the little room nearly good enough for me, but he said that big suite
               of rooms in front was just the thing. That made me laugh. Did he suppose any
               stenographer could afford a luxurious suite of rooms like that? There was a long room
               that ran across the front of the house, with big bay-windows and a wonderful
               fireplace, and opening out from this room was a large bedroom, with a bathroom
               adjoining it. As one may see, they weren’t exactly the rooms a girl getting fifteen
               dollars a week could afford.</p>
            <p>I said:</p>
            <p><q>Tell him just how much you intend to ‘soak’ your prospective roomer for these
                  palatial chambers</q>.</p>
            <p>She started to say, <q>Twenty-five dollars a week</q>, which was what she had told me
               she expected to charge, when I saw him make a sign to her, and she hesitated. Then I
               knew he intended to get her to name a cheap price just for me, and pay the difference
               himself. But now I was too quick for him. He had actually deceived me about those
               clothes. I had not the remotest idea till months afterward that he had paid for them
               and for many other things I subsequently bought, or thought I bought; but Mrs.
               Kingston had already told me the price of that room. So I said</p>
            <p><q>It’s no use. I know the price</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Yes, but for a friend</q>, he replied, <q>I’m sure Mrs. Kingston would make—er—a
                  considerable reduction</q>.</p>
            <p>She said nothing. I don’t know how she felt. Of course she knew that I was in love
               with him, but, as she told me afterward, she couldn’t quite make out just what our
               relations were.</p>
            <p><q>That’s all very well</q>, I said, <q>but Mrs. Kingston has to get her
               rent</q>.</p>
            <p>Then he said:</p>
            <p><q>Well, but—er—I’m sure her practice is going to soar from now on. A great lawyer
                  like Mrs. Kingston need not rent rooms at all</q>. Still she said nothing; but I
               saw her watching us both. He went on to urge me to have these rooms, but of course
               the idea was absurd. It was really provoking for him to keep pressing me to have
               things I simply could not afford and did not greatly want. I said all this. Besides,
               I added, it would be foolish for me to make any change at this time. Things were
               uncertain with me at the yards, now that Fred was leaving, and I should have to speak
               to Lolly, anyhow.</p>
            <p>He argued that if I expected to write, I should have to move. No one could write in
               such disturbing circumstances. Of course that was true enough, and I said I’d talk it
               over that night with Lolly.</p>
            <p>He took out some money then, and wanted to pay Mrs. Kingston so much down on the
               rooms, when I exclaimed that even if I did leave Lolly, I didn’t mean to take these
               rooms, but the little one, if Mrs. Kingston was still willing to let me have it. She
               said she certainly was; that she badly wanted me to come. Both she and Mrs. Owens
               (the woman with her) needed a young person about the place to make them forget what
               old fogies they were, and that it would be like a real home to have me there, and
               we’d all be very happy.</p>
            <p>It ended like this: <emph>he</emph> took that suite of rooms. He said they’d be there for me
               to have at any time I wanted them. I told him it was just a waste of money, for <pb n="414"/>
               I simply would not let him pay for my room any more than I would let him pay for my
               clothes, and that was all there was to it.</p>
            <p>He smiled curiously at that, and asked Mrs. Kingston what she thought of my
               clothes.</p>
            <p>She said:</p>
            <p><q>I haven’t been able to take my eyes off them. Nora is <emph>wonderful!</emph> Does it seem
                  possible that clothes can make such a difference?</q></p>
            <p>She wanted to know where I got them. I told her, and how cheap they were. She was
               amazed at the price, and Mr. Hamilton went over to the window and looked out. How
               clearly this all comes back to me now!</p>
            <p>All the way back to my rooms he argued with me about the matter. He said if I had a
               pleasant place like that to live in, I’d soon be writing masterpieces (ah, he knew
               which way my desires ran!), and soon I’d not have to work in offices at all. To take
               rooms like those, he said, was really an investment. Business men all did things that
               way. It was part of the game. He wanted me to try it for a while, and at last I said
               in desperation:</p>
            <p><q>What’s the use of talking about it? I tell you, I haven’t got the money</q>.</p>
            <p>Then he said (I never knew a man who could so persist about a thing on which he had
               set his heart):</p>
            <p><q>Now, look here, Nora, I’ve got more money than is decent for any one person to
                  have, and I <emph>want</emph> to spend it on <emph>you</emph>. I want to give you things—comforts
                  and luxuries and all the pretty things a girl like you ought to have. If you could
                  see yourself now, you’d realize what a difference even clothes make. And so with
                  other things. I want to take hold of you and make you over. I never wanted to do
                  anything so much in my life before. Now you’re going to be a good girl, aren’t
                  you, and not deny me the pleasure—the real <emph>joy</emph> it gives me to do things for
                  you, dear little girl?</q></p>
            <p>By this time I was nearly crying, but I set my teeth together, and determined not to
               be won over to something I knew was not right.</p>
            <p><q>You told me once</q>, I said, <q>that all any one had ever wanted of you was your
                  money—your dirty money, you called it; and now, just because I won’t take it from
                  you, you get angry with me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, but, confound it! I didn’t mean you then</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, yes, you did, too; because you said I’d be sending for more money in a week,
                  and you said that I was made to have it, and men would give—</q></p>
            <p>He put a stop to my too vivid recollections.</p>
            <p><q>But, <emph>child</emph>, I had no <emph>idea</emph> then of the kind of girl you were</q>,—he lowered
                  his voice, and added tenderly, he was trying so hard to have his way!—<q>of the
                  exceptional, wonderful little girl you are</q>.</p>
            <p><q>But I wouldn’t be exceptional or wonderful</q>, I protested, <q>if I took your
                  money. I’d be common. No; I’m not going to let people say you <emph>keep</emph> me!</q></p>
            <p><q>Where did you hear that word?</q> he demanded roughly.</p>
            <p><q>From Lolly—and the other girls that I know. Oh, don’t you suppose I know what that
                  means?</q> I was looking straight at him now, and I saw his face turn red, but
               whether with anger or embarrassment, I do not know. He said in a sort of suppressed
               way:</p>
            <p><q>Don’t you know that men who keep women are their lovers?</q></p>
            <p>I nodded.</p>
            <p>He sat up stiffly now, and he gave me a cold, almost sneering, look that made me
               shiver. Then he said:</p>
            <p><q>Have I ever given you the slightest reason to suppose I wanted to be <emph>your</emph>
                  lover?</q></p>
            <p>I shriveled up not only at his words, but at his look, and I turned my face away, and
               looked out of the window of the cab without seeing anything. It was true he had never
               pretended to care for me. I was the one who had done all the caring, and now it
               seemed as if he were throwing this up to me as something of which to be ashamed. But
               though my face was burning, I felt no shame, only a sort of misery.</p>
            <p><q>Well?</q> he prompted me, for I had <pb n="415"/> not answered that last brutal query.
               Without looking at him, I said, in a shaking little voice, for I was heartbroken to
               think that he could use such a tone to me or look at me in that way:</p>
            <p><q>No, you haven’t. In fact, if you had, perhaps I might have done what you
                  wanted</q>.</p>
            <p>He came closer to me in the carriage when I said that, but I shrank away from him. I
               was nearer to disliking him then than at any time in my acquaintance with him.</p>
            <p><q>You mean</q>, he said, <q>that if I <emph>were</emph> your lover, you <emph>would</emph> be willing
                  to—live with me—like that? Is that what you mean, Nora?</q></p>
            <p><q>Oh, I don’t know what I mean</q>, I said. <q>I don’t pretend to be respectable and
                  good in the way the women of your class are. I suppose I have no morals. I’m only
                  a girl in love with a man; and if—if—he cared for me as I did for him, I’d be
                  willing to do anything in the world he wished me to. I’d be willing to die for
                  him. But if he didn’t—if he didn’t care for me, don’t you see, I couldn’t take
                  <emph>anything</emph> from him. I should feel degraded</q>.</p>
            <p>It was a tangled, passionate sort of reasoning. For a long time after that we rode
               along in silence, I looking out of the window, and he looking constantly at me. I
               could <emph>feel</emph> his eyes on me, and I did not dare to turn around. Then presently he
               said:</p>
            <p><q>I’m all kinds of a rotter, Nora, but I’m straight about you. You’re my wonderful
                  girl, the oasis in my life. I wouldn’t harm a hair of your precious little head.
                  If I were to tell you I loved you, I would precipitate a tragedy upon you that you
                  do not deserve. So I am not going to say any such thing to you</q>. He cleared his
               throat, and as I said nothing, he went on strongly, it seemed to me:</p>
            <p><q>Your friend Lolly is right about men, and I’m no different from other men as far
                  as women are concerned; but in your case I am. My desire to do things for you is
                  based on no selfish design. I assure you of that. I simply have an overwhelming
                  desire to take care of you, Nora, to help you</q>.</p>
            <p>I said this with as much composure as I could command:</p>
            <p><q>Thank you, I don’t need help. I’m not so badly off as you think. I make pretty
                  good money, and, anyway, I’m independent, and that’s a big thing</q>.</p>
            <p><q>But you have to work like a slave. I can’t bear to think of that, and as for being
                  independent, you won’t be any the less so if you let me do things for you. You may
                  go on with your life in your own way. I’ll never interfere or try to dictate to
                  you about anything</q>.</p>
            <p>Almost hysterically I cried out:</p>
            <p><q>Oh, please stop talking about this! Every time you come here you scold me about
                  something</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Why, Nora</q>, he said aggrievedly, <q>I have never asked you to do anything but
                  this. That’s the only thing I ever scolded you about</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Look how you acted that first night, when you saw me with Lolly and Mr. Chambers,
                  and then the night I was up with Fred. You wanted to <emph>beat</emph> me! I saw it in your
                  face. You could no more help dictating to and scolding me than you can help coming
                  to see me now</q>.</p>
            <p>The last sentence slipped out before I knew it, and he sat up sharply at that, and
               then laughed uncomfortably.</p>
            <p><q>I am a dog in the manger as far as you are concerned</q>, he said; <q>but I’ll
                  turn over a new leaf if you’ll let me do these things for you</q>.</p>
            <p>I smiled ruefully, for I was beginning to know him so well now, and I sighed. He
               asked me why I sighed, and then I asked him in turn just why he wanted to do these
               things for me. He paused a moment, and then said slowly, and not without considerable
               emotion:</p>
            <p><q>I’ve told you why before, Nora. I’m interested in you. You’re my find, my
                  discovery. I take a special pride in everything connected with you. You’re my ‘ewe
                  lamb,’ the one thing in life I take a real interest in, and I want to watch you,
                  and see you develop. I haven’t the slightest doubt of your eventual
               success</q>.</p>
            <pb n="416"/>
            <p><q>Hum! You look upon me as a sort of curiosity, don’t you?</q></p>
            <p><q>Nonsense! Don’t talk so foolishly!</q> But I knew that that was just how he did
               regard me, and it made me sick at heart. My beautiful day had clouded over. I
               supposed that nothing in the world would ever induce this man to admit any feeling
               for me but interest. Well, I wanted to love and to be loved, and it was a cold sort
               of substitute he was offering me—pretty clothes and fine rooms. No, I could earn all
               those things myself in time.</p>
            <p><q>Now, then</q>, he said, <q>you <emph>are</emph> going to be my darling, reasonable little
                  girl, aren’t you? After all, it isn’t so much I am asking of you. All I want you
                  to do is to leave your position and go to live with this Mrs. Kingston. She struck
                  me as being all right, and the rooms are exceedingly attractive, though we’ll
                  furnish them over ourselves. And then you are going to let me get you the proper
                  kind of clothes to wear. I’ll choose them myself for you, Nora. Then, since you
                  won’t go to school,—and, you see, I’m willing to let that go,—why, we can arrange
                  for you to take special lessons in languages and things like that, and there are
                  certain English courses you can take up at Northwestern. And I want you to study
                  music, too, piano and vocal—the violin, too, if you like. I’m specially fond of
                  music, and I think it would be a good thing for you to take it up. Then in the
                  spring you shall go abroad. I have to go myself about that time, and I want to see
                  your face when you see Europe, honey</q>. That was the only Southern endearing
               term he ever applied to me, and I had never heard it used before. <q>It will be a
                  revelation to you. And now the whole thing is settled, isn’t it?</q></p>
            <p>I hated, after all this, to have to refuse again, so I didn’t answer him, and he
               said, taking my hand, and leaning, oh, so coaxingly toward me:</p>
            <p><q>It’s all settled, isn’t it, dear?</q> I turned around, and shouted at him almost
               hysterically:</p>
            <p><q>No, it <emph>isn’t</emph>. And I wish you’d shut up about those things. You only make me
                  miserable</q>.</p>
            <p>If I had stung him, he could not have drawn back from me more sharply.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, <emph>very</emph> well</q>, he said, and threw himself back in his seat, his face
               looking like a thunder-cloud.</p>
            <p>He didn’t speak another word to me, and when the carriage stopped at my door, he got
               out, assisted me from the carriage, and then immediately got in again himself. I
               stood at the curb, my hand on the door of the carriage, and I said:</p>
            <p><q>Please don’t go like this!</q></p>
            <p><q>I’m sorry, but I am taking the 6:09 train</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Take a later train</q>.</p>
            <p><q>No, thank you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Please!</q></p>
            <p><q>Sorry. Good-by</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Please don’t be angry with me!</q></p>
            <p>He didn’t answer. It was terrible to have him go like that, and I asked him when he
               was coming back.</p>
            <p><q>I can’t say</q>, was his curt response. Then his angry glance fixed me, and he
               said slowly:</p>
            <p><q>You can let me know when you take those rooms I chose for you. I’ll come then—at
                  once</q>.</p>
            <p>And that is the cruel way he left me. I was heartbroken in a way, but I was angry,
               too. I went up to my room, and sat on the couch, and as I slowly pulled off my new
               gloves, I was not thinking kindly of Mr. R. A. Hamilton. No man had a right to impose
               his will in this way on a girl and to demand of her something that she could not do
               without losing her self-respect. I asked myself whether, because I loved this man, I
               was willing to make of myself a pusillanimous little door-mat, or if I had enough
               pride to stand by my own convictions?</p>
            <p>I had humbled myself enough to him; indeed, I had virtually offered myself to him.
               But he did not want me. He had made that clear enough. If, in the circumstances, I
               took from him the gifts he offered me, I would roll up a debt I could never wipe out.
               Now, although poor and working, I was a free woman. What I <pb n="417"/> had, I honestly
               earned. I was no doll or parasite who needed to be carried by others. No! To retain
               my belief in my own powers, I must prove that they actually existed. Only women
               without resources in themselves, without gifts or brains, were <q>kept</q> by men,
               either as mistresses or wives or from charity, as Hamilton wished to <q>keep</q> me.
               I had the youthful conviction that <emph>I</emph> was one of the exceptional souls of the
               world, and could carry myself. Was I, then, to be bought by the usual foolish things
               that attract the ordinary woman? I asked myself scornfully. No! Not even my love
               could alter my character.</p>
            <p>Now, there really was a fine streak in me, for I did want pretty things (what young
               girl does not?), I hated my work, and I loved this man, and wanted above all things
               on earth to please him.</p>
            <p>Lolly said, to jerk one’s mind from too much brooding over one man, one should think
               of another. I discovered another method of distraction. Pretty clothes are a balm
               even to a broken heart, and although I was clever, I was also eternally feminine. My
               things had arrived from the shop, and they were so lovely,—so much lovelier than I
               had thought,—that I was enchanted. Lolly came in while I was lifting the things from
               the boxes. I hadn’t taken off my suit, and she turned me around to look at me.</p>
            <p><q>Isn’t it stunning, Lolly?</q> I asked. <q>And, just think, it was only fifteen
                  dollars, suit, hat, muff, and all</q>.</p>
            <p>Lolly’s unbelieving glance swept me, then she threw her cigarette down, and said
               spitefully:</p>
            <p><q>For the love of Mike, Nora, cut it out! You’re a poor little liar!</q></p>
            <p><q>Liar! What do you mean, Lolly Hope?</q></p>
            <p>I was furious at the insult, capping all I had gone through.</p>
            <p><q>That suit you have on never cost one penny less than $150. The fur alone is easily
                  worth half of that. It’s silver fox, an inch of which is worth several dollars,
                  and that muff—</q> She laughed disgustedly. <q>What do you take me for, any how,
                  to try to spring that fifteen-dollar gag on me?</q></p>
            <p><q>It was marked down, I tell you, at a bargain sale</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, come off, Nora! Don’t try that on me. I know where you got those clothes. That
                  man Hamilton gave them to you. You didn’t follow my advice, I see</q>. She
               shrugged her shoulders. <q>Of course it’s your own affair, and I’m the last to blame
                  you or any other girl for a thing like that, but, for heaven’s sake, don’t think
                  it necessary to make up fairytales to me!</q></p>
            <p><q>Lolly, I swear to you that I paid for these myself</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Tell it to the marines!</q> said Lolly.</p>
            <p><q>Then see for yourself. Here are the price-tags, and here’s the bill</q>, I cried
               excitedly, and I thrust them upon her. Everything came to exactly forty dollars.
               Lolly looked the bill over carefully; then she put her cigarette in her mouth, and
               looked at me. All of a sudden she began to laugh. She threw her head back upon the
               sofa pillows and just laughed and laughed, while I became angrier and angrier with
               her. I waited till she was through, and then I said, very much injured:</p>
            <p><q>Now you can apologize to me, Lolly Hope</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You blessed infant</q>, she cried, <q>I’m in the dust at your feet. One thing’s
                  sure, and I guess friend Hamilton is wise to that: there’s no one like <emph>you</emph> in
                  this dull old world of ours!</q></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXIV</head>
            <p>My new <q>boss</q> at the yards’ was a sharp-nosed, sharp-eyed old-young man who
               seemed to think that his chief mission in life was to crack a sort of mental whip,
               like an overseer, over the heads of those under him, and keep us all hustling and
               rushing like frightened geese.</p>
            <p>I had been accustomed to answer the correspondence of the soap department myself,
               Fred merely noting a few words in pencil on each letter, giving the gist of what he
               wanted said; but Mr. Hopkins dictated everything, and as soon as I was <pb n="418"/> through
               one batch of correspondence, he would find something else for me to do. It seemed to
               give him a pain for my type- writer to be idle a moment. I think I was on his mind
               all the time except when he was busily thinking up work for Red Top.</p>
            <p>My position, therefore, had become a very hard one. I worked incessantly from nine
               till six. Fred had let me off at five-thirty and often at five; but Mr. Hopkins kept
               me till six. I think he’d have made it seven, but the bell rang at six, and the
               office was supposed to close after that.</p>
            <p>Many a time I’ve seen him glance regretfully at the clock or make an impatient
               movement with his shoulders at the clanging of the bell, at which moment I always
               banged close my type-writer desk, and swiftly departed.</p>
            <p>How I missed Fred! He had made life at the yards tolerable and even amusing for me
               with his jokes and confidences. And, then, there’s a pleasure in working for some one
               you know approves of you and likes you. Fred <emph>did</emph> like me. In a way, I don’t think
               any one ever liked me better than poor Fred did.</p>
            <p>It makes me sad to think that the best girl friend I ever had, Lolly, and the best
               man friend, Fred, are now both gone out of this world, where I may have still such a
               long road to travel.</p>
            <p>I hated my position now. I was nothing but an overworked machine. Moreover, the
               routine of the work was deadening. When I answered the letters myself, it gave a
               slight diversion; but now I simply took dictation and transcribed it, and when I was
               through with that, I copied pages of itemized stuff. My mind became just like a
               ticker that tapped off this or that curt and dry formula of business letter in which
               soap, soap, soap stood out big and slimy.</p>
            <p>I now neither wrote at night nor went out. I was too tired from the incessant labor
               at the type-writer, and when I got to sleep,—after two or three hours, in which I lay
               awake thinking of Mr. Hamilton and wondering whether I would ever see him again; I
               always wondered about that when he was away,—I declare I would hear the
               <emph>tap-tapping</emph> of that type-writer all night long in my sleep! Other type-writists
               have had the same experience. One ought to escape from one’s treadmill at least in
               sleep.</p>
            <p>But this is a world of miracles; doubt it who can.</p>
            <p>There came a glorious day late in the month of November—to be exact, it was November
               24. No, Mr. Hamilton did not come again. He was still waiting for my capitulation
               anent the rooms at Mrs. Kingston’s.</p>
            <p>This is what happened: I was type-writing, when Red Top came in with the mail. He
               threw down on my desk some personal letters that had come for me. Although Mr.
               Hopkins was at his desk, and I knew it was a criminal offense to stop any office work
               to attend to a personal matter, I reached over and picked up my letters. I heard my
                  <q>boss</q> cough significantly as I glanced through them. Two were from home, and
               I put them down, intending to read them at noon. One was from Fred. I put that down,
               too. And the other! Oh, that other! It was from—listen! It was from—the editor of the
               great New York magazine! I opened it with trembling fingers. The words jumped up at
               me and embraced me! My story was accepted, and a check for fifty dollars accompanied
               that brief, but blessed, note.</p>
            <p>Mr. Hopkins was clearing his throat so pronouncedly now that I turned deliberately
               about in my chair and grinned hard at him. He glared at me indignantly. Little idiot!
               He thought I was trying to flirt with him!</p>
            <p><q>Are you through, Miss Ascough?</q> he asked.</p>
            <p><q>No, Mr, Hopkins</q>, I responded blandly, <q>and I never will be now. I’ve just
                  come into some money, and I’m not going to work for you any more</q>.</p>
            <p><q>What! What!</q> he said in his sharp little voice.</p>
            <p>I repeated what I had said, and I stood up now, and began gathering my things
               together—my pocket-book, handkerchief, <pb n="419"/> odds and ends, in my desk, and the rose
               that Mr. Smith had given me that day.</p>
            <p>Mr. Hopkins had a nasal, excitable, squeaking sort of voice, like the querulous bark
               of a dog--a little dog.</p>
            <p><q>But, Miss Ascough, you don’t mean to say you are leaving now?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes, I do mean to say it</q>, I replied, smiling gloriously.</p>
            <p><q>But surely you’ll finish the letter on the machine?</q></p>
            <p><q>I surely will not</q>, said I. <q>I don’t <emph>have</emph> to work any more. Good-by</q>.
               And out I marched, or, rather, flew, without waiting to collect three days’ pay due
               me, and resigning a perfectly good fifteen-dollar-a-week job on the first money I
               ever received for a story!</p>
            <p>I did not walk on solid ground, I assure you. I flew on wings that carried me soaring
               above that Land of Odors, where I had worked for four and a half hard months, right
               up into the clouds, and every one knows the clouds are near to heaven.</p>
            <p>Mr. Hamilton? Oh, yes, I did remember some such person. Let me see. He was the man
               who thought I was incapable of taking care of myself, and who grandiloquently wanted
               to <q>make me over</q>; who once said I was <q>ignorant, uncivilized,
                  undisciplined</q>, who would never get anywhere unless I followed his lordly
               advice. How I laughed inwardly at the thought of the effect upon him of those
               astounding conquests that <emph>I</emph> was to make in the charming golden world that was
               smiling and beckoning to me now.</p>
            <p>As soon as I got to my room, I sat down and wrote a letter to him. I wanted him to
               know right away. In fact, I had a feeling that if he didn’t know, then all the
               pleasure of my triumph might go. This is what I said to him:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Roger:         <note type="authorial">[Yes, I called him Roger now.]</note></salute>
                  </opener>
                     <p>Read, mark, learn, and inwardly digest the inclosed thrilling, extraordinary, and
                        absorbing indorsement of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Your abused and forsaken</salute>
                        <signed>NORA.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
           
            <p>How had he the heart not to answer that letter of mine? I wondered.</p>
            <p>Girls love candies, pretty clothes, jewelry, gewgaws, and, as the old song has it,
                  <q>apples and spices and everything nicest</q>. They like boys and men and all
               such trifling things. Those are the things that make them giggle and thrill and weep
               and sometimes kill themselves; but I tell you there isn’t a thrill comparable with
               that electric and ecstatic shock that comes to a young girl writer when, after many
               rebuffs, her first story is accepted. Of course, alas! that [corr] thrill is brief,
               and soon one finds, with wonder, that the world is actually going on just the same,
               and, more wonder of wonders! there [corr] is still trouble and pain and tragedy and
               other ugly things crawling about upon the face of the earth. Ah me! They say the
               weird, seeking sound of a new soul is the most beautiful music on earth to the ears
               of a mother. I think a poet feels that way toward his first poem or story that comes
               to life. The ecstasy, the pain, and thrill of creating and bearing—are they not all
               here, too? I know that often one’s <q>child</q> is unworthy, uncouth, sometimes
               deformed, or, worse, a misshapen and appalling monster, a criminal product, as it
               were; but none the less he is one’s own, and one’s love will accompany him, even as a
               mother’s, to the gallows.</p>
            <p><q>It never rains but it pours</q>, says homely old adage. I thought this was the
               case with me now. Within a few days after I got that letter and check, lo and behold!
               I had three stories accepted by a certain Western magazine. I was sure now that I was
               not only going to be famous immediately, but fabulously wealthy.</p>
            <p>Three stories, say, at fifty dollars each, made a hundred and fifty; add the fifty
               from the great New York magazine, and you perceive I would possess two hundred
               dollars. Then do not forget that I had as well a little black suitcase full of other
               stories and poems, and an abortive effort at a novel, to say nothing of a score of
               articles about Jamaica. Besides, my head was teeming with extraordinary and unusual
               <pb n="420"/> plots and ideas,—at least they seemed extraordinary and original to me,—and I
               felt that all I had to do was to shut myself up somewhere alone, and out they would
               pour.</p>
            <p>I now sat down on the floor, with my suitcase before me, and I made a list of all my
               stories, put prices opposite them, added up the list, and, bedad! as [corr] O’Brien
               would say, I was a rich girl!</p>
            <p>In fact I felt so confident and recklessly happy that nothing would do but I must
               treat Lolly and Hermann to a fine dinner and the theater. My fifty dollars dropped to
               forty. But of course I was to get one hundred and fifty for those other three
               stories. It’s true, the letter accepting them did not mention the price, but I
               supposed that all magazines paid about the same, and even though in the case of the
               Western magazine I was to be <q>paid upon publication</q>, I was sure my stories
               would be published soon. In fact, I thought it a good thing that I was not paid all
               at once, because then I might be tempted to spend the money. As it was, it would come
               in just about the time I was through with the fifty.</p>
            <p>If my ignorance in this matter seems infantile, I think I may confidently refer my
               readers to certain other authors who in the beginning of their careers have been
               almost as credulous and visionary as I. It’s a matter of wonder how any person who is
               capable of writing a story can in other matters be so utterly impractical and
               positively devoid of common sense.</p>
            <p>I never saw fifty dollars fly away as quickly as that fifty dollars of mine. I really
               don’t know <emph>what</emph> it went for, though I did swagger about a bit among my friends. I
               took Mrs. Kingston and Mrs. Owens, the woman who lived with her, to the theater, too,
               and I went over to the Y.W.C.A. several times and treated Estelle and a lot of my old
               acquaintances to ice-cream sodas and things like that.</p>
            <p>I avidly watched the news-stands for the December number of that Western magazine to
               appear, and when it did come out, I was so sure at least one of my stories was in it,
               that I was confounded and stunned when I found that it was not. I thought some
               mistake must have been made, and bought two other copies to make sure.</p>
            <p>I was now down to my last six dollars. I awoke to the seriousness of my position. I
               would have to go to work again and immediately. The thought of this hurt me acutely,
               not so much because I hated the work, but because I realized that my dream of instant
               fame and fortune was just a dream.</p>
            <p>The December number of the New York magazine also was out, but my story was not in
               it. I wrote to the editors of both the Eastern and Western magazines, and asked when
               my stories would appear. I got answers within a few days. The Eastern magazine said
               that they were made up for several months ahead, but hoped to use my story by next
               summer,—it was the first week in December now,—and the Western magazine wrote vaguely
               that they planned to use my stories in <q>the near future</q>.</p>
            <p>I wrote such a desperate letter to the editor of that Western magazine, imploring him
               to use my stories very soon, that I must have aroused his curiosity, for he wrote me
               that he expected to be in Chicago <q>some time next month</q>, and would be much
               pleased to call upon me and discuss the matter of the early publication of my stories
               and others he would like to have me write for them.</p>
            <p>I said my fifty dollars flew away from me. I except the last six dollars. I performed
               miracles with that. I paid my share of our room-rent for a week—three dollars—and
               lived eleven days on the other three. At the end of those eleven days I had exactly
               ten cents.</p>
            <p>For two reasons I did not tell Lolly. In the first place, while I had not lied to
               her, I had in my egotistical and fanciful excitement led her to believe that not only
               had I sold the four stories, but they had been paid for. And in the second place,
               Lolly at this time was having bitter troubles of her own. They concerned Marshall
               Chambers, She was suffering untold <pb n="421"/> tortures over that man—the tortures that
               only a suspicious and passionately jealous woman who loves can feel. She had no
               tangible proof of his infidelities, but a thousand little things had occurred that
               made her suspect him. They quarreled constantly, and then passionately <q>made
               up</q>. So I could not turn to Lolly.</p>
            <p>I had not heard a word from Mr. Hamilton, and after that glowing, boastful letter I
               had written, how <emph>could</emph> I now appeal to him? The mere thought tormented and
               terrified me.</p>
            <p>Toward the end, when my money had faded down to that last six dollars, I had been
               desperately seeking work. I think I answered five hundred advertisements at least,
               but although now I was well dressed, an asset to a stenographer, and had city
               references (Fred’s), I could get nothing. My strait, it will be perceived, was really
               bad, and another week’s rent had fallen due.</p>
            <p>I didn’t have any dinner that evening when I went over to Mrs. Kingston’s, but I had
               on my beautiful blue velvet suit. My luncheon had been a single ham sandwich. Mrs.
               Kingston had called me up on the telephone early in the day, and invited me over for
               the evening, saying she had some friends who wished to meet me.</p>
            <p>Her friends proved to be two young men from Indianapolis who were living and working
               in Chicago. One, George Butler, already well known as a Socialist, was head of a
               Charities Association Bureau (I hysterically thought it an apropos occasion for me to
               meet a man in such work), and the other, Robert Bennet, was exchange editor of the
                  <q>News</q>. Butler was exceedingly good-looking, but he had a thick,
               baggy-looking mouth that spoiled his face, and he dressed like a poet,—at least I
               supposed a poet would dress something like that,—wearing his hair longish and
               carelessly tossed back, a turn-over soft collar, flowing tie, and loose clothes that
               looked as if they needed to be pressed.</p>
            <p>Bennet had an interesting face, the prominent attribute of which was an almost
               shining quality of <emph>honesty</emph>. It illuminated his otherwise rugged and homely face,
               and gave it a curious attraction and strength. I can find no other word to describe
               that expression. He wore glasses, and looked like a student, and he stooped a little,
               which added to this impression. Both boys were in their early twenties, I should say,
               and they roomed together somewhere near Jane Addams’s Hull House, where both worked
               at night, giving their services gratuitously as instructors in English. They were
               graduates of the University of Indiana.</p>
            <p>Butler talked a great deal about Socialism, and he would run his hand through his
               hair, as Belasco does on first nights. Bennet, on the other hand, was a good
               listener, but talked very little. He seemed diffident and even shy, and he stammered
               slightly.</p>
            <p>On this night I was in such a depressed mood that, despite Mr. Butler’s eloquence, I
               was unable to rouse myself from the morbid fancies that were now flooding my mind.
               For the imagination that had carried me up on dizzying dreams of fame now showed me
               pictures of myself starving and homeless; and just as the first pictures had
               exhilarated me, now the latter terrified and distracted.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Kingston noticed my silence, and asked me if I was not feeling well. She said I
               did not seem quite myself. I said I was all right. When I was going, she asked me in
               a whisper whether I had heard from Mr. Hamilton, and I shook my head; and then she
               wanted to know whether he knew of my <q>success</q>. Something screamed and cried
               within me at that question. My success! Was she mocking me then?</p>
            <p>Bennet had asked to see me home, and as it was still early,—only about nine,—he
               suggested that we take a little walk along the lake.</p>
            <p>It was a beautiful moonlight night, and though only a few weeks from Christmas, not
               at all cold. Mrs. Kingston had apparently told Mr. Bennet that I wrote, for he tried
               to make me talk about it. I was not, however, in a very communicative <pb n="422"/> mood. I
               talked disjointedly. I started to tell him about the New York magazine and the
               Western magazine, and then all of a sudden I remembered how I was fixed, and then I
               couldn’t talk at all. In fact, I pitied myself so that I began to cry. It was dark in
               the street, and I cried silently; so I didn’t suppose he noticed me until he stopped
               short and said:</p>
            <p><q>You’re in trouble. Can’t you tell me what is the matter?</q></p>
            <p><q>I’ve got only ten cents in the world</q>, I blurted out.</p>
            <p><q>What!</q></p>
            <p><q>Just ten cents</q>, I said, <q>and I can’t get work</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Good heavens!</q> he exclaimed. <q>You poor girl!</q></p>
            <p>He was so sorry for me and excited that he stammered worse than ever, and I stopped
               crying, because, having told some one my secret, I felt better and knew I’d get help
               somehow.</p>
            <p>So then I told him all about how I had come down to such straits; how I had worked
               all those months, and my implicit belief that that fifty dollars would last till I
               was paid for the other three stories.</p>
            <p>When I was through, Bennet said:</p>
            <p><q>N-now, l-look here. I get thirty dollars a week. I don’t need but half of that,
                  and I’m going to give you fifteen a week of it till you get another place</q>.</p>
            <p>I protested that I wouldn’t think of taking his money, but I was joyfully hailing him
               in my heart as a veritable savior. Before we had reached my lodging-place, I had not
               only allowed him to give me ten dollars, but I agreed to accept ten dollars a week
               from him till I got work.</p>
            <p>It is curious how, without the slightest compunction or any feeling even of hurt
               pride or shame, I was willing to accept money like this from a person whom I had
               never seen before; yet the thought of asking Hamilton filled me with a real terror. I
               believe I would have starved first. It is hard to explain this. I had liked to think
               of myself as doing something very unusual and fine in refusing help from Hamilton,
               and yet where was my logic, since without a qualm I took money from Bennet? Our
               natures are full of contradictions, it seems to me. Perhaps I can explain it in this
               way, however. There was something so tremendously <emph>good</emph> about Bennet, so
               overpoweringly human and great, that I felt the same as I would have felt if a woman
               had offered to help me. On the other hand, I was desperately in love with Hamilton. I
               wanted to impress him. I wanted his good opinion. I unconsciously assumed a
               pose—perhaps that is it—and I had to live up to it. Then I have often thought that
               almost any woman would have confidently accepted help from Bennet, but might have
               hesitated to take anything from Mr. Hamilton.</p>
            <p>Some men inspire us with instant confidence; we are <q>on guard</q> with others. I
               can write this analysis now; I could not explain it to myself then.</p>
            </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXV</head>
            <p>Now my life assumed a new phase. No man like Bennet can come into a woman’s life and
               not make a deep impression. I have said that Tom was my <q>shadow</q>. Bennet was something
               better than that. He was my protector, my guide, and my teacher. He did not, as Tom
               had done, begin immediately to make love to me, but he came persistently to see me.
               Always he brought some book with him, and now for the first time in my life the real
               world of poetry began to open its doors for me. I a poet! Oh me!</p>
            <p>Hamilton had filled my bookshelves with novels, chiefly by French authors. They were
               of absorbing interest to me, and they taught me things just as if I had traveled; but
               Bennet read to me poetry—Keats, Shelley, Byron, Browning, Tennyson, Heine, Milton,
               and others. For hours I sat listening to the jeweled words. No, I could not write
               poetry,—I never shall,—but I had the hungry heart of the poet within me. I know it;
               else I could not so vividly, so ardently have loved the poetry of others.</p>
            <p>I cannot think of my acquaintance with Bennet without there running immediately <pb n="423"/>
               to my mind, like the refrain of an old song, of some of those exquisite poems he read
               to me—read so slowly, so clearly, so subtly that every word pierced my consciousness
               and understanding. Else how could a girl like me have gasped with sheer delight over
               the <q>Ode on a Grecian Urn</q>? What was there in a poem like that to appeal to a
               girl of my history?</p>
            <p>When we did not stay in and read, Bennet would take me to some good theater or
               concert, and I went several times with him to Hull House. There twice a week he
               taught a class in English poetry. The girls in his class were chiefly
               foreigners,—Russian Jewesses, Polish and Ger-man girls,—and for the most part they
               worked in factories and stores; but they were all intelligent and eager to learn.
               They made me ashamed of my own indolence. I used to fancy that most of his pupils
               were secretly in love with Bennet. They would look at his inspired young face as if
               they greatly admired him, and I felt a sense of flattering pride in the thought that
               <emph>he</emph> liked only me. Oh. I couldn’t help seeing that, though he had not then told me
               so.</p>
            <p>Sometimes he took me over to his rooms. They were two very curious, low-roofed rooms
               down in the tenement-house district, completely lined with books. Here Butler, with
               his pipe in his loose mouth, used to entertain me with long talks on Socialism, and
               once he read me some of Kipling’s poems. That was my first acquaintance with Kipling.
               It was an unforgetable experience. In these rooms, too, Bennet read me <q>Undine</q>,
               some of Barrie’s stories, and Omar Khayyam.</p>
            <p>Those were clean, inspiring days. They almost compensated for everything else that
               was sad and ugly in my life. For sad and ugly things were happening to me every day,
               and I had had no word, no single sign, from Mr. Hamilton. I tried to shut him from my
               mind. I tried hard to do that, especially as I knew that Robert Bennet was beginning
               to care for me too well. Through the day, it was easy enough. I could do it, too,
               when Bennet read to me from the poets; but, ah, at night, that was when he slipped
               back insidiously upon me! Sometimes I felt that if I did not see him soon, I should
               go mad just from longing and desire to see his dear face and hear the sound of his
               cruel voice.</p>
            <p>I got a position about two weeks after I met Bennet. It was in a steel firm; I stayed
               there only two days. There were two other stenographers, and the second day I was
               there, the head of the firm decided to move me from the outer to his private office,
               to do his work. Both of the girls looked at each other so significantly when my desk
               was carried in that I asked them if anything was the matter. One of them shrugged her
               shoulders, and the other said:</p>
            <p><q>You’ll find out for yourself</q>.</p>
            <p>Within ten minutes after I was in that inner office I did. I was taking dictation at
               a little slat on his desk when he laid a photograph upon my book, and then, while I
               sat dumfounded, trying to look anywhere save at what was before me, he laid more
               photographs, one after the other, on top of that first one, which was the vilest
               thing I have ever seen in my life.</p>
            <p>The girls at the Y.W.C.A. and the girls at the stock-yards used to talk about their
               experiences in offices, and we used to laugh at the angry girls who declared they did
               this or that to men who insulted them. As I have written before, I had become
               hardened to such things, and when I could, I simply ignored them. They were one of
               the dirty things in life that working-girls had to endure. But now, as I sat at that
               desk, I felt rushing over me such a surge of primitive and outraged feeling that I
               could find no relief save in some fierce action. I seized those photographs, and
               slammed them into the face of that leering old satyr.</p>
            <p>After that I went from one position to another. I took anything I could get.
               Sometimes I left because the conditions were intolerable; sometimes because they did
               not pay me; usually I was allowed to go after a brief trial in which I failed to
               prove my competence. I was very bad at figures and most offices require a certain
               <pb n="424"/> amount of that kind of work from their stenographers. These were the places
               where I failed.</p>
            <p>Of course, changing my position and being out of work so much, I made little
               progress, and although I had had only twenty dollars from Bennet, I was unable to pay
               him back. I had hoped to by Christmas, now only a week off.</p>
            <p>And now something happened that caused a big change in my life; that is, it forced me
               at last to separate from Lolly. For some time she had been most unhappy, and one
               evening she confided to me her suspicions of Chambers. She said she had <q>turned
                  down</q> Hermann, who wanted to marry her, for Chambers, though friends had warned
               her not to trust him; but that though he had at times been brutal to her, she adored
               him. Pacing up and down the room, she told me that she wished she knew some way to
               prove him. It was then that I made my fatal offer. I said:</p>
            <p><q>Lolly, I could have told you long ago about Chambers. I <emph>know</emph> he is no good. If
                  I were you, I’d have nothing more to do with him</q>.</p>
            <p>Lolly stopped in her pacing, and stared at me.</p>
            <p><q><emph>How</emph> do you know?</q> she demanded.</p>
            <p><q>Because</q>, I said, <q>he’s tried several times to make love to me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You lie, Nora Ascough!</q> she cried out in such a savage way that I was afraid of
               her. If I had been wiser, perhaps, I might have reassured her and let her think I did
               lie. Then the matter would have ended there; but I had to plunge in deeper.</p>
            <p><q>Lolly, I’ll prove it to you, if you wish</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You can’t</q>, retorted Lolly, her nostrils dilating.</p>
            <p><q>Yes, I can, I say. He ‘s coming to-night, isn’t he? Well, you stay in that inner
                  room, by the door. Let me see him alone here. Then you’ll see for
               yourself</q>.</p>
            <p>She considered the suggestion, with her eyes half closed, blowing the smoke slowly
               from her lips, and looking at the tip of her cigarette. Then she shrugged her
               shoulders and laughed sneeringly.</p>
            <p><q>The trouble with you, Nora, is that because a lot of muckers at the Union
                  Stock-yards got ‘stuck’ on you, a few poor devils of newspaper men are a little
                  smitten, and a fast rich man tried to keep you, you imagine every other man is
                  after you</q>.</p>
            <p>I couldn’t answer that. It was untrue. None the less, it hurt. I had never in my life
               boasted to Lolly about men. I supposed she knew that, like every other girl who is
               thrown closely into contact with men, I naturally got my share of attention. I had
               long ago realized the exact value of this. The girls at the yards, for instance, used
               to say that the men would even go after a hunchback or a girl that squinted if she
               gave them any encouragement. And as for Robert Bennet and Tom, it was mean of Lolly
               to refer to them in that contemptuous way. Lolly, I think, regretted a moment later
               what she had said. She was as generous and impulsive as she was hasty in temper. Now
               she said:</p>
            <p><q>Forget I said that, Nora. Just for fun I’ll try your plan. Of course, it’s
                  ridiculous. Marshall has never looked upon you as anything but a joke. I mean he
                  thinks you’re a funny little thing; but as for anything else—</q> Lolly blew her
               cigarette smoke in derision at the notion.</p>
            <p>Chambers came about eight-thirty. They never announced him, but we knew his double
               knock, and Lolly slipped into the inner room, but did not close the door tight.</p>
            <p>I had taken up Lolly’s mandolin, and now I painfully tried to pick out a tune on the
               strings. Chambers stood watching me, smiling, and when I finally did manage <q>The
                  Last Rose of Summer</q>, he said:</p>
            <p><q>Bully for you!</q></p>
            <p>Then he looked about quickly and said:</p>
            <p><q>Lolly out?</q></p>
            <p>I nodded. Whereupon he sat down beside me.</p>
            <p><q>Want to learn the mandolin?</q> he asked.</p>
            <p>I nodded, smiling.</p>
            <pb n="425"/>
            <p><q>This is the way</q>, he said. He was on my left side, and putting his arm about my
               waist, and with his right hand over my right hand, he tried to teach me to use the
               little bone picker; but while he was doing this he got as close to me as he could,
               and as I bent over the mandolin, so did he, till his face came right against mine,
               and he kissed me.</p>
            <p>Then something terrible happened. Lolly screamed. She screamed like a person gone
               mad. Chambers and I jumped apart, and I felt so weak I was afraid to go inside that
               room. Just then Hermann came rushing in with the landlady. She had heard Lolly’s
               screams, and she wanted to know what was the trouble. I said Lolly was ill; but as
               soon as she went out, I told Hermann the truth. When Chambers realized that he was
               the victim of a trap, and while Lolly was still crying,—a moaning sort of cry now,—he
               picked up his hat and made for the door. There he encountered Hermann, all of whose
               teeth were showing. Hermann’s hand shot up to Chambers’s collar, and he threw him
               bodily from the room. How he did this, I am sure I don’t know, for Chambers was a
               larger and seemingly much stronger man than Hermann. Then Hermann went in to Lolly,
               and I, feeling like a criminal, followed.</p>
            <p>I had never seen a woman in hysterics before. Lolly was lying on her back on the bed,
               with her arms cast out on each side. Her face was convulsed, and she was gasping and
               crying and moaning and laughing all at the same time. Hermann put his arms about her,
               and tried to soothe and comfort her, and I, crying myself now, begged her to forgive
               me. She screamed at me, <q>Get out of my sight!</q> and kept on upbraiding and
               accusing me. She seemed to think that I must have been flirting with Chambers for
               some time, and she said I was a snake. She said she hated me, and that if I did not
               go <q>at once! at once! at once!</q> [corr] she’d kill me.</p>
            <p>I didn’t know what to do, and Hermann said:</p>
            <p><q>For God’s sake! Nora, go!</q></p>
            <p>I packed my things as quickly as I could. I had no trunk, but two suitcases, and I
               made bundles of the things that would not go into them. I told Hermann I’d send for
               the things in the morning. Then I put on my coat and hat, and took the suitcase with
               my manuscripts and my night things. Before going, I went over to the bed and again
               begged Lolly to forgive me, assuring her that I never had had anything to do with
               Chambers till that night. I told her that I loved her better than any other girl I
               knew, better than my sisters even, and it was breaking my heart to leave her in this
               way. I was sobbing while I talked, but though she no longer viciously denounced me,
               she turned her face to the wall and put her hands over her ears. Then I kissed her
               hand,—women of my race do things like that under stress of emotion,—and, crying, left
               my Lolly.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXVI</head>
            <p>I went direct to Mrs. Kingston’s. As soon as I walked in with my bag in my hand, she
               knew I had come to stay, and she was so delighted that she seized me in her arms and
               hugged me, saying I was her <q>dearest and only Nora</q>. She took me right up to
               what she thought were to be my rooms, but I said I preferred the little one, and
               after we had talked it over a bit, she said she agreed with me. It was much better
               for me to have only what I myself could afford.</p>
            <p>I didn’t tell her a word about Lolly. That was my poor friend’s secret; but I told
               her of my straitened affairs, my poor position, and that I owed money to Bennet. When
               I ended, she said:</p>
            <p><q>That boy’s an angel. I can’t wish you any better luck than that you get
               him</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Get him?</q></p>
            <p><q>He is simply crazy about you, Nora. Can’t talk about anything else, and you
                  couldn’t do better if you searched from one end of the United States to the other.
                  He’s of a splendid family, and he’s going to make a big name for himself some day,
                  you mark my words</q>.</p>
            <pb n="426"/>
            <p>I agreed with all her praise of Bennet, but I told her I thought of him only as a
               friend, as I did of Fred O’Brien for instance.</p>
            <p>She shook her head at me, sighed, and said that she supposed I still cared for
                  <q>that man Hamilton</q>, and I didn’t answer her. I just sat on the side of the
               bed staring out in front of me. After a moment she said:</p>
            <p><q>Of course, if that’s the way you feel, for heaven’s sake! let [corr] poor Bennet
                  alone; though if I were you, it wouldn’t take me long to know which of those two
                  men to choose between</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You’d take Bennet, wouldn’t you?</q> I asked heavily, and she replied:</p>
            <p><q>You better believe I would!</q></p>
            <p><q>Don’t you like Mr. Hamilton?</q> I asked wistfully.</p>
            <p><q>I don’t entirely trust him</q>, said she. <q>Candidly, Nora, that was a nasty
                  trick he tried to play us here. I was ‘on to him,’ but I didn’t know just where
                  you stood with him, and I’m not in the preaching business. I let people do as they
                  like, and I myself do what I please; and then, of course, Lord knows I need all
                  the money I can get</q>. She sighed. Poor woman, she was always so hard up! <q>So
                  if he wanted to take those rooms and pay the price, I wasn’t going to be the one
                  to stand in the way. Still, I was not going to let him pull the wool over your
                  eyes, poor kiddy</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I suppose not</q>, I assented languidly. I was unutterably tired and heartsick,
               with the long strain of those weeks, and now with this quarrel with Lolly, and I
               said, <q>Yet I’d give my immortal soul to be with him again just for a few minutes
                  even</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You would?</q> she said. <q>You want to see him as much as all that?</q></p>
            <p>I nodded, and she said pityingly:</p>
            <p><q>Don’t love any man like that, dear. None of them is worth it</q>.</p>
            <p>I didn’t answer. What was the use? She said I looked tired out, and had better go to
               bed, and that next day she would send the man who looked after the furnace for my
               belongings.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Kingston was really delighted to have me with her. She said she could have had
               any number of girls in her house before this, but that she had set her heart on
               having <q>just me</q>, because I was uncommon. She had a funny habit of dismiss- ing
               people and things as <q>ordinary and commonplace</q>. I was not that, it seems.</p>
            <p>Here was I now in a really dear little home, not a boarder, but treated like a
               daughter not only by Mrs. Kingston, but by Mrs. Owens, who quickly made me call her
                  <q>Mama Owens</q>. She was pretty woman of about sixty, with lovely dark eyes, and
               white wavy hair that I often did up. She had periodical spells of illness, I don’t
               know just what. Both Mrs. Kingston and Mrs. Owens were widows.</p>
            <p>I brightened up a bit after I got there, for they wouldn’t give me a chance to be
               blue. We had a merry time decorating the house with greens and holly, and we even had
               a big Christmas-tree. Mama Owens said she couldn’t imagine a Christmas without one.
               Just think, though I was one of fourteen children, I can never remember a Christmas
               when we had a tree!</p>
            <p>Bennet came over and helped us with the decorations, and he and Butler were both
               invited to the Christmas dinner. Butler could not come, as he was due at some Hull
               House entertainment, but Bennet expected to have dinner with us before going to work.
               He was working nights now, and would not have Christmas off.</p>
            <p>I was getting only twelve dollars a week at this time, so I had little enough money
               to spend on Christmas presents. I did, however, buy books for Bennet and Mrs.
               Kingston and Mrs. Owens. Also for Lolly, to whom I had written twice, begging her to
               forgive me. She never answered me, but Hermann wrote me a note, advising me to
                  <q>leave her alone till she gets over it</q>.</p>
            <p>I had to walk to work for two days after that, as I didn’t have a cent left, and I
               did without luncheon, too. I rather enjoyed the walk, but it was hard getting <pb n="427"/>
               up so early, as I had to be at the office at eight. I was working for a clothing firm
               not unlike the one Estelle was with, and I had obtained the position, by the way,
               through Estelle.</p>
            <p>On Christmas eve Margaret had to go to the house of a client in regard to some case,
               so mama and I were left alone. We were decorating the tree with strings of white and
               colored popcorn and bright tinsel stuff, and I was standing on top of a ladder,
               putting a crowning pinnacle on the tree, — a funny, fat little Santa Claus, — when
               our bell rang. Our front door opened into the reception hall, where our tree was, so
               when mama opened the door and I saw who it was, I almost fell off the ladder. He
               called out:</p>
            <p><q>Careful!</q> dropped his bag, came over to the ladder, and lifted me down. You
               can’t lift a girl down from a ladder without putting your arms about her, and I clung
               to him, you may be sure. He kept smoothing my hair and cheek, and saying, — I think
               he thought I was crying against his coat, — <q>Come, now, Nora, it’s all right!
                  Everything’s all right!</q> and then he undid my hands, which were clinging to his
               shoulders, and shook himself free.</p>
            <p>Mama Owens had never met him, so I had to introduce them. She scolded me dreadfully
               afterward about the way I had acted, though I tried to explain to her that it was the
               surprise and excitement that had made me give way like that.</p>
            <p>It was queer, but from the very first both Margaret and Mama Owens were prejudiced
               against him. Both of them loved me and were devoted to Bennet. They were planning to
               make a match between us. Hamilton was the stumbling-block; and although in time he
               partly won Margaret over, he never moved mama, who always regarded him as an intruder
               in our <q>little family</q>.</p>
            <p>I now hinted and hinted for her to leave us alone, but she wouldn’t budge from the
               room for the longest time. So I just talked right before her, though she kept
               interrupting me, requiring me to do this or that. She didn’t ask him to do a thing,
               though if Bennet had been there, she would have seated herself comfortably and let
               him do all the work.</p>
            <p>However, I was so happy now that it didn’t matter if all the rest of the world was
               disgruntled. I hugged Mama Owens, and told her if she didn’t stop being so cross, Mr.
               Hamilton and I would go out somewhere and leave her <q>all by her lonesome</q>. I
               could do almost anything with her and Margaret, and I soon had her in a good humor;
               she even went off to get some Christmas wine for Mr. Hamilton.</p>
            <p>I had in a general way told Roger something of what I had been doing since I had seen
               him; but I did not tell him of the straits to which I had come, or of the money I had
               borrowed from Bennet. He suspected that I had passed through hard times, however. He
               had a way of picking up my face by the chin and examining it closely. The moment we
               were alone, he led me under the gas-light, and looked at me closely. His face was as
               grave as if he were at a funeral, and I tried to make fun of it; but he said:</p>
            <p><q>Nora, you don’t look as well as you should</q>.</p>
            <p>I said lightly:</p>
            <p><q>That’s because you didn’t come to see me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I came</q>, he returned, <q>as soon as you did what I told you. As soon as Mrs.
                  Kingston sent me word that you were here, I came, though it was Christmas eve, and
                  I ought to be in Richmond</q>.</p>
            <p>I saw what was in his mind: he thought I had taken those rooms! I put my arm through
               his, just to hold to him in case he went right away, while I told him I had only the
               little room.</p>
            <p>He said, with an expressive motion:</p>
            <p><q>Well, I give you up, Nora</q>.</p>
            <p>I said:</p>
            <p><q>No, please don’t give me up. I’ll die if you do</q>.</p>
            <p>Margaret came in then, and she greeted him very cordially. She chuckled when I called
               her a <q>sly thing</q> for writing to him, and she said she had to let him know,
               since he had paid for the big room.</p>
            <p><q>Yes, but, you didn’t tell him I had. the little room</q> I said.</p>
            <pb n="428"/>
            <p><q>What does it matter?</q> laughed Margaret. <q>You two are always making mountains
                  out of molehills. Life’s too short to waste a single moment of it in
               argument</q>.</p>
            <p>Roger said:</p>
            <p><q>You are perfectly right. After this, Nora and I are not going to quarrel about
                  anything. She’s going to be a reasonable child</q>.</p>
            <p>I had to laugh. I knew what he meant by my being reasonable. Nothing mattered this
               night, however, except that he had come. I told him that, and put my cheek against
               his hand. I was always doing things like that, for although he was undemonstrative,
               and the nearest he came to caressing me was to smooth my cheek and hair, I always got
               as close to him as I could. I’d slip my hand through his arm, or put my hand in his,
               and my head against him; and when we were out anywhere, I always had my hand in his
               pocket, and he’d put his hand in over mine. He liked them, too, these ways of mine,
               for he used to look at me with a queer sort of grim smile that was nevertheless
               tender.</p>
            <p>He was a man used to having his own way, however, and he didn’t intend to give in to
               me in this matter of the rooms. So this is how he finally arranged things: I was to
               have the little room, and he would take the suite in front. When he was in Chicago,
               he would use these rooms; but when he was not, I was to have the use of them, and he
               made me promise that I would use the big room for writing.</p>
            <p>This arrangement satisfied Mrs. Kingston and delighted me, but mama was inclined to
               grumble. She wanted to know just why he should maintain rooms in the house, anyway,
               and just what he was <q>after</q> me for. She was in a perverse mood, having drunk
               far too much Christmas wine. She talked so that I put my hand over her mouth and said
               she had a bad mind.</p>
            <p>Roger explained to Margaret — he pretended to ignore mama, but he was talking for her
               especially — that they need have no anxiety in regard to his intentions toward me;
               that they were purely disinterested; in fact, he felt toward me pretty much as they
               did themselves. I was an exceptional girl who ought to be helped and befriended; that
               he had never made love to me, and, he added grimly, that he never would. My! how
               [corr] I hated mama at that moment for causing him to say that. In fact he talked so
               plausibly that Margaret and I threw black looks at mama for her gratuitous
               interference, and Margaret whispered to me that it should not happen again. Mama
                  <q>stuck to her guns</q>, however, and finally said:</p>
            <p><q>Well, let me ask you a question, MIr. Hamilton. Are you in love with Nora?</q></p>
            <p>He looked over my head and said:</p>
            <p><q>No</q>.</p>
            <p>That was the first time he had directly denied that he cared for me, and my heart
               sank. I wouldn’t look at him, I felt so badly, nor did I feel any better when, after
               a moment, he added:</p>
            <p><q>I’m old enough to be Nora’s father, and at my time of life I’m not likely to make
                  a fool of myself even for Nora</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Hm!</q> snorted mama, <q>that all sounds very fine, but what about Nora? Do you
                  pretend that she is not in love with you?</q></p>
            <p>His stiff expression softened, but he said very bitterly, I thought:</p>
            <p><q>Nora is seventeen</q>.</p>
            <p>Then he laughed shortly, and added: <q>I don’t see how it can hurt her to have me for
                  a friend, do you? As far as that goes, even if she does imagine herself in love
                  with me, a closer acquaintance might lead to a complete cure and disillusionment,
                  a consummation, I presume, much to be desired</q>.</p>
            <p>He said this with so much bitterness; and even pain, that I ran over to him and put
               my face against his hand.</p>
            <p><q>Wait a bit, Nora. We’d better get this matter settled once and for all</q>. he
               said. <q>Either I am to come here, with the understanding and consent of these
                  ladies, whenever I choose and without interference of any sort, or I will not come
                  at all</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Then I won’t stay, either</q>, I cried. <pb n="429"/> <q>Margaret, <emph>you</emph> know that if he
                  never comes to see me again, I’ll jump into Lake Michigan</q>.</p>
            <p>They all laughed at that, and it broke up the strained conversation. Margaret said in
               her big, gay way:</p>
            <p><q>Of course you can come and go as you please. The rooms are yours, and I shouldn’t
                  presume to dictate to you</q>. And then she said to mama: <q>Amy, you’ve had too much wine. Let it alone</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXVII</head>
            <p>Everything being made clear, Roger and I went up to his rooms. He shut the door, and
               said that <q>the two old ones</q> were all right enough, but he had come over 250
               miles to see me, and he didn’t care a hang what they or any one else thought, and
               that if they’d made any more fuss, he’d have taken me away from there without further
               parley. Then he asked me something suddenly that made me laugh. He wanted to know if
               I was afraid of him, and I asked:</p>
            <p><q>Why should I be?</q></p>
            <p><q>You ‘re right</q>, he replied, <q>and you need never be, Nora. You can always
                  trust me</q>.</p>
            <p>I said mischievously:</p>
            <p><q>It’s the other way. I think <emph>you’re</emph> afraid of me</q>.</p>
            <p>He frowned me down at that, and demanded to know what I meant, but I couldn’t
               explain.</p>
            <p>He lighted the logs in the fireplace, and pulled up the big Morris chair and a
               footstool before it. He made me sit on the stool at his knee. Then we talked till it
               was pretty late, and mama popped her head in and said I ought to go to bed. I
               protested that as I didn’t have to go to work next day, I need not get up early.
               Roger said she was right, and that he must be going.</p>
            <p>I had thought he was going to spend Christmas with me, and I was so dreadfully
               disappointed that I nearly cried, and he tried to cheer me up. He said he wouldn’t go
               if he could help it, but that his people expected him home at least at Christmas.
               That was the first time he had ever referred to his <q>people</q>, and I felt a vague
               sense of jealousy that they meant more to him than I did. But I did not tell him
               that, for he suddenly leaned over me and said:</p>
            <p><q>I’d rather be here with you, Nora, than anywhere else in the world</q>.</p>
            <p>I sat up at that, and said triumphantly:</p>
            <p><q>Then you <emph>must</emph> care for me if that’s so</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Have I ever pretended not to?</q> he asked.</p>
            <p><q>You told them down-stairs—</q></p>
            <p>He snapped his fingers as though what he had said there didn’t count.</p>
            <p><q>Well, but you must be more than merely interested in me</q>, I said.</p>
            <p><q>Interest is a pretty big thing, isn’t it?</q> he said slowly.</p>
            <p><q>Not as big as love</q>, I said.</p>
            <p><q>We’re not going to talk about love</q>. he replied. <q>We’ll have to cut that out
                  entirely, Nora</q>.</p>
            <p><q>But I thought you said you wanted me to go on loving you, and that I was not to
                  stop, no matter what happened</q>.</p>
            <p>He stirred uneasily at that, and then, after a moment, he said:</p>
            <p><q>That’s true. Never stop doing that, will you, sweetheart?</q></p>
            <p>You see, I was succeeding beautifully with him when he called me <emph>that</emph>. He
               regretted it a moment later, for he rose and began fussing with his bag. I followed
               him across the room. I always followed him everywhere, just like a little dog. He
               took a little package out of his bag, and he asked me if I remembered the day in the
               carriage, when he told me to open my mouth and shut my eyes. Of course I did. He said
               that I was to shut my eyes now, but I need not open my mouth. He’d give me the real
               prize now.</p>
            <p>So then I did, and he put something about my neck. Then he led me over to the mirror,
               and I saw it was a pearl necklace.</p>
            <p>At that time I had not the remotest idea of the value of jewelry. I had never
               possessed any except the ring Tom had given me. In a vague sort of way I knew that
               gold and diamonds were costly things, <pb n="430"/> and of course I supposed that pearls
               were, too. It was not, therefore, the value of his present that impressed me, for I
               frankly looked upon it merely as a <q>pretty necklace</q>; but I was enchanted to
               think he had remembered me, and when I opened my eyes and saw them, they looked so
               creamy and lovely on my neck that I wanted to hug him for them. However, he held me
               off at arm’s-length, to <q>see how they looked</q> on me.</p>
            <p>He said I was not to wear them to work, but only on special occasions, when he was
               there and took me to places, and that he was going to get me a little safe in which
               to keep them. I thought that ridiculous, to get a safe just to keep a string of beads
               in; and then he laughed and said that the <q>beads</q> were to be only the forerunner
               of other things he was going to give me.</p>
            <p>He was going to create in me a taste for the best in everything, he said. I asked him
               why. It seemed to me that nothing was to be gained by acquiring a taste for luxurious
               things — a girl in my position, and he replied in a grim sort of way:</p>
            <p><q>All the same, you’re going to have them. By and by you won’t be able to do without
                  them</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Jewels and such things?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes—jewels and such things</q>. Then he added:</p>
            <p><q>There need never be a time in your life when I won’t be able to gratify your least
                  wish, if you will let me</q>.</p>
            <p>When he was putting on his coat, he asked me what sort of position I had, and I told
               him it was pretty bad. He said he wished me to go down to see Mr. Forman, the
               president of a large wholesale dry-goods firm. He added that he had heard of a good
               position there — short hours and good salary. I was delighted, and asked him if he
               thought I’d get the position, and he smiled and said he thought I would.</p>
            <p>He was drawing on his gloves and was nearly ready to go when he asked his next
               question, and that was whether I had made any new acquaintances; what men I had met,
               and whether I had been out anywhere with any particular man. He usually asked me
               those questions first of all, and then would keep on about them all through his
               visit. I hesitated, for I was reluctant to tell him about Bennet. He roughly took me
               by the shoulder when I did not answer him at once, and he said:</p>
            <p><q>Well, with whom have you been going out?</q></p>
            <p>I told him about Bennet, but only about his coming to see me, his reading to me, and
               of my going to his and Butler’s rooms and to Hull House. He stared at me so
               peculiarly while I was speaking that I thought he was angry with me, and he suddenly
               took off his coat and hat and sat down again.</p>
            <p><q>Why didn’t you tell me about this chap before?</q> he asked me suddenly.</p>
            <p><q>I thought you wouldn’t be interested</q>, I quibbled.</p>
            <p><q>That is not true, Nora</q>, he said. <q>You knew very well I would</q>.</p>
            <p>He leaned forward in the chair, with his hands gripped together, and stared at the
               fire, and then he said almost as if to himself:</p>
            <p><q>If I had come on, this wouldn’t have happened</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Nothing has happened</q>, I insisted.</p>
            <p><q>Oh yes, this—er—Bennet is undoubtedly in love with you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, suppose he is?</q> I said. <q>What does it matter to you? If you don’t care
                  for me, why shouldn’t other men?</q></p>
            <p>He turned around and looked at me hard a moment. Then he got up, walked up and down
               awhile, and then came over and took my face up in his hand.</p>
            <p><q>Nora, will you give up this chap if I ask you to?</q></p>
            <p>I was piling up proof that he cared for me more than he would admit. I said
               flippantly:</p>
            <p><q>Old ‘Dog in the Manger,’ will you love me if I do?</q></p>
            <p>He said in a low voice:</p>
            <p><q>I <emph>can’t</emph></q>.</p>
            <p>I said sadly:</p>
            <p><q>Is it so hard, then?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes, harder than you know</q>, he said. <pb n="431"/></p>
            <p>Then he wanted to know what Bennet looked like. I painted a flattering picture. When
               was he coming? To Christmas dinner, I told him.</p>
            <p>It was now very late, and I heard the clock in the hall strike twelve, and I asked
               him if he heard the reindeer bells on the roof.</p>
            <p><q>Nora, I don’t hear or see anything in the world but you</q>, he replied.</p>
            <p><q>If that’s so, you must be as much in love with me as I am with you</q>, I told
               him.</p>
            <p>He said, <q>Nonsense!</q> and looked around, as if he were going to put his things on
               again.</p>
            <p><q>Stay over Christmas!</q> I begged, and after staring at me a moment, he said:</p>
            <p><q>Very well, I will, then</q>.</p>
            <p>That made me tremendously excited. Mama came down the hall and called:</p>
            <p><q>Nora, aren’t you in bed yet?</q> I called out:</p>
            <p><q>I’m going now</q>. Then I seized his hand quickly, kissed it, and ran out of the
               room to my own.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>XXVIII</head>
            <p>Early next morning while we were at breakfast, a huge box of flowers and Christmas
               package from Bennet came for me. It was fun to see Roger’s face when I was unwrapping
               the flowers. I think he would have liked to trample upon them, he who did not love
               me! They were chrysanthemums, and the other present was a beautiful little painting.
               Mama asked Hamilton to hang it for us, and he said curtly that he didn’t know
               anything about such things.</p>
            <p>Christmas morning thus started off rather badly, for any one could see he was cross
               as a sore bear, which, I don’t mind admitting, gave me a feeling of wicked joy. To
               make matters worse, mama began to talk about Tom. I tried to change the subject, but
               she persisted, and wanted to know when I had heard from him last and whether he was
               still as much in love with me as ever. There was no switching her from the subject,
               so I left the table, and pretended to fool with the books in the library. He followed
               me out there, and his face was just as black!</p>
            <p><q>So</q>, he said, with an unpleasant laugh, <q>you’ve been having little affairs
                  and flirtations right along, have you? You’re not the naive, innocent baby child
                  you would like me to think, eh?</q></p>
            <p><q>Now, Roger, look here</q>, I said. <q>Didn’t you tell me you weren’t going to
                  scold me any more, and you said I could do as I pleased, and be independent
                  and—</q></p>
            <p><q>I supposed you would be candid and truthful with me; I didn’t suppose you’d be
                  carrying on cheap little liaisons—</q></p>
            <p>When he got that far, I turned my back on him and walked out of the room.</p>
            <p>I adored him, but I was not a worm.</p>
            <p>I went back to the kitchen, and watched Margaret clean the turkey and make the
               stuffing. I thought I was much interested in that proceeding, but all the time I was
               wondering what he was doing, and soon I couldn’t stand it any longer, and I went back
               to the living-room, which was also our library, but he was not there. I went
               up-stairs, with <q>my heart in my mouth</q>, fearing he had gone. I found him, if you
               please, in <emph>my</emph> room. He was looking at the photographs on my bureau.</p>
            <p>I came up behind him, slipped my hand through his arm, and rubbed my cheek against
               his sleeve. I could see his face in the mirror opposite us slowly softening.</p>
            <p><q>Are you still angry with me for nothing, Roger?</q> I asked.</p>
            <p><q>Was this fellow Morris in love with you, too?</q></p>
            <p>I nodded.</p>
            <p><q>All men aren’t like you</q>, I said slyly. <q>Some few of them do like me</q>.</p>
            <p>He took that in as if it hurt him.</p>
            <p><q>He’s in Cuba, you say?</q></p>
            <p>I nodded.</p>
            <p><q>You hear from him?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Where are his letters?</q></p>
            <p>I couldn’t show him the letters, I said. So then he tried to free himself from my
               hand, but he couldn’t; I held so tightly.</p>
            <p><q>It wouldn’t be square to Tom to show you his letters</q>, I said.</p>
            <p><q>So it’s ‘Tom,’ is it?</q> he sneered. <pb n="432"/></p>
            <p>I nodded.</p>
            <p><q>Yes, just as it was ’Fred’ with O’Brien</q>.</p>
            <p><q>O’Brien wasn’t in love with you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, well, maybe Tom isn’t. He just thinks he is</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Any understanding between you?</q></p>
            <p>I hesitated. I really think he would have taken pleasure in hurting me then for that
               long pause. I said at last:</p>
            <p><q>He asked me to wait for him, but I’m not going to, if you’ll come lots to see
                  me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Did you promise to?</q></p>
            <p>Again I paused, and this time he caught up my face, but savagely, by the chin.</p>
            <p><q>Well?</q></p>
            <p>I lied. I was afraid of him now.</p>
            <p><q>No</q>. I said.</p>
            <p>I showed him all the photographs on my bureau, but he swept them aside.</p>
            <p><q>Hang your family! I’m not interested in them. Now, about this Bennet—</q> and he
               started in all over again.</p>
            <p>Finally, thoroughly exasperated, I turned on him and said:</p>
            <p><q>You have no right to question or accuse me like this. No man has that right unless
                  I specially give it to him</q>.</p>
            <p>He said roughly:</p>
            <p><q>Give me the right then, Nora</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Not unless you care for me</q>. I said. <q>You say you are only interested in me.
                  Well, say you love me, and then I’ll do anything you wish. I won’t look at or
                  speak to any other man in the world</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, suppose I admit that. Suppose I were to tell you that I do love you, what
                  would you want then, Nora?</q></p>
            <p><q>Why, nothing</q>, I said. <q>That would be everything to me, don’t you see? I’d go
                  to school then, just as you want me to, and I’d study so hard, and try to pull
                  myself up till I was on your level —</q></p>
            <p><q>Oh, good God!</q> he said, <q>you are miles above me now</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Not socially</q>, I said. <q>In the eyes of the world I’m not. I’m just a
                  working-girl, and you’re a man in — in — fashionable society, rich and important.
                  I guess you could be President if you wanted to, couldn’t you?</q></p>
            <p><q>Oh, Nora!</q> he said, and I went on:</p>
            <p><q>Yes, you might. You can’t tell. Suppose you got into politics. You said your
                  grandfather was governor of your State. Well, why shouldn’t you be, too? So to be
                  your wife, I’d have to—</q></p>
            <p><q>To be—what?</q> he interrupted me, and then he said sharply and quickly:</p>
            <p><q>That’s out of the question. Put all thought of anything like that out of your
                  head. Suppose we change the subject. What do you say to a little
               sleigh-ride?</q></p>
            <p>I nodded and I tried to smile, but he had hurt me as hard as it is possible for a man
               to hurt a woman.</p>
            <p>It was not that I looked upon marriage as such a desirable goal; but it was at least
               a test of the man’s sincerity. As he had blundered on with his senseless jealousy of
               men who did want to marry me, I had dreamed a little dream.</p>
            <p>We had our ride, and then dinner in the middle of the afternoon. Bennet was there for
               dinner. He thought Mr. Hamilton was our new lodger, and before him at least I did
               conceal my real feelings. Anyhow, I confess that I felt none too warmly toward Roger
               now. He had descended upon me on this Christmas day, and while putting his gifts on
               my neck with one hand, he had struck me with the other. Do not suppose, however, that
               my love for him lessened. You can soothe a fever by a cooling drink; you cannot cure
               it.</p>
            <p>Bennet had to go immediately after dinner, and I went with him as far as the door.
               All our rooms on the ground floor ran into one another, so that from the dining-room
               one could see directly into the reception-hall. Bob — for I always called him that —
               led me along by the arm, and suddenly mama clapped her hands loudly, and he seized me
               and kissed me! I was under the mistletoe. Roger knocked over his chair, and I heard
               him swear. Bob also heard, but neither of us cared.</p>
            <p>(To be concluded)</p>
            <p>—</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
