<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MissNume1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miss Numè of Japan [Author Commentary]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:KI1">Ken Ip</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>ADD STUFF HERE</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl90"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna, Onoto</name></author>.
                     <title level="a">Miss Numè of Japan [Author Commentary]</title>. <publisher ref="org:Book"><title level="j">Book News</title></publisher>, <date when="1899-05">May 1899</date>, pp. <biblScope unit="page">487-88</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Archive.org</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-03" status="published">Added note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2020-02-12" status="published">Changed title to indicate difference between novel.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-06-17" status="published">Proofread.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2019-06-08" status="readyForProof">Downloaded document from Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2019-04-11" status="inProgress">Merged file, changed xml:id, and associated with bibliography entry bibl90 using XSLT.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2019-03-12">Created file from Project Gutenberg transcription.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:MissNume1">
      <pb n="487"/>
      <body>
         <head>Miss Numè of Japan</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>.</byline>
         </opener>
         
         <div>
            <p>I might give a score of reasons that suggest the writing of a book, and which would suit as a paragraph in the column in which you wish to use it, but I prefer to tell the truth, and the truth—-the reason why I wrote the book—-might not appeal to many people as a particularly worthy reason. Well, I wrote because I was hard up and wanted to make some money. I had been writing short story after short story—-some were accepted—-some not. Someone suggested my writing a novel, which they said would help me with the magazines. You doubtless know what it is to make a living solely by writing—-unless one has a big reputation and a big income, from a dozen books, say. Well, for some time I have been trying to make two ends meet solely by writing short stories, and when I tell you that there is not merely myself to be considered, you will understand somewhat of the struggle I had. When I started out with the book I did not even have a plot planned. I went ahead and the plot developed as I wrote. I took keen pleasure in writing it—-and as is my nature, suffered and rejoiced with my characters. But the book was written under pressure. I had to steal the time from my regular work of writing short stories—-which were my livelihood. I don’t know whether this story is good or bad—-I hope it is good. To me writing is something I enjoy, but which I am constantly questioning—-can I afford to do it, for art is a luxury, and one has to have something practical to live by in order to indulge one’s taste for writing. I have written ever since I could remember—-scribbled away at one thing and another—-fairy tales as a child—newspaper articles when I was on the little newspaper in the West Indies—I wrote under five different <choice><sic>nome-de-plumes</sic><corr>noms de plumes</corr></choice>. Now I am writing almost entirely Japanese stories, and as of course I am in sympathy with my subject I dare say I will please the fickle public. My new book I am putting my whole heart into, and it will be good—-better than anything I had done yet.</p>

            <p>I do not need to ask your pardon for being honest in this, but I am so sorry that I could not give you a nice reason for writing the book <q>Miss Numè of Japan</q>. You may, if you wish, use the real reason—-that I wrote it because I was hard up. You know it is a good thing that there is such a thing as want and poverty in the world. (Not that I have suffered that actually,) for there are so many people with the ability to do this or that and with talent—genius—dormant in them—-and yet who are <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr></choice> indolent—-yes actually too indolent to do anything towards developing it. Necessity brings it out—-they are crowded into a corner, and the world hears of them then. We have to thank grim old want, perhaps, for some of our masterpieces, both in literature and art. Don’t you think so?</p>
    
            <p>Well, I will never grow indolent in my work—-no matter how independent I become, because I love it for itself. Maybe I don’t know myself, however—I am only a girl in age yet. Years—-a lifetime is before me—-and if indeed I have any talent, I shall make the most of it.</p>
    
            <p>I am impulsive—-and write on impulse generally. A pathetic little incident or a thought appeals to me—-I scribble it out, and the little laughing things of life I grasp after also. The book <q>Miss Numè</q> does not pretend to be a great book—-it was written in a simple fashion—-all the world understands simplicity, though the wise pretend to despise it. I did not try to solve any problems in the book—-there is no psychological analysis. The good, great, old authors dished up so much of that to us that I thought I’d just go ahead and tell the story without pausing to ruminate or moralize. The book is pure—-as all my work shall be, even though they tell me to be successful in literature one must needs introduce harrowing or realistic plots and situations. Well then I will never be a success if that is so, for I cherish<pb n="488"/>the absurd idea that perhaps the world is just as interested in clean books as in clean people. I didn’t try to make any of my characters extraordinary or fine—-I tried to paint them as we are in life—-never wonderfully good, and let me believe it, seldom wonderfully bad. Just ordinary human beings. I write because I can’t help myself—-because I love to, and because I earn my living that way—-but I don’t think I have any particular mission in life—-save to play my part as the days go by—-and so, seldom write with an object. Life altogether to me is objectless—-I live from day to day in that day only, and make the most of it—-am glad I am alive. But your kind letter did not call for all this, and you must forgive me.</p>
            
            <closer>
               <dateline>Chicago, Ill. March 24, 1899.</dateline>
            </closer>
    
    
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>