<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MovieMadness5">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Movie Mandess [Third Instalment]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>4.1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl314"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred
                              Eaton</name></author>. <title level="a">Movie Mandess [Third
                           Instalment]</title>. MS in five parts. <distributor ref="org:WERFonds"
                           >Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>, <date when="1930"
                        >1930</date>, <idno>4.1</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p><!--[Add information about the holding library (i.e. the source of the facsimile) here]--></p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-27" status="published"></change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2022-04-28">Added catRef genre and exhibit.
            Added facsimile.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2022-04-28" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:MovieMadness5" prev="doc:MovieMadness4" next="doc:MovieMadness6">
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <fw type="continued" place="right">Third Instalment</fw>
         <head><q>MOVIE MADNESS</q></head>
         <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED EATON REEVE</name></byline>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter X.</head>
            <p>When Jane awoke, the radiant California sunlight was pouring into the room. Joybelle
               was <choice>
                  <sic>upand</sic>
                  <corr>up and</corr>
               </choice> moving about the kitchenette. Jane reached for the Ingersoll watch. Eight
               thirty! She would be late for work. Mere readers at Filmo were required to punch the
               time clock. She hurried with her shower and dressing. She had a longing to stay home
               that day---to sit by the window and just dream. Even while dressing, her mind was
               dancing along with the glorious thing that had happened to her.</p>

            <p>Joybelle called:</p>

            <p><q>Coffee ready--you got to hustle, kid</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Joy, I <choice>
                     <sic>have’nt</sic>
                     <corr>haven’t</corr>
                  </choice> time for coffee. I’m late</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Late nothing. <choice>
                     <sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> only 8.40 and Jim’ll run you out. Listen to him honking his horn--the
                  nerve of him!</q></p>

            <p><q>Jim</q> was Joybelle’s <q>Gentleman friend</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Here you, eat that egg and don’t answer back either</q>.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>With some people Love is a secret, jealously to be <pb n="2"/>guarded. With others it
               is a song that must be chanted aloud. It brims over like a full cup of joy. Jane
               could not keep her marvelous secret. She told it to Millie Cohen, when that very
               serious faced young person dropped in at her office.</p>

            <p><q>Millie--I’ve got to tell it. Millie--Mr. Blanton and I are in love with each
                  other. He told me so last night, and Oh! I’m the happiest girl in the whole
                  world</q>.</p>

            <p>Millie’s expressive eyes were registering amazement and profound worry. She hardly
               knew what to say.</p>

            <p><q>Jane, listen--don’t let a whisper of this get around the lot. <choice>
                     <sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> not as easy or as lovely as you think. I’ll talk to you at noon--<choice>
                     <sic>lets</sic>
                     <corr>let’s</corr>
                  </choice> have lunch in the Inn today--what do you say?</q></p>

            <p><q>That’ll be fine</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane was too happy to puzzle over the strange way in which Millie received her
               confidence. She did not go immediately to work, but stood at her window, looking out
               at the scores of people passing like busy bees through the studio streets.</p>

            <p>A company of cowboys on horse went clattering over the cobbled road. One of them was
               singing, and the others yipping and halooing as they swept by.</p>

            <p>Jane felt as if she were in some beautiful dream that had somehow come true. To think
               that she was the same girl who lived in the little eastern college town all of her
               life. Her mind wandered lovingly back to her home; clung tenderly about her father,
               her mother, her five little brothers <choice>
                  <sic>a and</sic>
                  <corr>and</corr>
               </choice> sisters. She dashed her hand across her eyes.</p>

            <p>Miss Dutton, the story editor, came in, manuscript of a <pb n="3"/> play in her
               hand.</p>

            <p><q>Miss Mercer</q> she said crisply, <q>I’ve been watching your work. I like the way
                  you write your synopses; now I’m going to try you out on treatments. Let me see
                  what you can do with this</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Thank you so much</q> said Jane, surprising Miss Dutton by her eager kindling
               glance. When the Editor had left, Jane, her eyes starry bright, tried to concentrate
               upon the manuscript. She turned the pages of <q>The Immense Pearl</q>, but could not
               read. The words fled before her like a meaningless thread on a kaleidoscope. She
               glanced at her wrist watch. Why--it was nearly 11.30 already. She recalled that
               Blanton had said he would telephone her first thing in the morning. She realized that
               almost unconsciously she had been waiting for this. She had an intense longing just
               to hear his voice.</p>

            <p><q>Well</q> she said gaily, to herself, <q>If the Mountain won’t speak to Mahomet,
                  Mahomet will speak to the mountain</q>. And she lifted the receiver from her phone
               and called Edmund Blanton’s office. There was a pause and a voice answered:</p>

            <p><q>Edmund Blanton Productions</q>.</p>

            <p><q>May I speak to Mr. Blanton?</q></p>

            <p><q>Name, please?</q></p>

            <p><q>Miss Mercer</q>.</p>

            <p>She heard her name repeated by the henna haired stenographer, and a moment later,
               quite distinctly she heard Blanton’s voice. It sounded strained, harsh.</p>

            <p><q>Say, I’m busy</q>.</p>

            <pb n="4"/>

            <p>Then:</p>

            <p><q>Mr. Blanton’s busy. Any message?</q></p>

            <p>Jane could not answer. She put the receiver back on the hook and a frightened shadow
               crept into her eyes. She had the look of one listening to a faraway, warning voice.
               Suddenly she shivered; tried to smile and then --to carry the thing off nonchalantly.
               Why <choice>
                  <sic>should’nt</sic>
                  <corr>shouldn’t</corr>
               </choice> he be busy? All directors were.....She <choice>
                  <sic>should’nt</sic>
                  <corr>shouldn’t</corr>
               </choice> have called him.</p>

            <p>Questions, doubts, intolerable fears began to creep over Jane Mercer, gripping her
               heart with their clammy fingers.</p>

            <p>Why was his voice so strange--harsh?</p>

            <p>If he could tell his assistant he was busy, why could he not have said that to
               her?</p>

            <p>Why had he not telephoned as he had said he would do.</p>

            <p>Desperately she sought to reassure herself.</p>

            <p>Making mountains out of molehills!</p>

            <p>It was just his way. He was abrupt and short like that. Just his queer, dear way. She
               was too sensitive, placed too much importance on little things.</p>

            <p>She closed her eyes, a sick surge of terror enveloping her. She opened them wide and
               said aloud:</p>

            <p><q>Oh, Oh, I <choice>
                     <sic>must’nt</sic>
                     <corr>mustn’t</corr>
                  </choice> let things engulf me</q>.</p>

            <p>And then:</p>

            <p><q>What is wrong? What am I to do? What am I to do?</q></p>

            <p>Millie was tapping at the door. Millie <choice>
                  <sic>did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>didn’t</corr>
               </choice> look her usual self. What was the matter with Millie? What was the matter
               with everyone?</p>

            <pb n="5"/>

            <p><q>Ready?</q> asked Millie dully.</p>

            <p><q>Oh yes--Millie--I want to ask you something?</q></p>

            <p><q>Shoot</q>. The usually garrulous Millie was singularly reticent and dull.</p>

            <p><q>That woman--Sylvia Laurence--tell me about her</q>.</p>

            <p><q>You’ve been here six weeks now</q> said Millie evasively. <q>You ought to
               know</q>.</p>

            <p><q>But I don’t. You see, I’ve stuck rather closely to my work--I don’t know any of
                  the people here</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Say, we better hustle</q> said Millie with sudden briskness. <q><choice><sic>Theres</sic>
                     <corr>There’s</corr>
                  </choice> a crowd of extras and if we want a seat in the Cafe, we’d better get in
                  before they grab everything</q>.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">

            <p>The Studio Inn was in fact crowded, as Millie had surmised. A horde of extras filled
               the place to overflowing. Most of them were herded along one side of the restaurant,
               where they picked their meals from various dishes displayed and cooked on a long
               counter.</p>

            <p>In the main dining room every table was taken. The two girls paused by the door,
               looking for a place. At a round table, midway of <choice>
                  <sic>thw</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> room, a man stood up and waved to the girls. Millie said:</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Theres</sic>
                     <corr>There’s</corr>
                  </choice> a couple of seats over there. <choice>
                     <sic>Lets</sic>
                     <corr>Let’s</corr>
                  </choice> nab them</q>.</p>

            <p>When they reached the table, they found Harron with a couple of his gag men there.
               Extra seats were dragged to <choice>
                  <sic>th</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> table and Harron welcomed the girls boisterously.</p>

            <p><q>Sit here baby. All kinds of room</q>.</p>

            <p>Officiously he held the menu card before Jane.</p>

            <pb n="6"/>

            <p><q>Now what does the little girlie like?</q></p>

            <p>She loathed the way he called her by familiar and endearing names. The table was
               small, meant only for four. With six of them around it, they were crushed quite
               closely to <choice>
                  <sic>eavh</sic>
                  <corr>each</corr>
               </choice> other. Harron’s knee pressed heavily against Jane’s. He maneuvered his foot
               very insidiously about till it practically closed Jane’s.</p>
           
            <p>Millie ordered their lunch, and bade the waitress make it snappy. Jane was scarcely
               aware of Harron, for she was looking for Blanton. She had an aching longing to have
               even a glimpse of the man who had held her in his arms the night <choice>
                  <sic>befo e fore</sic>
                  <corr>before</corr>
               </choice>.</p>

            <p>Harron’s heavy face came in between her and the plate the waitress had set before
               her. His loose mouth hung slightly open. Under the cover of the cloth his hand stole
               to her knee, smoothed it with a slow, sensuous stroke, his eyes on Jane’s. She jerked
               back.</p>

            <p><q>Take your hand off my <choice><sic>inee</sic><corr>knee</corr></choice></q> she said. <q>How dare you? Millie--let’s go</q>.</p>

            <p>Barron burst out laughing.</p>

            <p><q>Whew, what a little sweet spitfire we are. No offense meant, baby</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I wish you’d call me by my right name</q> said Jane sharply.</p>

            <p><q>Boo! I call all the girls dearie and cutie and baby and sweetie, and none of them
                  mind when Daddy Harron puts his hand on their knee</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Well I do---</q> said Jane. <q>Millie, <choice>
                     <sic>are’nt</sic>
                     <corr>aren’t</corr>
                  </choice> you through yet?</q></p>

            <pb n="7"/>

            <p>Hurrying across the little park, Millie adjured her:</p>

            <p><q>Careful that you don’t offend Harron. He’s no end influential here</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I don’t even know he’s alive</q> said Jane.</p>

            <p><q>He’s alive all right--and Oh--don’t look back--walk quick as you can--he’s
                  following us</q>.</p>

            <p>He overtook them just as they were about to enter the Scenario building. He came
               between the two <choice>
                  <sic>girls</sic>
                  <corr>girls</corr>
               </choice> slipping a soft, flabby hand through the arm of each.</p>

            <p><q>How about a little party tonight?</q></p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Gee !</sic>
                     <corr>Gee!</corr>
                  </choice> I’m sorry</q> said Millie swiftly, <q>but Jane and I are all dated
                  up</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Uh-huh! How about letting me see some of your stories, girlie. Hear you <choice>
                     <sic>dosome</sic>
                     <corr>do some</corr>
                  </choice> pretty nice originals</q>.</p>

            <p>Slightly stirred, as always by any reference to her stories, Jane said:</p>

            <p><q>Oh they’re not much</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Let me see--judge for myself. Maybe we could do a bit of collaboration together?
                  I’m in the market for some good old fashioned slush. Got it?</q></p>

            <p><q>I don’t know---yes--maybe I have</q> said Jane. A fleck of color had come to her
               cheeks. A ray of hope lightened the heaviness of her heart. In a dim sort of way Jane
               realized that the Director was offering her a rare opportunity. Her mind however was
               in a state of chaos. <q>I’ll --pick out something and send it to you</q> she
               said.</p>

            <p><choice>
                  <sic>Shefreed</sic>
                  <corr>She freed</corr>
               </choice> her arm from Harron’s grasp and trying to smile said:</p>

            <p><q>Goodbye--and thanks very much</q>.</p>

            <pb n="8"/>

            <p>She had the sense of fleeing, though from what she could not have said. She wanted to
               get to her office--away <choice>
                  <sic>fro from</sic>
                  <corr>from</corr>
               </choice> all praying eyes--away even from Millie.</p>

            <p>She locked the door; sat down breathlessly. A confused medley of things swept in a
               tumultuous flood through her mind.</p>

            <p>Edmund Blanton! He had held her in his arms only the night before. As long as she
               lived she would feel the pressure of his warm lips on hers. She visualized his eyes
               gleaming tenderly at her in the semi light of the car. Why had he not
               telephoned?</p>

            <p>Martin Harron! A big director, in spite of his odious character. A chance to have her
               name on the screen---to become at last a real scenario writer.</p>

            <p>Why had not Blanton telephoned?</p>

            <p>What had she done to offend him?</p>

            <p>Sylvia---Sylvia --Sylvia Laurence. Was she the same Sylvia whose name the woman at
               the author’s club had <choice>
                  <sic>mwntioned</sic>
                  <corr>mentioned</corr>
               </choice> so meaningly. What was she to Edmund Blanton? Why had the mere mention of
               her name so startled and changed him?</p>

            <p>LOVE IS A TORMENT!</p>

            <p>Love did not make life joyful.</p>

            <p>Bliss was illusory!</p>

            <p>She must see him. She must know the truth! She must demand a reason for his strange
               treatment of her. She had the right to know. He had given her that right when he had
               held her in his arms and told her that he loved her.</p>

            <p>Her heart was aflame; her mind filled with a hungry <pb n="9"/> desolation.</p>

            <p>Now she was crushing her hat on her head again, touching her eyes--there were no
               tears--her lips with her little handkerchief; glancing even, wide-eyed at the unhappy
               young face in the little mirror; unlocking the door and out into the long cool
               hall.</p>

            <p>Jane was running across the studio lot. She did not mind who might see her as she
               passed. Down the main avenue, through several little lanes, past the Film Library,
               the Art Department, through the electric plant. A camera man called after her:</p>

            <p><q>Where are you going my pretty maid?</q></p>

            <p>Jane went on and on, cutting down the distance by going through two stages, where no
               longer the music from the miniature pianos on the sets caused her to stop, fascinated
               and thrilled, as she watched a picture in process of <q>shooting</q>.</p>

            <p>The henna haired stenographer in the outer office half rose in her seat as Jane came
               in. There were several people waiting to see Director Blanton, but Jane went swiftly
               by them, ignoring the stenographer, and making straight for Blanton’s door.</p>

            <p>The stenographer called sharply:</p>

            <p><q>You can’t go in there. Mr. Blanton said she <choice>
                     <sic>was’nt</sic>
                     <corr>wasn’t</corr>
                  </choice> to be disturbed by anyone or anything</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane paid no heed to her. Without knocking, she opened his door, stepped inside.</p>

            <p>In spite of the people waiting to see him in the outer office, Blanton was alone in
               his office, his two clinched hands resting on the blotter on the desk before him. He
                  <pb n="10"/> was staring out in some painful concentration when Jane burst in, and
               a spasm of pain twisted across his face and turned it grey.</p>

            <p>Her back to the door, breathlessly, Jane faced him.</p>

            <p><q>Now you are going to tell me why you are offended with me? What have I
               done?</q></p>

            <p><q>You’ve done nothing, Jane</q> he said hoarsely. <q><choice><sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> I--who am to blame</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Blame--for what?</q></p>

            <p><q>For what happened last night</q> he replied in a low voice.</p>

            <p><q>You <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> mean it?</q> she asked in an agonized whisper.</p>

            <p><q>I had no right to mean it</q> he said hoarsely.</p>

            <p>After that there was a long pause, and Jane’s breath caught in a frightened sob. Her
               hand went to her throat, almost as though she held it there to control that
               insufferable lump that rose and threatened almost to choke her.</p>

            <p><q>I s-suppose</q> she said, speaking in short, jerky gasps--<q>this is an ordinary
                  thing --in your life---making love --to a girl and then hurting her cruelly. I’ve
                  heard of men like you----</q></p>

            <p>He groaned--made a motion as if to reach out to her; suddenly covered his face with
               his hands.</p>

            <p><q>Oh--Oh---</q></p>

            <p>Her face was tense, vivid with her emotions---the <choice>
                  <sic>anguis</sic>
                  <corr>anguish</corr>
               </choice> that wracked her. She put her two hands to either side her</p>

            <pb n="11"/>
            <note type="editorial">Page 11 and 12 are switched in original facsimile.</note>

            <p>face and stared down wildly at that bowed head.</p>

            <p>Someone knocked on the door. The stenographer thrust in her head, called:</p>

            <p><q>Miss Laurence waiting to see you Mr. Blanton</q>.</p>

            <p>Miss Laurence waited for no one; least of all for Edmund Blanton. She pushed by the
               office boy and stenographer and stepped into Blanton’s office. She was tall, very
               beautiful, with heavy lidded eyes, the <choice>
                  <sic>lashew</sic>
                  <corr>lashes</corr>
               </choice> of which <choice>
                  <sic>wwre</sic>
                  <corr>were</corr>
               </choice> thickly beaded. Behind that beaded fringe golden eyes gleamed with the
               dangerous light of a pythoness. Her every movement was the embodiment of studied
               grace--an insolent, arrogant grace. Beside this radiant star, Jane Mercer, with her
               flower like face, her slight long lissome limbs seemed strangely slight and
               pathetically young. The older woman’s glance swung from Blanton, now standing up, to
               Jane, her hand upon her desk, a stricken look on her face.</p>

            <p><q>I followed you across the lot, Miss Mercer. You see I know your name. You may as
                  well know mine. I’m Sylvia Laurence Blanton, and Edmund Blanton happens to be
                  my--husband</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane stared at the women. Her lips parted. She seemed to be seeing her as from some
               great distance--through a fog; yet the woman’s words had struck deep. Jane knew
               exactly what she had said--who was she? She was Edmund Blanton’s wife! What a
               joke---what a mad, fantastic joke! She tried to say something--to smile even; but it
               was a most tragic mockery of a smile.</p>

            <p>She went out blindly.</p>

            <pb n="12"/>

            <p>The man and the woman left in the office stared at each other. Then the woman began
               to laugh softly.</p>

            <p><q>So-o, we’ve got a sweetie at least, have we!</q></p>

            <p>Her mocking laughter rose triumphantly. With a half suppressed oath, Blanton seized
               her by the arm, roughly swung her away from the <choice>
                  <sic>doow</sic>
                  <corr>door</corr>
               </choice>, jerked it open.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>He tried to pick up Jane’s trail--to overtake her. He saw ahead the flicker of her
               pink smock and he hurried down the little alley between stage D and dressing rooms,
               stumbling over pulleys and waving aside and almost knocking over a stage carpenter who
               tried to speak to him.</p>

            <p>At the back of an old cutting room he came upon Jane. She was standing against the
               wall, a dazed look on her face--almost as if she did not know where she was or what
               she was doing. There was something pitifully distraught about her expression--as if
               the sensitive fibre of her mind had momentarily been shattered.</p>

            <p>He did not know what he was saying to her. The words poured out in a torrential
               disjointed stream--bitten off--flowing on again--and again.</p>

            <p><q>Jane--listen to me. Jane! For God’s sake try and believe the best you can of
                  me........ I know I’ve been a dog to hurt you like this...........I never meant to
                  hurt you, my little Jane. I swear that to you. I only wanted to help you......to
                  take care of you....to watch over and cherish you. Jane---I <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> mean to injure you.....my poor little one....I would sooner kill myself
                  than cause you a single pang</q>....</p>

            <pb n="13"/>

            <p>As he spoke she moved her head from side to side, as if trying to avoid meeting that
               agonizing, imploring gaze.</p>

            <p><q>Jane, you see, that woman... there’s much to explain. We <choice>
                     <sic>have’nt</sic>
                     <corr>haven’t</corr>
                  </choice> lived together for seven years. She belongs to a man named Chris
                  Cleveland, an actor. She’s belonged to a dozen men. She’s absolutely nothing to
                  me. She cares nothing about me. Never has. Her action is merely that of a dog in a
                  manger---blackmail......so she can control and use me for her own ends. She’s been
                  living with Cleveland for <choice>
                     <sic>nea ly</sic>
                     <corr>nearly</corr>
                  </choice> a year and expected to marry him when her contract with Filmo expired.
                  Oh don’t you see, dear---it was all a matter of a Movie contract. Not uncommon in
                  Hollywood. I agreed not to divorce her---I signed an agreement to that effect ---I
                  was not to divorce her till the expiration of the contract. As it <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> matter to me what she did, where she went, who she lived with. I had no
                  use for her or any other woman in the world, until <emph>you</emph> came into my
                  life--you, Jane--my little Darling, whom I have so terribly hurt....
                     <emph>Dear</emph>---I <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> realize what I was doing--<choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> realize what it would lead to. I should have waited until I was free
                  before I spoke to you. Jane---when love comes to us we cannot muffle it, can we,
                  my dearest little one? Now I know I can never give you up. You’re the only thing
                  in the world I have ever loved. I’m going to take you away from all this, Jane.
                  We’ll go away together--escape from the shackles of
                  convention--contracts---everything--just you and I, Jane!</q></p>

            <p>In a voice that seemed to come from some <pb n="14"/> unknown depths within her, Jane
               replied:</p>

            <p><q>We could not escape --from ourselves!</q></p>

            <p><q>We <choice>
                     <sic>would’nt</sic>
                     <corr>wouldn’t</corr>
                  </choice> need to, darling--we’d be always together---we’d go away---</q></p>

            <p>Jane said brokenly:</p>

            <p><q>I --<choice>
                     <sic>could’nt</sic>
                     <corr>couldn’t</corr>
                  </choice> do anything like that, Mr. Blanton</q>.</p>

            <p>Someone was calling her name, halooing it across the lot.</p>
            
            <p><q>Jane! Jane!</q></p>

            <p>Millie had found Jane at last. She rushed up to her, interposed herself rudely
               between Jane and Blanton.</p>

            <p><q>Mr. Blanton</q> she said--<q>Leave Jane to me. Suppose someone passes this
                  way---it’ll be all over the lot. She’ll lose her reputation--</q></p>

            <p>Blanton said hoarsely.</p>

            <p><q>Look here, Millie--I’ll get my car. We’ll take Jane home, and we’ll talk and plan
                  it all out there</q>.</p>

            <p><q>No <emph>sir</emph>-- Jane’s going with me. I’ve got my flivver right here and I
                  got the day off especially. I was expecting something like this</q>.</p>

            <p>She was leading Jane along, her arm about her. Her own shabby little Ford was parked
               only a short distance away. Blanton followed. He tried to come to the other side of
               Jane, but Millie kept her close to the wall of the buildings. He scarcely knew what
               he was saying or doing. When Millie helped Jane into her car, Blanton got on the
               running board.</p>

            <p><q>You can’t take her away like this. I’ve not told her half--I must
               explain----</q></p>

            <pb n="15"/>

            <p>Millie stepped on the starter. The car roared.</p>

            <p><q>Get off the car, will you</q> she said, and then as she caught a glimpse of the
               man’s face, she added:</p>

            <p><q>Ah, be a sport, Mr. Blanton. Let me get her home; then you can figure out some way
                  out of this mess</q>.</p>

            <p><q>All right</q> he said. <q>Take her then. I’ll follow. I’ll be <choice>
                     <sic>therr</sic>
                     <corr>there</corr>
                  </choice> probably ahead of you---</q></p>

            <p>He tried to entrap Jane’s gaze. She was looking straight before her.</p>

            <p><q>Jane---Jane---</q> he said, in a <choice>
                  <sic>,muffled</sic>
                  <corr>muffled</corr>
               </choice> voice.</p>

            <p>The car moved out along the sunny roads of Filmo city.</p>

            <pb n="16"/>

         </div>

         <div type="chapter">

            <head>Chapter XI.</head>

            <p>There was just one light going in the little living room where Joybelle and Millie
               Cohen kept a sort of faithful vigil. The room was in darkness on purpose, so the two
               girls could see through the blind the man on the curb below. He had been there for
               hours, looking up at Jane’s apartment. He wrote numerous notes--wild, passionate,
               imploring appeals and sent them across by the sombre faced chauffeur.</p>

            <p>Blanton left his post long enough to go to the corner drug store again to call up the
               little flat. Joybelle answered.</p>

            <p><q>Ye-eh?</q></p>

            <p><q>Mr. Blanton speaking. Will you let me---</q></p>

            <p><q>I won’t let you anything</q> said Joybelle viciously. <q>You got your nerve to
                  stand outside our house. I know all about what you done to my friend</q>.</p>

            <p>Millie interposed.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t talk to him like that. Let me speak to him</q>.</p>

            <p>Joybelle relinquished the telephone.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> Millie speaking Mr. Blanton</q> said Jane’s friend.</p>

            <p><q>Millie, is it true that Jane is very ill?</q></p>

            <p><q>She’s ill</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Where is she?</q></p>

            <p><q>She’s in bed. Doctor says she’s got to stay there</q>.</p>

            <pb n="17"/>

            <p>He began to plead for permission to come over. Said he would do nothing to upset <choice>
                  <sic>ordisturb</sic>
                  <corr>or disturb</corr>
               </choice> her--just wanted to be near Jane. Millie was touched:</p>

            <p><q>I’m sorry, but the doctor says <choice>
                     <sic>its</sic>
                     <corr>it’s</corr>
                  </choice> best for her not to see anyone; besides it’d only make things
               worse</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Who’s her doctor. I’ll see him at once</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t butt in. She’s asleep anyway--he gave her some dope to quiet her---she <choice>
                     <sic>waz</sic>
                     <corr>was</corr>
                  </choice> nearly off her head, poor kid---</q><note type="editorial">Ending
                  quotation mark missing in original.</note></p>

            <p><q>Millie, if I send some letters to her, will you promise to deliver them?</q></p>

            <p><q>No. If you keep on like this we’re going to wire her folks</q>.</p>

            <p><q>For God’s sakes don’t do that</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Well, you know how it is. She’ll never be able to go back to work with you there.
                  She’ll lose her job</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Not on my account. Listen to what I am saying:</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes, Mr. Blanton</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Tell her, as soon as she’s able to understand--that I’m going away---off somewhere
                  on location. Tell her not to worry--that everything will work out right.
                     <emph>I’ll make it</emph>!</q></p>

            <p>As Millie turned from the <choice>
                  <sic>’phone</sic>
                  <corr>phone</corr>
               </choice> she was crying.</p>

            <p><q>I’m sorry for him</q> she said.</p>

            <p><q>Well, I’m not</q> said Joybelle emphatically. <q>I’m not sorry for any married man
                  that chases after a young girl</q>.</p>

            <p><q>There were mitigating circumstances in his case</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Hmph! He knew darned well he was tied up. I get sick and tired of married men
                  trailing after kids like Jane</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Well you know how it is---he was that woman’s <pb n="18"/> Director and there was
                  a contract and all the rest. Besides you know how it is in Hollywood. Everybody
                  anybody’s wife or husband. <choice>
                     <sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> the very limit here. No one knows who’s who’s wife</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane was coming out of a dreamless peace to a dim world of dizzy chaos. Things seemed
               to move around the room like the fantastic figures of a cubistic drawing. Nothing was stable--everything slipping and sliding. She felt as if
               she were drowning--sinking, and she <choice>
                  <sic>calld</sic>
                  <corr>called</corr>
               </choice>:</p>

            <p><q>Joybelle!</q></p>

            <p>Presently she heard Joybelle’s voice above her.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> the dope. I’ll make a cup of black coffee</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane said drowsily:</p>

            <p><q>I’m not <emph>dying</emph></q>. She made an effort <choice>
                  <sic>tosmile</sic>
                  <corr>to smile</corr>
               </choice>.</p>

            <p><q>Course you’re not. The idea!</q> said Joybelle roughly. <q>When one’s young they
                  don’t die from any love bunk, believe me</q>.</p>

            <p><q>We have to go on living</q> said Jane.</p>

            <p>Millie said gently:</p>

            <p><q>You’ve had a shock, dear. It’ll all come out right</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Sure it will</q> agreed Joybelle. <q>You’ll forget all about the darned thing
                  soon. <choice>
                     <sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> just part of the days work. I’d like a dollar <choice>
                     <sic>eveey</sic>
                     <corr>every</corr>
                  </choice> time I been crossed in love. Why one fellow threw me down so hard I
                  nearly jumped off the roof, but <pb n="19"/> just as I was about to do it, I says
                  to myself: ’<choice>
                     <sic>Whats</sic>
                     <corr>What’s</corr>
                  </choice> the use? <choice>
                     <sic>Theres</sic>
                     <corr>There’s</corr>
                  </choice> other fish in the sea’, and <choice>
                     <sic>thats</sic>
                     <corr>that’s</corr>
                  </choice> how it turned out, <choice>
                     <sic>beca because</sic>
                     <corr>because</corr>
                  </choice> it <choice>
                     <sic>was’nt</sic>
                     <corr>wasn’t</corr>
                  </choice> no more <choice>
                     <sic>t an</sic>
                     <corr>than</corr>
                  </choice> a week before I met Jim Nolan, and I <choice>
                     <sic>would’nt</sic>
                     <corr>wouldn’t</corr>
                  </choice> change Jim’s little finger for the whole of the hide of the one I was
                  going to throw myself from the roof for</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I think we’re talking too much</q> said Millie.</p>

            <p><q>Oh are you here, Millie?</q> asked Jane weakly.</p>

            <p><q>You betchu. Mother telephoned and I told her you were a bit under the weather, and
                  she says for me to bring you over there and that she’ll cook you a real kosher
                  dinner. Wait till you taste gefelte fish</q>.</p>

            <p>A smile that was strangely piteous came across the girl’s woeful young face. A single
               tear brimmed over. She put out her hand weakly, searching for Millie’s.</p>

            <p><q>How good you are to me!</q> she said faintly, and buried her face in the
               pillow.</p>





            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
