<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MovieRelatives1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Movie Relatives</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno type="UofC">CU112046766</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <!--Include an msIdentifier if this text is from an archive-->
               <!--                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                        <idno>10.2</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>-->
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl><title level="a">Movie Relatives</title></bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at University of
                           Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with
                                a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-11-02" status="published">Edited name tags so that periods are outside. Periods and &#46; would results as warnings.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-24" status="published">Published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-19" status="inProgress">Transcribing.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-01-05" status="empty">Adding document from 2023 Calgary
            Transcribe-a-thon.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:MovieRelatives1">
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <div>

            <p><q>Movie relatives</q>, said a certain Motion Picture executive, <q>are like our
                  skin. They stick to us</q>.</p>

            <p>Probably fifty percent of the <choice>
                  <sic>employes</sic>
                  <corr>employees</corr>
               </choice> on a Motion picture studio lot are relatives of some executive or official
               in power. The other fifty percent <choice>
                  <sic>onclude</sic>
                  <corr>include</corr>
               </choice> among them the friends and friends of friends. It is in <choice>
                  <sic>facta</sic>
                  <corr>fact a</corr>
               </choice> rare achievement to obtain a position in a studio without the necessary
                  <q>pull</q> or relationship. To start from the top. The producers themselves seem
               to be possessed of an inexhaustible horde of relations far and near. It is but human
               nature to take care of <choice>
                  <sic>ones</sic>
                  <corr>one’s</corr>
               </choice> own first, and the Movie producer is <choice>
                  <sic>certaily certainly</sic>
                  <corr>certainly</corr>
               </choice> believes in the old adage that <q>Charity begins at home</q>. With a large
               and free hand he doles out charity in the shape of sinecure jobs and otherwise to his
               relatives.</p>

            <p>At Universal, it is said of the Laemmle relatives that they are like Heinz Pickles.
               There are fifty seven (and more) varieties, all of them edible.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:CL3">Carl Jr</name>. or <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> as he
               called by everyone naturally tops the list. <del>He is a good looking youngster of
                  nineteen or twenty</del> He is also known as <name ref="pers:CL3">the Crown
                  Prince</name>, and <name ref="pers:CL3">the Man who smiles</name>. <del><name
                     ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name>’s smile in fact</del>
               <del>He is nice looking youngster</del> He is a slight, delicate boy of nineteen or
               twenty, undersized, nervous, excitable. <del>On his slender shoulders</del>
               <del>He never</del> He does everything on the run. <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name>
               does not know what it means to mark time. He is always hurrying--whether at work or
               at play. <del>Considering the fact that nearly every one on the Un</del>
               <del>One hears <unclear>paens</unclear></del> One must take with a pinch of salt all
               the extravagant <choice>
                  <sic>paens</sic>
                  <corr>paeans</corr>
               </choice> of praise showered upon this youngster. No grown man could</p>

            <pb n="2"/>

            <p><q>Movie relatives</q> are like our di</p>

            <pb n="3"/>

            <p>accomplish so much <choice>
                  <sic>ir</sic>
                  <corr>or</corr>
               </choice> be so talented as the <choice>
                  <sic>Puvlicity</sic>
                  <corr>Publicity</corr>
               </choice> department of Universal would have the world believe <name ref="pers:CL3"
                  >Junior</name> is. To do him justice he is not to blame for all this ridiculous
               adulation and servile flatter, <del>and although</del> Everyone kowtowing and
               scraping and smooching. His presence on a set <choice>
                  <sic>createst</sic>
                  <corr>creates</corr>
               </choice> a stir of <choice>
                  <sic>excitemeng</sic>
                  <corr>excitement</corr>
               </choice>. Young men and girls turn pale at his approach, get heart failure at a
                     <del><gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="deleted"/></del> if they offend him,
               are raised to the Seventh heaven by a word of praise or a smile from <name
                  ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name>. <del>This and that</del></p>

            <p>As a matter of <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name>
               <del>he’s an average brain is an ordinary son of</del> could not <del>but be
                  above</del></p>

            <p>He has a good brain---restless, imaginative, even creative, shrewd. Considering the
               attention paid him ever since he was a boy, he is far less arrogant than might be
               expected in a youth of his age. In fact it is doubtful whether his head is <choice>
                  <sic>turne</sic>
                  <corr>turned</corr>
               </choice> by all this flattery. He is just keen enough to weight it at its face
               value. In fine he is the son of <name ref="pers:CL4">old Carl</name>, a rare and
               unique soul in every sense of the world. It is not astonishing that <name
                  ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> has the restless urge to do many things of a creative
               sort. He wants to write. He has a secret hankering to act. He plays at supervising;
               he is going to direct. He balks a bit at taking on the General managership of <choice>
                  <sic>Univerdal</sic>
                  <corr>Universal</corr>
               </choice> City, but he has no hesitation in telling the various general managers
               where they get off at. <del>He has one of the keenest mov</del> He has a surefire box
               office sense of the motion picture values of a story. He can write a bit. If his mind
               were not so diverted by the thousand and one distractions of the Universal lot,
                  <del>ii</del> this talent might be developed into something quite worth while. But
                  <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> is playing the <choice>
                  <sic>dilletante</sic>
                  <corr>dilettante</corr>
               </choice>. He’s a little afraid of himself. He writes the idea of a story down---a
               torrent of praise issues from all sides. He knows <choice>
                  <sic>th that</sic>
                  <corr>that</corr>
               </choice> praise is not altogether sincere. He’d give anything for <pb n="4"/> an
               honest sizing up of his writing. On the other hand he is aware that many who praise
               him have their tongues in their cheeks, and that others are running around with tales
               that this and that story that <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> is credited with
               writing was written for him by such and such a person. <del>As a matter of fact</del>
               His Collegian stories for instance. The idea actually emanated from <name
                  ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name>, and I myself read his first five stories. They were
               briefly sketched out, but the stuff was in them. Later, other writers worked on his
               scripts, but he has to be credited with originating the idea and writing at least the
               outline of the stories. So much for his writing. He is popular as a supervisor. Why
               not? Any picture under the supervision of <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> means
                  <del>that <gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="deleted"/></del> the director may
               go as far as he likes, so far as expense is concerned. Moreover, every aid is given.
               A picture supervised by <name ref="pers:CL3">Laemmle junior</name> simply has got to
               be boosted on all sides. <del><name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name></del> He really
               likes to work. At first it was thought he would just play around at Universal. Not
               so. The kid rolled up his sleeves and got literally down to work. Not but what he
                  <del>has</del> quite agrees with the old adage that all work and no play makes
               Jack a dull boy. <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name>
               <choice>
                  <sic>does’nt</sic>
                  <corr>doesn’t</corr>
               </choice> intend to be dull. Therefore he plays when he feels like it. He is a poker
               fiend. He likes the ladies. He has his <del>sprees and</del> favorite friends and is
               off on sprees with them, and taken all in all he’s a regular and human sort of kid.
               Not at all the phenomenal genius they tell him he is; <choice>
                  <sic>buta</sic>
                  <corr>but a</corr>
               </choice> likeable, <choice>
                  <sic>goodlooking</sic>
                  <corr>good-looking</corr>
               </choice> fun loving youngster, whose greatest handicap and greatest asset is that he
               is the son of <name ref="pers:CL4">Carl Laemmle</name>.</p>

            <p>I remember a few years ago---three--- en route to the coast with <name ref="pers:CL4"
                  >Mr. Laemmle</name>, that he expressed some concern as to his boy’s future. He
               said that for several years both of his children, <pb n="5"/><name ref="pers:RB1"
                  >Rosabelle</name> and <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> had been brought up to
               know every angle of the Motion Picture business.</p>


            <p><q>Every night</q> said <name ref="pers:CL4">Karl Laemmle</name>, <q><choice><sic>Itake</sic>
                     <corr>I take</corr>
                  </choice> home with me, all the letters, memos &amp;c. and <choice>
                     <sic>mychildren</sic>
                     <corr>my children</corr>
                  </choice> read and go over them with me. I don’t know what I’d do without their
                  advice</q>.</p>

            <p>At that time <name ref="pers:CL3">Junior</name> was about sixteen and <name
                  ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name> a few years older. It has been said that Rosabelle
               has one of the sanest most level heads of any girl<del>s</del> in Hollywood. She
               discounts all the adulation and fame and attention showered upon her; <del>takes
                  people at their</del> has a disconcerting gift of <choice>
                  <sic>sixing</sic>
                  <corr>sizing</corr>
               </choice> people up, and comes to <choice>
                  <sic>she</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> keenest shrewdest <choice>
                  <sic>conclusions.</sic>
                  <corr>conclusions</corr>
               </choice> which she passes along to her famous father. Remaining in the background,
               seemingly content with the social life, a charming chatelaine of their magnificent
               home ---a domain of the Spanish sort--- <name ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name>
               <del>knew</del> is the <choice>
                  <sic>silen</sic>
                  <corr>silent</corr>
               </choice> but very significant partner of the Universal. <name ref="pers:CL4">Carl
                  Laemmle</name> has hundreds of advisers and important people in executive <choice>
                  <sic>positoobs bu</sic>
                  <corr>positions but</corr>
               </choice> he values most and goes by the advice of the pretty, quiet, almost
               <choice><sic>diffedent</sic><corr>diffident</corr></choice> little personage who so efficiently runs his home--and his business.</p>

            <p>There is something <choice>
                  <sic>aomost</sic>
                  <corr>almost</corr>
               </choice> pathetic and touching in his reliance upon his daughter’s <choice>
                  <sic>judgment</sic>
                  <corr>judgement</corr>
               </choice>. Many stories are told in regard to <name ref="pers:CL4">Carl
                  Laemmle</name>’s reference to <name ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name>’s opinion.
                  <del>Pronable</del> Once when a story by a famous author was recommended, it was
               rejected by <name ref="pers:CL4">Mr. Laemmle</name> as <q>Out. Can’t be much. <name
                     ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name> never heard of it</q>. After that the story
               department always (in whispers) would say: <q>So you suppose <name ref="pers:RB1"
                     >Rosabelle</name> ever heard of it?</q></p>

            <p><name ref="pers:CL4">Laemmle</name>’s nephews are reputed to be legion. <choice>
                  <sic>Thats</sic>
                  <corr>That’s</corr>
               </choice> a myth however. He only has three or four. There is <name ref="pers:EL1"
                  >Eddie</name>, the <name ref="pers:EL1">Eddie Laemmle</name>, son of his oldest
               brother, who has had to fight every <pb n="6"/>inch of the way up to his present
               secure position as one of the ablest directors of <choice>
                  <sic>Univ rsal</sic>
                  <corr>Universal</corr>
               </choice>. No sinecure job was handed to<name ref="pers:EL1">Eddie</name>. <del>He
                  had</del>
               <name ref="pers:CL4">Uncle</name> gave him a place at Universal, it is true, but
               smaller pay than any other man doing the same work. On and on he plodded, working
               against serious odds, and presently the trade became aware that pictures directed by
                  <name ref="pers:EL1">Eddie Laemmle</name> were always sellers. <name
                  ref="pers:EL1">Eddie</name> had hit the box office.<del>oth</del> They who had
               laughed at him laughed with him. They who had doubted and scouted him, now began to
               regard with respect the little plucky nephew of <name ref="pers:CL4">Uncle
                  Carl</name>.</p>

            <p><del>Another nep</del></p>

            <p>Then there are <del><name ref="pers:EL2">Ernst</name></del> the brothers <name
                  ref="pers:EL2">Ernst</name> and Walter Laemmle, sons of another brother of <name
                  ref="pers:CL4">Carl Laemmle</name>. They have <del>a t</del> the thick accent of
               the homeland, <choice>
                  <sic>nd</sic>
                  <corr>and</corr>
               </choice> quite the old world <choice>
                  <sic>manner</sic>
                  <corr>manner.</corr>
               </choice> Heels clicking together, as they bow from the waist down. Well educated,
               cleancut nice boys, with considerable talent. Of Walter little <choice>
                  <sic>caj</sic>
                  <corr>can</corr>
               </choice> be said, as he was <del>only a li</del> such a short while in this country. <choice>
                  <sic>Etnst</sic>
                  <corr><name ref="pers:EL2">Ernst</name></corr>
               </choice> was beginning to make a real place for himself. <del>He belonged to t
                  at</del> A protege and <del>pupil of</del> disciple of <name ref="pers:EL3"
                  >Lubitsch</name>, <name ref="pers:EL2">Ernst</name> was forging ahead on his own
               account, being entrusted with the directing of some of the best of the Universal
               pictures. <del>But Etn</del> Then one day <name ref="pers:EL2">Ernst</name> was in a
               bad automobile accident. For months he was confined to the hospital, his hand
               amputated and injured in other parts. A few months ago <name ref="pers:EL2"
                  >Ernst</name> returned to his native</p>

            <p>There are <name ref="pers:WW3">Willie</name> and <name ref="pers:RW1">Bob
                  Wyler</name>. Nephews once or twice removed. <name ref="pers:WW3">Willie</name>
               is a director and a good one. <name ref="pers:RW1">Bob</name> is a supervisor. If <choice>
                  <sic>theres</sic>
                  <corr>there’s</corr>
               </choice> a touch of genius and madness in any member of the family, it comes out in
                  <name ref="pers:RW1">Bob</name>. From the time when he delivered the baccalaureate
               sermon in his graduating year at the Sorbonne in Paris, <name ref="pers:RW1"
                  >Bob</name> has been leaping up at the stars.</p>

            <pb n="7"/>

            <p><del>He is</del></p>

            <p>Still in his early twenties, he has done some outstanding work as a supervisor, but
               his brain sees <choice>
                  <sic>thes</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> plots <del>and</del> for stories. He will tramp up and down like some
               driven thing. <choice>
                  <sic>his</sic>
                  <corr>His</corr>
               </choice> hands <choice>
                  <sic>gesticulatong</sic>
                  <corr>gesticulating</corr>
               </choice>, as story after story <choice>
                  <sic>poure</sic>
                  <corr>pour</corr>
               </choice> from him. The <del>crying</del> cruel part is his inability to set down in
               writing what is in his head. Or rather not inability, but <emph>fear</emph>. He is
               afraid of his own power. He can tell a story, so he says, but he cannot write it.
               Some day, he will take pen in hand and write with letters offire. He is like a
               highbred colt straining at his leash.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:PK1">Paul Kohner</name> is <choice>
                  <sic>generall</sic>
                  <corr>general</corr>
               </choice> reputed to be a relative, but <name ref="pers:PK1">Paul</name> is merely a
               very good friend of the family. <name ref="pers:CL4">Mr. Laemmle</name> brought this
               young executive to Universal from his home <choice>
                  <sic>in</sic>
                  <corr>and</corr>
               </choice>
               <name ref="pers:PK1">Kohner</name> acquired an extraordinary influence over <name
                  ref="pers:CL4">Mr. Laemmle</name> from the first, and has been held in the highest
               esteem by him. <name ref="pers:PK1">Kohner</name> has been advanced from one position
               to another, till at the present time he is in charge of all Universal’s affairs in
               Europe. He is engaged to be married to Universal’s lovely young star, <name
                  ref="pers:MP3">Mary Philbin</name>.</p>

            <p>The head of the casting office is a Laemmle relative. He is Victor Nordlinger.</p>

            <p>One must not forget the Stern brothers, or the Gold Dust Twins as they have been
               nicknamed. They are brothers-in-law to <name ref="pers:CL4">Mr. Laemmle</name>, and
               large stockholders in the Universal. They are never <del><unclear reason="illegible"
                     >l</unclear></del> far from <name ref="pers:CL4">the old General</name>, and
               their sister Mrs. Fleckles has long been the chaperon and favorite aunt of <name
                  ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name>, and has given her <add place="above">the
                  motherless girl</add> a mother’s care.</p>

            <pb n="8"/>

            <p><name ref="pers:CL5">Beth Laemmle</name> might be called the Cinderella of the
               family. <name ref="pers:CL5">Beth</name> is the daughter of <name ref="pers:CL4">Carl
                  Laemmle</name>’s oldest brother. She lives with her Irish mother and Jewish father
               in a tiny little very humble bungalow adjoining the Universal lot. <name
                  ref="pers:CL5">Beth</name> is pretty and blonde, with a little snub nose and
               bluebell eyes. <del>They</del>
               <del>She is a dancer by profession, but although</del> Although a <q><foreign
                     xml:lang="fr">Premiere danseuse</foreign></q> by profession, she lives the life
               of a little retiring nun, and is very much under the <del>shade</del> patriarchal
               shadow of the Laemmle millions, in which neither she nor her parents share. <del>Of
                  cour</del> The family have always dependents <choice>
                  <sic>upo</sic>
                  <corr>upon</corr>
               </choice> the bounty of <choice>
                  <sic>Uncle C Carl</sic>
                  <corr><name ref="pers:CL4">Uncle Carl</name></corr>
               </choice>. <del>Perhaps Uncle</del> The Laemmle relatives are disposed to look
               somewhat askance at this branch. <name ref="pers:CL5">Beth Laemmle</name> is the
               queer little unwanted duckling that somehow hatched out under the Laemmle wing.
                  <del>She</del> Her mother, a quiet, retiring sort of woman keeps in the silent
               background. Her father has for a number of years been blind. <name ref="pers:CL5"
                  >Beth Laemmle</name> presents a rather extraordinary contrast to the <del><unclear
                     reason="illegible"> affluent</unclear></del>
               <name ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name>
               <name ref="pers:CL5">Beth Laemmle</name> in her <choice>
                  <sic>h mble</sic>
                  <corr>humble</corr>
               </choice> little cottage and her made over dresses presents an odd contrast to <name
                  ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name> in the gorgeous manor house in <choice>
                  <sic>Benedicti</sic>
                  <corr>Benedict</corr>
               </choice> Canyon. <name ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name>, with her dozens of <choice>
                  <sic>ser vants</sic>
                  <corr>servants</corr>
               </choice>, the score of young men, with one eye on <name ref="pers:CL4">papa
                  Laemmle</name>, and one on <name ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name>, dancing in
               attendance. <name ref="pers:RB1">Rosabelle</name> with her <del><gap quantity="1"
                     unit="char" reason="deleted"/></del> sport roadsters and limousines, her
               chauffeurs and maids and her girl friends whose father’s millions match those of
                  <name ref="pers:CL4">Uncle Carl</name>’s. <name ref="pers:CL5">Beth
               Laemmle</name>, on the other hand, cooks and keeps house for her parents, between the
               periods when she can get a <del>bit of</del> an engagement as a dancer or if <choice>
                  <sic>fifen</sic>
                  <corr>given</corr>
               </choice> a <q>bit</q> to do in a Universal picture.</p>


            <pb n="9"/>

            <p>The Laemmle family</p>

            <pb n="10"/>

            <p>If <name ref="pers:CL5">Beth Laemmle</name> had not been born a Laemmle it is quite <choice>
                  <sic>possib;e</sic>
                  <corr>possible</corr>
               </choice> that she might have gone far in her chosen profession. Not only is quaintly
               pretty, but she is a charming dancer. Someone seeing her dance, exclaimed: <q>The
                  trouble with that girl lies in the fact that she <choice>
                     <sic>does’nt</sic>
                     <corr>doesn’t</corr>
                  </choice> let herself go. She’s repressing the best in herself. She <choice>
                     <sic>s eems</sic>
                     <corr>seems</corr>
                  </choice> to be afraid of herself. She out to kick loose</q>. Maybe someday <name
                  ref="pers:CL4">Uncle Carl</name>’s little Jewish Irish rose of a niece will
                  <q>kick loose</q>. Tis a consummation devoutly to be wished. Incidentally, <name
                  ref="pers:CL5">Beth Laemmle</name> is a half sister of <name ref="pers:EL1">Eddie
                  Laemmle</name>, but <choice>
                  <sic>theres</sic>
                  <corr>there’s</corr>
               </choice> no Irish in <name ref="pers:EL1">Eddie</name>. <del>In a rather shamefaced
                  way <name ref="pers:EL1">Eddie</name></del> In point of fact <name ref="pers:EL1"
                  >Eddie</name>
               <choice>
                  <sic>does’nt</sic>
                  <corr>doesn’t</corr>
               </choice> know whether to be ashamed or proud of his Irish relatives.</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p><del>On the</del> Metro Goldwyn lot</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>At Metro Goldwyn, where <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B. Mayer</name> rules the roost,
               the Mayer relatives are not very much in evidence. <del>It is true that several</del>
               A couple of nieces, a nephew or two, a brother and maybe a distant cousin or so hold
               their positions not so much by grace of <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B. Mayer</name>,
               but because of the merit of their work. <choice>
                  <sic>Truu</sic>
                  <corr>True</corr>
               </choice> not doubt, to start with the jobs were made for them. Why not? With <name
                  ref="pers:LM2">Uncle Louis B</name>. at the head of the big producing company, why <choice>
                  <sic>should.he</sic>
                  <corr>should he</corr>
               </choice> not give employment to his <q>poor relatives</q> as well as to strangers?
               However, <choice>
                  <sic>mo</sic>
                  <corr>no</corr>
               </choice> sinecure places were made for Mayer relatives. <del>Is stern</del>
               <del>With almost</del> No partiality; no favoritism In fact it is well known fact
               that a Mayer relative is expected to work harder for less pay than a stranger would
               receive.</p>

            <pb n="11"/>

            <p><del>If <name ref="pers:LM2">Mr. Mayer</name></del></p>

            <p><choice>
                  <sic>Al,ost</sic>
                  <corr>Almost</corr>
               </choice> grudgingly <name ref="pers:LM2">Mr Mayer</name> has given his relatives
               employment. He would prefer to keep the family off the lot. <del>He would glad</del>
               His generosity toward his relatives away from the studio lot is well known. <del>Not
                  only</del>
               <name ref="pers:LM2">Mr. Mayer</name> He and his wife and daughters are always
               devising ways and means of making his <choice>
                  <sic>relativew</sic>
                  <corr>relatives</corr>
               </choice> more comfortable, and of showering favors and gifts upon them. But as for
               jobs on the Metro lot. <choice>
                  <sic>Thats</sic>
                  <corr>That’s</corr>
               </choice> another matter---one that makes <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. shake
               his head. <name ref="pers:LM2">Mayer</name> is old fashioned in his ideas for his f
               As head <del>and</del> of the family, he governs all of the relatives with an almost
               military patriarchism. As chieftain of the clan he has a say in everything they do.
                  <del>The <gap quantity="1" unit="char" reason="deleted"/> must</del> He would
               prefer the women of his family to remain at home. Why should they go out work? What
               need of a career? He is able and willing to give them generous allowances. And as for
               marriage---<name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. will have something to say in the
               choice of their husbands. His displeasure is not something any of the family care to
               cultivate. When <name ref="pers:RC1">Ruth Cummings</name>, his niece, eloped with a
               good looking youngster, she returned to <choice>
                  <sic>facenot</sic>
                  <corr>face not</corr>
               </choice> the wrath of the cold and frozen ignoring of her uncle. Ruth was one member
               of the family who believed she could gang her ain gait. A girl of exceptional talent,
                  <del>social</del> mere social life did not appeal <choice>
                  <sic>tp</sic>
                  <corr>to</corr>
               </choice> her, and she grew restive under the too governing eye of her uncle.</p>

            <p>If <name ref="pers:RC1">Ruth</name> has made a reputation as one of the best title
               writers in the industry, it is not because of <choice>
                  <sic>anyboost</sic>
                  <corr>any boost</corr>
               </choice> or hoist she has had as the niece of <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B.
                  Mayer</name>, but in spite of that relationship. Her sister indeed---<name
                  ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi Cummings</name>--<pb n="12"/> has found the relationship
               almost a handicap. <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> is as pretty and peppy as a
               little gypsy,<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This is an offensive racial slur. Please see our <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note on language</ref>.</note> and she is wild to for a career on the spatage or in pictures.
               Easy---with her uncle President at Metro? Not by a long shot. <name ref="pers:MC4"
                  >Mitzi</name>, <choice>
                  <sic>thoufhn</sic>
                  <corr>though</corr>
               </choice> she has played in a score of pictures has never been allowed to get out of
               the extra rank. Smarting under what she imaged <choice>
                  <sic>wto</sic>
                  <corr>to</corr>
               </choice> be discrimination against her by supervisors and directors, <name
                  ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> sought other studios, applying for work over another
               name. Here she fared better, was even making a bit of headway, when--as always-- it
               would be discovered she was <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>’s niece. Then the
               word would go out:</p>

            <p><q>If she’s any good, why <choice>
                     <sic>does’nt</sic>
                     <corr>doesn’t</corr>
                  </choice> Metro give her a break</q>.</p>

            <p>Once at Universal, when she applied for a <choice>
                  <sic>c3rtain</sic>
                  <corr>certain</corr>
               </choice> part, she was met with this flat query from Henry Hennigson:</p>
            <p><q>We’ll give you work if Metro will take on <name ref="pers:CL5">Beth
                  Laemmle</name></q><note type="editorial">Ending quotation mark and ending
                  punctuation missing in original.</note></p>
            <p>In other words Universal were willing to swap a Laemmle for a Mayer.</p>

            <p>Finally dejected and disappointed, <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> gave over the
               unequal struggle. The studio had a <choice>
                  <sic>fasctinattin</sic>
                  <corr>fascination</corr>
               </choice> she could not resists. <del>Uncle was <gap quantity="1" unit="char"
                     reason="deleted"/> into</del> Her uncle’s face was set against her continuing
               to work as an extra. Inducements were offered <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name>---a
               tempting allowance, a trip abroad--what would you? <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name>
               replied with tears and a passionate insistence that they were trying to freeze her
               out. <del>The fin</del> A <choice>
                  <sic>compro mise</sic>
                  <corr>compromise</corr>
               </choice> resulted, with <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> given a secretarial
               position on the lot. <del>Out on mischief</del>
               <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name> released a sigh of relief. He hoped <name
                  ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> would now be satisfied. <pb n="13"/><del>In time the
                  kid</del>
               <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> who is something of a magnet so far as boys are
               concerned, would no doubt soon be married. <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. had
               her promise that she would not elope as her sister had done, and though he <choice>
                  <sic>did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>didn’t</corr>
               </choice> relish her working at Metro, still what could you do with a girl-creature
               who was three parts elf? <del><name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> satisfied-happy</del>
               <del>Not so you would notice it. She is the</del> The solution is not wholly a
               satisfactory <choice>
                  <sic>onr</sic>
                  <corr>one</corr>
               </choice>. It is quite possible that <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. did not
               take into consideration the reluctance of <choice>
                  <sic>dire tors</sic>
                  <corr>directors</corr>
               </choice> or scenario writers or executives to have as a secretary the niece of the
               President <del>Mit</del>
               <q>It makes me hot under the collar</q><note type="editorial">Missing beginning
                  quotation mark in original.</note> says <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name>, <q>to
                  see them lower their voices when I pass, or look at me askance. They think I’m a
                  sort of spy. That I’ll run and tittle tattle this or that to my uncle</q>.</p>

            <p>The angry tears sparkled in the girl’s bright eyes. <q>Oh well</q><note
                  type="editorial">Ending quotation mark missing in original.</note> she said,
               whistling to cover her feelings<choice>
                  <sic>’’</sic>
                  <corr>.</corr>
               </choice>
               <q>I should worry. <choice>
                     <sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice>all in the day’s work</q>.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:JC3">Jack Cummings</name>, brother of <name ref="pers:RC1">Ruth
                  Cummings</name> and <name ref="pers:MC4">Mitzi</name> and nephew of <name
                  ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. possesses more than the average amount of the
               family brains. <name ref="pers:JC3">Jack</name> is in charge of one of the <choice>
                  <sic>unites</sic>
                  <corr>units</corr>
               </choice> on the Metro lot. It has not been all easy sliding for <name ref="pers:JC3"
                  >Jack</name>. He has had to watch his step, and guard his tongue. Someone once
               remarked that if <name ref="pers:JC3">Jack</name> made any false mistakes, tried to
               Ritz anyone on the lot, <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. would be the first to
               have his head off. He is a well <choice>
                  <sic>liked.</sic>
                  <corr>liked,</corr>
               </choice> sunny natured young <choice>
                  <sic>fellow.</sic>
                  <corr>fellow</corr>
               </choice> with a sense of humor and an ability to take punishment.</p>

            <p><del>The Cummings family</del></p>

            <pb n="14"/>

            <p>The mother of these up and coming young Cummings is the only sister of <name
                  ref="pers:LM2">Louis B. Mayer</name>. His fondness for her, his generosity and
               kindness has made him more or less of an idol to Mrs. Cummings. She has no hesitation
               in expatiating upon all he has done for her.</p>

            <p><q>My brother gave me this beautiful house---everything we have. <del>His wife Mrs.
                     Mayer</del> My brother’s wife is the noblest and sweetest woman in the world.
                  She can’t do enough for me. My brother’s daughters---have you met them? Ah! <choice>
                     <sic>is’nt</sic>
                     <corr>isn’t</corr>
                     <!-- proofed -->
                  </choice>
                  <name ref="pers:EM1">Edith</name> a beauty? And <name ref="pers:IM1"
                  >Irene</name>---did you know she is to sing <del>in O</del> at the Metropolitan in
                  New York. Such a marvelous voice. You much hear her. And such <del>sweet</del>
                  darling girls--so unspoiled and human and real. Let me <del>tell you what <name
                        ref="pers:IM1">Irene</name></del> show you what <name ref="pers:IM1"
                     >Irene</name> brought over this morning? <del>I <gap quantity="1" unit="char"
                        reason="deleted"/></del> I simply remarked how pretty that costume <choice>
                     <sic>was</sic>
                     <corr/>
                  </choice> she was wearing. She went right out and had it duplicated for me? There
                  never was a lovelier family</q>.</p>

            <p><unclear>Set</unclear>
               <choice>
                  <sic>Mrs..</sic>
                  <corr>Mrs.</corr>
               </choice> Cummings started on her brother and brother’s family and there is no
               stopping her. Even her own children must take second place.</p>

            <p>Finally there is <name ref="pers:LM3">Louis B. Mayer, sr</name>. That is to say, the
               father of <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B</name>. and Mrs. Cummings. An <choice>
                  <sic>pld</sic>
                  <corr>old</corr>
               </choice> Hebrew scholar, <del>mild, kind</del> an infinitely wise, infinitely kind
               old man of culture, who <del>is a philosopher</del> has <choice>
                  <sic>th</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> broadest sort of philosophy and religion by which to govern his declining
               years. <q>Life</q> says <name ref="pers:LM3">old Mr. Mayer</name>, <q>is like a great
                  wheel, slowly turning. Always remember, when you are under the wheel, that sooner
                  or later it must turn, and you will come up <pb n="15"/> with the turn of the
                  wheel</q>.</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p><del>They are beginning</del></p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>Little more than a year ago, they used to refer to the Warner brother with a laugh,
               and some joking query as to that theatre that would arise in another decade. The
               Warner boys were butt of every foolish joke on the loose tongues of smart alecks in
               the colony. I remember well two Universal banquets where the Warners were pilloried,
               both in wise cracks in speeches, and in little plays and motion pictures, and a I was
               at another Laemmle banquet, where <name ref="pers:JW3">Jack Warner</name> gave one of
               the most biting speeches in retort, impaling his tormentors with his wit and
               sarcasm.</p>

            <p><del>Now one runs in</del></p>

            <p>Now when they allude to the Warners in Hollywood it is with the most profound
               respect. They are called <q>The Amazing Warners</q>. They have set everyone by the
               ear. They have caused almost a revolution in the industry. It is the <choice>
                  <sic>Qa rners</sic>
                  <corr>Warners</corr>
               </choice> who knocked tradition into a cooked hat, and overnight caused an upheaval
               by coming with the First Talkies.</p>

            <p>The Warner relatives are many, and they stand shoulder to shoulder.
                  <unclear>Mack</unclear> and <name ref="pers:HW1">Harry</name> and <name
                  ref="pers:SW1">Sam</name> and <name ref="pers:AW2">Abe</name> and Izzy and Moe and
               the rest, whatever one does is O.K. to the other. Then there is one shining star
               among them. True she is but a Warner by blood, but the family take a special pride <choice>
                  <sic>ij</sic>
                  <corr>in</corr>
               </choice>
               <name ref="pers:LB3">Lina Basquette</name>, the widow of their brother <name
                  ref="pers:SW1">Sam</name>.</p>

            <pb n="16"/>

            <p>If <name ref="pers:LM2">Louis B. Mayer</name> is reluctant to have members of his
               family working on the Metro lot, <name ref="pers:IT1">Irving Thalborg</name> does not
               share his sentiments. Not that here are many Thalbergs on the lot, but such as are
               there are sitting pretty. <name ref="pers:ST2">Sylvia Thalberg</name> for instance,
               whose name is planted upon many a screen play as the scenarist, regardless sometimes
               of <del>whether</del> who wrote the script or not. We will grant <name ref="pers:ST2"
                  >Sylvia</name>’s ambition on as a scenarist, but it is not good sportsmanship on <choice>
                  <sic>herpart</sic>
                  <corr>her part</corr>
               </choice> to take the credit of another’s work, and this charge has been laid too
               often at her door.</p>

            <p>Recently <name ref="pers:ST2">Sylvia</name> was <choice>
                  <sic>marrued</sic>
                  <corr>married</corr>
               </choice> to one at that time holding a minor position at Metro, and since elevated
               to the important post of supervisor. Now various members of the Weingarten clan are
               holding down positions of more or less importance.</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>Another team of brothers are the Selznicks. <name ref="pers:MS2">Myron</name> and
                  <name ref="pers:DS2">Davy</name>. <name ref="pers:DS2">Dave</name> is a supervisor
               on the <choice>
                  <sic>Faous</sic>
                  <corr>Famous</corr>
               </choice> Players lot and <name ref="pers:MS2">Myron</name> conducts an agency for
               players and writers. An ideal arrangement exists between the brothers<choice>
                  <sic>.</sic>
                  <corr/>
               </choice> and which appears to be entirely satisfactory to the Paramount
               organization. <del>There is</del> great rush among the <name ref="pers:MS2"
                  >Myron</name>’s clients are always sure of a berth at Paramount.</p>

            <p><q>Every second man or woman at Tiffany Stahl is related to <name ref="pers:MH2">Mr.
                     Hoffman</name> or <name ref="pers:JS4">Mr. Stahl</name></q> said someone with
               utmost solemnity.</p>

            <p>One of <choice>
                  <sic>thebest</sic>
                  <corr>the best</corr>
               </choice> examples of what relationship will do is what happened to <name
                  ref="pers:JM4">John</name> when he married <name ref="pers:CM3">Coleen
                  Moore</name>. <name ref="pers:JM4">John</name> was a publicity man at that time,
               and <name ref="pers:CM3">Coleen</name>
               <pb n="17"/> was a star. <name ref="pers:JM4">John</name>’s rise after that marriage
               was simply phenomenal. He went up in leaps and bounds, toll <choice>
                  <sic>pesently</sic>
                  <corr>presently</corr>
               </choice> he sat in the <choice>
                  <sic>autocratoc</sic>
                  <corr>autocratic</corr>
               </choice> chair of General Manager of First National.</p>

            <p><name ref="pers:CD1">DeMille</name> does not go in for <q>relatives</q><choice>
                  <sic>,,</sic>
                  <corr/>
               </choice> so much as <q>friends</q>. <name ref="pers:JM5">Jeanie MacPherson</name>
               owes her start to <name ref="pers:CD1">De Mille</name>. For years their friendship
               has been a matter <choice>
                  <sic>pf</sic>
                  <corr>of</corr>
               </choice> the sort of <name ref="pers:DB2">Belasco</name> and <name ref="pers:LC1"
                  >Leslie Carter</name>. Some folks say <choice>
                  <sic>deMille</sic>
                  <corr><name ref="pers:CD1">DeMille</name></corr>
               </choice> believes in harems &amp;c b</p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
