<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MovieMadness4">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Movie Mandess [Second Instalment]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>4.1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl97"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Winnifred
                              Eaton</name></author>. <title level="a">Movie Mandess [Second
                           Instalment]</title>. MS in five parts. <distributor ref="org:WERFonds"
                           >Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>, <date when="1930"
                        >1930</date>, <idno>4.1</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p><!--[Add information about the holding library (i.e. the source of the facsimile) here]--></p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-27" status="published"></change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2022-04-28">Added catRef genre and exhibit.
            Added facsimile.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-31">Changed instalment.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-05-23">Changed genre.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and
            exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl97 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:MovieMandess4" next="doc:MovieMandess5">
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <fw type="continued" place="right">Second serial installment</fw>
         <head><q>MOVIE MADNESS</q></head>
         <byline>by <name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED EATON REEVE</name></byline>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter VI.</head>

            <p>Jane was typing a <q>rush</q> script, entitled <q>Lawless Laws</q>. It was
                  <q>Western</q> of the sort manufactured over night <unclear>in a studio</unclear>.
               She had reached a place in the story where the hero was suspended on a rope over the
               top of a chasm above a swollen river. On a log jam, which was rushing furiously down
               the river headed for deadly falls, lay the Golden Haired Heroine.</p>

            <p>On the opposite bank the blackhearted <q>Heavy</q> was taking unerring aim at the
               suspended Hero, while hidden by a transparent veil of Jungle ivy, a faithful Indian
               friend of the Hero awaited his chance to spring. The Noble Hero was half way down the
               rope, when the Heavy’s rifle shot grazed the rope, and at the same moment the Indian
               leaped. As Heavy and Indian closed in a death grapple, <choice>
                  <sic>th</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> rope began to break. Anguish of the heroine on the logs was shown in a
               closeup of a lovely face over which glycerine tears were pouring. There was a cut
               back to the rich New York home of the Hero, and a <q>fade into</q> the gorgeously
               gowned mother, pausing at Bridge to internally pray, just at <choice>
                  <sic>th</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> moment that the rope busted and down into the river went the Hero. By one
               of those blessed Movie coincidences, although the river was revealed <choice>
                  <sic>rush ing</sic>
                  <corr>rushing</corr>
               </choice> along at a frantic rate, and the rock to which the rope was attached was
               stationary, nevertheless the hero falls just <pb n="2"/> within a stone’s throw of
               the heroine.</p>

            <p>Jane typed breathlessly. The author, a fresh faced youth, a product of Larchmont, New
               York, grinned as he watched her. <q>Johnny</q> as everyone called Mr. Heglin was
               sorting the pages of the script. Jane pulled the last sheet from the typewriter.</p>

            <p><q>Rip snorter, eh?</q> said Johnny.</p>

            <p><q>Terrible</q> said Jane, and they both laughed.</p>

            <p><q>What’re you doing tonight?</q></p>

            <p>The inevitable <choice>
                  <sic>imvitation</sic>
                  <corr>invitation</corr>
               </choice> was coming. Jane had had many of them of late, and especially from Johnny
               who had a real <q>crush</q> on her.</p>

            <p><q>Mending runners in silk hose</q>.</p>

            <p><q>You should worry about ’runners’. <choice>
                     <sic>Lets</sic>
                     <corr>Let’s</corr>
                  </choice> go----</q></p>

            <p>Nellie Ross was <add place="above">calling</add> across the room to Jane.</p>

            <p><q>Ja-ane! Here, dearie</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane picked up her note book, shook her head at Johnny, hurried across to Nellie’s
               desk, <choice>
                  <sic>pulld</sic>
                  <corr>pulled</corr>
               </choice> out the slat.</p>

            <p><q>Not dictation this time. I’ve some wonderful news for you dear. <choice>
                     <sic>Theres</sic>
                     <corr>There’s</corr>
                  </choice> a request come through from one of our biggest directors to have you as
                  script girl on his set</q>.</p>

            <p><q>What does a script girl do?</q></p>

            <p><q>Hold script for the director right on the set. <choice>
                     <sic>Sor Sort</sic>
                     <corr>Sort</corr>
                  </choice> of secretary--makes notes of everything shot. Fine <choice>
                     <sic>opportuniry</sic>
                     <corr>opportunity</corr>
                  </choice> and training for continuity work</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Oh Nellie--how gorgeous! Thanks so much</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t thank me--the call came in</q>.</p>

            <pb n="3"/>

            <p>Johnny Heglin was at her elbow.</p>
        
            <p><q>What set is she going on?</q> he inquired.</p>

            <p><q>Ladies of the Jury</q>.<note type="editorial">Ending punctuation missing in
                  original.</note></p>

            <p><q>Harron’s?</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes, Mr. Harron’s picture</q>.</p>

            <p>Johnny whistled. He drew Jane to one side.</p>

            <p><q>Stick to your typing</q> he advised. <q><choice><sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> safer</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane replied indignantly:</p>

            <p><q>Think I’m going to throw away an opportunity like this</q>.</p>

            <p>Johnny knotted his young brows.</p>

            <p><q>Wish I could give you a job</q> he said gloomily. <q>Know anything about cowboy or
                  ranch stories?</q></p>

            <p><q>Not a thing. I’m eternally and infernally feminine and sentimental</q> laughed
               Jane.</p>

            <p><q>God help you then!</q> said Johnny, going off <choice>
                  <sic>. </sic>
                  <corr/>
               </choice>shaking his head, his continuity under his arm.</p>

            <p>Millie had come over to Jane’s desk. She had heard the news via Nellie Ross.</p>

            <p><q>I told you Harron was stuck on you</q> she said laconically.</p>

            <p>She <choice>
                  <sic>did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>didn’t</corr>
               </choice> seem overly pleased. All the girls in the department were looking at Jane
               and exchanging significant <choice>
                  <sic>glamce</sic>
                  <corr>glances</corr>
               </choice> with each other. Jane in her happiness and excitement was oblivious to all
               this. Nellie Ross called out sharply:</p>

            <p><q>Well, what the idea?</q></p>

            <p>There was the click and clack of a dozen typewriters resuming work.</p>

            <pb n="4"/>

            <p>Down the sunlit streets and alleys of Filmo City sped Jane Mercer. Her heart was as
               light as a feather and she felt as if she were literally treading on air. Up the
               steps of Edmund Blanton’s office she ran.</p>

            <p><q>Is Mr. Blanton in?</q> she asked eagerly of the henna-haired young woman in charge
               of the outer office.</p>

            <p><q>He’s in conference</q> said the latter briefly, and returned to an incipient
               flirtation with an assistant director that Jane had interrupted. The latter was
               looking at Jane out of the tail of his eye. He had made the discovery that she was
               exceptionally pretty.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Could’nt</sic>
                     <corr>Couldn’t</corr>
                  </choice> I see him just for a moment?</q> asked Jane.</p>

            <p><q>I said he was in conference</q> returned the girl, impatiently, and rolled her
               eyes toward the ceiling expressively. The Assistant director gave Jane the faintest
               flicker of a wink, and reaching across knocked on Blanton’s door. A moment later,
               Blanton himself loomed in the doorway. Jane saw the distinct lighting up of his
               somewhat weary eyes.</p>

            <p><q>Mr. Blanton, I <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> mean to interrupt your conference but I just wanted to tell you about my
                  good news</q>.</p>

            <p><q>One minute</q>.</p>

            <p>He turned back, spoke to someone inside. Gerald Keith, star of Blanton’s picture
               then in production strode out <choice>
                  <sic>sulkkly</sic>
                  <corr>sulkily</corr>
               </choice>. He was a tall goodlooking, nattily dressed young man, with the frame of a
               prize fighter and the weak face of a spoiled girl. He moved temperamentally toward
               the door, when he <choice>
                  <sic>cha chanced</sic>
                  <corr>chanced</corr>
               </choice> to see a large new photograph of himself on the wall of the outer office.
               Instantly he paused. When at last, reluctantly he turned from a survey of his
               pictured self, it was <pb n="5"/>to <choice>
                  <sic>enpunter</sic>
                  <corr>encounter</corr>
               </choice> the deeply admiring gaze of the henna haired stenographer. He felt in a
               much better humor, and went off whistling right merrily.</p>
            <p>Inside the office of Blanton, Jane was telling him of the marvelous opportunity that
               had come to her. Her kindling, joyousness met no response. His face had darkened. She
               faltered:</p>

            <p><q>I wanted you to know first of all</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Why?</q> he asked shortly. <q>What have I to do with it?</q></p>

            <p>She was hurt, stammered.</p>

            <p><q>Well I owe everything to you. I <choice>
                     <sic>would’nt</sic>
                     <corr>wouldn’t</corr>
                  </choice> be here if it <choice>
                     <sic>was’nt</sic>
                     <corr>wasn’t</corr>
                  </choice> for you</q>.</p>

            <p><q>You feel <choice>
                     <sic>rhat</sic>
                     <corr>that</corr>
                  </choice> way, do you?</q> demanded Blanton, his keen glance raking the flushed
               and glowing young face.</p>

            <p><q>Of course I do</q>.</p>

            <p><q>All right. Will you do what I tell you?</q></p>

            <p><q>Why yes, but---</q></p>

            <p><q>No buts about it</q> said he grimly.</p>

            <p>He remained a moment in thought, pursing out his lips in a way he had and silently
               whistling.</p>

            <p><q>You’re not going to work for Harron. <choice>
                     <sic>Thats</sic>
                     <corr>That’s</corr>
                  </choice> that</q>.</p>

            <p>Her startled, <choice>
                  <sic>disapointed</sic>
                  <corr>disappointed</corr>
               </choice> gaze left him unmoved. In the dictatorial way that was either assumed or
               natural with him, he said roughly:</p>

            <p><q>Now don’t start to cry. Cut out the blubbering</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Who’s blubbering?</q> asked Jane indignantly, surreptitiously <choice>
                  <sic>wipimg</sic>
                  <corr>wiping</corr>
               </choice> away an angry tear. A curious grin briefly illuminated Blanton’s face.</p>

            <pb n="6"/>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Thats</sic>
                     <corr>That’s</corr>
                  </choice> settled then. You don’t work for Harron</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I’m terrifically <choice><sic>disapointed</sic><corr>disappointed</corr></choice></q> she said.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Thats</sic>
                     <corr>That’s</corr>
                  </choice> all right. Life’s made up seventy five percent of <choice>
                     <sic>disapointments</sic>
                     <corr>disappointments</corr>
                  </choice>. Besides, I’ve something else in mind for you</q>.</p>

            <p>Her expression was more hopeful.</p>

            <p><q>What?</q></p>

            <p><q>Well we’ll see if we can’t get you in the Story department. Would you like
                  that?</q></p>

            <p><q>I’d adore it</q>.</p>

            <p>He beamed it.</p>

            <p><q>O.K. Now trot along. I’m busy</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Mr. Blanton---</q> She went as near to him as she dared. Her violet eyes sought to
               entrap his. He glanced at her, stared, frowned, looked away. <q>Why are you so kind
                  to <emph>me</emph>?</q></p>

            <p><q>Speculation. I discovered you and want to realize on my investment</q>.</p>

            <p>He grinned, looked at her again and added softly:</p>

            <p><q>I’m a hardboiled miser, Jane</q>.</p>

            <p>She was <choice>
                  <sic>disapointed</sic>
                  <corr>disappointed</corr>
               </choice>. She <choice>
                  <sic>did’nt</sic>
                  <corr>didn’t</corr>
               </choice> know what she had expected him to reply. She could not read his mind; could
               not suspect even that he was thinking <choice>
                  <sic>shelooked</sic>
                  <corr>she looked</corr>
               </choice> as fresh and sweet as a spring violet.</p>

            <p><q>I see</q> she said. <q>Your interest in me is just--impersonal?</q></p>

            <p><q>Absolutely</q> said he solemnly, and suddenly shouted: <q>Now young woman, scat!
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Raus mid dir</foreign>!</q><note type="editorial"
                     ><q>Raus mid dir!</q> is German for <q>Out with you!</q></note></p>

            <p>He became furiously absorbed in a pile of stills on his desk---went searching
               intensely through them, as if seeking some special <choice>
                  <sic>phtograph</sic>
                  <corr>photograph</corr>
               </choice>. Jane went out.</p>

            <pb n="6b"/>
            <note type="editorial">Page 6 is repeated in original.</note>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Thatssettled</sic>
                     <corr>That’s settled</corr>
                  </choice> then</q>.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <pb n="7"/>

            <head>Chapter VII.<note type="editorial"><q>VII</q>. is underlined by hand in pencil
                  with a handwritten comment above the chapter heading that reads:
                  <q>Rewrite</q>.</note></head>

            <p>In the studio Inn, where at the noon hour the Filmo <choice>
                  <sic>employes</sic>
                  <corr>employees</corr>
               </choice> foregathered, there was one large table especially reserved for certain of
               the executives, supervisors, directors and writers. There, on the following day,
               Harron greeted Blanton with assumed affability, while the latter nodded curtly and
               perused the menu card. Harron’s little eyes glittered. He leaned across the table,
               and above <choice>
                  <sic>th</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> <choice><sic>hubub</sic><corr>hubbub</corr></choice> of noises, tried to get the attention of Bennie Minton, General
               Manager of Filmo.</p>

            <p>Minton was a crafty looking little man, with eyes and mouth that turned up like a
               satyr’s at the corners. He was always laughing softly, with his pointed tongue
               slightly lapped out, and his eyes shifting inconstantly. He had a habit of talking
               with his hand before one side of his mouth, or back of an ear. He was not without
               ability, in an executive way, but he was handicapped by <choice><sic>apalling</sic><corr>appalling</corr></choice> ignorance and
               illiteracy. Moreover his mind was a cess-pool. He was a collector and retailer of
               filthy stories, and his entire conversation was peppered with lascivious and lewd
               allusions. All the girls on the Filmo studio lot knew of this weakness and feared to
               enter his private office, because of his straying hands and lips.</p>

            <p>Seated on one side of Minton, and listening to his <pb n="8"/> latest rotten story,
               with pretended guffaws of delight was Ted Mabie, Scenario Editor of Filmo.<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">The text from this line until the end of the
                  paragraph is crossed out in the manuscript.</note> Mabie had the face of a
               super-fox, very wary, very cunning. There was a razor like sharpness to <choice>
                  <sic>gis</sic>
                  <corr>his</corr>
               </choice> quick glance. As a salesman and politician he was without his equal in the
               industry. Moreover he had considerable reputation as a scenario writer and editor.
               This was due to his sharp use of his powerful position. He was enabled to put his
               name upon every picture regardless of whether he had contributed to the story or
               not. He had risen to his present very important position through the success of
               certain of his scenarios. He manufactured <q>sure fire</q> stories, that <choice>
                  <sic>we were</sic>
                  <corr>were</corr>
               </choice> built on a <q>movie formula</q>, which the Sales Department termed <q>Box
                  office</q>. He would take a bit from this story, an idea from that, a character
               from a play, a situation from a submitted manuscript, an episode from a novel or a
               poem. Gags emanated from <q>College Humor</q>, <q>Life</q> and other humorous
               publications, and he transposed big climaxes from pictures and books in such a way
               that the author himself would never have recognized his original product.</p>

            <p>Mabie was the man for whom Jane Mercer was now working, though her immediate chief
               was a Miss Dutton, story Editor of Filmo and under the supervision of Mabie.</p>

            <p>Minton and Mabie, the General Manager and the Scenario Editor, were the <q>brains</q>
               and governing heads of Filmo, though officially they were both under Charlie Fulton,
               Director General and Personal Representative of the President. Charlie however was a
               nonentity, or as one wise-cracking title writer had described him--official ornament
               of Filmo. He looked guileless <choice>
                  <sic>anc</sic>
                  <corr>and</corr>
               </choice> harmless, with <pb n="9"/> his round, moonlike face, his white spate and
               flashy spots checked suit and <choice><sic>flambuoyant</sic><corr>flamboyant</corr></choice> vest. His cheeks were touched <choice>
                  <sic>ith</sic>
                  <corr>with</corr>
               </choice> rouge; he powdered his face and pencilled his eye brows. He was hail follow
               with everyone and a born backslapper, and because <choice>
                  <sic>ofnhis</sic>
                  <corr>of his</corr>
               </choice> flattering oily tongue he held his fine position and saw one administration
               after another come and go. It was he who always arranged the big hullabaloos from the
               Old Chief, as the President of Filmo was called. Annually the President made a trip
               to the coast, to survey the Filmo studios. Then it was that Fulton’s ability as a
               show-man was revealed. The entire Filmo lot would be decorated with flags and
               banners, as though it were Armistice or Election day. Banquets and extraordinary
               anniversary and birthday affairs ensued. The bedazzled old President of Filmo, who
               loved all this sort of adulation, would return to New York more than ever convinced
               that he was the greatest man since Moses.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This
                  paragraph which starts on page 8 is crossed out in the manuscript.</note></p>

            <p>Harron was knocking his fork against the side of his glass to attract Minton’s
               attention. The noise brought a waitress scurrying across the room. Harron
               shouted:</p>

            <p><q>Minton! <choice><sic>Heh</sic><corr>Hey</corr></choice> there!</q></p>

            <p>Minton looked over his glasses; gave the director his attention.</p>

            <p><q>How about that script girl? What was the grand idea of sending me another girl in
                  her place?</q></p>

            <p>Minton moved his fork through a piled up cone of noodles. He twisted the slippery
               stuff about his fork.</p>

            <pb n="10"/>

            <p><q>What script girl are you talking about?</q></p>

            <p><q>The one I asked to be assigned to work with me. I talked to you about her</q>.</p>

            <p>Minton’s tongue went into this cheek. He gave Blanton a sly flicker of a wink.</p>

            <p><q>Maybe some body else was stuck on her too</q> said he softly.</p>

            <p>Minton caught just a glimpse of Blanton’s face. He ceased to grin, licked his lips,
               his eyes gleaming behind his glasses.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This
                  paragraph is crossed out in the manuscript.</note></p>

            <p>Mildly interested Mabie inquired:<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This line is
                  crossed out in the manuscript.</note></p>

            <p><q>Who is the dame that all the <choice>
                     <sic>excitemente</sic>
                     <corr>excitement</corr>
                  </choice>’s about?</q><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This line is crossed
                  out in the manuscript.</note></p>

            <p>Harron’s loose mouth opened and then suddenly closed. He was looking into the steely,
               menacing eyes of Edmund Blanton. The latter’s words cut across the table with cool
               precision.</p>

            <p><q>If you mention a girl’s name at this table, I’ll knock your damned face in</q> he
               said between his teeth.</p>

            <p>There was a breath taking gasp all around the table. A gag man swallowed a huge lump
               of steak<choice>
                  <sic>.</sic>
                  <corr>,</corr>
               </choice> choked coughed. Mabie chewed methodically on fried ham; while Minton went
               on quietly lifting his noodles. At the adjoining table, where the <q>Foreign
                  Legion</q>, as they called the German supervisors, directors and writers, were
               lunching, there was a suspense of conversation. Everyone was waiting for something to
               happen. A quarrel between two directors; both of them highly important-- was not a
               matter of everyday <choice><sic>occurence</sic><corr>occurrence</corr></choice>. Charlie Fulton plunged in, as usual, like a clumsy
                     <q><foreign xml:lang="fr">enfant terrible</foreign></q>.<note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">This line is crossed out in the manuscript.</note></p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Whats</sic>
                     <corr>What’s</corr>
                  </choice> all the music about?</q> he asked his wide guileless gaze going from
               Blanton to Harron and back again to Blanton.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"
                  >This line is crossed out in the manuscript.</note> The latter had pushed back his
               chair, snapped his fingers at a passing waitress, got his check and leaving a quarter
               tip on the table, he was on his way to the Cashier’s window, before anyone at the
               table spoke. Then Fulton asked eagerly:</p>

            <p><q>Who is she? Who is she?</q></p>

            <p>Harron’s face was almost purple, the veins standing out and twitching. He glared
               around at the circle of faces.</p>

            <p><q>What the hell difference does it make? I’ll get her yet. Watch! I’m the waiting
                  kind</q>.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter VIII.</head>
            <p>Jane was a week in her position before she saw Edmund Blanton again. Then he dropped
               in on her one afternoon. Jane was hard at work, typing a synopsis she had just
               written.</p>

            <p><q>How are you getting on?</q> Blanton called from the door. Jane looked up, saw him
               and <choice>
                  <sic>herheard</sic>
                  <corr>her heart</corr>
               </choice> gave a great bound. Quite <choice>
                  <sic>demurely ,</sic>
                  <corr>demurely,</corr>
               </choice> however, she answered.</p>

            <p><q>Sir, behold your handiwork! You see before you a perfectly contented and happy
                  woman</q>.</p>

            <p>Blanton chuckled, and then in the way he had frowned and cleared his throat severely.
               Jane was thinking how nice he looked in his loose grey tweeds, his face cleanly
               shaven.</p>

            <p><q>Well, <choice>
                     <sic>thats</sic>
                     <corr>that’s</corr>
                  </choice> good news. See you again some day</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Wait a minute. Don’t go yet</q>.</p>

            <p><q>On my way to a story conference. Must be off</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Please stay a wee moment, won’t you</q>.</p>

            <p>His eyes, lingering on Jane’s flushed face, moved away unwillingly. He was blowing
               out his lips in the silent whistle.</p>

            <p><q>Thought possibly you’d forgotten about my existence</q>.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Thats</sic>
                     <corr>That’s</corr>
                  </choice> likely</q> said Jane.</p>

            <p><q>You seem mighty happy and absorbed in your work; probably no time to think of an
                  old crab like me</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I adore my work; <choice>
                     <sic>thats</sic>
                     <corr>that’s</corr>
                  </choice> true enough; just the same-</q><note type="editorial">Ending quotation
                  mark missing in original.</note></p>

            <p>She <choice>
                  <sic>hadmoved</sic>
                  <corr>had moved</corr>
               </choice> around to the other side of the desk and was now leaning across it, looking
               very earnestly at Blanton.</p>

            <pb n="11"/>

            <p><q>Just the same---?</q> He <choice>
                  <sic>repeatedher</sic>
                  <corr>repeated her</corr>
               </choice> words with pretended indifference.</p>

            <p><q>Just the same, <emph>you’ve</emph> been back of my mind all of the time</q> said
               Jane softly.</p>

            <p>He plunged his two clinched fists into his pockets. His words were harsh and he
               turned toward the door.</p>

            <p><q>If <choice>
                     <sic>thats</sic>
                     <corr>that’s</corr>
            </choice> true, <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it’s</corr></choice> more or less of a calamity. It would be better for you not to
                  think of me at all</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane’s face had paled; she was trembling. Blanton looked. He spoke roughly, yet with
               a singular tenderness underlying his words.</p>

            <p><q>I take that back. The fact that you have held me in your thought is the one
                  compensating, beautiful thing in my life</q>.</p>

            <p>Before Jane could reply, he had closed the door sharply between them. She leaned against
               that door. She wanted to press her lips to it. She wanted to laugh, to cry.</p>

            <p>There was a rap upon her door, and she started, all aflutter and <choice>
                  <sic>frightened,half</sic>
                  <corr>frightened, half</corr>
               </choice> fearing and half hoping that Blanton had returned. Johnny Heglin’s smooth
               brown head was thrust in.</p>

            <p><q>Say girl, I’ve tickets for the premiere of ’Say it again’. How about it? Going
                  with me?</q></p>

            <p><q>No--no---I’m sorry</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Oh hell-o! What the deuce do you do with your evening anyway</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane had recovered somewhat <choice>
                  <sic>ofher</sic>
                  <corr>of her</corr>
               </choice> composure. Her hands, trembling, slipped a sheet back into the
               typewriter.</p>

            <pb n="12"/>

            <p><q>Oh one thing or another</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Well listen here-you’ve got to get out a bit. You can’t narrow yourself down to
                  going to the studio and going back to your flat. This is a darned provincial town.
                  We talk, think, live just Movies and more movies. <choice>
                     <sic>Its</sic>
                     <corr>It’s</corr>
                  </choice> bad for you. The darned place gets into your blood</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I love Hollywood</q> said Jane dreamily.</p>

            <p>She typed three words. Blanton’s face formed before the type.</p>

            <p><q>You’re hopeless. First thing you know you’ll get the town’s worst
                  infection---Movie Madness</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I’ve got it already</q> said Jane.</p>

            <p><q>Rot. We all feel that way at first; you’ll get a good nostalgia soon. This picture
                  game is the limit--<choice>
                     <sic>its</sic>
                     <corr>it’s</corr>
                  </choice> not normal</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane merely smiled. In a vague way she was wishing that Johnny would go, and she had
               her wish, for a few minutes later, he heaved a big sigh, said:</p>

            <p><q>All right then. I’m off--cut to the soul</q>.</p>

            <p>Jane went back to her typing. Her mind reverted to Blanton. She thought of him with a
               passionate eagerness--and yet with a yearning tenderness.</p>

            <p>The telephone on her desk rang. She reached over, picked it up. Her heart gave an
               ecstatic leap as she heard his voice.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Whats</sic>
                     <corr>What’s</corr>
                  </choice> your address?</q> he asked.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>AApartment</sic>
                     <corr>Apartment</corr>
                  </choice> B. 10 Sunburst Ave</q>.</p>

            <p><q>O.K. I’ll be there about 7.30</q>.</p>

            <p>She heard the receiver hung up and she thought her heart would burst with joy.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <pb n="13"/>

            <head>Chapter IX.</head>

            <p>Jane had a warm, luxurious sense as she settled down on the low seat of Blanton’s
               car. He asked her quizzically whether she had ever ridden in a Rolls Royce before,
               and she answered swiftly:</p>

            <p><q>I <choice>
                     <sic>shouldsay</sic>
                     <corr>should say</corr>
                  </choice> not</q>.</p>

            <p>He laughed. She had never seen hin in the mood like this. His eyes were lighted. She
               could <emph>feel</emph> them searching hers. He asked suddenly:</p>

            <p><q>Happy, Jane?</q></p>

            <p>She answered swiftly.</p>

            <p><q>Oh <emph>very</emph></q>.<note type="editorial">Ending punctuation missing in
                  original.</note></p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Thats</sic>
                     <corr>That’s</corr>
                  </choice> all that matters. The main thing is that you should be happy</q>.</p>

            <p><q>How could I help being</q> she asked breathlessly, <q>when I’m with
                     <emph>you</emph>?</q></p>

            <p>He gave her arm a little squeeze. Then sat back in the seat and they rode along in
               this thrilling silence for some <choice>
                  <sic>ti time</sic>
                  <corr>time</corr>
               </choice>. He studied the girl’s oval face, occasionally lighted by the street lamps
               and vanishing again into the shadow. Suddenly he asked her how old she was.</p>

            <p><q>Nineteen and a half</q> she said.</p>

            <p>He could see her smiling hesitantly, trying to get up <pb n="14"/> the courage <choice>
                  <sic>toask</sic>
                  <corr>to ask</corr>
               </choice> his age. Before she could put the question he had answered it.</p>


            <p><q>Thirty seven. Twice your age, Jane</q>.</p>

            <p>Her swift reply was so utterly ingenuous and young and impulsive that he could not
               refrain from laughing, though he sobered immediately. Jane had said:</p>

            <p><q>I like middle aged people</q>.</p>

            <p><q>So you think me middle aged?</q></p>

            <p>She was overcome with confusion. Why had she said such a stupid thing. He pursued the
               subject grimly.</p>

            <p><q>To a girl of nineteen thirty seven is pretty old, eh?</q></p>

            <p><q>Oh dear, I <choice>
                     <sic>did’nt</sic>
                     <corr>didn’t</corr>
                  </choice> mean that</q>.</p>

            <p>She was distressed. He seemed to be ruminating over her words.</p>

            <p>The car was going down Hollywood Boulevard. There was a parade of cars moving along
               slowly. They turned down Gower and on to Sunset Boulevard. Presently they drew up
               before the brightly lighted Authors Club.</p>

            <p>The chauffeur opened the door. Jame saw a seething crowd of Motion Picture stars,
               directors, producers, writers and celebrities. She felt a moment of panic, and then a
               warm sense of relief and joy, for Blanton’s hand was under her arm. She felt its
               pressure.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="section">

            <p>It was the kind of affair that the newspapers would <choice>
                  <sic>refe refer</sic>
                  <corr>refer</corr>
               </choice> to the next day as brilliant. Hollywood <choice>
                  <sic>excellead</sic>
                  <corr>excelled</corr>
               </choice> in adjectives. It was a Paradise for publicity men and women and slush and
               sob writers, who rolled over their pens gilded names, and whose articles reeked with
               hysterical accounts of <pb n="14b"/> the question.<note type="editorial">Page
                  unnumbered in original.</note></p>

            <pb n="15"/>

            <p>how<note type="editorial">Lower case in original.</note> this or that star looked so beautiful and sweet and lovely and so forth and so
               on.</p>

            <p>The dinner was good, but Jane was too excited and happy <choice>
                  <sic>tp</sic>
                  <corr>to</corr>
               </choice> know or care what she was eating. Blanton took a singular satisfaction in
               watching her. Nor was he the only one in that room interested in the girl’s lovely
               young face.</p>

            <p>At a table nearer the stage, a dark haired <q>sheiky</q> type of young man advised
               the woman with him to stop nagging him long enough to see what he was seeing. The
               woman, who had a magnificent head of red hair, craned her neck caught a glimpse of
               Blanton and stood up in order to see his companion. She stared incredulously.</p>

            <p>After <choice>
                  <sic>thedinner</sic>
                  <corr>the dinner</corr>
               </choice>, when the waiters were moving the tables away and the diners pulling their
               chairs to places where they would have the best view of the stage, Jane was surprised
               to find seated on the other side of her the Filmo director Martin Harron. She
               returned his greeting, given out of the corner of his mouth: <q>How’s the girlie?</q>
               with the prim <unclear>rejoiner</unclear>. <q>Oh quite well</q>.<note
                  type="editorial">Ending punctuation missing in original.</note></p>

            <p>In a confidential way, Harron leaned nearer.</p>

            <p><q><choice><sic>Have’nt</sic>
                     <corr>Haven’t</corr>
                  </choice> seen you lately</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I’ve been working</q>.</p>

            <p><q>So I heard. Understand you write <q>stories</q></q>.</p>

            <p>Jane’s eyes lighted.</p>

            <p><q>Who told you that?</q></p>

            <p><q>Your editor</q>.</p>
            
            <p>Jane was about to say something, when she felt the deliberate prod of Blanton’s
               elbow. Like a guilty child she <choice>
                  <sic>tur turned</sic>
                  <corr>turned</corr>
               </choice> back, only to find him sitting up stiffly his face like a thunder cloud. He
               was furious with her.</p>

            <pb n="16"/>

            <p>His face had hardened to a forbidding mask. During the performance, which was good,
               comic fare, elicited gales of approval and applause from the delighted audience, Jane
               made several efforts to speak to Blanton. He continued to ignore <choice>
                  <sic>he her</sic>
                  <corr>her</corr>
               </choice>, and her natural gaiety was dashed. She felt a sense of depression. Not
               till Blanton put his hand under her arm, as they were moving out of the club, and
               guided her through the crowds to the door, did she feel some slight sense that
               perhaps he had forgiven her.</p>

            <p>On the steps of the clubhouse, while waiting for Blanton’s car, someone behind them
               said in a rather loud whisper:</p>

            <p><q>Who’s the girl with Blanton</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t know. New face. Darned pretty, what?</q></p>

            <p>A woman said:</p>

            <p><q>What will Sylvia say about it?</q></p>

            <p><q>Ssh! They’ll hear you. You can’t imagine how your voice carries</q>.</p>

            <p>Blanton had helped her into the car. She was tormented with a new agonizing fear. Who
               was Sylvia? What was she to Blanton?</p>

            <p>Blanton, in his corner of the car was staring out moodily, and Jane could see his
               brows knotted in a tight frown. They rode along in silence. Suddenly he spoke.</p>

            <p><q>Jane, do you value my friendship</q>.</p>

            <p><q>You know I do</q> she replied tremulously/</p>

            <p><q>Promise me then that you’ll have nothing more to do with that fellow
               Harron?</q></p>

            <p><q>I scarcely know him. One has to <choice><sic>bepolite</sic><corr>be polite</corr></choice> to people who speak to <choice><sic>then</sic>
                     <corr>them</corr></choice></q>?<note type="editorial">Question mark outside quotation marks in
                  original.</note></p>

            <pb n="17"/>

            <p><q>No they don’t. I want you to snub him. Cut him</q>.<note type="editorial">Ending
                  punctuation missing in original.</note></p>

            <p><q>Why?</q></p>

            <p><q>Because I tell you to</q>.</p>

            <p><q>But what do you care?</q></p>

            <p>He hesitated. She felt a tightness about her heart, and suddenly she said:</p>

            <p><q>Oh I believe you’re jealous of him--are you?</q></p>

            <p><q>Suppose I am</q> he replied huskily.</p>

            <p>Jane said, with a most radiant look:</p>

            <p>What would mean that you <emph>care</emph> a lot about me then. <q>Do you?</q></p>

            <p>He replied with a sort of repressed force.</p>

            <p><q>So much that I can’t bear to have my man--least of all Harron--even look at you.
                  I’d like to carry you away-shut you up somewhere where no one in the world would
                  see you but myself. <choice>
                     <sic>Thats</sic>
                     <corr>That’s</corr>
                  </choice> how much I care</q>.</p>

            <p>She was pressing her hands together, her illuminated face turned irresistibly <choice>
                  <sic>tiward</sic>
                  <corr>toward</corr>
               </choice> him. She said:</p>

            <p><q>Do you mean you’re in love with me, Mr. Blanton?</q></p>

            <p><q>I <emph>adore</emph> you!</q> he said, in a thrilling voice.</p>

            <p>They rode along half a block.</p>

            <p><q>Jane--I’ve no right to speak to you like this. Give me your little
               hand----</q></p>

            <p>She held back a moment. The full sweet lips parted, and in the half light of the car
               their eyes met with a passionate joy. He had drawn her roughly to him, and her face
               turned up against his shoulder.</p>

            <p><q>Jane-- Jane---do you love me?</q></p>

            <p>She replied unfalteringly.</p>

            <pb n="18"/>

            <p><q>Oh I do-- I do---you know it. Oh--h---Oh--</q><note type="editorial">Beginning
                  quotation mark missing in original.</note></p>

            <p>She felt almost as if she were passing out of herself; that she would swoon from
               sheer <choice><sic>ecstacy</sic><corr>ecstasy</corr></choice> in his arms. His lips never left hers till the chauffeur drew up
               suddenly before Jane’s house.</p>

            <p>Up the few little steps of the stoop, their hands fumbling as she unlocked the door.
               Inside the hall, very dimly lighted, again he took her into his arms.</p>

            <p>Now, suddenly, like a vague distant pain, Jane recalled something. It lay in her mind
               coiled there like a serpent. She pressed back from him.</p>

            <p><q>I must ask you something</q>.</p>

            <p><q>What is it, darling---<emph>my</emph> darling?</q></p>

            <p>The words struck him like a flail. He recoiled, and she could see his burning eyes
               staring at her with that look of intolerable pain. His words came stumblingly, as
               though he was scarcely aware of what he was saying.</p>

            <p><q>Tomorrow-----not tonight. I’ll call you first thing in the morning......<choice>
                     <sic>telll</sic>
                     <corr>tell</corr>
                  </choice> you all --then</q>.</p>

            <p>He did not kiss her again. He seemed intent only upon getting away.</p>

            <p>Outside, blindly, he plunged toward his car. His thoughts surged <choice>
                  <sic>ovrr</sic>
                  <corr>over</corr>
               </choice> him like a madman’s.</p>

            <p><q>What have I done?</q> he muttered. <q>Good God! What have I done?</q></p>



         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
