<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="OregonTrail1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oregon Trail</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile provided by Jean Lee Cole.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:266"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreFilm"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-08-24" status="inProgress">With <name ref="pers:LW1"/>, experimenting with encoding screenplays.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Added facsimile and note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Oregon_Trail">
      <pb n="titlePage"/>
      <!--TODO: Add title page later-->
      <body>
         <div>
           <div>
              <pb n="A-1"/>
              <head>SEQUENCE A</head>
              <camera>FADE IN:</camera>
              <view>An Indian Village.</view>
              <p>From out of the sky vaguely and hazily, swooping down over the village comes the emaciated and ghostly figure of FAMINE.</p>
              <p>The Village itself is revealed in a state of destitution and misery.</p>
              <p>Against the skyline appear four fiery columns of smoke, and at the same time is heard the arousing beat of Indian drums. This is the Indian summons to a counsel.</p> 
              <p>There is a stir in the village and the Indians are seen leaving their tents and wigwams. Like a swarm of shadows they plod and push dumbly along toward a hill slope.</p>
              <pb n="A-2"/>
              <fw type="pageNum">A-2</fw>
              <p>On the crest of the hill a young Indian chief stands silhouetted against the sky. His arms are extended, his face is passionate and exalted. Below him, on the slope of the hill, is the great congregation of silent Indians. The young chief addresses them.</p>
              <p>He tells them that unless the white men are driven from the Indian hunting grounds the Indian hunting grounds the Indian will not live throughout the coming winter. Already they are dying like flies from starvation and plague. No longer do the buffalo roam the plains and prairies. The deer have gone from the forests. The white men have slaughtered the natural food of the Indian for their fur and hides. Now a horde of white people have gathered at Independence and are preparing to invade the Oregon lands in overwhelming numbers. They are forerunners of the hosts of whites who seek to rob the Indian of the land of his forefathers. Unless they are driven back the Indians will starve to death or be forced out of his own lands. The time has come when the Indian must repel the advance of these white people. They must be prevented from crossing the Cascades.</p>
              <p>His words are greeted by savage cheers.</p>
              <p>Through the clamoring throngs a very old chief pushes his way to the fore until he comes alongside the young chief on the brow of the hill. He raises his hands to command silence.</p>
              <pb n="A-3"/>
              <fw type="pageNum">A-3</fw>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>I have hung the scalps of many white men upon my belt - but always came <emph>more</emph> white men!</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                 <p>They shall come no more!</p>
              </sp>
              <sp><speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>They are rich! We are poor! They are many! We are few! Their government is powerful and remorseless. The Indian has no friends but his brothers.</p></sp>
              <sp>  
                 <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                 <p>Are our hearts those of rabbits? Shall we lie down and permit the white man to trample upon us?</p>
              </sp>
              
              <p>The old chief tries to raise his voice above the roar. The young chief places his arm about the old chief’s shoulders and commands silence - old age must be respected.</p> 
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>War is terrible! Let us deal with the chiefs of these white people! Let us demand justice!</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                 <p>For justice they will give - promises! Who can believe the word of a white man? We must drive them back! </p></sp>
              <sp> 
                 <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>We cannot dam up the ocean with our hands.</p>
              </sp>
              <pb n="A-3-A"/>
              <fw type="pageNum">A-3-A</fw>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>YOUNG CHIEF</speaker>
                 <stage>(shouting)</stage>
                 <p>The Thunder God fights within us! Ee-yah! Eeii---ya-a-a-a!</p>
              </sp>
              <p>The Indians take up the cry. They begin to circle, screaming and shouting and yelling, as they move in a savage war dance.</p>
              <camera>FADE OUT.</camera> 
           </div>
            <div>
               <!--JT > LW: COPY + PASTE SEQUENCE B HERE-->
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
