<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="OregonTrail1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oregon Trail</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>11.15</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl266"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred
                           Reeve</name></author>. <title level="a">Oregon Trail</title>. ms., <date
                           notBefore="1917" notAfter="1935">1917-1935</date>, <distributor
                           ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>,
                           <idno>11.15</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile provided by Jean Lee Cole.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreFilm"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-05-01" status="published">Corrected typos.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-04-25" status="published">Corrected typos.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-01-29" status="published">Proofing.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-01-13" status="published">Proofing and encoding complete.
            Future changes to tags are welcome.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="readyForProof">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-01-01" status="readyForProof">Testing view vs p.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2023-11-11" status="readyForProof">encoding
            completed.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2023-11-10" status="inProgress">encoding until sequence
            J</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2023-08-28" status="inProgress">encoding</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2023-08-28" status="inProgress">encoding</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-08-24" status="inProgress">With <name ref="pers:LW1"/>,
            experimenting with encoding screenplays.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Added facsimile and note about
            source.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Oregon_Trail">
      <pb n="titlePage"/>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <byline>Original Story for Screen</byline>
         </opener>
         <head>OREGON TRAIL</head>
         <byline>By</byline>
         <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">WINNIFRED REEVE</name></byline>
         <div>
            <milestone unit="page"/>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="1."/>
            <opener>
               <byline>Original Story for Screen based on novel by</byline>
               <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name>.</byline>
            </opener>
            <head>THE OREGON TRAIL</head>
            <opener>
               <byline>By</byline>
               <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name></byline>
            </opener>
            <div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="A-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE A</head>
                  <camera>FADE IN:</camera>
                  <stage type="setting">An Indian Village.</stage>
                  <p>From out of the sky vaguely and hazily, swooping down over the village comes
                     the emaciated and ghostly figure of FAMINE.</p>
                  <stage type="setting">The Village itself is revealed in a state of destitution and
                     misery.</stage>
                  <view>Against the skyline appear four fiery columns of smoke, and at the same time
                     is heard <sound>the arousing beat of Indian drums.</sound> This is the Indian
                     summons to a counsel.</view>
                  <view>There is a stir in the village and the Indians are seen leaving their tents
                     and wigwams. Like a swarm of shadows they plod and push dumbly along toward a
                     hill slope.</view>
                  <pb n="A-2"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">A-2</fw>
                  <view>On the crest of the hill a young Indian chief stands silhouetted against the
                     sky. His arms are extended, his face is passionate and exalted. Below him, on
                     the slope of the hill, is the great congregation of silent Indians. The young
                     chief addresses them.</view>
                  <p>He tells them that unless the white men are driven from the Indian hunting
                     grounds the Indian will not live throughout the coming winter. Already they are
                     dying like flies from starvation and plague. No longer do the buffalo roam the
                     plains and prairies. The deer have gone from the forests. The white men have
                     slaughtered the natural food of the Indian for their fur and hides. Now a horde
                     of white people have gathered at Independence and are preparing to invade the
                     Oregon lands in overwhelming numbers. They are forerunners of the hosts of
                     whites who seek to rob the Indian of the land of his forefathers. Unless they
                     are driven back the Indians will starve to death or be forced out of his own
                     lands. The time has come when the Indian must repel the advance of these white
                     people. They must be prevented from crossing the Cascades.</p>
                  <sound>His words are greeted by savage cheers.</sound>
                  <view>Through the clamoring throngs a very old chief pushes his way to the fore
                     until he comes alongside the young chief on the brow of the hill. He raises his
                     hands to command silence.</view>
                  <pb n="A-3"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">A-3</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                     <p>I have hung the scalps of many white men upon my belt - but always came
                           <emph>more</emph> white men!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                     <p>They shall come no more!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                     <p>They are rich! We are poor! They are many! We are few! Their government is
                        powerful and remorseless. The Indian has no friends but his brothers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                     <p>Are our hearts those of rabbits? Shall we lie down and permit the white man
                        to trample upon us?</p>
                  </sp>

                  <view>The old chief tries to raise his voice above the roar. The young chief
                     places his arm about the old chief’s shoulders and commands silence - old age
                     must be respected.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                     <p>War is terrible! Let us deal with the chiefs of these white people! Let us
                        demand justice!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                     <p>For justice they will give - promises! Who can believe the word of a white
                        man? We must drive them back! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                     <p>We cannot dam up the ocean with our hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="A-3-A"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">A-3-A</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>YOUNG CHIEF</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(shouting)</stage>
                     <p>The Thunder God fights within us! Ee-yah! Eeii---ya-a-a-a!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view><sound>The Indians take up the cry. They begin to circle, screaming and
                        shouting and yelling,</sound> as they move in a savage war dance.</view>
                  <camera>FADE OUT.</camera>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>SEQUENCE B</head>
                  <camera>FADE IN</camera>
                  <stage type="setting">A trail winding around the side of a precipitous canyon
                     wall.</stage>
                  <stage type="modifier">Two riders are loping along. Their outfit consists of their
                     horses, surefooted, swift and tough Indian ponies, and two pack mules, in
                     charge of an Indian who plods along behind. The older of the two men is Ren
                     Bullock. He is tall, long-legged, with hair the color of corn-shuck and a long
                     lean body. His eyes are clear and his face tanned. He has a look of
                     intelligence and honesty and is as strong as a young ox. He is a Missourian.
                     His speech is slow and drawling. He hesitates before speaking as if weighing
                     his words. He never hurries, yet, at the right moment, seems literally to
                     spring like lightning into vivid action and life.</stage>
                  <stage type="modifier">His companion is of a totally different type. A happy go
                     lucky, light-hearted, careless, pleasure-loving and likeable young chap with a
                     natural quality of refinement about him. He goes by the name of Thad Jones. The
                     two men are close pals, and partners.</stage>
                  <view>As they ride along, Ren sitting loosely ahorse, and looking out silently
                     before him and Thad whirling his lariat and whistling the night begins to fall
                     softly around them. The wind sings in the pine tops and through the canyon
                     walls. A silvery sunlight, a glow of fading red still lingers in the sky. Ren
                     points vaguely. </view>
                  <pb n="B-2."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-2.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>That’s one plumb fine sight - that thar sunset.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Thad laughs. It is natural for him to laugh.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>I’ve seen prettier sunsets than that in Kentucky.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>You come from Kentucky? You never told me that before.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(uneasily)</stage>
                     <p>That’s right- I’ve never told anyone. Mebbe <note type="editorial"
                           >Maybe</note> I had a reason.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Ren nods understandingly.</stage>
                  <view>The shadows deepen about them. They top the brow of a hill and draw rein to
                     look down across a great sweep of plain. There, in a wide valley below them,
                     the flares of a score of campfires are seen.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>How many are there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Two thousand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(Anxiously)</stage>
                     <p>That’s a considerable job you’ve taken on. Think you can pilot two thousand
                        immigrants into the Oregon?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="action">(with a wry smile)</stage>
                     <p>What me? Reckon I’ll be lookin’ for a heap a help from you young one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="B-3"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-3</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage type="action">(chest swelling)</stage>
                     <p>Well I reckon we can manage somehow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sound>Sound of music and singing comes floating upon the air.</sound>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Listen to them singing. Sounds like gospel hymns.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="action">(nodding)</stage>
                     <p>They’s a powerful lot of religion ‘mong them. Guess we better be driftin’
                        along. They’ll be lookin’ for us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Let’s go on into the town first. I got a parched throat and an empty
                        stomach. And I’m aiming to stretch out on a real bed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Ren gives him a good humored thump on the back.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>We’ll ride on into the town and look up our friends down thar later.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">They turn their <choice>
                        <sic>horses</sic>
                        <corr>horses’</corr>
                     </choice> heads and move off.</stage>
                  <milestone unit="scene"/>
                  <stage type="setting">THE IMMIGRANT ENCAMPMENT</stage>
                  <stage type="location">This is a large field or plain on the outskirts of the town
                     of Independence (now a part of Kansas City). Here a host of immigrants,
                     hunters, trappers, voyageurs, traders, gamblers, adventurers, missionaries,
                     teachers, farmers, as well as the rag tag and bobtail and outcasts of the
                     frontier <pb n="B-4."/><fw type="pageNum">B-4.</fw> town have gathered from all
                     parts of the country to keep a rendezvous at the starting off place for the
                     Oregon trail.</stage>
                  <view>Vehicles of all manner and kind form an immense circle about a central
                     point.</view>
                  <tech type="light">The flares of campfires, stream up, flooding the place with a
                     mellow light, illuminating the faces of these hardy adventurers and
                     pioneers.</tech>
                  <stage type="novelistic">In a way this scene should parallel the Indian scene in
                     as much as the immigrants are addressed by their commander in chief Colonel
                     Blair Appleton.</stage>
                  <view>The Colonel is a man of striking appearance, six feet four, stalwart and
                     strong in spite of his sixty-five years. His glance is keen and piercing from
                     under beetling brows. His carriage is military yet his whole personality
                     emanates a fine graciousness and cheer.</view>
                  <p>He thanks the immigrants for electing his commander in chief. He tells them
                     that they are about to set out into an unknown country - a country reputed to
                     be a land of Milk and Honey. In glowing words he paints Oregon - the richness
                     of its soil - the trees loaded with fruit - the streams abounding in fish; the
                     forest alive with game; to say nothing of the fabulous possibilities from trade
                     with the Indians; the pelts of beaver, of silver-fox, of mink, of ermine and
                     other fur-bearing animals. He <choice>
                        <sic>declaires</sic>
                        <corr>declares</corr>
                     </choice> Oregon to be the greatest agricultural country in the world needing
                     only the courageous pioneers to break its soil and dig from its bowels its
                     mineral wealth.</p>
                  <pb n="B-5."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-5.</fw>
                  <camera>The camera pans around the circle of faces of the pioneers. Nearly every
                     man and woman there is inspired by hope and the desire to reach the <q>Promised
                        Land</q>. Their commander’s words evoke the wildest enthusiasm and
                     excitement and he is cheered to the echo.</camera>
                  <view>We show Colonel Appleton’s own wagon. This is an especially fine covered
                     wagon, practically a moving household.</view>
                  <view>Standing up on the back step of the wagon looking out over the heads of the
                     engrossed crowd is the Colonel’s pretty daughter, Sally Lou. She is thrilled
                     and excited and does not hesitate to join in the applause for her
                     father.</view>
                  <stage type="mixed">From behind Sally comes out of the wagon Mandy, an old black
                     nurse and nanny. Nanny beams at the loudly clapping Sally Lou but her attention
                     is distracted by a less pleasing object. From around the side of the wagon a
                     tall black boy with a bullet head and rolling eyes comes slouching lazily to
                     the fore, a bucket in his hand which spills and shakes as Mose moves along.
                     Just as he comes under where Sally is standing Mose puts his thumb and
                     fore-finger into his mouth and <sound>lets out a most unearthly
                        whistle.</sound> Mandy casts one enraged glance at Mose and then reaching
                     her left foot she gives him a hard prod on the head knocking him over and the
                     pail of water spilling as he falls.</stage>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">SALOON AND DANCE HALL</stage>
                  <stage type="location">This is the town of Independence.</stage>
                  <view>The atmosphere of the place is smoky and sultry. <pb n="B-6."/><fw
                        type="pageNum">B-6.</fw> rough men of all sorts and kind are about the place
                     gambling, making love to the girls, drinking and lining the bar.</view>
                  <p>Here are dark French Canadian Voyageurs, long blonde Missourians, Mexicans,
                     Swedes, Yanks, Jews, Englishmen, big fellows from the frontier towns.</p>
                  <view><choice>
                        <sic>Handsfull</sic>
                        <corr>Hands full</corr>
                     </choice> of silver are thrown or slapped down upon the bar. All comers are
                     treated regardless.</view>
                  <view><sound>The fiddles scrape and the music rises above the discordant murmurs
                        and imprecations.</sound> Buxom girls of all colors spin out upon the floor.
                     They are grabbed by the men, whooping with delight, and they thumping or
                     spinning with them across the floor. Near fights or real ones are precipitated
                     and averted.</view>
                  <view>One black eyed girl - she is known as Black Eyed Susan is the center of a
                     group of men all clamoring to dance or drink with her. Sue has large, bold,
                     roving eyes. Everyone is asking her where Bull is and she says he’s somewhere
                     in town. One fellow says; <q>Well don’t tell on me</q>! He pinches her on the
                     backside and gives her a good smack on the lips. Susan though she laughs gives
                     him a push.</view>
                  <p>The one subject of conversation everywhere is - OREGON. Everybody is talking of
                     Oregon, and the immense train of Immigrants starting out for Oregon lands. Even
                     the dancing girls talk Oregon to their partners. <view>Some of them ask the men
                        if they are going too, and when the men nod, <pb n="B-7"/><fw type="pageNum"
                           >B-7</fw> they pretend to bid them mock farewells, saying that the man
                        who goes into Oregon never comes out</view>. They make jokes about not
                     liking baldheads, and the Indians always get their men. They think it funny to
                     suggest that 2000 scalps will make a splendid carpet for Indian wigwams. They
                     say that Immigrant scalps are especially soft. </p>
                  <view>In one of the rooms of the saloon, Bull Doreen and his men are also
                     discussing the Immigrants. Bull is a huge, brutal looking customer. He wears a
                     red flannel shirt and buckskin breeches. His knife is stuck in his belt, his
                     gun on his hip.</view>
                  <p>Bull has done a profitable and illicit trade among the Indians, supposedly as a
                     trapper; in reality as a vendor of corn whiskey and rum. The Indians have
                     cached away immense quantities of valuable silver fox and beaver pelts. Bull is
                     anxious to get up into the country to trade his booze for this fur, before the
                     immigrants pour in. If once they settle upon the land; if in fact they reach
                     the Williamette valley<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Eaton is likely
                        referring to Oregon’s Willamette Valley which is written throughout the
                        screenplay as <q>Williamette</q>.</note> ahead of Bull’s outfit, his
                     business will be ruined. Already too many immigrants have gone through. Now
                     this largest of all trains - 2000 strong - will spread over the Indian lands
                     like locusts. It will mean the end of Bull’s trade with the Indians.</p>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>In the saloon, some commotion and stir is occasioned by the arrival of the
                     two young scouts Ren and Thad. They are popular and well known, and their
                     entrance is greeted with whoops. The young fellows goodnaturedly set up the
                     drinks for the crowd.</view>
                  <pb n="B-8."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-8.</fw>
                  <view>Bull and his men have also come into the saloon, and at a signal from Bull
                     Susan speeds to his side. He gives her some orders, and she nods and hurries to
                     obey him. Susan insinuates her way through the crowd till she manages to come
                     alongside Thad and slips her hand through his arm. Thad has had a couple of
                     drinks and is in high good humor. He looks down his shoulder and meets Susan’s
                     black seductive eyes.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SUSAN</speaker>
                     <p>‘Lo Thad! Gee, I’m sure glad to see you. Where you been?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>I’m glad to see you too, Susy. I’ve been up in the woods for sometime.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SUSAN</speaker>
                     <p>Pretty lonesome, ain’t it? You was always fond of good times.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(uneasily, yet affected)</stage>
                     <p>Well, I got into a peck of trouble with good times.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren, leaning against the bar, with a couple of girls interposing between him
                     and his partner. Ren gives a wry squint across at the pair, and then as the
                     bartender puts another drink before Thad, and as Thad picks it up, Ren reaches
                     a long arm across and takes the glass from his hand. His action is good
                     humored, but firm. There is a squall of protest.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Guess we better be driftin’ along <pb n="B-9."/><fw type="pageNum">B-9.</fw>
                        partner. Them immigrants is waitin’ fer us.</p>
                  </sp>

                  <p>The girls and men make remarks:</p>
                  <sp>
                     <p><q>Let ’em wait</q>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p><q>What’s the hurry</q>?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p><q>You’ll be a long time on the trail with those psalm singing folk. Wait a
                           bit</q>!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>And so forth. Susan is hanging tight onto Thad, and her body is pressed
                     against him. Thad’s glance shifts from his pal to Sue. He feels a bit sheepish. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SUSAN</speaker>
                     <p>Gee, I’ve missed you! The town’s not been the same since you left.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Ren’s attention is turned from his pal, by Bull’s greeting. </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>How’re you -- Ren Bullock?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Ren slowly turns, and still leaning up against the bar he
                     looks with a queer, quizzical slowly sizing up glance at Bull Dorien. </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>What you doin’ in Independence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>What me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>Thought you was up in the Oregon. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>What me? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="B-10."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-10.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>How’s tradin’ and trappin’ up to the North? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>You oughter know. You wuz up there recent - talkin’ with your Indian
                        friends, wasn’t you? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Bull glares. Ren grins. His grin is not without a touch of boyish malice.
                     Almost lazily and reluctantly he slouches a bit nearer to the black browed
                     Bull. Bull’s glance goes by Ren. His eyes bore like gimlets into Susan’s. Hers
                     reflect their momentary fear. </view>
                  <view>Thad, as his pal moves toward Bull, half starts to follow. The bartender has
                     set another glass before Susan. She lifts it first toward her own lips and then
                     coaxingly toward his. Thad holds back a moment; but the liquor and Susan’s eyes
                     are too much for the weak Thad. He swallows, licks and smacks his lips. Another
                     glass slid across the bar. Thad glances at it wistfully out of the tail of his
                     eye. Susan lifts it to his lips. He holds back a moment, and then, his eyes on
                     Susan he downs it. Susan plucks at his sleeve. She puts her lips against his
                     ear and whispers. Thad’s <choice>
                        <sic>drousy</sic>
                        <corr>drowsy</corr>
                     </choice> eyes glean with awakening desire, for Susan’s body is pressed against
                     his. He swallows, his head nodding. They move off. </view>
                  <view>Ren does not see them go. Elbow on bar, his back against it, Ren’s wry
                     glance is on Bull. Bull shifts his tobacco, spits, waits for the smiling Ren to
                     speak. Ren says not a word. </view>
                  <pb n="B-11"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-11</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>Hear tell yo’re plannin’ to steer them Immigrants up to the Williamette.
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>What me? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>What trail you aimin’ to go by?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren pushes back his wide hat, scratches his head thoughtfully. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Which would you take if you was me? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>You’ll never get across the Divide with them wagons. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Reckon you’re right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>And there ain’t a chance of them green tenderfeet crossin’ the Columbia
                        neither.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Now you got me worried. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Bull slouches nearer to him. He lowers his voice to a husky whisper.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>That ain’t no man’s job -- playin’ nursemaid to a bunch of soft immigrants.
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren considers this, screwing up his eyes thoughtfully.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Mebbe you’re right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="B-12"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-12</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> What’re they payin’ you? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> We--cl-- the price ain’t exactly set yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Bull comes back quickly this time.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> Whatever they offer -- I’ll double -- see?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren raises his eyes wide with apparent surprise and unholy joy.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Thought you knew the Oregon Country better than I did. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> So I do. I ain’t hirin’ you for a guide. </p>
                  </sp>

                  <view>Ren’s manner is guileless and friendly. His eye now lifts unquestioningly.
                     He lets the other do the talking.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> Without guides them Immigrants can’t get beyond the Dalles. They’ll never
                        get across the Columbia. There ain’t no other guides to be had. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> That so? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(confidentially)</stage>
                     <p>You know it. What’s more we don’t want them Immigrants up in the Oregon.
                        They aint’ good for nothin’. They’ll spread <pb n="B-13"/><fw type="pageNum"
                           >B-13</fw> all over the land like lice.</p>
                  </sp>

                  <view>Ren appears to be impressed.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I hadn’t thought a that. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> The Oregon ain’t no country for the likes a them. The Indians aren’t
                        lookin’ for no religion. What they want is booze. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I’m thinkin’ what the Indians need is -- food. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> Well where they gonna get the good if them Immigrants settle on their land?
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> It ain’t the Immigrants that’s poison to the Indians. They’ll do a fair and
                        honest trade with them. It’s the fellows with the Booze that ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>He stops abruptly and smiles at Bull.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Fergot all about that bein’ ye’re game, Bull. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (angry) </stage>
                     <p>It don’t make no different what my game is. I put a proposition up to ya. Is
                        it yes or no? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (considering) </stage>
                     <p> I’ll talk it over with my pardner -- </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="B-14"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-14</fw>
                  <view>He glances toward where Thad had been, and straightens up.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ren</speaker>
                     <p> Well guess I’ll drift. See you later. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>He moves away, strolling lazily along, good-naturedly pushing aside the
                     girls that come around him, or pausing to joke, throwing a handful of silver on
                     the bar and treating all hands except himself, and <q>drifting</q> off
                     gradually till he comes to a door, giving upon an alley way and exits. </view>
                  <view>Once outside, his careless lazy manner changes. He is alert, as he looks
                     swiftly about him. With a hand to the side of his mouth he gives forth <sound>a
                        peculiar whistle three times.</sound> At first there is no response.
                        <sound>Ren whistles again.</sound>
                  </view>
                  <view>From a room at the far end of the alley, where a dim light shows comes
                     somewhat waveringly <sound>Thad’s answering whistle.</sound> Ren wheels about,
                     and is off in the direction from which the whistle has come. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">THE IMMIGRANT ENCAMPMENT</stage>
                  <stage type="setting">The camp presents a cheerful appearance. Groups of cattle,
                     horse and other stock are grazing on the prairie hardby, while the numerous
                     white tents, the wagon covers and the flares and glow of the brightly burning
                     campfires give almost the appearance of a village, or a homelike community. The
                     music of the fiddle and guitar are heard, and around <pb n="B-15"/><fw
                        type="pageNum">B-15</fw> the Colonel’s wagon, a number of young folks are
                     gathered, some of them dancing a gay measure on the greensward.</stage>
                  <view>Sitting by the fires, on the steps of their wagons, on boxes, or camp
                     stools, the older people look on indulgently. </view>
                  <view>Gayest of all the young people and the most sought after is Sally Lou,
                     laughing as she dances, and having her hands full keeping pace among the young
                     blades of the party already contesting for her favor. </view>
                  <view>Over the brow of a hill, that lies between the encampment and the town of
                     Independence, a party of horsemen are seen. They ride down toward the Immigrant
                     camp, dismount outside the circle and come into the enclosure. They are Bull
                     Dorien and a couple of his men. Bull inquires who is in charge of the
                     expedition and is directed to Colonel Appleton. Bull’s manner is all affability
                     as he holds out his hand to the Colonel and explains that he is a trader and
                     trapper in the Oregon country; that he is returning there the following day and
                     thought possibly he could be of some assistance to the train -- perhaps the
                     Immigrants could use a couple of fine guides. Colonel Appleton thanks him but
                     replies that they have already arranged to apply two well known scouts - Ren
                     Bullock and Thad Jones. The two men have been highly recommended by the <choice>
                        <sic>Hudsons</sic>
                        <corr>Hudson’s</corr>
                     </choice> Bay Company at Fort <choice>
                        <sic>VanCouver</sic>
                        <corr>Vancouver</corr>
                     </choice> with whom the Colonel has been in correspondence and he has been
                     informed that they know every inch of the country and are absolutely reliable.
                        <pb n="B-16."/><fw type="pageNum">B-16.</fw>
                  </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>You ain’t speakin’ of Ren Bullock and Thad Jones? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>COLONEL</speaker>
                     <p>Those are the names of our guides, sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage><sound>Bull whistles.</sound></stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> Well that’s too bad! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>COLONEL</speaker>
                     <p> What do you mean? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Bull pretends to hesitate and shakes his head as if worried. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>COLONEL</speaker>
                     <p> Kindly explain yourself, sir. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> We-el ya see - them two fellows are up in town on a spree. There ain’t a
                        chance of them bein’ able to pull out for several days. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>This statement causes immense excitement among the Immigrants, who are
                     crowding about the Colonel’s wagon. Sally runs up beside her father and takes
                     his arm. Everyone around is talking at once, and the word soon spreads right
                     and left through the camp that their guides are on a drunk. The Immigrants are
                     opposed to trusting their fortunes to a couple of drunkards.</view>
                  <view>While the matter is being heatedly debated and argued, a curious little
                     cavalcade rides into the encampment. Sitting straight and easy in the saddle is
                     Ren Bullock. He is leading <pb n="B-17."/><fw type="pageNum">B-17.</fw> another
                     horse across which is the dead drunk Thad, clumsily concealed by a great burlap
                     spread. He brings his horse to a stop, puts back his wide hat and scratches his
                     head as if puzzled. As he raises his voice the Immigrants turn and look toward
                     him. Red rides right into the circle.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Can any of you folks tell me who all is in charge here? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Colonel Appleton steps forward. He bows a bit stiffly. Ren looks down at him
                     from his place on his horse, and then quite by chance his glance goes beyond
                     the Colonel, and he sees Sally Lou. Sally is standing by her father’s side. She
                     is watching the new arrival with tense interest. For a moment the two young
                     people look at each other, and then with an embarrassed motion, Ren awkwardly
                     removes his big hat and dismounts. He stands between the two horses, holding
                     their heads by the reins. He has not heard a word of Colonel Appleton’s
                     dignified explanation, to the effect that he has been elected commander in
                     chief; that there are three divisions each with its individual captain, and
                     that every man in the outfit has been assigned to some special duty. He pauses
                     to ask Ren who he is and what he wants. Ren replies; <q>I’m your guide,
                     sir</q>.</view>
                  <view>During the foregoing a certain inquiring spinster has been suspiciously
                     looking at the burden on the other horse’s back. She has edged near to it, and
                     has begun to lift the <pb n="B-18."/><fw type="pageNum">B-18.</fw> burlap, when
                     her hand touches something and she emits a <choice>
                        <sic>squeel</sic>
                        <corr>squeal</corr>
                     </choice> of terror. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SPINSTER</speaker>
                     <p> What’s that? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Jes a piece of no account baggage, <choice>
                           <sic>maam</sic>
                           <corr>ma’am</corr>
                        </choice>. </p>
                  </sp>

                  <stage type="action">The spinster looks at him in suspicion. She edges over to the
                     Colonel and says in a hollow whisper;</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SPINSTER</speaker>
                     <p> Colonel -- it’s a corpse! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Bull, who had kept in the background, gives the wink to one of his men. The
                     latter is a skinny, foxy little one-eyed man named Lefty. <choice>
                        <sic>Left</sic>
                        <corr>Lefty</corr>
                     </choice> slips over and pulls the burlap from the sprawled over figure,
                     revealing Thad, lying face downward, his head dangling over one side of the
                     horse, his legs on the other. There are screams from some of the women.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> It’s just my pardner. </p>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (slightly embarrassed) </stage>
                     <p> He’s takin’ a little sleep. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LEFTY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (cackling) </stage>
                     <p> He’s drunk. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>The Immigrants by now are thoroughly opposed to being guided by such a
                     disreputable pair. Colonel Appleton tells Ren that the deal is off. Ren is
                     disposed to argue the matter. He and his pardner have come all the way from the
                     Williamette Valley to take on the job. They are good guides -- none better in
                     the country. What’s more the Immigrants will have a hard time finding guides
                     who know the Oregon Trail. Col. Appleton tells him they have already engaged
                     other men, and he indicates Lefty and Pete. Ren stares at the two men, and then
                     his glance rests on Bull. A wry smile twists his features, </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I’m powerful sorry for you, sir. Guess me and my pal’ll drift. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>He throws his leg over his horse’s back, and moves off. He barely reached
                     the side of the encampment when he is hailed by a curious looking man, who
                     comes running after him. Ren pulls up, and looks down at the bespectacled
                     little man, with rifle slung on his shoulder, and helmet on his head, a
                     portfolio under his arm, and his pockets bulging with various articles. Ren’s
                     face lights with a friendly grin.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIGGINS</speaker>
                     <p> One minute! I’ll have a word with you. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Yes sir? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIGGINS</speaker>
                     <p> My name’s Diggins - Prof. Alonzo Diggins. I’m going into Oregon by the
                        mountain route to make a practical study of geological strata and flora of
                        that interesting region. I need a guide. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Fine. I’m your man, sir. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIGGINS</speaker>
                     <p> You’re engaged. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="B-20"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-20</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> How many are you? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIGGINS</speaker>
                     <p>Just myself, sir. <q>He travels the fastest who travels alone</q>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="action"> (smiling) </stage>
                     <p> I reckon ye’re right. Me and my pardner was engaged to take two thousand so
                        I reckon we can handle your outfit of one. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIGGINS</speaker>
                     <p> That’s my wagon over there. It’s completely outfitted with every scientific
                        instrument and implement necessary for such a trip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action"> They are moving along toward <choice>
                        <sic>Diggins</sic>
                        <corr>Diggins’s</corr>
                     </choice> wagon. </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I hope it’s outfitted with plenty of food, sire. It takes a powerful lot of
                        food for a four months’ trip to the Oregon. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIGGINS</speaker>
                     <p> Yes, yes, food of course -- the necessary evil I suppose. But as I was
                        saying, the scientific importance --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> They are now at <choice>
                        <sic>Diggins</sic>
                        <corr>Diggins’s</corr>
                     </choice> wagon. <choice>
                        <sic>Diggons</sic>
                        <corr>Diggins</corr>
                     </choice> is proudly opening the flap and has crawled into the wagon but Ren
                     does not follow him. Ren has made the delightful discovery that the next wagon
                     to Diggins is none other than the Appleton wagon, on the steps of which sits
                     Sally Lou. </view>
                  <view>Ren stands perfectly still, smiling at Sally. Sally, forgetting herself,
                     starts to return the smile and then her face becomes very cool as she tosses
                     her head and looks over the head of Ren as if he were not there at all. </view>
                  <pb n="B-21."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-21.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Mandy! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker> MANDY’S VOICE </speaker>
                     <stage type="location"> (inside wagon) </stage>
                     <p> Yes, Miss Sally Lou. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> I’ll be right in, Mandy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> She stands up. Out of the tail of her eye she manages to see that the young
                     man is still standing looking at her and then Sally goes inside. </view>
                  <stage> Ren gives a big blissful sigh and turns to <choice>
                        <sic>Diggin’s</sic>
                        <corr>Diggins’s</corr>
                     </choice> wagon. </stage>
                  <!-- Note by LW1: Should this be stage or view? -->
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="C-0"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE C</head>
                  <stage type="setting"> The Immigrant train is now on its way. The long line of
                     wagons, horses, mules, herds of cattle and other stock move like an army in
                     review. Wide-horned oxen yoked eight to a wagon. These wagons moving households
                     in which the family life is carried on. </stage>
                  <view>Hickory shirted teamsters roaring <q>Whoos</q> or cursing the oxen. Singing,
                     shouting niggers;<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This is an offensive
                        racial slur that appears multiple times in this text. Please see our <ref
                           target="doc:note_on_language">note on language</ref>.</note>
                     corn-crackers in homespun and high boots <q>gee-hawing</q> their mule teams.
                     Teamsters, cracking eight foot bull whips and squirting yellow tobacco juice
                     from bulging jaws; wagons milling in their dust. Some of the owners of the
                     outfits driving in light springed wagons; other ahorse. Men plodding afoot at
                     the side of each wagon. </view>
                  <view> Healthy children, rosy faces, peering from the wagons. </view>
                  <view> Buxom damsels in sunbonnets and cotton dresses on the front seats of the
                     wagon, beside the driver, or driving themselves. Others riding horseback, with
                     a youngster or two behind them. </view>
                  <view> Some of the women knitting and sewing as the wagons move along. Others idly
                     strumming on banjo or guitar. </view>
                  <view>In the rear of the caravan the droves of cattle and an endless army of
                     mules.</view>
                  <view> Immediately following the guides, at the head of the long parade comes the
                     fine covered wagon of the Commander in Chief, Col. Appleton. It is driven by
                     the drowsy Mose, and <pb n="C-1."/><fw type="pageNum">C-1.</fw> sitting beside
                     Mose is Sally Lou. Occasionally Sally Lou takes the reins in her own competent
                     hands, and once she orders the sleepy Mose off the wagon, and the latter tags
                     on afoot, yawning. </view>
                  <view>Riding alongside the Appleton wagon on a fine Kentucky horse is the Colonel.
                     He looks very splendid and important and Sally is proud of her father.
                     Occasionally the Colonel forgets his dignity, in so far as to ride to the tail
                     of the wagon, from whence Mandy’s big black hand issues with some favorite
                     edible or delicacy. The Colonel bites into a luscious doughnut or piece of
                     Johnny cake. Then he clears his throat wipes the crumbs from his vest,
                     straightens up in his saddle and looking very stern and serious, canters down
                     the line of wagons, on a military tour of inspection.</view>
                  <p>The train is broken up into three companies, each in its way distinctive. The
                     companies are divided from each other by the pack mules, but none the less they
                     are within close touch of each other and <choice><sic>then</sic><corr>when</corr></choice> they go into camp all three
                     companies are on hand. </p>
                  <p>The first of the companies and the largest is made up mainly of the farmers.
                     The second includes the missionaries, teachers and others. The third is made up
                     of a bold congregation of adventurers, gamblers, hunters, trappers and traders.
                     Bull Dorien and a number of his men have cast their lot with this third
                     company. Although each company has its individual captain they are all under
                     the head of the expedition Commander <pb n="C-2."/><fw type="pageNum">C-2.</fw>
                     in Chief, Col. Appleton. </p>
                  <view>Travelling over a hill trail comes the little train in charge of Thad and
                     Ren. the two young guides are on horseback, but Prof. Diggins sits on the front
                     seat of the prairie schooner, and ever and anon almost gives the driver heart
                     failure, as he leaps agilely out in search of some particular specimen in flora
                     or to examine, on the edge of some steep precipice, certain rock formations. </view>
                  <view>Once the little professor gets out of the wagon and slides down a cliff to
                     examine some bright specimens he had seen through his field glasses. He seems
                     to have a charmed life, and by clinging to stumps and roots, actually returns
                     with his portfolio of pressed flowers still under his arm and his hand
                     clutching the specimens he went after. Ren and Thad who have dismounted, assist
                     him to the top, but are in no mood to listen to his excited rhapsodies over his
                     find. Ren picks up his field glasses. As he looks off across the skyline, great
                     clouds of dust or sand seem to be arising. Ren puts the glasses to his eyes,
                     and focuses them. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Here they come!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>On the lower trail the Immigrant train is coming into sight. Ren watches
                     intently, but his glass moves along the line till it picks out and stays turned
                     on the first wagon of the train. Then he sighs and smiles.</view>
                  <pb n="C-3"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">C-3</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p> What are you looking at, Ren? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> There’s a powerful fine girl in that first wagon and she’s pretty as a
                        daisy, an’ she’s different from other gels<note type="editorial"
                           >girls</note> -- </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage> (laughing) </stage>
                     <p> Well, you old, long-legged cayuse you! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Well take a look fer yerself an’ give yer eyes a treat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Ren hands the glasses to Thad. Thad focuses them upon the first wagon. The
                     girl in the driver’s seat turns her face so that he sees it clearly - she is
                     Sally Lou Appleton. The glasses almost drop from Thad’s hands, his lips are
                     quivering, his face has turned pale. Ren gives him a sharp look then he smiles. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Thought you’d get a shock! They ain’t many girls as pretty as that one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action"> Thad does not reply. His glance shifts nervously about. </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> What say we go down an’ make a neighborly call? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p> One of us ought to stay with the Professor and the outfit. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Never knew you to be so concerned with the Professor before. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="C-4"/>

                  <view>He turns around in his saddle and gives a beaming look at Thad.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> That’s darn handsome of you, Thad. All right then I’ll be driftin’ along.
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Twilight is falling. The western sky is like a sea of Mother of Pearl. The
                     inescapable charm of the desert pervades the land. </view>
                  <view>The caravan of the Immigrants is seen rising and dipping along its course,
                     men, wagons, horses, mules, cattle. <sound>Occasionally voices rise and can be
                        heard over a vast distance because of the clearness of the air. Men speak to
                        their horses; shout to each other. The crack of whips is heard. Someone
                        whistles. There is the sound of the clear notes of a bugle, calling for a
                        halt.</sound> The train has reached a suitable place for encampment.
                        <sound>Now a movement that is almost military ensues.</sound> The train is
                     wheeling into three circles, the leading wagons circling along individual
                     tracks, till an almost perfect formation results. As each wagon is brought into
                     position, with their tongues turned toward the center, the teams are unjoked.
                     The cattle turnout out to graze. Horses are hobbled. The men fall to work
                     making fires and setting up the rude tents for the night, while the teamsters
                     and mule boys take care of their charges. The women, both in the wagons, and on
                     the ground prepare the evening meal.</view>
                  <view> Ren is disclosed riding toward the camp. He goes directly to the first
                     wagon, dismounts and stands hesitatingly <pb n="C-5."/><fw type="pageNum"
                        >C-5.</fw> outside for a moment. As he hesitates, Sally Lou’s voice inside,
                     calls out; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker> SALLY LOU </speaker>
                     <p> Is that you, darling? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="location"> (outside wagon) </stage>
                     <p> Yes--no--that is--er--yes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> There is silence for a moment. Inside the wagon, Sally Lou, who has been
                     setting the table, pauses as she looks at Mandy busy at the stove. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> That doesn’t sound like daddy --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> She opens the flap at back and stands looking down at Ren. The latter
                     removes his hat and tries to appear at his ease. Sally gives him a very severe
                     look however. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> I thought I was speaking to my father. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I was hopin’ you might be speakin’ to me. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> You certainly have most extraordinary hopes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> She is about to go inside, when Ren makes an impulsive movement toward
                     her.</view>
                  <pb n="C-6"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">C-6</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Excuse me, Miss, but I come on down to pay you all a little neighborly
                        visit. </p>
                  </sp>

                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Now I recall you. You were the guide who got drunk and --- </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> Not me. That was my ornery pardner. You see I reckoned that mebbe you all
                        would be needin’ real guides. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> We’ve got along very well with the ones we have, thank you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Colonel Appleton, who has been on a tour of inspection over the camp, rides
                     up and dismounts. He does not immediately recognize Ren, and Sally for the
                     moment forgets that she has told Ren that all has gone well with them. She asks
                     anxiously; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Well, daddy? Have they found the stock? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>APPLETON</speaker>
                     <p> No. Most remarkable and mysterious matter. Sixty head now -- to say nothing
                        of the mules. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(distressed)</stage>
                     <p> That’s dreadful. If this keeps on -- if we lose any more stock, we won’t
                        have enough to --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> She stops, recalling Ren. Her father too looks at the young man
                     inquiringly. </view>
                  <pb n="C-7."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">C-7.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Daddy, this man was to have been our guide and --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Appleton frowns now. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>APPLETON</speaker>
                     <p> Rumph! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I’m travelin’ over the Mount Hood route, and I come down thinkin’ mebbe
                        you’d be needin’ help -- </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>APPLETON</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (curtly) </stage>
                     <p> We are not in need of your services. I do not believe in swapping hoses
                        amid stream -- </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Oh, Daddy -- er -- maybe this gentleman could help us find some of our
                        cattle. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> You losin’ your stock, sir? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Appleton</speaker>
                     <p> Not at all -- nothing to speak of.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> He glares grouchily, and then moves to go into the wagon bellowing: </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>APPLETON</speaker>
                     <p> Mandy! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MANDY</speaker>
                     <stage type="setting" place="inline">(inside)</stage>
                     <p> Ya-as--sir? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>APPLETON</speaker>
                     <p> Is dinner ready? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="C-8."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">C-8.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MANDY</speaker>
                     <p> Jes’ in a shake, Marse Appleton.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Sally Lou steals a ruseful glance from her father to Ren. Ren looks at
                     Sally. He smiles. Sally starts to return the smile and then tries to look very
                     dignified and haughty. Ren mounts his horse and rides off. </view>
                  <p> Sally stands looking after him a moment and then she flashes around on her
                     father. </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Daddy, I think you were horridly rude. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>APPLETON</speaker>
                     <p> Now Sally. I know what I’m about. With sixty head of our cattle and any
                        number of mules missing we can’t afford to take up with any strangers that
                        come to our camp. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> He came over to see if he could help us, and that’s all the thanks he
                        got.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> She runs up steps of wagon and exits inside. </view>
                  <view> She appears a few minutes later in the front of the wagon where Mose is <choice>
                        <sic>dosing</sic>
                        <corr>dozing</corr>
                     </choice>. She gives him a shake. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (in big whisper) </stage>
                     <p> Mose! Mose --you lazy nigger<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This is
                           an offensive racial slur that appears multiple times in this text. Please
                           see our <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note on language</ref>.</note>
                        you -- wake up! </p>
                  </sp>

                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MOSE</speaker>
                     <p> Ya-as-sum, Miss Sally Lou. what you all want?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Look-a-here Mose.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="C-9."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">C-9.</fw>
                  <view> She shows him a generous portion of a chicken and a big piece of cornbread.
                     They are rolled up in a snowy napkin. Mose’s eyes roll, and he swallows. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p> Now listen to me Mose. You see that horseman travelin’ yonder ----? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MOSE</speaker>
                     <p> Yassum, Miss Sally Lou. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I want you to ketch<note type="editorial">catch</note> up with him.
                        Run your hardest Mose - and I want you to take this chicken to him and you
                        can mention the fact that it’s sent with the compliments of Col. Appleton’s
                        wagon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>The more Mose looks at the chicken the wider awake he becomes. He takes the
                     napkin with its precious contents from Miss Sally, jumps down from the wagon
                     and is off.</view>
                  <view>We show Mose. Ahead of him, loping slowly and disconsolately along is Ren.
                     Mose’s nostrils dilate. He slackens his pace. Mose lifts the chicken to his
                     nose - sniffs. He begins to go <choice>
                        <sic>shower and shower</sic>
                        <corr>slower and slower</corr>
                     </choice>. Now he licks his lips. His eyes shift and roll. He stops. He turns
                     back a bit of the napkin, and succumbs to temptation. He takes first a nibble,
                     and then a bigger bite. Finally he swallows the whole of the meal.</view>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="D-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE D</head>
                  <stage type="setting"><camera>A series of dissolve shots</camera> should mark the
                     passage and reveal the gradual deterioration of the Immigrant train.</stage>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p> In the beginning it was smooth going. The trail is excellent; the weather
                     clear and fine. Hearts are light and hopes high. The train moves along like a
                     great, well captained army. </p>
                  <p> Then begins the hazards. </p>
                  <p>First the almost daily loss of cattle and stock. This, we will bring out, is
                     the work of Bull and his gang, but with the loss of their stock, and the
                     mysterious destruction of harnesses and other equipment, a panic spreads
                     throughout the companies. Arguments and dissensions arise; fostered by agents
                     of Bull. Many are in favor of turning back. </p>
                  <p> The morale of the companies is weakened. Everyone looks to Col. Appleton for a
                     solution. He has his hands full maintaining order and keeping the peace. </p>
                  <p> Sally watches wistfully for the return of Ren Bullock. That little olive
                     branch sent by Mose has not proven fruitful. Sally is hurt. </p>
                  <p> Ren, never having received Sally’s gift, (demolished by the hungry Mose) has
                     struck out over the hill route. </p>
                  <p> Meanwhile, as the Immigrant train proceeds more hazards and hardships were
                     their lot. </p>
                  <pb n="D-2."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">D-2.</fw>
                  <view> Mosquitoes and flies and gnats and ants swarmed in clouds about them. <choice>
                        <sic>Rattles names</sic>
                        <corr>Rattlesnakes</corr>
                     </choice> and rats got into their wagons. Axels give way. Tops of poorly built
                     wagons were blown off. </view>
                  <p> Cholera broke out in the camp, taking its heavy toll. </p>
                  <view> After a vicious sandstorm, when for hours the cutting blasts of hot sand
                     beat back the travellers, filling their nostrils, burning their eyes, with
                     alkali dust, the morale of the train is so affected that a faction arises
                     demanding that they give up the expedition and return. Delegations wait upon
                     the Commander, and when Appleton refuses to accede to their demands, large
                     groups of the Immigrants begin to desert in growing numbers, carrying away with
                     them, not only their own stock and supplies but quite often the property
                     belonging to the others. </view>
                  <stage type="setting"> Miles over a desert country - no water. A long trek and at
                     last a pool of water. Thirstily the Immigrants dip their cups into the water
                     only to find it alive with squirming tadpoles. </stage>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - - - - - -</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="E-2"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE E</head>
                  <sound>Indian drums.</sound>
                  <view><sound>Three hundred Indians beating their drums, singing and
                        shouting</sound> and circling in a savage war dance. Their dresses simulate
                     wild buffalo and wolves. <sound>Their padding feet seem to become louder with
                        every step.</sound> As they circle, their women and old men and children,
                     squatting on the ground, <sound>wail and screech.</sound>
                  </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>
                     <sound>Suddenly from over the hill resound other wild war whoops.</sound> A
                     crowd of horsemen appear and ride full speed toward the circling Indians.
                     Another tribe has come to join. As they ride, <sound>each warrior sings his war
                        song.</sound> They are in war regalia, antelope skins and eagle feathers,
                     and around their tunics they carry the scalps of the enemies. On their backs
                     are bows and arrows, and some carry long lances. Their advent is greeted with
                     savage zeal and joy. They join the circling warriors, themselves forming an
                     outer circle on horse. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - -</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="F-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE F.</head>
                  <stage type="setting">A thickly wooded glen.</stage>
                  <view>Here we find encamped, Ren and his outfit. It is midday, and their horses
                     are saddled; their mules yoked to the wagon, yet they are not moving. The delay
                     is caused by the absence of Diggins who has wandered off, in his usual way. Ren
                     is a bit uneasy, and sends his Indian off to look for Diggins. </view>
                  <stage type="novelistic"> There will be dialogue here between Ren and Thad
                     bringing out that they are now in Indian territory, and have been about three
                     months on the trail. The train had left in mid-July. It is now mid-September.
                     Ren, a thorough woodsman, and knowing the country well, has taken excellent
                     care of his outfit. They show no signs of hardship. Thad is bored.</stage>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><camera>We cut to another part of the woods,</camera> and show the wandering
                     Diggins. Magnifying glass in hand he is absorbedly peering through it at some
                     specimen. </view>
                  <view> Watching him from behind the interlacing shrubbery is an Indian. He drops
                     on his knees, crawls a few paces on the ground, kneels up, takes his quiver and
                     bow and aims. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view> The arrow comes in and barely grazes the cheek of the abstracted and
                     absorbed Diggins. The latter merely blinks makes an absent motion with his hand
                     and continues to examine <pb n="F-2."/><fw type="pageNum">F-2.</fw> specimen. </view>
                  <view> The Indian in the woods has been joined by others -- five of them. They are
                     creeping silently and stealthily toward the unconscious Diggins. Now they are
                     on their feet, in a semicircle behind him. One of them brings his two hands
                     down on <choice><sic>Diggins</sic><corr>Diggins’s</corr></choice> shoulders, and the latter is swung around. One of the knocks
                     the helmet off <choice><sic>Diggins</sic><corr>Diggins’s</corr></choice> head which is revealed as practically bald, save for a
                     tuft of hair in front. Startled, but not terrified, the little scientist looks
                     up at the Indians, and then guilelessly smiles. The Indians are puzzled.
                     Diggins makes a confident, friendly motion, and says he’ll show them something
                     very remarkable. He holds the magnifying glass over an ant. It becomes
                     enormously enlarged under the glass. The Indians are astonished. They look
                     under the glass - start to touch it and then draw back, afraid. Diggins,
                     pleased with their interest, shows them his other treasures - the portfolio of
                     pressed flowers; the microscope, etc. The Indians are really amazed. They look
                     at Diggins with respect. Undoubtedly he is a magic man and these are his
                     talismans and charms. Diggins traps the heat from the sun with his magnifying
                     glass and burns the hand of first one then another Indian. The Indians are
                     divided between fleeing or taking the magic man. Diggins decides for them. He
                     is extremely interested in the Indians and has set his glasses more firmly on
                     his nose to study them. Making signs to them, he suggests that he <pb n="F-3."
                        /><fw type="pageNum">F-3.</fw> would like to accompany them. One of the
                     Indians speaks English and interprets. The others nod vigorously. They are now
                     very friendly. The leader takes off his moccasins. Diggins asks what this
                     means, and the interpreter replies: </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>INTERPRETER</speaker>
                     <p>It is the peace sign of our tribe, and means; <q>May I forever go barefoot,
                           if I deal not truly by thee</q>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> So pleased is Diggins to hear this, and anxious to study the Indians at
                     close quarters in their own village and wigwams, that he takes out a real
                     treasure, in the shape of a gold watch. This he dangles by the chain before the
                     chief, holds it to his ear and presents it to him. Then stooping he takes off
                     his own shoes. The Indians raise their hands, circle him in a dance of peace. </view>
                  <view> During the foregoing, Ren’s Indian is seen watching from behind a screen of
                     bushes. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">REN’S CAMP</stage>
                  <p><sound>The sound of muffled Indian drums is heard.</sound> Ren, concerned, is
                     listening. His Indian, Bowlegs, comes on. Ren asks him where Diggins is and
                     Bowlegs explains that he has made friends with the Indians and gone with
                     them.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I reckon that’s the last of little Diggins -- </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="F-4."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">F-4.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>INDIAN</speaker>
                     <p> Indians think him magic man. They no harm him. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery"> (grimly) </stage>
                     <p> Well, they’ll have a hard time scalping him anyway. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>INDIAN</speaker>
                     <p> He only got small piece of hair in front. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sound> The drums seem to be coming louder. </sound>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> I been hearin’ them drums all day. What do they mean? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BOWLEGS</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(somberly)</stage>
                     <p>They speak the language of war. Many braves of many tribes gather a moon’s
                        journey to the east.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Ren is startled. </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>What are they gathering for? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BOWLEGS</speaker>
                     <p>Maybe perhaps they attack white men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren turns about sharply. Thad, who has been stretched out on the ground half
                     asleep, raises himself on his elbow. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p> Think there’s any danger? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> There’s always danger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="F-5."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">F-5.</fw>
                  <view>He speaks to the Indian. He decides to dispatch him with a message to
                     Hudson’s Bay at Fort Vancouver, asking them to send down boats and supplies so
                     that the Immigrants may make the passage down the Columbia River unmolested and
                     safely. Leaving Thad in charge of the outfit, Ren rides off to scout the
                     neighborhood for signs of Indians and a possible <choice><sic>truce</sic><corr>trace</corr></choice> of Diggins. Bowlegs,
                     mounted on Thad’s horse, is off to the Hudson’s Bay Fort. Thad left alone is in
                     a bad humor and sulky.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - - - -</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="G-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE G</head>
                  <stage type="setting">Dawn is breaking over the Snake River.</stage>
                  <view>It discloses the Immigrant encampment at the base of a great canyon wall. Of
                     the 2000 souls that had left Independence, but two hundred remain.</view>
                  <stage type="novelistic"><sound>The bugle summons everyone to the morning
                        council.</sound> Col. Appleton<choice><sic>,</sic><corr></corr></choice> calls the roll of his people. There is a
                     brief summing up of the resources of the train, and then the old Colonel breaks
                     some painful news. During the night, their two guides have deserted the train,
                     taking with them the best of the mules and raiding the supply wagons. </stage>
                  <p>This is the crowning blow. Their supplies are depleted, their best mules gone;
                     they have no guides to lead them. It is characteristic of these hardy pioneers
                     however that after the first consternation and shock, they swiftly rally, and
                     in a short time, men are picked for a posse to go out in search of the renegade
                     guides and carry out without mercy the punishment decreed by the crude little
                     court. </p>
                  <view>Riding through a thickly wooded mountain trail, Ren stops suddenly, as he
                     sees coming up over the circuitous canyon route the two guides, Lefty and Pete.
                     They are driving a number of mules and are riding Appleton’s Kentucky horses.
                     Ren dismounts. From behind a giant rock, thickly overgrown with brush, Ren
                     watches the men as they come up around the circling trail, passing one by one
                     over the peak <pb n="G-2."/><fw type="pageNum">G-2.</fw> of the foothill. For a
                     moment Ren, puzzled, and at the same time having his suspicions aroused,
                     pauses, and then he follows. </view>
                  <view>When the last mule goes over the crest and dips down to the other side, Ren
                     realizes that he is taking a chance if he follows, as he will be clearly seen
                     from below. So he takes a perilous trail around the edge of the cliff that
                     comes out presently into the same canyon for which the guides are making. </view>
                  <view>He sees, then, camped in a glen halfway down the mountain, near the falls,
                     the company of trappers and others who had left the Immigrant train with Bull
                     Dorien. After watching the camp for a few moments, Ren remounts and rides back
                     along the trail over which he had come. </view>
                  <view> Ren returns to his camp. He sees no sign of Thad. <sound>Giving his
                        customary whistle,</sound> he receives no reply. A survey of the wagon and
                     the hobbled mules show, everything more or less shipshape, though one mule is
                     missing. <sound>Again he sends out the three whistle signals that the two men
                        are accustomed to give.</sound> No reply. <sound>Ren whistles again,</sound>
                     and this time, <sound>there is an answering shout,</sound> but not of the sort
                     he had expected. It sounds as if someone were hollering with hands to mouth. It
                     is not an Indian call. </view>
                  <pb n="G-3."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">G-3.</fw>
                  <view> While Ren looks about him puzzled the Immigrant Posse ride into sight and
                     dismount. Ren hears their story, and his own face becomes as grim as theirs. </view>
                  <view> It is now getting toward sundown. The men of the posse are weary. Their
                     horses are watered and turned out, hobbled to graze. Ren builds a fire, and
                     soon has bacon and potatoes sizzling over it. The Immigrants eat ravenously.
                     Ren learns that for days the entire train has been on rations. </view>
                  <milestone unit="scene"/>
                  <stage type="setting">BULL’S CAMP</stage>
                  <view> The flares from the campfires light the circle of rough faces. It is about
                     ten o’clock at night. </view>
                  <view>Sprawled on the ground<choice><sic>,</sic><corr></corr></choice> is Thad. he is half drunk and tossing dice with a
                     number of men. Prominent in the circle about the fire are the two guides from
                     the Immigrant train. They are talking to Bull, who grunts with approval.
                     Occasionally the men guffaw and slap their sides. There are about a dozen or
                     more men in the outfit - some of them from the original train, hunters,
                     trappers, voyageurs and others, as well as Bull’s own rum sellers. </view>
                  <view>
                     <sound>Suddenly three whistles are heard from out the bush.</sound> Thad lifts
                     his head and half unconsciously <sound>he replies to the whistles.</sound> Bull
                     starts up; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery">(furiously)</stage>
                     <pb n="G-4."/>
                     <fw type="pageNum">G-4.</fw>
                     <p>Who are you signalling to?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> From outside the circles comes the answer from a quiet drawling voice, as
                     Ren lazily strolls toward the fire. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>What me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Thad has partly recovered from his fright, and his shaking hand reaches for
                     the booze. Bull whirls around and sees the coolly smiling Ren. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>Well you then - who you whistlin’ to?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Ren has come up at the back of Thad and, as if by accident, his knee knocks
                     the drink from Thad’s hand. The latter looks about him uneasily. Bull strides
                     over till he is facing Ben. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> Thad has joined up with my outfit. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p><emph>What</emph> -- Thad?</p>
                  </sp>

                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>Ye-eh - Thad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Thad squirms miserably as Ren’s keen glance rests on him a moment. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p> That so? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>Ye-eh - thas so. Ask him.</p>
                     <pb n="G-5."/>
                     <fw type="pageNum">G-5.</fw>
                     <p> Come on, Thad - speak up. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p> I -- I -- th-think --- </p>
                     <stage> (gulping) </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p> I got enough on him to put the rope around his neck.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Thad crouches back. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>‘Less it gits round your own first.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> As if unaware of the menacing movement toward him, Ren turns around and his
                     eyes sweep the circle. A sardonic smile breaks over his face, as his glance
                     becomes fixed on the two guides. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Thought you wuz packin’ along with the Immigrants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LEFTY</speaker>
                     <p>Aw -- they’re on their way back.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>You don’t say.</p>
                     <stage type="delivery">(guilelessly)</stage>
                     <p>Are they leavin’ their horses and mules behind?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <stage place="inline">(raging)</stage>
                     <p>What business is that of yours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, I wuz jes mildly interested.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <p>You’re the only white or red man in</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="G-6."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">G-6.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                     <stage place="inline">continued</stage>
                     <p>these parts wants to see them immigrants git to Oregon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(thoughtfully)</stage>
                     <p>I reckon it wouldn’t be so good for some folks. Here tell the Immigrants are
                        takin’ through ploughs and threshers instead of <emph>RUM</emph>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view> Bull pulls off his hat and sends it sailing into the dark. He peels his
                     buckskin shirt over his head and flings it to the ground. The group fall back,
                     making a wide circle, their excited faces lighted by the camp fire flares. </view>
                  <view> Ren, who out of the tail of his eye, has watched the action of the other,
                     but has made no stir, suddenly takes a step forward and drives in with a right
                     swing. Bull ducks back, tries to run in and catches Ren’s left with the side of
                     his head. He falls a dozen feet away, but comes up spluttering and cursing,
                     with blood trickling down the side of his face. He circles the other warily.
                     Bull is bigger and a gorilla for strength, though Ren is half a head taller and
                     strong as a young ox. He waits for Bull with knees and hands lifted. Bull spits
                     curses, and calls him vile names challenging him to come on. Ren has a slight
                     smile on his face - a cool, amused look, and his left eyebrow lifts
                     quizzically. The infuriated Bull springs suddenly, driving with a lifted knee
                     and hard left. Ren sidesteps and gives him a terrific jolt in the belly. The
                     blow lands with a <pb n="G-7"/><fw type="pageNum">G-7</fw>
                     <sound>great thud.</sound> Bull stops in his tracks, while Ren throws a long
                     right at his mouth that splits it open. Bull sits down, spitting blood and
                     nearly mad with rage. </view>
                  <view><sound> The crowd is yelling and roaring. </sound></view>
                  <view> From out of the darkness and shadows of the encircling woods, step the
                     Immigrants, their guns cocked. Involuntarily hands are up. </view>
                  <view> Lefty and Pete are nearly petrified with terror. Pete makes a dive for
                     freedom but finds an iron grip upon his neck, as he is jerked back. Lefty,
                     shaking and stuttering tries to explain that they’d only come for a visit and
                     to get some help for the train. The Immigrants say nothing. They are doing
                     their work competently. While a couple of them round up the lost mules, hobbled
                     hardby; place packs of supplies upon their backs, others keep their guns cocked
                     on the company, while the group about the now <sound>screaming,
                        squealing</sound> guides deliberately place nooses about their necks, and
                     prepare to hand them then and there within sight of the camp. </view>
                  <p> A hunter hoarsely demands to know what the men have done, and Ren’s quiet,
                     incisive voice answers for the Immigrants. They have committed the crime of
                     crimes in that country. They had taken on the job of guiding two thousand
                     people into the Oregon country. They have misled and finally deserted them. As
                     a last act of cruelty, they <pb n="G-8."/><fw type="pageNum">G-8.</fw> have
                     stolen the <choice><sic>Immigrants</sic><corr>Immigrants’</corr></choice> mules and most of their chuck. </p>
                  <view> The men are hanged in the presence of the entire camp. </view>
                  <view> The little company of Immigrants and Ren, with their mules and supplies,
                     are leaving. Several of the hunters are returning with them. They prefer to
                     cast their fate again with the Immigrant train rather than continue with Bull’s
                     outfit. Ren is on his horse. He looks dead serious; almost sad, as he throws a
                     last look at the now almost deserted camp. A figure comes staggering toward
                     him. It is Thad. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Ren!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Yes - pardner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>I’d like to go with you ---- b-b-b-but--I d-d-d-don’t dare. He’s found out
                        ----</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Git on that horse!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>He reaches down a long arm and helps Thad onto the saddle of one of the
                     horses on which the late guides had ridden. The little cavalcade is off.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - - - - -</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="H-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE H</head>
                  <stage type="setting">The Immigrant camp on the banks of the Snake River.</stage>
                  <view>The Immigrants are in a state of tense anxiety. Their men, three days gone,
                     have not yet returned. Their chuck is reduced to the lowest ebb. A line of men,
                     women and children, are passing with tin plates and tin cups before a chuck
                     wagon. Sally is passing out the meagre rations.</view>
                  <stage type="novelistic">Inside the wagon Mandy discovers that they have come
                     practically to the end of their supplies. She warns Sally to hand out the stuff
                     sparingly and to be sure and keep enough for her father and herself.</stage>
                  <stage type="business">Some human stuff here, of Sally going among the women and
                     children, cheering them up, and assuring them their men will be back soon with
                     the lost chuck.</stage>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><camera>We cut to the top of the steep canyon wall.</camera> Crouched down
                     behind a boulder we see three Indians. One of them has just shot an arrow into
                     the Immigrant camp directly below them.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><camera>Dissolve to two of the Immigrant sentries.</camera> They are
                     patrolling the encampment. The first one comes around the side of the cliff. An
                     Indian leaps on him from behind. We see the hand of the Indian grasping the
                     sentry’s hair, and we know the hideous scalping operation is in force. </view>
                  <view>The second sentry has patrolled a portion of his beat <pb n="H-2."/><fw
                        type="pageNum">H-2.</fw> and has paused to listen to <sound>some
                        unaccustomed sound</sound>. He starts to move on, when we see the shadow of
                     an Indian cast before him. For a moment he is petrified with fear. Then he
                     leaps forward but not before an Indian knife plunges into his back. He whirls
                     around. A death struggle ensues between Indian and <choice>
                        <sic>whiteman</sic>
                        <corr>white man</corr>
                     </choice>. The white man is the victor.</view>
                  <view>Fearfully wounded he nonetheless leaps over the cliff to the river bank.
                     Staggering to his feet he tries to run to warn the Immigrants; but his life is
                     ebbing. He plunges face downward; tries to rise again; holds himself up by his
                     two hands on the ground and gives forth his last cry; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <p>INDIANS! INDIANS!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Five or six scenes to show the Indians. Huge lines of them are topping the
                     knolls and hills and seem to be plunging and charging down toward the River. As
                     they come their savage yells and war whoops rise above the beating of their
                     drums and the pounding of their horse’s feet. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><stage type="location">The Immigrant Train. It is strung out in a long line
                        on the River bank.</stage> The custom was to form the wagon in a circle.
                     This cannot be done in the narrow space, for on one side are the towering walls
                     of the canyon, and on the other the river. Women and children are under the
                     wagons. The men are behind barricades at the front and the rear and the side of
                     the train. To advance upon them the Indians must <pb n="H-3."/><fw
                        type="pageNum">H-3.</fw> come from either side of the trail. They are met
                     with a fusilade of shots.</view>
                  <stage type="novelistic">The Indians failing to charge the train, on account of
                     its position, have been examining<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">The
                        typo <q>examin</q> has been corrected in the original text.</note> the top
                     of the boulder lined canyon walls. They discover that it is possible to uproot
                     some of the stupendous boulders and roll them down upon the train
                     below.</stage>
                  <view><sound>While covering their purpose with a continual barrage of firing,
                        yells and shouts and the beating of war drums,</sound> numbers of them work
                     to shatter the top part of the natural wall of stone.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <camera>Open up on an Iris long shot.<note type="editorial">An Iris shot is a camera technique that was common in silent films. The frame is black except for a growing or shrinking circle to highlight the visual in the circle.</note></camera>
                  <camera>Away in the distance in center of the Iris can be seen a black dot, moving
                     rapidly toward the camera.</camera>
                  <camera>The black dot dissolves itself into Ren Bullock riding at the head of the
                     Immigrants and hunters. They seem to be plunging literally into the
                     camera.</camera>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>The Indians have nearly achieved their purpose. A <choice> <sic>colossol</sic><corr>colossal</corr></choice> boulder is about to be <choice><sic>loosed</sic> <corr>loosened</corr></choice>. It hangs, trembling on the edge of the cliff, above the camp of the
                     all unconscious Immigrant train.</view>
                  <view>Drunk with war fever, the Indians <choice>
                        <sic>begins</sic>
                        <corr>begin</corr>
                     </choice> a monster war dance, circling and tramping in front of the great
                     boulder, raising their lances to the skies, <sound>yelling and chanting and
                        shouting, while their war drums are pounded.</sound> They do not see <pb
                        n="H-4."/><fw type="pageNum">H-4.</fw> the company of horsemen coming down
                     from the higher hills, and forming into a regulation battle line behind a
                     natural rock wall. Ren and the Immigrant posse have arrived.</view>
                  <sound>Suddenly multiple shots bark out.</sound>
                  <view>Half a dozen Indians throw up their arms and drop. The others from the sheer
                     momentum of their war dance tramp over them. More Indians fall. Pandemonium and
                     fright seize the Indians. The shots are coming from the opposite direction of
                     the Immigrant camp. They cannot see their new antagonists. <sound>Screeching
                        wildly</sound> they flee. Ren and the others fire after them, and more fall.
                     Others slip down the sides of their horses bellies, and ride off, <choice>
                        <sic>clining</sic>
                        <corr>clinging</corr>
                     </choice> by the bare heels.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>In the camp below, the Immigrants begin to realize that help has come to
                     them from an unexpected source. With the panic stricken flight of the Indians,
                     the Immigrants come out from behind their wagons. They scan the cliffs above.
                     They are half mad with apprehension. They scan the trail on either side of the
                     camp, and then presently they hear <sound>a sound</sound> that changes their
                     fears and apprehensions to wild joy. <sound>The clear sound of a bugle is
                        heard, followed by three shots.</sound> The Immigrants know what that means.
                     Their men are coming back.</view>
                  <view>Half beside themselves with relief and joy the entire camp sweep down to
                     meet the oncoming little company of horsemen. <pb n="H-5."/><fw type="pageNum"
                        >H-5.</fw> Ren is riding at the head of the troop. Thad is next to him, and
                     the Immigrants, hunters and traders follow. In the rear of the horsemen, a long
                     file of mules and horses, some of them with heavy packs upon their backs are
                     being driven along.</view>
                  <view><sound>Crying, laughing, cheering,</sound> the Immigrants can scarcely wait
                     for their people to reach the camp. They surge all around the posse, dragging
                     the men literally from the saddles, embracing and kissing and heaping blessings
                     on them. One excited woman runs from one man to the other kissing each in turn.
                     Col. Appleton is shaking hands with each and every one of them. The men are
                     telling him of the fate of the other guides; but that now they have real scouts
                     to take charge of the expedition. The Col. turns to thank and shake the hands
                     of the scouts.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>Thad, who has ridden along behind Ren, has drawn his horse to an abrupt
                     stop. He sees whom Ren is looking at. Over the heads of the Immigrants Ren is
                     looking at Sally Lou, whose eyes are luminous. When Thad sees Sally Lou he is
                     powerfully moved and startled. His glance goes swiftly about; he sees Mandy,
                     and coming directly toward him Col. Appleton.</view>
                  <view>Thad’s hand unconsciously goes to the beard that has grown on his face. He
                     tugs his big hat down over his face and half turns away, as Col. Appleton
                     strides up to him, his hand held out. Thad does not give the Colonel a chance
                     to say much, for with a rough rejoinder, he turns to speak to <pb n="H-6"/><fw
                        type="pageNum">H-6.</fw> one of the men. Col. Appleton looks at him
                     uncertainly, as though puzzled and then a woman runs up to the Colonel and
                        <stage type="delivery">cries hysterically;</stage>
                  </view>
                  <sp>
                     <p><q>Oh, Colonel Appleton, isn’t it <emph>wonderful</emph>! A miracle! We
                           would all have been scalped but for these brave men! -- and that
                           wonderful young scout</q>!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>She indicates where moving slowly toward the camp Sally Lou and Ren are
                     walking. </view>
                  <view>They seem to be oblivious to everyone else there. Sally Lou is looking up at
                     Ren. and Ren is looking down at Sally. They both start to speak at once, and
                     stop and laugh. Then after a moment Sally says;</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I’m sorry you didn’t like that -- chicken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Chicken?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Yes -- I sent it to you -- thinking -- well -- thinking -- you’d
                        understand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(bewildered)</stage>
                     <p>Understand? Ma’m -- I don’t even understand now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>But I thought if Mose gave you my special message with the chicken -</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Mose? I never saw Mose -- did you send him to me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="H-7."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">H-7.</fw>
                  <view>Sally stops abruptly. She begins to realize that Mose had eaten the chicken
                     himself. She is very angry. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>That wicked nigger<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This is an
                           offensive racial slur that appears multiple times in this text. Please
                           see our <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note on
                        language</ref>.</note>! He must’ve eaten it himself. Oh-h! I’m going to skin
                        him alive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Colonel Appleton comes into the scene, and Sally turns to him.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Daddy -- that no account ornery nigger<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"
                           >This is an offensive racial slur that appears multiple times in this
                           text. Please see our <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note on
                              language</ref>.</note> ate the chicken I sent to Mr. --- er --- Mister
                        ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Ren Bullock ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Colonel Appleton holds out his hand. The two men shake.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>COLONEL</speaker>
                     <stage place="inline">(smiling)</stage>
                     <p>This is the first I’ve heard about a chicken <stage>(smacking his lips and sighing)</stage><choice><sic>Missing ending punctuation</sic><corr>.</corr></choice> Most any kind of food would taste good to me now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>We shouldn’t talk about food --- when we’re so hungry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(eagerly)</stage>
                     <p>But we’ve brought your chuck, as well as other stuff back with us. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Hurray! That’s why they’re building the fires. Come along - I’m starving.
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(gravely)</stage>
                     <p>I’d like a word with your father first. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="H-8."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">H-8.</fw>
                  <view>Sally runs off to where the men and women are beginning the preparations for
                     a meal. The men are building the fires. The women tearing food out of the bags,
                     and shipping stuff on the frying pans and thrusting them over the blazes. </view>
                  <p>Ren tells the Colonel that the Indians will undoubtedly return. This time,
                     probably in greater numbers. It will be necessary for the entire train to get
                     to the other side of the river. The waters are rough - of unknown depths, but
                     they must take the chance. And the sooner they leave the better. He tells the
                     Colonel that he has sent for help to the <choice>
                        <sic>Hudsons</sic>
                        <corr>Hudson’s</corr>
                     </choice> Bay at Fort Vancouver. He feels sure that boats will be sent up the
                     river to convey the party on its journey, and that supplies and firearms will
                     also arrive. As soon as the party is landed on the opposite shore, Ren will go
                     on a scouting sortie down the river and if there are no signs of the <choice>
                        <sic>Hudsons</sic>
                        <corr>Hudson’s</corr>
                     </choice> Bay boats, Ren will continue on to the Fort. Meanwhile, the train
                     will be safe in the hands of his partner, and although the main trail is this
                     side of the river, they must build rafts and bateaus, cork up their wagons and
                     prairie schooners, and on these make the rest of the journey.</p>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">The incident of the crossing of the Snake River.</stage>
                  <view>The wagons are all fastened together in one long <pb n="H-9."/><fw
                        type="pageNum">H-9.</fw> string; the strongest in the lead. The women and
                     children and weaker and older men are also in the wagons. </view>
                  <view>As soon as the teams were in position, Ren ties a rope around his waist, and
                     starting his horse into the current, swims over to the other side. Others
                     follow, until a number of the men are on the opposite side of the river. When
                     they have force enough to pull the rope, the lead team is started in. All are
                     drawn over safely.</view>
                  <view>As soon as the leading teams are able to get a foothold all is well. Guided
                     by the strong arms of the men pulling the rope, the weaker ones are helped and
                     drawn along.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>They have barely reached the opposite side of the river when the Indians
                     come swooping down in overwhelming numbers, around the trail on to the beach,
                     where but recently the Immigrant train had been. On the opposite side of the
                     river, the Immigrants have begun to cut a trail through the thick brush. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - -</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="H-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE I</head>
                  <view>Four or five scenes of the Immigrants cutting the trail through the dense
                     woods bordering the river.</view>
                  <p>This is pioneer work -- the real work of the first pathfinders. No moose, nor
                     bear, nor Indian trails to follow now. The Immigrants are hewing their way
                     through, their intent being to keep along the river, till they reach a place
                     where they can build rafts and trust their fortunes to the swift river itself;
                     a fearfully dangerous undertaking and fraught with inconceivable dangers.</p>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>As the men cut the passage, the lumbering wagons, drawn by the wide horned
                     oxen, and the long train of pack mules, follow slowly.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>Work stops only with the setting of the sun. Then camp is made for the
                     night.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">THE ENCAMPMENT</stage>
                  <stage type="setting">There is a redness still in the sky, though it is long
                     past sunset. The river runs along one side like a streak of dancing
                     quicksilver. On the other are the deep mysterious woods, from whose depths come
                     occasionally the call of wild things.</stage>
                  <pb n="I-2"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">I-2</fw>
                  <view>Stretched or crouched upon the ground by the camp fires, the tired
                     Immigrants are resting. <sound>Some of the younger ones are singing.</sound>
                  </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="location">OUTSIDE THE APPLETON WAGON</stage>
                  <view>Ren stands uncertainly, twisting his hat in his hand and looking longingly
                     at the door of the wagon. Finally he summons the courage to knock. There is a
                     somewhat startled sound within as if someone inside has cried out something
                     and then quickly muffled the sound. Then the flap door is pushed aside, and
                     Sally Lou stands lookin down at Ren. Sally Lou is breathing swiftly, almost as
                     if she were frightened about something.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Miss Sally--c-c-could I have a word w-w-with you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Why certainly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>She looks back and then closes the flap behind her. She hesitates a moment
                     and then sits down on the step of the wagon. The moonlight is on Sally’s hair
                     turning its darkness to a glorified bronze. Ren feels a dryness in his throat.
                     He does not know how to begin. Sally looks at him curiously, but her eyes are
                     starry and luminous. Ren points to the tumbling stream.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <pb n="I-3"/>
                     <fw type="pageNum">I-3.</fw>
                     <p>They’s a powerful lot of rainbow trout in the shallow parts of that there
                        stream.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="novelistic">Ren is finding it more difficult than he had
                     thought.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Was that what you wanted to speak to me about?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Yes -- no -- yes -- I mean -- no --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Sally laughs. Her laughter is tender, with a teasing quality to it. She
                     leans a bit nearer to the young man, and her lovely young face so close to his
                     own fills him with a panic of ecstasy. <stage type="delivery">His words rush
                        on:</stage></view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I got a homestead over to the Oregon -- finest part of the Williamette
                        Valley -- a whole section of the land.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>A section of land’s an awful lot, isn’t it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Six hundred and forty acres, and I’ll have it fenced and a quarter of it
                        broke by this time next year.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>That will be wonderful!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>And I’m aimin’ to put up a little snug cabin --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Sally bent still lower. One little hand steals out, almost as if seeking
                     his. It wavers on his shoulder a <pb n="I-4"/><fw type="pageNum">I-4.</fw>
                     moment and then rests on his arm. Ren feels as if he were in heaven.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>You like me a lot -- don’t you, Ren?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Yes. <choice>
                           <sic>Maam</sic>
                           <corr>Ma’am</corr>
                        </choice>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Then why don’t you tell me so. A girl likes to hear a man say that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren’s hands unclinch. His voice is husky. He finds he has no control of his
                     actions.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I’ll be telling you in <emph>this</emph> way -- Miss Sally.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>He reaches up, lifts her clear down from the step of the wagon and holds her
                     in his arms. Closer and closer. And closer and closer Sally clings to him; her
                     face upturned, her eyes and lips inviting his that closed upon her own.
                     Presently, gently, Sally, her hands on his shoulders holds him back from
                     her.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I must go. There’s someone -- someone waiting for me inside.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Sally, I’m leavin’ first thing in the morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(startled)</stage>
                     <p>Leaving!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="1-5."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">I-5.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I’m ridin’ for Fort Vancouver. I sent my Indian on ahead, and he never come
                        back. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>But we can’t get on without you!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Someone’s got to go.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>But I can’t bear to see you go. Not now!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I’d be a poor sort of man if I didn’t take the proper means to protect the
                        girl I love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>A poor sort of man! You’re the most wonderful man in the world. The only man
                        in the world!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>They go into an embrace again, from which they are brought to earth by the
                     sound of coughing of someone in the wagon. Sally breaks away. She is now the
                     prey to nervousness and fear.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I must go -- good-night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(huskily)</stage>
                     <p>Good-night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Sally goes into the tent.</view>
                  <view>Ren, like one in a blissful dream moves away, but turns and stands in the
                     shadows, just looking toward where Sally had gone into the wagon.</view>
                  <pb n="I-6."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">I-6.</fw>
                  <view>Suddenly he tenses. His gaze becomes fixed. The flap door of the Appleton
                     wagon has been pushed aside and Sally followed by Thad Jones comes out of the
                     wagon. They pause a moment on the step. Then Sally speaks; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I’m glad Daddy didn’t see you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Guess he’s got enough to worry about without havin’ me on his mind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(in little shaking voice)</stage>
                     <p><choice><sic>THad</sic><corr>Thad</corr></choice>, Ren’s leaving in the morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>That’s good. He’ll get help - and I’ll be here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(wearily)</stage>
                     <p>Yes -- you’ll be here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Goodnight.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Goodnight, dear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>They kiss. Thad jumps down from steps of wagon and runs out of scene. Sally
                     turns and goes into wagon.</view>
                  <view>Ren, who has witnessed the scene between Sally and his pardner,<note
                        type="editorial">partner</note> stands for a moment as if rooted to the
                     spot. His world seems to be tumbling about him; his dreams shattered his
                     illusions destroyed. He makes a passionate, almost savage motion toward the
                     wagon. <choice>
                        <sic>They</sic>
                        <corr>Then</corr>
                     </choice> he stops short. His <pb n="I-7"/><fw type="pageNum">I-7</fw> hands
                     cinch. His head drops between his shoulders. He moves away with a shambling,
                     almost staggering gait.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">The following morning.</stage>
                  <stage type="setting">The first pale steaks of the rising sun are seen in the sky.
                     There is the murmur and stir of small live things in the bush. The camp is
                     still wrapped in silence and slumber, for it is but four o’clock in the
                     morning. As the scene proceeds, the light of morning spreads, and over the
                     horizon the sun raises an inquiring ruddy eye.</stage>
                  <view>At first, only the shadowy outline of tent and wagon top are visible in the
                     grey dawn. The we see to one side of the camp a man with a horse, which he is
                     saddling, tightening the cinch, and throwing heavy saddle bags on either side.
                     On the ground is other travelling gear, and he kneels on one knee to sort and
                     pack then.</view>
                  <view>The man is Ren Bullock. He wears a white blanket coat (for it is now
                     October) a broad felt hat, moccasins and deer skin trousers. His knife is stuck
                     in his belt. Bullet pouch and powder horn are hanging at side. A rifle rests on
                     high pummel of his saddle in front of him; for he is now a-horse.</view>
                  <view>Suddenly from the Appleton wagon, Sally appears. She pauses a moment, and
                     then comes running toward where Ren is on his horse.</view>

                  <view>Ren is sitting very still and straight. His wide grey <pb n="I-8."/><fw
                        type="pageNum">I-8.</fw> eyes are dead ahead. His thoughts are bitter. To
                     hell with everything!</view>
                  <view>His fists are <choice><sic>clinched</sic><corr>clenched</corr></choice> so tightly that the reins feel hard against his
                     palms. </view>
                  <view>Sally, breathless with the long run, her hair flying about her, comes into
                     the scene. She stands by his saddle, looking up at him appealingly. Ren gives
                     one look at her, and then again he looks dead ahead.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Ren -- you weren’t going without saying goodbye first.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren does not answer. Ren cannot answer. Sally, puzzled, troubled, peers up
                     at him. The dawn is breaking all around them. Ren’s face seems carved like a
                     statue, so unmoving and stern is it. Sally’s little hand goes up, rests upon
                     that clinched pair on the pummel.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I couldn’t sleep all night. All I could think was -- Ren is going away --
                        Ren is going -- Ren is going --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren’s face contorts. <stage type="delivery">His voice is almost loud. It is
                        harsh.</stage></view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>But -- <emph>Thad’ll</emph> be here!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>His heel presses sharply against his horse’s flank. Before Sally can
                     comprehend, he is off at a stiff canter. <pb n="I-9."/><fw type="pageNum"
                        >I-9.</fw> She stands for a moment startled, shocked, and then she starts
                     running after the now flying horse. As she runs she calls; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Ren -- Ren -- Ren -- my Ren ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>She tries to make her voice carry, by putting her hands to her mouth, and
                     she keeps on calling, <stage type="delivery"/>frantically; </view>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Ren! Ren!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="delivery">Her voice breaks in <choice>
                        <sic>an</sic>
                        <corr>a</corr>
                     </choice> hysterical gasp.</stage>
                  <view>The sunrise is wide over the heavens now. Over a bit of rising ground, the
                     flying horseman is seen for a moment, and then disappears from sight.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - - -</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="J-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE J</head>
                  <stage>This is about a month later.</stage>
                  <view>The immigrants have literally out and hewed their way around the Cascades,
                     from the Upper to the Lower, and now they are halted at the Columbia River, for
                     lack of boats. Their situation is a desperate one. They dare not attempt the
                     passage of the Columbia, with its treacherous rapids and whirlpools merely by
                     the <choice>
                        <sic>pairie</sic>
                        <corr>prairie</corr>
                     </choice> schooners (wagons) and they are hard at work constructing rafts and a
                     canoe, hewn out of the trunk of a giant tree. The canoe is to go ahead of the
                     train, and scout down the river, to discover whether it is navigable.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>A steady rain, which has been falling for days, has turned to snow, bringing
                     with it penetrating chill and cold. A cutting wind comes out of the North,
                     driving all the women and children and the weaker and older men to the wagon
                     for shelter.</view>
                  <view>Sally is not to be daunted so easily. She stays with the workmen, herself <choice>
                        <sic>weilding</sic>
                        <corr>wielding</corr>
                     </choice> a hammer. Thad, no longer the lighthearted youth who had sung on the
                     trail, but feeling the heavy burden of responsibility on his young shoulders,
                     urges her to go with the women. Sally shakes her head.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>But father needs you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="J-2."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">J-2.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>No -- I’m afraid to be with father. He asks so many questions. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>About --me? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>About everything. I think his mind wanders. Sometimes he thinks we’re back
                        home and --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>She breaks off, her eyes filling. Thad goes on hammering. They are both at
                     work on one end of a raft, in process of building. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Thad, when he’s well again, we must tell him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Thad shakes his head and continues to hammer.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="setting">Farther down the Columbia River.</stage>
                  <stage type="setting">A good sized steamboat is moving up the river. Her upper
                     deck is covered with sacks and boxes filled with blankets, arms and munitions,
                     bales containing merchandise, medicines, meal, pork, dried flesh and other
                     provisions, and its hold is crammed with supplies for the Immigrants. It is a <choice>
                        <sic>Hudsons</sic>
                        <corr>Hudson’s</corr>
                     </choice> Bay vessel, and Ren Bullock is on deck at the rail with the
                     captain.</stage>
                  <view>Ren points to the banks of the river, where groups of Indians are standing,
                     excitedly gesticulating. Ren does not believe they are friendly. The Captain
                     assures him that they have nothing to fear from the Indians.</view>
                  <pb n="J-3."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">J-3.</fw>
                  <view>As the boat moves along, more and more Indians seem to be gathering along
                     the banks. <sound>Their drums are beating.</sound> War dances are enacted. The
                     Indians are yelling;</view>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Immigrants are coming!</l>
                        <l>They will drive the Indian off his lands</l>
                        <l>They will eat the Indian’s food</l>
                        <l>The Indian will starve</l>
                        <l>It is good to kill the white man before the white man kills the
                           Indian.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>And so forth.</p>
                  <view>Parties of the Indians ride off disappearing from the banks of the river,
                     and reappearing on higher land, still following the river.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <p style="text-align: center">- - - - - - - - - - -</p>
               </div>

               <div>
                  <pb n="K-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE K</head>
                  <camera>FADE IN:</camera>
                  <view>On a heavy mist and fog. At first it is hard to see anything, but <sound>we
                        hear the sound of the wind blowing, the ripple of waters, the sound of the
                        waves.</sound> Through the mist the outlines of a canoe is seen, with three
                     people in it. One of the men, Thad, is wielding an oar. He is to the fore of
                     the <choice>
                        <sic>unweildy</sic>
                        <corr>unwieldy</corr>
                     </choice> little craft that the Immigrants have made. The other man seems
                     crouched down, and Sally Lou is also wielding an oar. Her head is wrapped in a
                     small shawl, tied under the chin. Thad looks back, sees Sally and speaks
                     sharply:</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Take that oar, Charlie. What do you mean by letting Miss Sally work.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>But Thad I wanted to. I made him give it up. His hands are all torn and
                        --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Never mind about his hands - here you -</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>The other man takes the oar. He is a middle-aged, painfully thin and
                     undernourished immigrant. Though he tries conscientiously to work the oar, it
                     nearly tears him to pieces. Sally kneels in the boat, her shoulders slightly
                     hunched. <sound>There is no sound for <choice>
                           <sic>awhile</sic>
                           <corr>a while</corr>
                        </choice>, but the waves beating against the boat, and the whistling wind,
                        blowing.</sound> They seem to be alone on the river. It is lighting up, but
                     the drizzling rain has turned to sleet. After awhile, Sally asks:</view>
                  <pb n="K-2."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-2.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Thad --d’you suppose Ren reached Fort Vancouver?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>If Ren Bullock set out for Fort Vancouver - he got there. Ren always does
                        what he says he will do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="location">The boat drifts on. The wind is dying down. The overcast
                     skies gradually lighten.</stage>
                  <view>Suddenly an exclamation escapes Sally. She almost stands up in the canoe in
                     her excitement. Thad tries to steady the boat and calls out <stage
                        type="delivery">sharply</stage>: </view>

                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Look out! We’ll go over.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(bated excitement)</stage>
                     <p>Oh, Thad - look--<emph>look</emph> - off there --</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>I don’t see anything</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>B-but--Oh Thad am I dreaming?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view><camera>In a very long shot</camera> we see at a great distance, what looks
                     like the shadowy outline of a ship. The Immigrant in the back of the boat stops
                     paddling. His eyes seem to be starting from his head, as he too peers through
                     the mist of the early day. Then he <stage type="delivery"/>shouts:</view>
                  <pb n="K-3."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-3.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARLIE</speaker>
                     <p>Praise be to God!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>The oar drops from his hands and into the river. He kneels in the bottom of
                     the boat raising his hands in prayer, and half singing, half praying, he rocks
                     in an ecstasy. He has gone temporarily out of his mind. Thad, too, sees the
                     vessel. His care now is all for the little craft with its one paddle oar, and
                     he has his hands full steadying it, for they are in a rough part of the
                     river.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><camera>Medium long shot</camera> of the ship. Ren is pacing its deck,
                     restlessly.</view>
                  <view>Suddenly he stands stock still, his hands gripping the rail. From somewhere
                     up the river, <sound>he hears a whistle. It is repeated three times. Three
                        clear, familiar notes.</sound> For a moment Ren cannot believe he hears
                     aright. His first reaction is one of powerful joy and exhilaration. His next -
                     he remembers the last time he had seen his pal. Sally Lou raising her face to
                     kiss him goodbye. Ren’s face hardens. He stares out before him. </view>
                  <view><sound>Again the three long whistling notes.</sound> The man by the rail
                     remains unmoving, but a curious change is breaking over his face. Something
                     soft, tender, gentle, makes it as fine as the face of a mother. He leans
                     forward. He purses his lips. <sound>Three times he sends back that whistling
                        signal.</sound> Then, <pb n="K-4."/><fw type="pageNum">K-4.</fw> as if
                     springing to electrical life he rushes toward the Captain.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Do you hear that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CAPTAIN</speaker>
                     <p>Yes--some wild bird.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>No--not a wild bird. It’s my partner--my pal, Captain. He’s out there
                        somewhere--in the river.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>A few minutes later everything is activity aboard the vessel. Full steam is
                     put on. As the ship proceeds, the sunshine breaks through the clouds, and in
                     the glow far up the stream, tossing upon<note type="editorial"><q>upon</q> has
                        been added in the original text.</note> the turbulent water, they descry the
                     canoe.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>There is the business of taking Thad, Sally and the Immigrant aboard. Though
                     cold and wet through, Sally’s eyes are luminous with happiness. The Captain,
                     much concerned that a girl should have been exposed to such hardship and
                     weather, begs her to go immediately to the cabin, but Sally is looking past the
                     captain at the now sombre and stern Ren. Though he has helped them aboard he is
                     standing back. Thad holds out his hand to him, and after a moment, Ren, without
                     a word grasps it. The two men silently shake. Then Thad’s hand clasps the other
                     on the shoulder. Thad starts to explain how they came to be on the river, and
                     to tell about the plans of the Immigrants, but Sally comes up <pb n="K-5."/><fw
                        type="pageNum">K-5.</fw> beside him. She tries to entrap Ren’s glance, but
                     Ren is afraid to look at her. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Thad--tell him later. I-I want to say something now. Ren!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Yes <choice>
                           <sic>maam</sic>
                           <corr>ma’am</corr>
                        </choice>.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I ran after you--the morning you left--Oh--ran and ran-- and I called to
                        you-- didn’t you hear me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Ren does not answer.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <p>I had something terribly important I wanted you to know.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Still Ren does not answer.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <p>You see----you see------</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Now Ren can no longer avoid looking at her, for Sally has put one little
                     hand on either of his arms, and her face is directly under his.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>You see---Thad’s my brother---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="novelistic">Ren takes this big. So big that Sally catches her breath
                     as she laughs. </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Yes--my brother--my big, bad brother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="novelistic">Ren gulps. Waves of contrition are rolling over him of
                     remorse; of powerful joy. He longs to take Sally in his arms; he wants to cry
                     like a child. His voice is hoarse;</stage>
                  <pb n="K-6."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-6.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Miss Sally---I reckon, I’m the most powerful dunce in Oregon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Sally, looking at him, catches her breath in a laugh that breaks, and
                     suddenly her eyes fill with tears -- tears of a long hurt, and of utter
                     physical strain and exhaustion. She sways. With an incoherent murmur Ren takes
                     her into his arms. </view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>Further up the river a fleet of Indian canoes are coming. Each canoe
                     contains about eighteen men, dressed in skins and sea otter, their hair
                     powdered with the white <choice><sic>dawn</sic><corr>down</corr></choice> of birds and their faces befogged with
                     paint.</view>
                  <view>The Chief occupies a place in the middle boat and is distinguished by his
                     high cap, ornamented with a tuft of eagle feathers. As they come down the river
                        <sound>they beat time against the <choice>
                           <sic>gunwhale</sic>
                           <corr>gunwale</corr>
                        </choice> of the boat with their paddles. They are chanting a war
                        song,</sound> and at the end of each verse, they point with extended arms to
                     the North and the South. There is no yelling or whooping; just the <stage
                        type="delivery">monotonous chanting, triumphant and bold.</stage> There are
                     probably two hundred braves in the canoes, as well as <sound>the squaws who
                        shriek in accompaniment,</sound> beating their hands together
                     fiercely.</view>
                  <pb n="K-7."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-7.</fw>
                  <stage type="setting">On board the <choice>
                        <sic>Hudsons</sic>
                        <corr>Hudson’s</corr>
                     </choice> Bay ship.</stage>
                  <view>In the cabin Sally and Thad and the Immigrant are having their first meal
                     since they set out in their crude canoe. Across the table from Sally sits Ren,
                     his elbows on the table, his chin in his hands. He looks only at Sally, and his
                     gaze is tender, devouring, adoring.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>A sort of <choice>
                        <sic>suddering</sic>
                        <corr>shuddering</corr>
                     </choice> motion of the boat, and then it stops. A couple of the ship’s men run
                     past. <sound>The Captain’s voice is heard shouting orders. There is the clink
                        of chains, etc.</sound></view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>Ren has started up. He is about to go on deck, when the Captain comes to the
                     door.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CAPTAIN</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing to worry about. We’ve gone aground; but we’ll get her off.
                        Hello--what’s that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view><camera>Off</camera> - <sound>the voices of the Indians can be
                        heard.</sound> Ren looks at the Captain; the latter, an old pilot of the
                     Columbia says that they are probably to have some visitors. He exits on deck
                     followed by Ren. Thad starts to go also, but Ren bids him remain with Sally;
                     Thad walks about restlessly, moodily. He is apprehensive and worried.</view>
                  <view>The Indian canoes are now parading in a circle around the ship. The Captain
                     and Ren are at the rail. The <pb n="K-8."/><fw type="pageNum">K-8.</fw> Captain
                     points out that these are Cayuse Indians, friendly to the whites. However, they
                     are standing up in their canoes, their hands raised the peace sign.</view>
                  <stage type="novelistic">One of the Indians, who speaks English, calls out that a
                     delegation of the chiefs would like to come aboard to trade buffalo hides for
                     brass metals and knives.</stage>
                  <stage type="novelistic">The Captain, pleased, in spite of Ren’s uneasiness and
                     suspicion, tells them to come aboard, and soon about fourteen of the braves
                     climb aboard.</stage>
                  <view>All unsuspecting the captain examines their buffalo hides, and gives them in
                     exchange the desired brass buttons and knives. </view>
                  <sound>Suddenly one of them lets out a terrifying war whoop. This is immediately
                     echoed by the others, while an answering roar comes from the men in the canoes
                     below.</sound>
                  <view>They rush upon the whites. The clerk is stabbed in the back. The Captain,
                     sitting on the taffrail is clubbed and falls overboard, there to be knifed by
                     the Indians in <choice>
                        <sic>thecanoes</sic>
                        <corr>the canoes</corr>
                     </choice>. One big burly sailor fights for his life with his bare fists, before
                     he is clubbed and stabbed to death.</view>
                  <view>Ren, his gun spitting fire leaps for the companionway and reaches the cabin.
                     There he and Thad and the other men barricade themselves in.</view>
                  <view>The Indians pour down <choice>
                        <sic>passageway</sic>
                        <corr>the passage way</corr>
                     </choice>. Ren and Thad cut holes for their <choice>
                        <sic>fire arms</sic>
                        <corr>firearms</corr>
                     </choice> in the walls of the cabin, and pour out a withering fire of shot,
                     that has deadly effect <choice>
                        <sic>Missing ending punctuation</sic>
                        <corr>.</corr>
                     </choice></view>
                  <pb n="K-9."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-9.</fw>
                  <view>Leaving their dead and wounded, the Indians flee back up the
                     companionway.</view>
                  <view>It is now dusk, and the thin snow storm has become a dense one. The Indians
                     scuttle across the deck, and go over the rail making for their canoes.</view>
                  <stage type="setting">IN THE CABIN</stage>
                  <view>Sally is asleep. The Immigrant too is stretched out on the floor, dead to
                     the world. Ren lights a ship’s lantern. He sets it on the table. <tech
                        type="light"/>In this flickering light he and Thad sit opposite each other.
                     For a long time no word is spoken. Then:</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Indians never attack or fight at night. We can get away in one of the ship’s
                        boats; they are all well-stocked. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>I’m thinking of our people. They’ll be on their way down the river. Those
                        red devils know it. They’re waiting for them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Thad’s head drops on his arms on the table. Ren reaches across and pats him
                     on the head. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Brace up. This is no time to lose your nerve. I’m <emph>leanin</emph> on
                        you, Thad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Thad gives him a singularly boyish look at that.</stage>
                  <pb n="K-10"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-10</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Are you, Ren?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Of course.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Thad swallows.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>You see, I never did amount to anything, and I’ve given my father all kinds
                        of worry. Why--I’m to blame for the fix we’re all in now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>How do you figger <note type="editorial">figure</note> that out?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>If I hadn’t gone on that drunk in Independence we’d’ve been the guides for
                        the Train, and we’d’ve got through two months ago.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>They’ll get through yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Not if the Indians can stop them. I got a lot to answer for--a lot upon my
                        conscience. Killing one man when we were in a fight is nothing compared to
                        what’s happened to -- those Immigrants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>While the men have been speaking the shadows have been steadily deepening.
                     Thad gets up, paces. Ren sits at table, <tech type="light">his fine young face
                        lighted by the lantern.</tech> He speaks quietly;</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Come back here, Thad. sit down again. I want to speak to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="K-11"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-11</fw>
                  <view>Thad sits. Ren gives him an intent look. He lowers his voice as he slightly
                     leans across the table, fixing the other with his steady regard. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I been doin’ a powerful lot of thinkin’.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>On the <choice>
                        <sic>courch</sic>
                        <corr>couch</corr>
                     </choice>/choice> Sally stirs. Her eyes half open. At first she listens almost
                     unconsciously; and then with tense interest and fear.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>There’s a big powder magazine aboard this ship ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage type="delivery" place="inline">(breathlessly)</stage>
                     <p>Ye-eh--?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>We gotta get rid of them Indians!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Yeh!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>If we don’t they’ll massacre our people! I say we gotta get rid of them
                        Indians!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>How can we! How can we!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="delivery">Ren lowers his voice.</stage>
                  <pb n="K-12."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-12.</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>You all are goin’ on the ship’s boat as soon as it’s dark enough. I’m stayin’
                        here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <stage type="action">(swallowing hard)</stage>
                     <p>Stayin’ - <choice><sic>her</sic><corr>here</corr></choice> - alone you mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Ren nods.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>What for?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Soon as it’s day break, those Indians’ll be comin’ back - they’ll be comin’
                        aboard - well then -</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Yes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>If I touch that powder magazine off - the whole ship and everyone aboard it
                        will be blown to pieces.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Sally is now sitting up. Thad is staring at Ren, his eyes widening with
                     horror as he comprehends what Ren intends to do.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Whoever lights that powder magazine will be blown up himself, won’t he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I’ll take care of that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="K-13"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-13</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>No, by God! I will!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Both men have started to their feet.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I’ll handle my own job.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Not this time. I’ll do it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>No, you won’t. You’re goin’ back to take care of your father. He’ll be
                        needin’ you -- and your sister--- Sally ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                     <p>Nobody needs me. I can’t go back. Sooner or later they’ll get me. They’s a
                        price on my head-- they’re lookin’ for me in every border town. I’d rather
                        go this way--than--by the rope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Suddenly Sally screams. She comes screaming in between them. She cannot
                     speak. She can only cry. She clings to Ren. She clings to Thad. She keeps
                     crying and sobbing. Ren, holding her in his arms, looks across at Thad. His
                     face is stern, grave. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Sally, I’m goin’ to take you down the river a little ways. We’ll be meeting’
                        up presently with our people--</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">Sally clings to him.</stage>
                  <pb n="K-14"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">K-14</fw>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>I won’t go without <emph>you</emph>!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>I’m aimin’ to ‘scort you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>And Thad--my brother--he shan’t stay here either. Oh, what a terrible thing
                        to think of! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>It is terrible. We’ll not talk of it any more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>He soothes her. After awhile, he gently puts a heavy coat about her. </view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Come, we better be driftin’. You go ahead, Thad!</p>
                     <p>Here, <choice><sic>Charley</sic><corr>Charlie</corr></choice>--come on now--wake up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="action">He shakes the Immigrant awake.</stage>
                  <view>They all go out through the dark passage and up the companionway to the
                     deck. The men release the boat. It is a big roomy boat, seaworthy, and
                     well-provisioned and stocked for an emergency. There is also in the rear a
                     place for shelter and it is propelled both by oars and sail.</view>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="L-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE L</head>
                  <camera>FADE IN:</camera>
                  <p>On the boat. They have a hoisted small sail, <choice>
                        <sic>A</sic>
                        <corr>a</corr>
                     </choice> stiff wind is billowing it out, but the current is against them, for
                     they are going up stream, and they are making slow time.</p>
                  <stage type="setting">It is still quite dark, though drawing toward morning.
                        <sound>Occasionally the voice of the Immigrant rises in a gospel
                        hymn.</sound>
                     <stage type="delivery">He sings like a madman.</stage></stage>
                  <sound>The others are all silent.</sound>
                  <view>Ren is at the helm. Sally is at his side, crouched close to him, her eyes
                     never leaving his face. He bends to draw her wrap closer about her. She shakes
                     her head dumbly. His arms are all she needs. He holds her close. Her arms go
                     around his neck. She says passionately:</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Promise me--you’ll never leave me now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage type="delivery">There is a long, deep pause. Then Ren in a hoarse, steady
                     whisper, replies:</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <p>I must go back! It is the only way!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>In the stern of the boat, Thad peers at the two in front. There is something
                     very tense about him - something tense and cautious. He <choice>
                        <sic>courches</sic>
                        <corr>crouches</corr>
                     </choice> farther down in the shadow of the sail.</view>
                  <pb n="L-2."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">L-2.</fw>
                  <view>The lovers are still in <choice>
                        <sic>each others</sic>
                        <corr>each other’s</corr>
                     </choice> arms. <tech type="light">Their faces are illuminated.</tech> Whatever
                     may befall them, this moment is all their own.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>Half kneeling, half <choice>
                        <sic>couuching</sic>
                        <corr>crouching</corr>
                     </choice>, in the shade of the sail, Thad looks at them, and a smile breaks
                     over the boy’s face making it singularly young and singularly poignant.
                        <sound>Without a sound he swings over the side of the boat.</sound> He drops
                     in the water.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view>Sally stirs in Ren’s arms. They can see each other’s faces now, for it is
                     becoming lighter.</view>
                  <view>Suddenly Sally holds Ren back from her. A troubled look comes over her
                     face--an expression of strange and almost psychic fear.</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Thad--Thad--I had a sudden feelin that Thad was not ---</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Don’t worry dear. Thad’s asleep.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Sally break away from Ren. She is still under some restless spell. She <choice>
                        <sic>call</sic>
                        <corr>calls</corr>
                     </choice>:</view>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Thad! Thad!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>There is no answer. Now her fear has communicated itself to Ren.</p>
                  <pb n="L-3."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">L-3.</fw>
                  <stage type="delivery">He calls out roughly:</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>Thad! Are you all right?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>But Thad does not answer. Ren moves back to the rear of the boat. Sally
                     comes behind him. She is holding to the side of the boat and half crawling,
                     half climbing, over the impediments, the ropes, etc.</view>
                  <stage type="delivery">Ren, in a stunned silence, is staring down at the empty
                     place where Thad had been. His voice sounds strange. He scarcely knows that it
                     is he who is speaking.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p><emph>Thad</emph>---has gone back--for us!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>SALLY</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, no-no--no,--no! While we were there--while we were in each other’s
                        arms--he--Oh, Thad-- Thad!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <view>Ren places her on the seat, covers her gently, and then springs for the
                     sail. A few words to the half cracked Immigrant to hoist the sail, which he
                     cannot do, though he sits gibbering there, holding the rope. Ren swings the
                     helm around. The boat turns, slanting, as the wind slaps at the sail. Then it
                     steadies itself and we<camera> - FADE</camera></view>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="M-1"/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">M-1</fw>
                  <head>SEQUENCE M.</head>
                  <stage type="setting">We <camera>fade in</camera> on the <choice>
                        <sic>Hudsons</sic>
                        <corr>Hudson’s</corr>
                     </choice> Bay Vessel. It is still aground, and the waves are beating about
                     it.</stage>
                  <view>It is about five o’clock in the morning! The boat is entirely surrounded by
                     Indian canoes. But the canoes are empty. The Indians are swarming over the
                     deck. Not merely a delegation, but the entire tribe. They are going through the
                     bales and sacks and boxes. They are eating and drinking and wrapping the stuffs
                     about them, and there is great jubilation among them.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><camera>DISSOLVE</camera> to the powder magazine of the ship. Pressed up
                     against the wall is Thad. He is listening to the Indians. Some of them are
                     coming down into the hold. Thad shrinks back farther. <sound><tech type="light"
                           >There is a slight crackle as he lights the torch.</tech></sound></view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <view><camera>CUT TO</camera> - The ship’s boat. It is coming along at
                     considerable speed. Both Sally and Ren are at the helm, but they are not in
                     each others’ arms. Their faces are white and lined with fear. They are looking
                     dead ahead. Suddenly the air seems rent as by some tremendous shock. <sound>The
                        roar of a monster explosion is heard from one end of the river to the
                        other.</sound></view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
                  <stage type="novelistic">Note: (If desired, show the blowing up of the
                     ship)</stage>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <pb n="N-1"/>
                  <head>SEQUENCE N</head>
                  <stage type="setting">This shows the Immigrant train. Down the river, on rafts, on
                     boxes, on crude boats, with a few of the prairie schooners, the Immigrants are
                     coming down the river.</stage>
                  <stage type="novelistic">No saga or iliad ever penned could do justice to their
                     heroism, courage and valour; for despite their privations and sufferings, they
                     are coming along on this, the last lap of their journey, their faces still
                     radiant with hope. <sound>They are singing!</sound></stage>
                  <view>Farther down the river, in their boat, Ren and Sally are seen coming. <tech
                        type="light">Sally’s face is illuminated</tech> - poignantly beautiful. Ren
                     removes his hat. His head bows. FADE.</view>
                  <milestone unit="line"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
