<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="OregonTrail1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oregon Trail</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile provided by Jean Lee Cole.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:266"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreFilm"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-08-24" status="inProgress">With <name ref="pers:LW1"/>, experimenting with encoding screenplays.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Added facsimile and note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Oregon_Trail">
      <pb n="titlePage"/>
      <!--TODO: Add title page later-->
      <body>
         <div>
           <div>
              <pb n="A-1"/>
              <head>SEQUENCE A</head>
              <camera>FADE IN:</camera>
              <view>An Indian Village.</view>
              <p>From out of the sky vaguely and hazily, swooping down over the village comes the emaciated and ghostly figure of FAMINE.</p>
              <p>The Village itself is revealed in a state of destitution and misery.</p>
              <p>Against the skyline appear four fiery columns of smoke, and at the same time is heard the arousing beat of Indian drums. This is the Indian summons to a counsel.</p> 
              <p>There is a stir in the village and the Indians are seen leaving their tents and wigwams. Like a swarm of shadows they plod and push dumbly along toward a hill slope.</p>
              <pb n="A-2"/>
              <fw type="pageNum">A-2</fw>
              <p>On the crest of the hill a young Indian chief stands silhouetted against the sky. His arms are extended, his face is passionate and exalted. Below him, on the slope of the hill, is the great congregation of silent Indians. The young chief addresses them.</p>
              <p>He tells them that unless the white men are driven from the Indian hunting grounds the Indian hunting grounds the Indian will not live throughout the coming winter. Already they are dying like flies from starvation and plague. No longer do the buffalo roam the plains and prairies. The deer have gone from the forests. The white men have slaughtered the natural food of the Indian for their fur and hides. Now a horde of white people have gathered at Independence and are preparing to invade the Oregon lands in overwhelming numbers. They are forerunners of the hosts of whites who seek to rob the Indian of the land of his forefathers. Unless they are driven back the Indians will starve to death or be forced out of his own lands. The time has come when the Indian must repel the advance of these white people. They must be prevented from crossing the Cascades.</p>
              <p>His words are greeted by savage cheers.</p>
              <p>Through the clamoring throngs a very old chief pushes his way to the fore until he comes alongside the young chief on the brow of the hill. He raises his hands to command silence.</p>
              <pb n="A-3"/>
              <fw type="pageNum">A-3</fw>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>I have hung the scalps of many white men upon my belt - but always came <emph>more</emph> white men!</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                 <p>They shall come no more!</p>
              </sp>
              <sp><speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>They are rich! We are poor! They are many! We are few! Their government is powerful and remorseless. The Indian has no friends but his brothers.</p></sp>
              <sp>  
                 <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                 <p>Are our hearts those of rabbits? Shall we lie down and permit the white man to trample upon us?</p>
              </sp>
              
              <p>The old chief tries to raise his voice above the roar. The young chief places his arm about the old chief’s shoulders and commands silence - old age must be respected.</p> 
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>War is terrible! Let us deal with the chiefs of these white people! Let us demand justice!</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>Young Chief</speaker>
                 <p>For justice they will give - promises! Who can believe the word of a white man? We must drive them back! </p></sp>
              <sp> 
                 <speaker>Old Chief</speaker>
                 <p>We cannot dam up the ocean with our hands.</p>
              </sp>
              <pb n="A-3-A"/>
              <fw type="pageNum">A-3-A</fw>
              <sp>
                 <speaker>YOUNG CHIEF</speaker>
                 <stage>(shouting)</stage>
                 <p>The Thunder God fights within us! Ee-yah! Eeii---ya-a-a-a!</p>
              </sp>
              <p>The Indians take up the cry. They begin to circle, screaming and shouting and yelling, as they move in a savage war dance.</p>
              <camera>FADE OUT.</camera> 
           </div>
            <div>
               <head>SEQUENCE B</head>
               <camera>FADE IN</camera>
               <view>A trail winding around the side of a precipitous canyon wall.</view>
               <p>Two riders are loping along. Their outfit consists of their horses, surefooted, swift and tough Indian ponies, and two pack mules, in charge of an Indian who plods along behind. The older of the two men is Ren Bullock. He is tall, long-legged, with hair the color of corn-shuck and a long lean body. His eyes are clear and his face tanned. He has a look of intelligence and honesty and is as strong as a young ox. He is a Missourian. His speech is slow and drawling. He hesitates before speaking as if weighing his words. He never hurries, yet, at the right moment, seems literally to spring like lightning into vivid action and life.</p> 
              <p>His companion is of a totally different type. A happy go lucky, light-hearted, carless, pleasure-loving and likeable young chap with a natural quality of refinement about him. He goes by the name of Thad Jones. The two men are close pals, and partners.</p>
               <p>As they ride along, Ren sitting loosely ahorse, and looking out silently before him and That whirling his lariat and whistling the night begins to fall softly around them. The wind sings in the pine tops and through the canyon walls. A silvery sunlight, a glow of fading red still lingers in the sky. Ren points vaguely. </p>
               <pb n="B-2."/>
               <fw type="pageNum">B-2.</fw>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>That’s one plumb fine sight - that thar sunset.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Thad laughs. It is natural for him to laugh.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <p>I’ve seen prettier sunsets than that in Kentucky.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                     <p>You come from Kentucky? You never told me that before.</p>
               </sp> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <stage>(uneasily)</stage>
                  <p>That’s right- I’ve never told anyone. Mebbe <note>Maybe</note> I had a reason.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Ren nods understandingly.</p>
               <p>The shadows deepen about them. They top the brow of a hill and draw rein to look down across a great sweep of plain. There, in a wide valley below them, the flares of a score of campfires are seen.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <p>How many are there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>Two thousand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <stage>(Anxiously)</stage>
                  <p>That’s a considerable job you’ve taken on. Think you can pilot two thousand immigrants into the Oregon?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <stage>(with a wry smile)</stage>
                  <p>What me? Reckon I’ll be lookin’ for a heap a help from you young one.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="B-3"/>
               <fw type="pageNum">B-3</fw>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <stage>(chest swelling)</stage>
                  <p>Well I reckon we can manage somehow.</p>
               </sp> 
               <p>Sound of music and singing comes floating upon the air.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <p>Listen to them singing. Sounds like gospel hymns.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <stage>(nodding)</stage>
                  <p>They’s a powerful lot of religion ‘mong them. Guess we better be driftin’ along. They’ll be lookin’ for us.</p>
               </sp> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <p>Let’s go on into the town first. I got a parched throat and an empty stomach. And I’m aiming to stretch out on a read bed.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Ren gives him a good humored thump on the back.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>We’ll ride on into the town and look up our friends down thar later.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>They turn their horses heads  //sic// and move off.</p>
               <milestone unit="line"/>

               <view>THE IMMIGRANT ENCAMPMENT</view>
               <p>This is a large field or plain on the outskirts of the town of Independence (now a part of Kansas City). Here a host of immigrants, hunters, trappers, voyageurs, traders, gamblers, adventurers, missionaries, teachers, farmers, as well as the rag tag and bobtail and outcasts of the frontier <pb n="B-4."/><fw type="pageNum">B-4.</fw> town have gathered from all parts of the country to keep a rendezvous at the starting off place for the Oregon trail.</p>
               <p>Vehicles of all manner and kind form an immense circle about a central point.</p>
               <p>The flares of campfires, stream up, flooding the place with a mellow light, illuminating the faces of these hardy adventurers and pioneers.</p>
               <p>In a way this scene should parallel the Indian scene in as much as the immigrants are addressed by their commander in chief Colonel Blair Appleton.</p>
               <p>The Colonel is a man of striking appearance, six feet four,  stalwart and strong in spite of his sixty-five years. His glance is keen and piercing from under beetling brows. His carriage is military yet his whole personality emanates a fine graciousness and cheer.</p>
               <p>He thanks the immigrants for electing his commander in chief. He tells them that they are about to set out into an unknown country - a country reputed to be a land of Milk and Honey. In glowing words he paints Oregon - the richness of its soil - the trees loaded with fruit - the streams abounding in fish; the forest alive with game; to say nothing of the fabulous possibilities from trade with the Indians; the pelts of beaver, of silver-fox, of mink, of ermine and other fur-bearing animals. He declaires //sic// Oregon to be the greatest agricultural country in the world needing only the courageous pioneers to break its soil and dig from its bowels its mineral wealth.</p>
               <pb n="B-5."/>
               <fw type="pageNum">B-5.</fw>
               <p>The camera pans around the circle of faces of the pioneers. Nearly every man and woman there is inspired by hope and the desire to reach the <q>Promised Land</q>. their commander’s words evoke the wildest enthusiasm and excitement and he is cheered to the echo.</p> 
               <p>We show Colonel Appleton’s own wagon. This is an especially fine covered wagon, practically a moving household.</p> 
               <p>Standing up on the back step of the wagon looking out over the heads of the engrossed crowd is the Colonel’s pretty daughter, Sally Lou. She is thrilled and excited and does not hesitate to join in the applause for her father.</p>
               <p>From behind Sally comes out of the wagon Mandy, an old black nurse and nanny. Nanny beams at the loudly clapping Sally Lou but her attention is distracted by a less pleasing object. From around the side of the wagon a tall black boy with a bullet head and rolling eyes comes slouching lazily to the fore, a bucket in his hand which spills and shakes as Mose moves along. Just as he comes under where Sally is standing Mose puts his thumb and fore-finger into his mouth and lets out a most unearthly whistle. Mandy casts one enraged glance at Mose and then reaching her left foot she gives him a hard prod on the head knocking him over and the pail of water spilling as he falls.</p>
               <milestone unit="line"/>
               <view>SALOON AND DANCE HALL</view>
               <p>This is the town of Independence.</p>
               <p>The atmosphere of the place is smoky and sultry. //B-6.// rough men of all sorts and kind are about the place gambling, making love to the girls, drinking and lining the bar.</p>
               <p>Here are dark French Canadian Voyageurs, long blonde Missourians, Mexicans, Swedes, Yanks, Jews, Englishmen, big fellows from the frontier towns.</p>               <p>Handsfull of silver are thrown or slapped down upon the bar. All comers are treated regardless.</p>
               <p>The fiddles scrape and the music rises above the discordant murmurs and imprecations. Buxom girls of all colors spin out upon the floor. They are grabbed by the men, whooping with delight, and they thumping or spinning with them across the floor. Near fights or real ones are precipitated and averted.</p>
               <p>One black eyed girl - she is known as Black Eyed Susan is the center of a group of men all clamoring to dance or drink with her. Sue has large, bold, roving eyes. Everyone is asking her where Bull is and she says he’s somewhere in town. One fellow says; <q>Well don’t tell on me</q>! He pinches her on the backside and gives her a good smack on the lips. Susan though she laughs gives him a push.</p>
               <p>The one subject of conversation everywhere is - OREGON. Everybody is talking of Oregon, and the immense train of Immigrants starting out for Oregon lands. Even the dancing girls talk Oregon to their partners. Some of them ask the men if they are going too, and when the men nod, //B-7// they pretend to bid them mock farewells, saying that the man who goes into Oregon never comes out. They make jokes about not liking baldheads, and the Indians always get their men. They think it funny to suggest that 2000 scalps will make a splendid carpet for Indian wigwams. They say that Immigrant scalps are especially soft. </p>
               <p>In one of the rooms of the saloon, Bull Doreen and his men are also discussing the Immigrants. Bull is a huge, brutal looking customer. He wears a red flannel shirt and buckskin breeches. His knife is stuck in his belt, his gun on his hip.</p>
               <p>Bull has done a profitable and illicit trade among the Indians, supposedly as a trapper; in reality as a vendor of corn whiskey and rum. The Indians have cached away immense quantities of valuable silver fox and beaver pelts. Bull is anxious to get up into the country to trade his booze for this fur, before the immigrants pour in. if once they settle upon the land; if in fact they reach the Williamette //sic Willamette// valley ahead of Bull’s outfit, his business will be ruined. Already too many immigrants have gone through. How this largest of all trains - 2000 strong - will spread over the Indian lands like locusts. It will mean the end of Bull’s trade with the Indians.</p>
               <milestone unit="line"/>
               <p>In the saloon, some commotion and stir is occasioned by the arrival of the two young scouts Ren and Thad. They are popular and well known, and their entrance is greeted with whoops. The young fellows goodnaturedly set up teh drinks for the crows.</p>
               <pb n="B-8."/><fw type="pageNum">B-8.</fw>
               <p>Bull and his men have also come into the saloon, and at a signal from Bull Susan speeds to his side. He gives her some orders, and she nods and hurries to obey him. Susan insinuates her way through the crowd till she manages to come alongside Thad and slips her hand through his arm. Thad has had a couple of drinks and is in high good humor. He looks down his shoulder and meets Susan’s black seductive eyes.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SUSAN</speaker>
                  <p>‘Lo Thad! Gee, I’m sure glad to see you. Where you been?</p>
               </sp>               
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <p>I’m glad to see you too, Susy. I’ve been up in the woods for sometime.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SUSAN</speaker>
                  <p>Pretty lonesome, ain’t it? You was always fond of good times.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>THAD</speaker>
                  <stage>(uneasily, yet affected)</stage>
                  <p>Well, I got into a peck of trouble with good times.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Ren, leaning against the bar, with a couple of girls interposing between him and his partner. Ren gives a wry squint across at the pair, and then as the bartender puts another drink before Thad, and as Thad picks it up, Ren reaches a long arm across and takes the glass from his hand. His action is good humored, but firm. There is a small protest.</p> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>Guess we better be driftin’ along //B-9.// partner. Them immigrants is waitin’ fer us.</p>
               </sp>
               
               <p>The girls and men make remarks:</p>
               <sp>
                  <p><q>Let ’em wait</q>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p><q>What’s the hurry</q>?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p><q>You’ll be a long time on the trail with those psalm singing folk. Wait a bit</q>!</p>
               </sp>
               <p>And so forth. Susan is hanging tight onto Thad, and her body is pressed against him. Thad’s glance shifts from his pal to Sue. he feels a bit sheepish.
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SUSAN</speaker>
                  <p>Gee, I’ve missed you! The town’s not been the same since you left.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Ren’s attention is turned from his pal, by Bull’s greeting.
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>How’re you -- Ren Bullock?</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Ren slowly turns, and still leaning up against the bar he looks with a queer, quizzical slowly sizing up glance at Bull Dorien.
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>What you doin’ in Independence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>What me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>Thought you was up in the Oregon.
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>What me?
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="B-10."/>
                  <fw type="pageNum">B-10.</fw>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>How’s tradin’ and trappin’ up to the North?
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>You oughter know. You wuz up there recent - talkin’ with your Indian friends, wasn’t you? </p>
               </sp>
               <p>Bull glares. Ren grins. His grin is not without a touch of boyish malice. Almost lazily and reluctantly he slouches a bit nearer to the black browed Bull. Bull’s glance goes by Ren. his eyes bore like gimlets into Susan’s. Hers reflect their momentary fear. 
               </p>
               <p>Thad, as his pal moves toward Bull, half starts to follow. The bartender has sets another glass before Susan. She lifts it first toward her own lips and then coaxingly toward his. Thad holds back a moment; but the liquor and Susan’s eyes are too much for the weak Thad. he swallows, licks and smacks his lips. Another glass slid across the bar. Thad glances at it wistfully out of the tail of his eye. Susan lifts it to his lips. He holds back a moment, and then, his eyes on Susan he downs it. Susan plucks at his sleeve. She puts her lips against his ear and whispers. Thad’s drousy //sic drowsy// eyes glean with awakening desire, for Susan’s body is pressed against his. He swallows, his head nodding. They move off.
               </p>
               <p>Ren does not see them go. Elbow on bar, his back against it, Ren’s wry glance is on Bull. bull shifts his tobacco, spits, waits for the smiling Ren to speak. Ren says not a word. 
               </p>
               <pb n="B-11"/><fw type="pageNum">B-11</fw>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>Hear tell yo’re //sic you’re// plannin’ to steer them Immigrants up to the Williamette //sic Willamette//. 
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>What me?
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>What trail you aimin’ to go by?</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Ren pushes back his wide hat, scratches his head thoughtfully.
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>Which would you take if you was me?
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>You’ll never get across the Divide with them wagons.
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>Reckon you’re right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>And there ain’t a chance of them green tenderfeet crossin’ the Columbia neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>Now you got me worried. 
</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Bull slouches nearer to him. He lowers his voice to a husky whisper.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>That ain’t no man’s job -- playin’ nursemaid to a bunch of soft immigrants.
</p>
               </sp>
               <p>>Ren considers this, screwing up his eyes thoughtfully.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>Mebbe //sic Maybe// you’re right.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="B-12"/><fw type="pageNum">B-12</fw>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>               What’re they payin’ you?
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               We--cl-- the price ain’t exactly set yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Bull comes back quickly this time.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>               Whatever they offer -- I’ll double -- see?</p>
               </sp> 
               <p>Ren raises his eyes wide with apparent surprise and unholy joy.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               Thought you knew the Oregon Country better than I did.
</p>
               </sp> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>               So I do. I ain’t hirin’ you for a guide.
</p>
               </sp>
                
               <p>Ren’s manner is guileless and friendly. His eye now lifts unquestioningly. He lets the other do the talking.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>               Without guides them Immigrants can’t get beyond the Dalles. They’ll never get across the Columbia. There ain’t no other guides to be had. 
</p>
               </sp> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               That so? 
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <stage>               (confidentially)
</stage>
                  <p>               You know it. What’s more we don’t want them Immigrants up in the Oregon. They aint’ good for nothin’. They’ll spread //B-13// all over the land like lice. ]]
</p>
               </sp>
               
               <p>Ren appears to be impressed.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               I hadn’t thought a that.
</p>
               </sp> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>               The Oregon ain’t no country for the likes a them. The Indians aren’t lookin’ for no religion. What they want is booze.
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               I’m thinkin’ what the Indians need is -- food.
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <p>               Well where they gonna get the good if them Immigrants settle on their land?
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               It ain’t the Immigrants that’s poison to the Indians. They’ll do a fair and honest trade with them. It’s the fellows with the Booze that --- ]]
</p>
               </sp>
               <p>He stops abruptly and smiles at Bull.</p> 
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <p>               Fergot all about that bein’ ye’re game, Bull.
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>BULL</speaker>
                  <stage>               (angry)
</stage>
                  <p>               It don’t make no different what my game is. I put a proposition up to ya. Is it yes or no?
</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>REN</speaker>
                  <stage>               (considering)
</stage>
                  <p>               I’ll talk it over with my pardner //note partner//--
</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="B-14"/><fw type="pageNum">B-14</fw>
                <p>He glances toward where Thad had been, and straightens up.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ren</speaker>
                  <p>               Well guess I’ll drift. See you later. 
</p>
               </sp>
               <p>He moves away, strolling lazily along, good-naturedly pushing aside the girls that come around him, or pausing to joke, throwing a handful of silver on the bar and treating all hands except himself, and <q>drifting</q> off gradually till he comes to a door, giving upon an alley way and exits.
               </p>
               <p>Once outside, his careless lazy manner changes. He is alert, as he looks swiftly about him. With a hand to the side of his mouth he gives forth a peculiar whistle three times. At first there is no response. Ren whistles again. 
               </p>
               <p>From a room at the far end of the alley, where a dim light shows comes somewhat waveringly Thad’s answering whistle. Ren wheels about, and is off in the direction from which the whistle has come. 
               </p>
               <milestone unit="line"/>
               <view>THE IMMIGRANT ENCAMPMENT 
               </view>
            </div>
            <div>
               <!--JT > LW: COPY + PASTE SEQUENCE B HERE-->
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
