<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="OtherPeoplesTroubles2">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Other People’s Troubles: An Antidote to Your Own (20 Feb. 1922)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:105"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovelSerial"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-21">Begin transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl105 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Other_Peoples_Troubles2">
      <pb n="202"/>
      <body>
         <head>Other People’s Troubles</head>
        
           <head type="subtitle">An Antidote for Your Own</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto
                  Watanna</name>)</byline> 
            <note>Author of <q>A Japanese Nightingale</q>, <q>Heart of
            Hyacinth</q>, <q>Wisteria</q>, <q>Marion</q>, <q>Me</q>, <q>Delia</q>, etc., etc.</note></opener>
        
         <div type="content">
            <div>
               <p><q>Oh, please don’t joke about it, Uncle Dan</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Why not? May as well be cheerful about it, as I tell a friend of mine whose
                     been through a sores experience than yours, Laura. And the chap is beginning to
                     buck up a bit. Comes to an old dried-up fossil like your Uncle Dan, who matches
                     his troubles with others that make his seem like mere shadows. And what’s more,
                     he lets your old uncle Dan give a hand to the still more wretched ones, and
                     then trots back to his own daily treadmill of pain and bears it like a
                  man?</q></p>
               <p>She sighed and shook her head helplessly, as if to say that she knew just what
                  panacea her uncle had to offer, but in her case at least his <q>medicine</q> would
                  fail. Unmindful of her little motion of despair, he continued:</p>
               <p><q>You know, dear child, we’ve all got to bear our share of sorrow in this world
                     of ours. We can’t evade it. I believe God meant us, each, to have his
                     individual portion of pain. We cannot fathom his design in the matter, but that
                     it was his design I think is proven by the tortures of His own Son</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But people to-day are denying the very existence of pain. The new religious
                     tell us there is no pain—no—no real sorrow or trouble in the world. <choice>
                        <sic>Its</sic>
                        <corr>It’s</corr>
                     </choice> all an—error—that’s what they call it. That everything is good and
                     right, and <choice>
                        <sic>its</sic>
                        <corr>it’s</corr>
                     </choice> only our wrong thinking that forces this—<q>error</q> which we call
                     pain or trouble, or what not. It’s a philosophy I should think you might
                     understand—and believe</q>. </p>
               <p><q>It’s a lame philosophy</q>, said her uncle gently. <q>By our own pain we can
                     understand and feel that of others, and we must feel <choice>
                        <sic>tha</sic>
                        <corr>that</corr>
                     </choice> pain of others. It is that alone will soften the hard heart of the
                     world. When we deny or ignore the existence of suffering and sin, we lose our
                     ability and heart to pity, and therefore help. We become selfish, inhuman. It’s
                     a much better, a much even brighter philosophy I am preaching to you, and I
                     wish I could shout it aloud to the whole world. I know your griefs and feel for
                     them. Could I help them, if I denied their existence? No. as it is, I am going
                     to treat you—just like the rest of my patients. I’m going to give you my chief
                     and universal prescription</q>. </p>
               <p><q>I know what that is</q>, she said softly, and again she signed.</p>
               <p><q>It is</q>, said he, solemnly, <q>to show you other griefs greater than your
                     own, and in the contemplation, and, if possible, alleviation of which you may,
                     in time, forget your own</q>.</p>
               <p>She rested with her cheek against his hand, her eyes closed.</p>
               <p><q>I don’t deny there are worse—troubles than mine</q>, she said, <q>but, oh,
                     indeed, dear Uncle Dan, the mere knowledge of them will not cure my own
                     pains</q>.</p>
               <p><q>That’s because you are still at the primary—the selfish stage; still drowning
                     yourself in your own tears. You have not been aroused—interested in other
                     people’s troubles yet, because your own case is still acute; but, mark my
                     words, the medicine I offer you works slowly, but surely!</q></p>
               <p><q>Slowly—but surely!</q> she repeated, and the suddenly sobbed, her face pressed
                  against her uncle’s hand. She spoke with her face still hidden:</p>
               <p><q>If you knew all that I have suffered! The waiting—waiting—the terrible waiting.
                     I think that eas the worst of all. And then—</q></p>
               <p>She uncovered her face and looked up at him with a tragically, piteous
                  expression.</p>
               <p><q>Aunt Marthy died of nothing else but—a broken heart. Just that—call it by any
                     other medical term you please. It was that that killed her. And old Mary—our
                     old Mary—died in the poor-house. Oh, think of it!</q></p>
               <p>She wrung her hands desperately together.</p>
               <p><q>I want to pull him down, Uncle Dan! I want to pull him down. There is murder in
                     my heart!</q> she cried.</p>
               <p><q>I expect your lawyer to-morrow night, Laura. You shall have your wish. I’ll
                     have a talk with him first. There’s a slight doubt whether he’ll take the
                     case</q>.</p>
               <p><q>You think then there’s a question of my——</q></p>
               <p><q>No, no. You’ve a clear case. No doubt of that. But Holt has been out of
                     professional harness for a year or more. He was—or thinks he was—forced to
                     retire. He’s the man I was speaking to you about a few minutes since. Life has
                     been a hard battle for holt, and he has had to fight with his back to the wall.
                     He’s practically a recluse now; but I’m inclined to think that the very thing
                     to save the man from his own dark broodings would be to interest him anew in
                     his work. If he takes your case, it will be a re-entry into his old field. Once
                     there, I believe he will stay</q>.</p>
               <p><q>A good lawyer?</q> she asked dubiously.</p>
               <p><q>Good as they make ’em</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Then, why?</q></p>
               <p><q>A case like your own, Laura. A personal obsession. An acute case of personal
                     sorrows. As I’ve told you, however, I’ve done my bit to jerk his mind at times
                     from his own pangs and interest him in others, and he’s marching the treadmill
                     now like a veritable giant</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Was his case then so sad?</q> she asked wistfully.</p>
               <p><q>It was more lasting than sad. It was like a cyclone, which roots up one’s very
                     being. One of those gigantic storms not all men are forced to <choice>
                        <sic>weather</sic>
                        <corr>whether</corr>
                     </choice> I’m going to tell you all about him. Laura, for I want you to know
                     something of the man who is to defend your rights</q>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p><q>You probably know my friend by <choice>
                        <sic>repuration</sic>
                        <corr>reputation</corr>
                     </choice> at least</q>, said the doctor. <q>He is Lenox Holt</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But he is a—murderer!</q> she gasped, sitting back and regarding her uncle
                  aghast.</p>
               <p><q>No, no, my child. He is reputed to be a murderer you mean</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But I thought he killed the man. I remember reading in the newspapers portions
                     of the trial</q>.</p>
               <p><q>And I</q>, said the doctor, <q>had the personal confidence of the man himself.
                     He was quite young when he married the woman. She was of questionable origin
                     and beneath him in every way. I remember the wedding very well, for the reason
                     that I was called in to attend the bride. She told her husband she was subject
                     to fainting spells. I diagnosed her case as dipsomania</q>.<note
                     type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation mark in
                  original</note></p>
               <p><q>She was a light, foolish thing, and like many of her kind as sly and cute as
                     she was weak and frail. He saw only her beauty, which was of a sort alluring
                     sort that baffles one as to why it should be associated with mean qualities of
                     mind and heart</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation
                     mark in original</note>
               </p>
               <p><q>At this time, for a young man, he was really at the top of his <choice>
                        <sic>peofession</sic>
                        <corr>profession</corr>
                     </choice>. His friends watched with no small degree of irritation and contempt
                     the devastating effect upon him of marriage. He seemed interested in only one
                     thing on earth. His profession, his friends, his few relatives even—all were
                     slighted for the woman he had married and upon whom he lavished a soul that
                     overflowed with a bondless love. His was an unsuspicious, trusting nature—like
                     your own, my child—and possibly when the <choice>
                        <sic>revellation</sic>
                        <corr>revelation</corr>
                     </choice> came, that was the reason he saw fire and blood, as perhaps you do
                     now, and his hands leaped forth to perform the will of his brain. In desire, at
                     least, so he has told me, he was for a moment, a murderer. Such impulses<pb
                        n="203"/>Come to us all, Laura, at the crucial moment. We are all sons of
                     Cain, but not all of us are tempted!</q></p>
               <p><q>They were in Boston at the time—she and her lover, that is. She had trumped up
                     some plausible excuse for her absence. Her mother, I believe she claimed, was
                     dying. She even produced a telegram to that effect, and strenuously and
                     virtuously she opposed his going with her. She was supposed to be in Westland,
                     Mass., and, indeed, she managed to have letters sent to him daily from this
                     town. He told me, at the time, he had not the slightest suspicion of her, and
                     his sudden <choice>
                        <sic>determiuation</sic>
                        <corr>determination</corr>
                     </choice> to go to Westland was due simply to an overwhelming impulse to see
                     her—his wife!</q></p>
               <p><q>At Westland, of course he found she was not there, and still unsuspicious of
                     the truth, though alarmed for her safety, he started for Boston. You see he
                     found one of his own letters at the house redirected to the Boston address.
                     What took place in Boston had been pretty well threshed out in the papers. The
                     argument was that finding his wife with his friend, he shot and killed the man
                     in the presence of his wife and with the man’s own revolver. He was tried
                     twice, and finally acquitted</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No
                     closing quotation mark in original.</note></p>
               <p><q>There was one point in dispute. Did, or did he not fire the shot that killed
                     his betrayer? Only one person besides himself, could answer that question and
                     she had set a price upon her testimony. Can you guess what that price was? No,
                     not mere money, but the pardon of herself by her husband</q>. <note
                     type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation mark in
                  original</note></p>
          
            <p><q>It’s one of the curious ironies of life that we often blindly injure those we love
                     the best. This was the case with this weak woman. She did love her husband, in
                     spite of her hopeless vileness of character, but she did not realize how much
                     she loved him until she had lost him</q>. <note type="editorial"
                     resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation mark in original</note></p>
            <p><q>At first she sought to win him back by cajolery and tears, and previous to the
                     trial was quite a figure in the papers and about the tombs. But I don’t believe
                     he even saw the woman. What he did see was his past and future—the former
                     glowing with hope and promise; the latter stretching out like a black desert,
                     dark and without a dawn. he saw the woman as others had seen her always,
                     shallow, vain, weak, wicked and wanton. Even her beauty had a tarnished
                     glitter, which now irritated him</q>. <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No
                     closing quotation mark in original</note></p>
            <p><q>He spent his hours pondering over how he had ever come to love so mean a thing, he
                     who had set his ideals so high. The one bit of comfort was the thought that if
                     freedom should come to him he would be—alone!</q>
                  <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation mark in
                     original</note></p>
            <p><q>It was a hard fight they made, and harder because his attorneys knew of the eye
                     witness’ knowledge of his innocence. That there had been a struggle between the
                     men, with Holt as aggressor was admitted; but it was the other man who seized
                     the revolver from the drawer of a table, where he must have kept it for just
                     such an emergency, and it was he who shot himself, accidentally or otherwise.
                     The only thing that saved Holt from the chair was public opinion and the fact
                     that the revolver was not Holt’s. it showed at least he had come unprepared.
                     The wife’s deliberate absence in Europe at the time of the trial, however, had
                     a damning effect, since, having loudly proclaimed her lover and repentance it
                     was taken as proof of her knowledge of his guilt that she did not testify in
                     his behalf</q>. <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation
                     mark in original</note></p>
            <p><q>Stupid and weak as I have said she was, it was natural for her to make this false
                     step. Had she gone upon the stand, and freely told the truth, which would have
                     removed from her husband the last suspicion of guilt, his heart might have been
                     touched; but she sought to force him to take her back by withholding the truth;
                     by threats, since rears had failed</q>. <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1"
                     >No closing quotation mark in original</note></p>
            <p><q>Now that’s Holt’s tragedy, Laura. You, like every one else who have heard of the
                     case, believe him guilty. I do not. I am sure, in fact, he is not. But holt is
                     aware of the fact that the world, like you, still holds him in suspicion, and
                     although the law has set him free, it has not taken the blot from his name and
                     fame. There is nothing harder to bear than injustice. Holt is smarting under a
                     sense of the cruel injustice of his situation. He has brooded over it so much,
                     in fact, that it has become monomania with him</q>
                  <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation mark in
                     original</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <p>(To be continued)</p>
            </div>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
