<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="OtherPeoplesTroubles3">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Other People’s Troubles: An Antidote to Your Own [Part 3]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl106"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna, Onoto</name></author>.
                     <title level="m">Other People’s Troubles: An Antidote to Your Own [Part
                     3]</title>. <publisher ref="org:Farm"><title level="j">Farm and Ranch
                        Review</title></publisher>, <date when="1919-03-20">20 Mar. 1919</date>, pp.
                     <biblScope unit="page">331-334</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from University of Saskatchewan</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovelSerial"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="published" when="2022-03-10">Added trailer.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2021-05-14">fixed typos.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-08-12">set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-24">renumbered instalments.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-07-01">added note about source</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-30">added next instalment link</change>
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-21">Begin transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2019-07-29">changed text link to pdf.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl106 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Other_Peoples_Troubles3" prev="doc:OtherPeoplesTroubles2" next="doc:OtherPeoplesTroubles4">
      
      <pb n="331"/>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Other People’s Troubles</head>
            <head type="subtitle">An Antidote for Your Own [Part 3]</head>
            <opener>
               <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto
                     Watanna</name>)</byline>
               <note>Author of <q>A Japanese Nightingale</q>, <q>Heart of Hyacinth</q>,
                     <q>Wisteria</q>, <q>Marion</q>, <q>Me</q>, <q>Delia</q>, etc., etc.</note>
            </opener>
            <div type="paratext">
               <p>Synopsis—<q>Other People’s Troubles</q> is the new type of a continued story
                  wherein each episode is a complete story itself, but the whole is connected
                  through the central figure of Dr. Carpenter, a very fine character, who believes
                  that to get interested in other people’s troubles is the best cure for your own.
                  Dr. Carpenter has his niece, Laura, living with him, and also the servant, telling
                  her of the great sorrow of Lenox Holt, a lawyer, who has been accused of killing
                  his wife’s lover, and, although let free by the court, has the stigma of murder
                  attached to his name To him the doctor is going to entrust Laura’s case. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <p><q>So he lives in an old house, just outside Fort Washington Park; and he avoids
                     his friends and shrinks away from that portion of the city where previously he
                     had been one of the leading lights. There are no servants even in the old Holt
                     place, just an ancient Irish pair who previously cared for the place as
                     janitors, at the time when Holt and his wife were part of the gay rushing life
                     of Newport and Manhattan. They don’t take very good care of the place. It looks
                     dog-eared and run-down, forsaken and neglected. You’d never suspect he was
                     under forty, and a man of means. For he looks more like a tramp. He roams about
                     Fort Washington Park and its environs, looking at the water and sometimes
                     muttering to himself. He fancies people point him out, and often he turns upon
                     them like a savage and asks them what they are staring at. And he wont go away,
                     because he says it was here he was born, and it was away from here he was
                     betrayed. Friends who had not cut him, he has cut, for when shame throws its
                     black mantle upon us, it is then one’s friends drop off like withered leaves,
                     or cling greenly to the branches. And I cling on to Lenox Holt, in spite of his
                     oftentimes insulting cynicisms regarding my profession and my aims. For Holt
                     believes all men are knaves and all women wantons and liars</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No closing quotation mark in
                  original.</note></p>
               <p><q>Are you asleep, Laura?</q></p>
               <p>Her face was hidden against his knee. She looked up slowly, her dark eyes
                  moist.</p>
               <p><q>No</q>, she said gently. <q>Oh, the poor man, the poor man!</q></p>
               <p>She was very silent for a long time after that; presently she stood up and,
                  bending over, softly kissed the top of his head.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, Uncle Dan, dear, why is the world not all sad when there is so much trouble
                     in it?</q></p>
               <p><q>Because the world’s so sweet, my dear. It’s a recompense for the blacker
                     things. When the sordid, harrowing things of life press the hardest on us,
                     there is still always the sky and the stars left us to see—and be thankful
                     for</q>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Dr. Carpenter picked up the telephone on his desk and grunted into the
                  receiver.</p>
               <p><q>Er-hum! Yes, it’s Dr. Carpenter</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Where?</q></p>
               <p><q>Can’t you get——</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>But I want to go to bed. What’s that?</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>Er-hum! Very well</q>.</p>
               <p>He grunted again, and rang off.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, Uncle Dan dear</q>, said Laura, in a tone of gentle exasperation: <q>Have
                     you got to go out again?</q></p>
               <p>She followed him into the hall and helped him slip into his great-coat.</p>
               <p><q>You were up all last night, dear</q>, she said plaintively.</p>
               <p><q>Yes</q>, admitted the doctor, and then clearing his throat with his cheery
                  rough <q>Er-hum!</q>:</p>
               <p><q>But remember, Laura—there were twins last night—twins! It was worth it. It was
                     worth it!</q></p>
               <p><q>I had hoped you could get to bed early to-night. Dear old dear! They’ll wear
                     you out between them. Who is the call from this time?</q></p>
               <p><q>Barnato’s Theatre</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Little Bonnie Snow in some sort of trouble—conglomeration of sprained ankle and
                     hysterics, I imply from the message. You remember Bonnie?</q></p>
               <p><q>Of course, though I haven’t seen her since I came to New York. Tell her, wont
                     you, that I’m here with you now, Uncle Dan</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Er-hum! Now trot along to bed with you</q>.</p>
               <p>He raised her face, with his hand under her chin. Then he flicked a forefinger
                  across the shadows under her eyes.</p>
               <p><q>To-morrow morning I expect to see these gone</q>, said he.</p>
               <p>She smiled sadly and shook her head a bit.</p>
               <p><q>I’m out of cold cream</q>, she said, whimsically, <q>and really, Uncle Dan,
                     dear, I don’t want to get the regulation ‘massage face’</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Sleep is the best Masseur in the world!</q> growled the doctor, and closed his
                  gloves with a snap upon each button. <q>You get into bed and blow your mind
                     adrift, and whenever you find it fastening upon things that disturb you, pull
                     it away with a firm grip, and fasten it at once upon other people’s troubles. I
                     prescribe Lenox Holt’s for to-night. Think of him—of his tragedy to-night, as
                     Mrs. Holmes has thought of Mrs. Finnerty, and——</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>Did you know</q>, she interrupted earnestly, <q>that she went to see Mrs.
                     Finnerty, and she is giving her work of a lighter kind than washing,
                  and——</q></p>
               <p><q>Did she say anything about her own—delusions?</q></p>
               <p><q>No, she didn’t. You see she was fixing her flat all up for the coming of her
                     mother, and Mrs. Finnerty was helping her. I thought she looked quite well, for
                     her</q>.</p>
               <p>The doctor chuckled, and pursed out his lips. Then he kissed his niece with a
                  great deal of tenderness, and hurried <pb n="332"/> out, slamming the door
                  cheerfully behind him.</p>
               <p>There was some confusion behind the scenes of Barnato’s Theatre, but in front a
                  shrill, triumphant voice was wildly proclaiming:</p>
               <p><q>I’m the cutest thing on Broadway, so they say!</q></p>
               <p>The doctor had little difficulty in making his way back of the scenes, for it
                  seems he had been expected. A young, sad-eyed chorus man, with a dejected
                  cigarette hanging loosely in his mouth, seized the doctor by the arm and dragged
                  him along through the wings.</p>
               <p><q>I tell you what, it’s a sad case if ever there was one</q>, he volunteered
                  mournfully.</p>
               <p><q>No bones broken, I hope</q>, said the doctor.</p>
               <p><q>No—o. I guess not. Just a nasty twist, ugly enough to knock her flat for a
                     time</q>.</p>
               <p>Somewhere close at hand now the doctor could hear sounds of muffled moaning, and
                  as his guide threw open the door of a diminutive dressing-room, the sole occupant
                  changed her moaning to loud wailing, much as a child would have done at the advent
                  of a parent.</p>
               <p><q>Well, well</q>, said the doctor, briskly, <q>and how’s Bonnie?</q></p>
               <p>Instead of answering the doctor, she bounced up on the couch, and turned a
                  wrathful face upon the doctor’s guide.</p>
               <p><q>What’s the matter with you? Can’t you get the doctor a chair. Oh, doctor! Oh-h!
                     Oh-h-h!</q></p>
               <p><q>In great pain?</q></p>
               <p><q>Agony! Torture! I wish I was dead!</q></p>
               <p><q>Stuff and nonsense. Here, let me see your foot. Er-hum!</q></p>
               <p>He pursed out his lower lip in his characteristic way. Then he frowned upon the
                  girl on the couch.</p>
               <p><q>Why, this is nothing—nothing! A little measly sprain. I’m surprised at you,
                     Bonnie. To get your good old doctor friend out of his comfortable bed for a
                     mean little sprain like this!</q></p>
               <p>Bonnie sat up again with a jerk.</p>
               <p><q>Mean little sprain!</q> she shrieked. <q>D’ye know what that sprain’s going to
                     mean? The ruin of—my—c-career! The loss of my one ch-chance—my only hope on
                     earth. I wish I were d-dead and b-buried!</q></p>
               <p><q>Aw, Bonnie!</q> began her friend, but she threw the slipper the doctor had
                  removed from her foot at his head.</p>
               <p><q>You shut up!</q> she cried. <q>It’s all your fault!</q></p>
               <p>The doctor was shaking his head gravely, and was examining the sprained foot from
                  several angles.</p>
               <p><q>Where would you care to have the amputation, Bonnie?</q></p>
               <p><q>Now, Doctor Carpenter, if you’re going to make odious remarks you can just go.
                     I know you’re sore because I got you out when you wanted to stay in, b-but I
                     didn’t want you because of the ankle. It doesn’t hurt anyhow worth a snuffle.
                     It’s—it’s—other——</q></p>
               <p><q>You’re hurt somewhere else?</q> asked the doctor anxiously.</p>
               <p><q>Ye-es</q>, she sobbed. <q>My heart’s broke. It is. Literally broke, and you’ve
                     got to give me some sort of dope to put me to sleep to-night, or I’ll——Oh, I
                     could almost kill myself for the f-fool I’ve been—f-for my dam luck!</q></p>
               <p>The doctor had moved a bit nearer to the girl, and now he took Bonnie’s hand. It
                  was very hot, and he hastily felt her head, blinked, drew out his thermometer and
                  put it under her tongue, holding her pulse meanwhile. She tried to talk with the
                  thermometer still in her mouth, but he stopped her.</p>
               <p><q>One minute, Bonnie. Now, let’s see!</q> and he held the glass to the light.
                     <q>I think I’ll have to put you to bed, Bonnie, for—say— Can you afford a
                     week’s rest?</q></p>
               <p><q>Afford it! Why they’ll hand it to me to-morrow in chunks</q>, she said
                  bitterly.</p>
               <p>The chorus man threw away his cigarette viciously. It was unlighted, and he had
                  aimed it at an ash-tray, but she shrieked as it touched her hand, and in an
                  instant the boy—for he was nothing but a boy—was kneeling by her, frantically
                  kissing the hand, and imploring the doctor to assure him that he had not burned
                  it.</p>
               <p><q>Burn!</q> said the doctor, examining the hand, <q>Stuff and nonsense!</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="333"/>
               <p><q>Who said it was?</q> demanded Bonnie. <q>I screamed because I’m all nerves. Joe
                     Forrest, if you do tha again—</q></p>
               <p>The doctor looked at his watch, and clicked it close again. Bonnie threw him a
                  look of such piercing reproach that he resumed his seat.</p>
               <p><q>I thought you at least would want to know about my troubles, seeing you’ve
                     known me all my life—and brought me into the world too, for that matter. And
                     I’ve played with your niece Laura when we were little kids, and Joe there too,
                     is from Newtown, though you mayn’t recognize him. He’s followed me now for the
                     past two years, and the big gump is working in the chorus himself, because he
                     says he can get nearer to me that way, but I say he’s just trying to spy on me,
                     and it’s all his fault that my career has—ended—and——</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>Aw, Bonnie!</q> put in Joe again, and again was squelched wrathfully:</p>
               <p><q>You know it was. If you hadn’t held me back talking all that love rot, with me
                     so excited and happy, I let you run on. Oh, Doctor, I felt as if I could love
                     the whole world—anybody—even him! You see the chance I had been waiting for all
                     these months—years—had come to me at last</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Your chance?</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>Yes, the chance they say comes only once to an actress!</q> said she,
                  tragically. <q>I was understudying Adele Hopper, but she got healthier every day
                     and there didn’t seem a ghost of a show for me. And Mamie Langhorm was at it
                     too—both of us. I knew I had it in me to make the high hit if I was only given
                     the chance. Then Jimmy there got a brilliant idea, and he fixed it up with Miss
                     Hopper ‘s chauffeur, and to-night she’s stuck somewhere up Westchester way on
                     some lonely road near her home, and she couldn’t get here even if she could fly
                     now. And so my chance was come, and everybody was ready to lick my boots. And I
                     was all dressed up for the part, just crazy for the chance, when that loon
                     there began to squirt his love-talk at me, and I—feeling grateful, was
                     listening when my time came, and I lost my wits and went running on, and I
                     tripped over Annite Sibley’s black cat and twisted my toe in a loose board.
                     There I sprawled flat on my face, with everybody laughing at me in front, and
                     everybody cursing me behind. And then that Mamie Langhorne jumped into the
                     breach—— and—and—Joe carried me here, and indeed I wish I were dead and buried,
                     f-for my only on earth to do, and—and I’ll be fired to-morrow anyhow
                  and—</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Bonnie</q>, said the doctor, gravely, <q>How much do you get a week?</q></p>
               <p>She stopped her wailing a moment: </p>
               <p><q>$25.00</q>, she said.</p>
               <p><q>That’s not so bad</q>, said the doctor. </p>
               <p><q>Why, I’m not a mere chorus girl</q>, said Bonnie, with dignity. <q>You see I’m
                     one of the two ladies that hold the canopy over the queen’s—that’s Miss
                     Hopper’s—head. We don’t say nothing, but we dance when she sings, and we laugh
                     and nod our heads at her jokes. Mamie’s—the other one</q>. She sighed heavily.
                     <q>But after to-night I suppose she’ll be doing something more than
                  kicking</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Aw, I don’t know</q>, said Joe. <q>I see her do the stunt, Doc. Thought she was
                     on the blink, after Miss Hopper</q>.</p>
               <p><q>What’s your business, Joe?</q> inquired the doctor.</p>
               <p><q>Don’t you remember me, Doc?</q></p>
               <p><q>No, I can’t say I do</q>.</p>
               <p><q>I’ve swallowed many of your pills, Doc, when you were practising in Newtown,
                     and my father—well, he used to have most of your trade</q>.</p>
               <pb n="334"/>
           
            <p><q>You are not Joe Forrest’s boy?</q> </p>
            <p><q>That’s me, O.K</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, you’ve certainly changed. What are you doing with a show like this? Any talent
               in that line?</q></p>
            <p>Bonnie snorted loudly, turned over on her sofa pillow and closed her eyes with
               contemptuous weariness.</p>
            <p><q>We-el</q>, said Joe, with a touch of bashfulness, <q>to tell you the truth, Doc, I’m just
               toting along with it because of Bonnie, there</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, you needn’t trouble on my account</q>, said the lady in question, thumping her
               pillow viciously. <q>And let me tell you, Joe Forrest, if fever get over this, I’m
               going to take advantage of Mr. Guns law’s offer</q>.</p>
            <p><q>He’s a mutt</q>, said Joe, savagely. </p>
            <p><q>Oh, I don’t know</q>, said Bonnie, loftily. <q>There are others; and besides, next to my
               ambition to be a prima-donna, I’ve always longed to be one of a vaudeville team, and
               this’d be my chance</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Aw, Bonnie, you know you wouldn’t—</q>
               </p>
            <p><q>I appeal to you, Doctor Carpenter. I’m feeling down-in-the-mouth, and it don’t add
               to my health to have that gentleman there hanging around me. Won’t you please, as my
               doctor, get him out of here?</q></p>
            <p><q>Aw, Bonnie —</q>
               </p>
            <p><q>Suppose you see about getting a taxicab for Bonnie</q>, suggested the Doctor.</p>
            <p><q>Aw— aw-right</q>, and he went out forlornly, shutting the door very gently behind him,
               as though he feared a bang might disturb his lady-love.</p>
            <p><q>Ain’t he the limit?</q> was her comment, and then returning to her grievance: <q>I’m all
               in, Doc—just heart-broke. Really, kidding aside, my sole chance to make a hit has
               slipped through my fingers like dishwater. I’d rather become a famous actress
               than—than—well, than become the bride of a Pittsburg millionaire, and that’s a fact.
               But look at me, will you? Can you imagine anything worse? Why nothing worse could
               happen to an actress</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, yes, something could</q>, said the doctor, gently.</p>
            <p><q>What-now, I defy you to tell me what?</q></p>
            <p><q>You really want me to tell you of another actress’ misfortune?</q></p>
            <p><q>Yes, I do. Oh, I know there’s lots of hard luck tales of the stage—but you can’t
                     beat mine as a starter. You see my career is blasted just at the
                  beginning</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Which is better than having it happen at the end</q>, said the doctor, gently.</p>
            <p><q>I don’t see that</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Well, because you can start over again. The woman I am going to tell you about was
                     old and hopeless at the time. Now, lie back there comfortably, don’t think
                     about your own case ever, but give me your attention. Er-hum!</q></p>
            </div>
            
               <div type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p><q>Madame Mazurka’s fame was before your time, Bonnie, but you may have heard of
                     her?</q></p>
               <p><q>Heard of her!</q> ejaculated Bonnie, sitting bolt upright. <q>Heard of Mazurka!
                     Well, I should smile!</q></p>
               <p>The doctor sighed. He was running his hand a hit wearily through his shock of iron
                  gray curls, which were one of his characteristic features.</p>
               <p><q>Mazurka was quite an actress in her time, but she retired somewhat early from
                     the stage, and married a man who earned his living in stock gambling-a broker,
                     in other words. When I first knew them, they were rich, and lived in a high
                     manner. In fact, my first thought of them was that they were living on the
                     crest of a wave which was bound to break over against the shore, as waves have
                     a habit of doing. For I knew not only that his method of livelihood was
                     precarious but that he was impractical and somewhat reckless</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation mark in original</note></p>
               <p><q>She was radiant in those days, quite the most radiant creature I have ever
                     seen. Passionately in love with her husband, she was surrounded by a coterie of
                     people who lavished upon her the adulation without which an actress’ life feels
                     flat and unreal. She lived on excitement-and flattery, heard it literally
                     shouted, sung or breathed into her ears on all sides</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation mark in original</note></p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>(To be continued)</trailer>
      </body>
         </text>
</TEI>