<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PlentyOfOpportunity1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Plenty of Opportunity for Men in Alberta If They Will Go on the Land</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:NC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl116"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Reeve, Mrs.
                     Francis</name></author>. <title level="a">Plenty of Opportunity for Men in
                     Alberta If They Will Go on the Land</title>. <publisher ref="org:Calgary"><title level="j">Calgary Herald</title></publisher>, <date when="1924-01-19">19 Jan. 1924</date>, p. <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile from University of British Columbia Library</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-05" status="published">Proof completed. Edited and
            added text to repository. </change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-05" status="readyForProof">Proof in progress. Proofed
            up to The RailRoads.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2021-11-29" status="readyForProof">Edited and added text to
            repository.</change>
         <change who="pers:NC1" status="inProgress" when="2021-10-28">Completed
            Transcription</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-01">Added note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and
            exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl116 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Plenty_of_Opportunity_for_Men_in_Alberta" prev="doc:AlbertaLandOfWork1">
      <pb n="7"/>
      <body>
         <head>Plenty of Opportunity For Men in Alberta If They Will Go on the Land</head>
         <head type="subtitle">A Place for Them Not Only in Summer but in the Winter--Fifteen
            Thousand Homes and Positions Were Offered For Twelve Thousand Men--Cities Afford Only
            Limited Employment--Work to Be Had in Lumber Camps, in The Mines, on the Railroads--No
            Man from the Old Country Need Be Ashamed of Starting to Work with His Hands--Alberta Has
            No Promise of Silken Ease in Luxury, but She Extends the Boon of Honest Toil.</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">MRS. FRANCIS REEVE</name></byline>
            <note>(Continued from Last Week)</note>
         </opener>

         <div>
            <p>But to come back to the solicitation of the farmers to take in the English harvesters
               for the winter. After the harassing events of the summer above mentioned, it may be
               thought that Mr. Farmer would turn a deaf ear to these canvassers for the men from
               the old land. Far from it. The result was quite remarkable, if one takes the figures
               of the railroads and the government into consideration. Fifteen thousand homes and
               positions secured for twelve thousand men! That was the tremendous response of the
               Canadian farmer.</p>
            <p>I am told that out of the 12,000 men who came here only about 1,000 returned to
               England. In our own district of Calgary, 300 positions on farms were found for men
               for the winter. The winter wage, it is true, was not high--probably averaging about
               $20 to $30 a month--in some cases lower. I have heard of some men who went out to
               farm and are working for the winter for their board. A great many of these harvesters
               had saved harvest and threshing wages. It is no uncommon thing in this country for
               harvesters and threshers to have enough saved from their season’s work to lay off for
               the entire winter.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Other Kinds of Jobs</head>
            <p>First of all, I might recall the fact that this is an agricultural country. The
               cities afford only limited employment, and they should therefore be eliminated in
               considering possible places of employment.</p>
            <p>Most people cherish the erroneous notion that farming is a simple occupation that
               anyone can undertake; that requires no brains, no apprenticeship, no experience, no
               especial gift. That is a most fallacious idea. Farming, properly conducted, is as
               skilled and important a business as any that exists. The farmer, indeed, needs both
               knowledge and skill in a hundred directions. In fact if a man desires to go in for
               farming in this country, it would be well for him first, to go to work for another
               farmer and learn his trade. Too many come out here, take up a homestead or buy a
               farm, go out upon the land and then blunder along helplessly till they are either
               broke or have won out. The most successful farmers here are those who either started
               in the service of another farmer or who have had experience elsewhere before coming
               here.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Lumber Camps</head>
            <p>Next to farming the lumber camps offer perhaps the best opportunities for employment.
               The camps are unable to get anything like the labor they want. The work is healthy
               and the hours are regular. It is, of course, hard and husky work, but many men prefer
               it to any other type of physical labor. In some camps--I might especially mention the
               camps of British Columbia--modern appliances are afforded. There the men have bathing
               facilities and are given clean quarters and good bedding. The lumberjacks and loggers
               demand and get the best of grub.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Mines</head>
            <p>Work in the coal mines is hard, and not especially pleasant, but it is well paid for.
               I believe the wage is from $8.00 to $20.00 a day, and it is fairly regular
               employment. There will likely be a considerable development of the mines in the
               coming years, as Alberta is being recognized as a great coal country and only time
               and capital are needed to bring it up to a producing centre that will compare with
               that of other coal countries.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Railroads</head>
            <p>I am told by railroad official heads that there is always work on the railroads. In a
               big country like this, railroad construction goes on constantly, and the man who is
               willing to handle a pick and shovel will find employment.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Trapping</head>
            <p>A good living is made by the successful trapper. This is a limited field, however,
               and to make an actual living, a man needs to know the country well and be a good
               woodsman. He should understand the habits of the animals whose pelts he is after.
               Some men spend a whole lifetime in the woods acquiring such knowledge.</p>
            <p>However, many of the farmers and more of the men working on the farms do make
               considerable on the side by trapping or killing beavers, lynx, coyotes, muskrats and
               other animals. We had a man who worked on our grain ranch who made $250 in a single
               season from muskrat and coyote hides.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Road Work</head>
            <p>Road work is done in the summer. The roads of this country are kept in shape by gangs
               of laborers. They are paid from $4.00 to $6.00 per day and board, and if they possess
               a team of horses they are allowed $3 a day extra for the labor of each horse.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Riders</head>
            <p>Good riders are always in demand on a cattle ranch. It is a favorite employment with
               younger men. Some outfits employ only the experienced riders, but others prefer men
               who are new at the <q>game</q> but are willing to <q>learn the ropes</q>. The
               experienced rider is often spoiled for other work on a ranch. They balk at any job
               not directly connected with the horse or cattle, such as branding, dehorning,
               vaccinating and, of course, riding and rounding up, and in the case of horses,
               cutting out, breaking, etc. Most of the ranchers prefer men who besides riding will
               give a hand at fencing and also work in the field at haying time.</p>
            <p>Physical labor in this country carries with it a certain dignity. A man does not lose
               caste by working with his hands. Sons of our best families, and some of the best
               families in England go into our fields at harvest time, while others are engaged upon
               road building and in the lumber camps. College men are as numerous in the harvest
               fields as men of no education.</p>
            <p>Snobbery is out of place in a country like Alberta. It’s not the employment, but the
               man, that counts. Personally, I have more respect and a feeling of fellowship for the
               overall-clad chap upon the land or in the shop, who is contributing his honest share
               toward the productive work of the world, than I have for the white-collared,
               spats-footed, cigarette-smoking boozefighters and joyriders who are the main props of
               pool rooms, dance halls, gambling houses and other places. There is no work, however
               hard or even menial, that can degrade a man. It’s the man who degrades the work.
               There is no reason why any work should not call for the tribute of respect.</p>
            <p>For the past seven years I have watched the men of the farming and ranching country
               who have worked for us and for neighboring ranchers. In boosting the wage from $4.00
               to $6.00 a day at harvest time, or holding out for top wages during the war years, I
               do not doubt but what they had their side to the question. Take the case of the
               harvesters this summer. Eight to ten hours a day, laboring in the field, under a hot
               sun, stooking up bundles that this summer at least weighed from 20 to 40 lbs. each! A
               man’s job, indeed, and deserving of a man’s pay. Or at threshing time, working in all
               kinds of weather, fair or rough, tossing those same bundles into stook wagons.
               Unloading maybe in wind and biting cold, with chaff flying from the separator and
               blowing into their faces, their eyes and down their lungs. Changing from farm to
               farm, wherever the threshing machine might go. Sleeping in bunk house or caboose, in
               tent or granary or shed, or any old place the farmer could afford--sometimes upon a
               bed, but more often that not upon straw upon the ground.</p>
            <p>Small wonder that these men demanded the highest wages possible for their sacrifice
               and labor. But in asking for more than the farmer was himself earning, showed poor
               judgement. In considering the work of the harvester, we must at the same time look at
               the average farmer, who employed the harvester. Was he not working hard--yes, harder,
               than any man in his employ? I know of few outfits where the farmer was not working
               shoulder to shoulder with the harvest and threshing hands and when the day’s work was
               done in the field, unlike the man he employed, the farmer still worked--and on. Nor
               could he be sure of the daily wage upon which at least the harvester could count.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Climate of Alberta</head>
            <p>We suffer abroad from an erroneous conception of the climate of Canada. We can trace
               this curious idea of our country to the pernicious literature which has been
               circulated in the form of stories, articles, plays, motion pictures and even lectures
               by people who are not Canadian, but who have sojourned for a brief season in Canada,
               and returned to their own countries to exploit and misrepresent Canada. Some day we
               will realize the incalculable harm done to Canada by these libels. We are always
               represented as being a land of ice and snow, where hardships and privation and
               poverty are the general rule of life. Only in certain parts of Canada, very sparsely
               populated, do we suffer from the extremes of cold and privation thus pictured. Taken
               as a whole, Canada has a healthy robust winter, and summers that are almost
               unrivalled. The climate of British Columbia, the year around--or rather a part of
               British Columbia, compares with that of part of the boasted climate of California,
               where the flowers bloom the year around. For my part I consider that Alberta
               possesses the finest climate in the world. Its sunlight and its Chinook winds make it
               unique. It is true, that we have spells of bitter zero weather in winter, but they
               never last long, and they are broken by Chinooks that compensate for the transient
               cold by long spells of warm days of sunshine. Our springs are not as warm or balmy as
               one might wish. I do not like our springs, but they are not unendurable at all
               events. I believe our summers and falls cannot be surpassed, and the long sun-lighted
               days stretch sometimes clear up till the end of December.</p>
            <p>Even the temporary sojourner in Alberta feels something of the fascination of this
               country, and I believe it is more or less due to the climate--the eternal sunlight,
               and the bracing air; through the magnificent scenery on all sides of us, whether it
               be in the hill country, with its stretch of matchless peaks, or the wide spreading
               prairie lands, stretching into unlimited distances and seeming to be merged into the
               sky itself, these contribute their share to the spell of Alberta. The tang of the big
               new land; the pull of the immense open spaces--these are the magnets that draw and
               hold us.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Immigrants From All Over the World</head>
            <p>It is now generally known that immigrants from all over the world are preparing to
               pour into this country during the coming year. Already a great number of Russians and
               Mennonites have come during the past year. They have been filtering in gradually, but
               I was surprised when told that of 20,000 Russians had come in during the past year.
               Central Europe, the United States, the Scandinavian countries, Holland, Italy,-- all
               are preparing to send a large quota into Canada. Canada has all the potentialities
               that go to the making of the greatest of countries, but she lacks capital and
               population. The signs point to the fact that these will ultimately come to her either
               from the motherland or our neighbors to the south.</p>
            <p>Canada recognizes that her crying need is population, and she is anxious to select
               the type of immigrant who will be a credit to the country. For that reason many
               schemes are under way to induce the best kind of immigration. One plan, which is
               likely to be laid before the British government, considers the desirability of
               bringing whole families into Canada, and settling them upon five and ten-acre farms
               in good farming districts, where the father, and possibly the sons, if old enough,
               may find regular employment among the neighboring farmers. Meanwhile the small farm
               would not only supply a home to which they might return nightly, but contribute
               materially through dairy products, poultry, pigs and garden truck. It is certain that
               such a plan would be most desirable so far as the farmers are concerned. A steady man
               in a farming neighborhood would be sure of work from the farmers who have to depend
               upon the uncertain help supplied from the city. With his wages, which should be
               considerable over harvest and threshing period, this man would be comfortably fixed,
               and after a couple of years would have earned the right to take up the quarter
               section homestead which it is then intended should be allowed him.</p>
            <p>I have heard it said that many of the immigrants from Central Europe and Russia speak
               of Canada as the land of promise and refuge, the sure haven and retreat from the
               torturing problems that make of mere living a desperate and stark struggle against
               the grimmest of antagonists.</p>
            <p>Splendidly immense, aloof, yet holding out warm mothering, inviting arms, Canada
               calls across to the war weary and hungry ones of the old world. She offers no
               promises of silver or gold, of silken case or luxury; but she extends a great--indeed
               the greatest of all boons--honest toil!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>