<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="RoyalTitledRanchers1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royal and Titled Ranchers in Alberta</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:119"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-05">Added transcription</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl119 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs= "facs:RoyalTitledRanchers1">
      <body>
         <head>Royal And Titled Ranchers in Alberta</head>
         <opener> <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Eaton Reeve</name></byline></opener>
         <div>
            <p>Long before the Prince of Wales bought the E. P. Ranch at High River in Alberta, he
               had been preceded by other royalties and men and women of title, who had found this
                  <q>last of the big lands</q> an ideal place for ranching and adventure. The names
               of Alberta’s royal and titled ranchers read like pages from the Peerage.</p>
            <p>In the early days when Alberta was still in a raw and pioneer state, upon the heels
               of the missionaries and the C. P. R. came such men as Sir Francis McNaughton son of
               Lord McNaughton, who for thirty years ranched at Bow Ness, Alberta, and who still
               maintains a home in this country to which he pays an annual visit. A colony of French
               aristocrats was established at a place named Trochu, after the leader of the party. </p>
            <p>From one of the oldest and noblest families in France came to Alberta, with his wife
               and children, the Marquis de Roussy de Sales. They settled at High River, and are now
               residents of Montreal.</p>
            <p>Another French family which arrived in those early days, accompanied by a retinue of
               servants, was that of the Count and Countess de Foras, also of High River. They lost
               considerable money in their venture in the new land, but stuck pertinaciously at
               ranching, and although today there remains but a single one of the many servants that
               accompanied them from France, it is doubtful whether the de Foras could be induced to
               leave Alberta. They are working, practical ranchers. They have a large family of
               girls, noted for their beauty and exceptional talent. One of them, Countess Odette de
               Foras, won the scholarship of the Royal College and the Royal Academy of Music of
               London, England, and her phenomenal voice is now being trained for Grand Opera. Two
               of the sons put in the crop each year and then go out to work for the Telephone
               Company as mechanics and linemen. </p>
            <p>Lady Adela Cochrane was one of the first of the <q>Old Timers</q>. She established
               her ranch at what was then known as Mitford on the Bow River. Lord Norberry was her
               neatest neighbor. Bernard Howard, son of the Earl of Carlisle, ranched also in that
               part of the country. He made a great reputation as a polo player. Howard served with
               distinction in the recent war, was taken prisoner by the Germans, escaped and
               returned to England, and was soon again in action. </p>
         </div>
        <div n="1">
            <head>A Problem For the Authorites</head>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
