<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="SavageInSilks1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Savage in Silks</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>12.18</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl260"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Anonymous</name></author>.
                           <title level="a">Savage in Silks</title>. ms., <date notBefore="1917"
                           notAfter="1926">1917-1926</date>, <distributor ref="org:WERFonds"
                           >Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>, <idno>12.18</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p><q>A Savage in Silks</q>, c. 1917-1926, (CU2337784) by Eaton, Winnifred.
                           Courtesy of Libraries and Cultural Resources Digital Collections,
                           University of Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreFilm"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-10-24" status="inProgress">Transcription in progress. Completed to page 33 in PDF.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info and
            facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:SavageinSilks1">
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <fw type="continued" place="right">(TH)</fw>
         <fw type="continued" place="left"><q>A SAVAGE<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">This is
                  an offensive racial slur that occurs multiple times in this text. Please see our
                     <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note on language</ref>.</note> IN
            SILKS</q></fw>
         <fw type="continued" place="right">Treatment by</fw>
         <fw type="continued" place="right">Barbara Chambers</fw>
         <fw type="continued" place="left">An original story for the screen by</fw>
         <fw type="continued" place="left"><name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name></fw>

         <div type="content">

            <head>SYNOPSIS</head>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>Gloria Glendon, a fabulously wealthy girl of eighteen, has the temper of a wildcat.
               Wilful, turbulent, lawless, she has defied and combatted every effort of her
               guardians, and those who have been retained to assist them, either to guide or
               discipline her. Time and time again servants, companions, and tutors have felt the
               sting of Gloria’s sharp tongue and fist, or have fled ignominiously before flying
               missiles; until the problem fo finding the proper persons to fill positions in the
               great sombre Fifth Avenue mansion, in which Gloria makes her home, has become a
               perplexing issue to the directors of the Trust Company; who, are not only responsible
               for the administration of the vast Glendon fortune, but for the proper upbringing of
               Gloria as well.</p>

            <p>Gloria is svelte, slender -- with no hint of thinness. There is something
               panther-like in the flowing <choice>
                  <sic>symmety</sic>
                  <corr>symmetry</corr>
               </choice> of her slightest movement. Her eyes are wide and slightly green, fringed
               with curling blash lashes; eyes that contract at the corners when their tempestuous
               young owner is annoyed -- signals of uncompromising combat. At time, in repose,
               Gloria has the tranquil beauty of a Cellini angel -- the bright intriguing
               personality fo a confiding child.</p>

            <p>Though but eighteen years of age, Gloria is cynical, bitter, suspicious, defiant --
               the same little wild thing with her back against the wall that her father’s agents
               had taken from her mother’s arms when Gloria was only six years old; and Gloria has
                  <pb n="2"/> never forgotten or forgiven the enforced separation. The years have
               failed to dim Gloria’s memory of her vivid Gypsy mother,<note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">This is an offensive racial slur that occurs multiple times in
                  this text. Please see our <ref target="doc:note_on_language">note on
                     language</ref>.</note> that pretty young creature of tinsel and spangles who
               had petted her one moment and slapped her the next -- who was always hugging,
               laughing, kissing, coughing. Her memory of her father is short, but equally clear --
               she had seen him but once; the day when his agents brought her, a desperately
               struggling and stormily protesting child, into the great room, wehre he stood
               waiting, codlly, to receive her. She was held firmly on either side as he surveyed
               her - this screaming, fighting young savage, a Glendon!</p>

            <p><q>Take her away!</q> he had ordered stonily -- and then, still kicking and fighting,
               Gloria was carried from his sight.</p>

            <p>Gloria never saw her father again -- Gwynne Glendon went down on the Titanic. She
               never saw her mother again -- Folly Glendon laughed and kissed, and coughed herself
               out of life. Teh marraige of Gwynne Glendon to Folly, the Gipsy, had been the
               enforced climax of a fit of moon mandess -- a very rich young man camping in the
               wilderneess, a provacative, dark eyed witch, flitting alluringly through the trees,
               an enraged band of Gypsy relatives refusing protestations of innocence -- a gypsy
               marriage, a mad, wild, honeymoon; then a sudden awakening to the truth of his
               position -- and Gwynne Glendon returned to civilization, without explanation or
               farewell.</p>

            <p>Though orphaned by the deaths of her parents, Gloria was not alone -- there were
               other relatives, a horde of them; whispering strangers who regarded her askance or
               speculatively, and who referred to her mother as <q>That woman</q>; - relatives who
               said uncomplimentary things about the child as she kicked and spat the <pb n="3"/>
               truth at them. Gloria hated them, with all the fierceness of her savage little
               soul.</p>

            <p>The years brought no abatement of Gloria’s aversion and contempt for her relatives.
               There were cousins, aunts, uncles and more still distant kinsfolk -- all of whom
               foregathered at intervals to discuss ways and means of controlling Gloria and
               Gloria’s millions.</p>

            <p>Moreover, Gloria was increasingly aware that even the servants in the great house
               were in the pay of her <q>relatives</q> - a spying, snivelling crew of talebearers;
               very well, she would give them real tales to bear. So Gloria kept things hotly active
               in the great house; defying and flouting them all, she resisted both blandishments
               and threats, and her sharp littel teeth and nails had left their mark on more than
               one who attempted to restrain her by force -- they were all <q>against her</q> Gloria
               believed, and she had not a friend to turn to.</p>

            <p>At last she was the subject of a solemn judicial inquiry when she sat through tedious
               sessions and heard logn arguments from lawyers retained by the <q>relatives</q>, who
               sought to have her declared incompetent, and themselves appointed guardians and
               trustees of her person and wealth; but a benign, fatherly looking old man, who sat at
               the head of a long table, had watched the lovely, innocent young face and his eyes
               had brightened at her swift and sharp retorts to the questions he had put to her. He
               had smiled at the word <q>incompetent</q> and had shaken his shaggy head; then he
               began to speak. Quietly, incicisviely, the relatives were ignored -- the old man at
               the head of the table ahd appointed a hard boiled trust company to act <pb n="4"/> as
               guardian of the estate as well as the person fo Gloria Glendon.</p>

            <p>Gloria -- though she was but ten ,marched out of the courtroom with her little heart
               beating over what she knew weas victory. Checkmated, the relatives contineud to watch
               the girl who stood between them and millions. Gloria met all overtures and advances
               on their part with open hostility and contempt -- she scorned even the pretense of a
               truce. With only servants and paid attendants as companions, Gloria came up into
               young girlhood. She had never had a real friend or confidante. She trusted no one,
               and no one trusted her; for her relatives and the servants had given her a reputation
               that she deliberately sought to live up to.</p>

            <p>Major MacClellan, a soldierly old gentleman of sixty-five, is the president of The
               Franklin Trust Company -- the banking house that has Gloria’s affairs in hand. The
               Major has been designated Gloria’s personal mentor. But, though the Major runs
               affairs at the bank with the military precision of an army under siege; he is
               absolutely impotent before the rebellion of his beautiful young ward.</p>

            <p>Gloria’s latest chaperone is Miss Julia Farnsworth -- a worthy spinster of fifty.
               Miss Farnsworth belongs to the generation by whom ankles were referred to in the most
               discreet of tones -- legs were never mentioned. Gloria’s idea of solid comfort is a
               chaise longue, a recent novel -- a box of Maillards and a position that includes the
               crossing of one slender leg across the upraised knee of the other, in such a manner,
               that her dark <choice>
                  <sic>towseled</sic>
                  <corr>tousled</corr>
               </choice> head is at least forty degrees lower in altitude than the satin toe of her
               slender foot.</p>

            <p>Finding Gloria in this position, one memorable afternoon, Miss Farnsworth lectures,
               censors, nags. Gloria retorts first by <pb n="5"/> throwing bonbons at the indignant
               chaperone -- then followed these sweet confections with the novel she has been
               reading. Miss Farnsworth, angrily standing her ground, indignantly declares she is
               accustomed to the chaperonage of <emph>respectable</emph> young ladies only. After
               laughing naughtily over the furious exit of her chaperone, Gloria detaches herself,
               and hearing a voice outside, tiptoes to the door. In the hall she catches Dobbs, the
               footman, at the telephone, giving a hectic version of the affair to one of the
                  <q>relatives</q>. Gloria slips up behind him, grabs him by the neck of his coat
               with one hand; and with the other, delivers a business like punch directly in the
               footman’s eye. The footman’s outcry brings servants hurrying from several quarters,
               only to be swiftly dispersed before the fury of the young termagent.</p>
            <p>Miss Farnsworth, in the safety of her own room, telephones an S.O.S. for help to
               Major MacClellan; and he-- fearing anything short of murder, hurries over to the
               Fifth Avenue home. As the Major arrives, the door is opened by Dobbs, the footman,
               displaying a perfectly beautiful eye. Immediately Miss Farnsworth hurries down
               stairs, followed by Wilkins, the butler, Anna, Gloria’s personal maid, and an array
               of other servants, all with separate and personal grievance and demands.</p>
            <p>While the great hall of the big house busses with the voices of the outraged
               chaperone and the complaining servants, Gloria suddenly appears at the head of the
               huge winding staircase. Lips curling, eyes blazing, she seems -- to the terrified
               servants -- <pb n="6"/>to literally leap down the stairs; and as she comes she hurls
               missiles, oranges and apples that she had carefully collected for the purpose -- at
               the hapless head of her fleeing victims. The bruised and frightened servants take
               refuge in the butler’s pantry, while the Major and Miss Farnsworth seek safety behind
               protecting articles of furniture; where-on Gloria, laughing in quiet scorn, well
               satisfied with her triumph, perches herself upon the arm of a big chair -- behind
               which, incidentally, the trembling Miss Farnsworth is hiding; and taking a silver
               cigarette case from the top of her stocking, Gloria coolly lights a gold tipped
               cigarette. From behind the barricade of a Louis Quinze sofa, the Major raises an
               almost apoplectic face and points a wrathful forefinger at Gloria:</p>

            <p><q>What you need, young woman</q>, he thunders sternly, <q>is a man to teach and
                     <emph>tame</emph>you!</q></p>

            <p>The gold tipped cigarette twists thoughtfully between Gloria’s full red lips as she
               considers this drastic statement; she draws a long breath, then exhales, <choice>
                  <sic>expells</sic>
                  <corr>expels</corr>
               </choice> a curling cloud of perfumed smoke, finally a devilish little smile suffuses
               her features, and her queer green eyes narrow sharply at the corners:</p>

            <p><q>Bring him on!</q> she invites ominously.</p>

            <p>That night, Major MacClellan takes the problem of Gloria to the wife of his
               bosom:</p>

            <p><q>What are we to do about it?</q> he asks impotently == and it is easy for Mrs.
               MacClellan to see that her husband has reached the end of his resources. <q>Here’s a
                  glorious young creatures simply going to smash and ruin from the lack of direction
                  and discipline. We can’t beat her, we can’t lock her up. Hang it all, we’ve got to
                  see the thing through; but unless we take some step to curb her, by <pb n="7"/>
                  hurling something something heavier than chocolate and apples -- someone’s likely
                  to be hurt, and there’ll be thunder to pay!</q> When Mrs. MacClellan manages to
               get a word in edgewise, she makes the obvious suggestion:</p>

            <p><q>Why not marry her off?</q></p>

            <p><q>Marry her?</q> exclaims the Major incredulously.</p>

            <p>Mrs. MacClellan is serene.</p>

            <p><q>What the child needs, is not so much discipline as -- affection</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Affection!</q> storms the Major, <q>Who in the world is going to love a young
                  wildcat like Gloria?</q></p>

            <p>The <choice>
                  <sic>anser</sic>
                  <corr>answer</corr>
               </choice> comes promptly:</p>

            <p><q>Her husband</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Husband! And who is going to be bamboozled into marrying her?</q> The Major’s wife
               debates the matter; then her face lights brilliantly; <q>I know just the man. He was
                  made for her. Jack Hemingway</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Jack ---</q> The Major scouts the idea. <q>Preposterous! the boy’s not thinking of
                  marrying</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Of course he’s not -- but we’ll think for him. Now, yu leave this to me</q>,
               orders the Major’s wife in a tone that the Major has learned to obey. And then,
                  <q>Waht is Jack doign now?</q></p>

            <p>The Major snorts:</p>

            <p><q>Thumping the piano in a cabaret orchestra. The young fool was in my office today.
                  He’s just inherited some worthless land way up in North western Canada -- insists
                  that radium can be mined there; and he’s trying to get the crazy scheme floated.
                  Radium -- of all things!</q></p>

            <pb n="8"/>

            <p>Mrs. MacClellan’s smile broadens:</p>

            <p><q>I’ve got it! Go to that cabaret, find Jack, and engage him to teach Gloria the
                  piano. Warn him that she’s a handful; and if I know Jack, that will be an
                  incentive rather than a detriment</q>.</p>

            <p>For a moment the Major demurs; but he finally tears himself from his hearthside and
               starts for the cabaret.</p>

            <p>John Paddington Hemmingway, better known as <q>Jack</q> recent star half back on the
               team, ahs <q>steamed</q> his way through college playing the piano for <q>frat</q>
               dances. Now a graduate engineer, Jack is determined to float his mining project. He
               has supreme confidence in the existence of Radium on his property -- an old Indian,
               named Black Hawk, ahving actually discovered a specimen of the precious substance
               there. By day, Jack hautns the business and social haunts of the mighty determiend to
               float his enterprise -- from the pages of his pocket dictionary he has carefully
               deleted the words <q>cannot</q> and <q>fail</q>.</p>

            <p>When the Major enters the cabaret, where Jack is pounding the ivories in the rhythm
               of a popular jazz tune, Jack is delighted to see his father’s old friend. Howeve,r he
               takes the proposition of eaching Gloria the piano, as a huge joke; but when the odler
               man mentions the unusually large sum he is willing to pay Jack for his services as a
               teacher of the piano forte, Jack is astounded -- and his natural query, is:</p>

            <p><q>Waht’s the idea, sir?</q></p>

            <p><q>The fact is</q>, explains the Major, <q>the girl has such a temper that we
                     <emph>have</emph> to pay high. No one has ever been able to handle her yet;
                  someone’s <emph>got</emph> to do it soon -- and if anyone <emph>can</emph>, you’re
                  the man</q>. JAck Hemmingway grins cheerfully, as he swings <pb n="9"/> around on
               the piano stool, just as the cabaret orchestra prepares to launch into <choice>
                  <sic>anew</sic>
                  <corr>a new</corr>
               </choice> dance number; <q>For the sum you mention, Governor, I’d take an aboriginal
                  savage</q>. The Major looks at Jack almost in pity as he remarks assuringly:</p>

            <p><q>You’re going to</q>.</p>

            <p>The next morning, promptly at ten o’clock, Jack Hemmingway, folio under arm, presents
               himself at the Glendon mansion to give Gloria her first lesson. JAck, in spite of his
               size, looks quite harmless and meek. He is arrayed for the occassion in a neat, black
               suit as befits a professor of the <choice>
                  <sic>pianoforte</sic>
                  <corr>piano forte</corr>
               </choice>, and his eyes are sheltered by smoke, bone rimmed glasses. At the front
               door JAck is met by Wilklins, the butler, who, learning Jack’s identity, immediately
               warns him of Gloria’s terrific temper, calling Dobbs with his injured eyes as Exhibit
               A; and finally intimidating taht because of the difficulty in keepign servants and
               teachers, the situation works into a pretty good thing -- financially, for anyone who
                  <q>has the ourage to put up with Miss Gloria’s attacks</q>. Ten dollars a month
               extra for a slap, twenty-five for a scratch -- as much as fifty for a black eye; and
               if a chap were really laid up as a result of Gloria’s temper, Wilkins wouldn’t be
               surprised if the Trust Company wouldn’t do something <q>real handsome</q> like a
               coupel of hudnred or so. A nice reception for a prospective music teacher -- Jack
               merely grins.</p>

            <p>In the music room, Gloria looks Jack over with evident disapproval -- within three
               minutes, she frankly demands to be told why a big husky brute of a man of Jack’s size
               shoudl be fiddling his time away teaching five finger exercises. It’s absurd! The
               next moment her mood changes -- she sits at the piano and meekly invites him to
               ---</p>

            <pb n="10"/>

            <p><q>Go ahead, let’s see what you can teach me</q>.</p>

            <p>Gravely, methodically, Jack begins the usual instruction. Gloria’s fingers dash over
               the keys in a lightning chromatic scale; then with a bang on her open palms come down
               upon the keyboard with a discordant thud. Swinging aroudn on the stool, she stares up
               impudently at <q>teacher</q>, demanding:</p>

            <p><q>Now, what are you going to do about it?</q></p>

            <p>Jack regards her gravely:</p>

            <p><q>That is the action fo a spoiled child</q>.</p>

            <p><q>O-o-oh, is it?</q> insquires Gloria aminously, <q>Well, how do you handle spoiled
                  children, when they don’t do waht they’re told?</q></p>

            <p><q>I generally shake them</q><choice>
                  <sic>.,</sic>
                  <corr>,</corr>
               </choice> Jack said quietly.</p>

            <p>Gloria’s head goes back, and she shakes with mocking laughter:</p>

            <p><q>Go ahead, shake me! I <emph>dare</emph> you to</q><choice>
                  <sic>.</sic>
                  <corr>,</corr>
               </choice> she cries delightedly.</p>

            <p>Looking at the beautiful, mocking, young creature, Jack feels the blood mounting to
               his face; and Gloria, watching him, is both delighted at his discomfiture and curious
               as to its outcome.</p>

            <p><q>Miss Glendon</q>, he begins sternly -- annoyance creeping aroudn the edges of his
               self control, <q>I am here to teach you, not to chastise you -----</q> and he adds
               grimly, <q>much as I’d like to</q>.</p>

            <p>Jack puts a sheet of music on the rack in front of Gloria and orders her to play a
               five finger exercise. Gloria pretends to begin, her eyes on the teacher, not the
               music; unexpectedy Jack finds himself disconcerted by Gloria’s bald scrutiny. The
               deliberate discords made by the saucy girl outrage JAack’s musical ear; and he cries
               out sharply:</p>

            <p><q>Hear! That’s all wrong! <choice>
                     <sic>Begain</sic>
                     <corr>Begin</corr>
                  </choice> again -- one -- two --</q></p>

            <pb n="11"/>

            <p>He gets no further. The pencil with which he has been beating time is snapped out of
               his fingers, the musci is swept off the rack and torn into bits; then Gloria, her
               eyes blazing faces him beliigerently:</p>

            <p><q>Who are you that yu dare to order me, one, two, three? Clear out! Clear out, I
                  say!</q> She screams.</p>

            <p>Gloria’s feet stamp in sheer rage, her hand shoots out and grasps a heavy silver
               candlestick. Raising the candlestick above her head, Gloria prepares to hurl it; but
               Jack is too quick for her, he seizes Gloria’s wrist, wrenches the canglestick from
               her hand, then -- <emph>he shakes her</emph>.</p>

            <p>Breathless, gasping in speechless rage, Gloria suddenly finds herself alone in the
               musci room. As if waking from a trance, she seizes several objects, rushes ot the
               window and hurls them after the departing young music teacher, who is now making
               angrily for the nearest bus.</p>

            <p>During the entire encounter between Jack and Gloria, Miss Farnsworth, Gloria’s
               companion, had been peeping through a crak in the door from the hall, now takes a
               hand. Scandalized by the vulgar spectacle of Gloria hurling both missiles and
               invectives from an open window into the Avenue, Miss Farnsworth rushes into the music
               room, shuts the window, berore the infuriated Glroia realizes waht is happenign -
               then she turns tail and runs like a frightened rabbit up the stairs twoard her room.
               But before she has covered the first flight, Gloria is up on her heels, promising
               reprisal, snatching at the tail of Miss Farnsworth’s prim black skirt; the terrified,
               companion barely manages to whisk into the sanctuary of her own room, locking the
               door, as Gloria reaches the landing outside. Safe, forthe moment, Miss Farnsworth
               goes to <pb n="12"/> the telephone, calls Major MacClellan at the Trust Company, and
               proceeds to give a hectic recital of Gloria’s latest outbreak. With her ear against
               the door panel, Gloria hears - and going to her own room, teakes down the extension
               phone and breaks tempestuously into the conversation. Hsi ears assailed by this mad
               jumble of female voices, the Major abruptly hangs up the receiver = just as Mrs.
               MacClellan, short of cash while on a shopping tour, breezes smilingly into his
               office.</p>

            <p><q>There you are</q>, announces the Major with a sweeping gesture. <q>Gloria has
                  thrown most of the bric-a-brac from the music room into the middle of Fifth Avenue
                  -- and JAck Hemmingway has <emph>quit</emph>, is to <emph>die</emph></q>.</p>

            <p>As though in answer to this assertion, we find Jack slighting from a green bus, not
               far from the main entrance of the Trust Company and just in front of Brentano’s old
               book store. He is still angry - and plainly perplexed. His attention had been to go
               at once to the Major and ask advice but this, on second thought, goes against the
               grain. He hesitates - thinks of Gloria, laughs a bit, amused in spite of himself, and
               more annoyed than ever because of this involuntary mirth, then he turns his eyes to
               the show window of the book store, where THE COMPELTE WORKS OF WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE
               bound in <choice>
                  <sic>vellu</sic>
                  <corr>vellum</corr>
               </choice>, are for sale. Next, his gaze narrows down to the slender volumes labeled,
                  <q>THE TAMING OF TEH SHREW</q> -----, the big inspiration comes to him, and
               purchasing the <pb n="13"/> small volume dealing with the matrimonial affairs of the
               termagent, Katherine, and the masterful Petrucio, he shoves it into his pocket,
               hurries across the street, and through the entrance of the Franklin Trust.</p>

            <p>Jack is ushered into the Major’s office, just as Mrs. MacClellan, her dainty purse
               amply filled, is preparing to take her departure. The Major Jack sternly:</p>

            <p><q>Well, young man, I understand that you’ve quit -- cold! The young savage must have
                  outdone herself</q>.</p>

            <p>Jack’s jaw drops in blank amazement.</p>

            <p><q>Quit -- Hell!</q> then conscious of Mrs. MacClellan’s presence, he blushes and
               stammers apology.</p>

            <p>Mrs. MacClellan smiles, pats Jack’s shoulder and looks triumphantly at the Major. The
               Major is convinced.</p>

            <p><q>Miss Farnsworth has just phoned that amid a storm of verbal abuse and flying <choice>
                     <sic>projectives</sic>
                     <corr>projectiles</corr>
                  </choice>, you <emph>left</emph>!</q></p>

            <p>Jack explodes:</p>

            <p><q>Left -- nothing!<choice>
                     <sic>’’</sic>
                     <corr/>
                  </choice> You don’t suppose I’d let the little shrew get away with anything like
                  that, do you? I shook her until her teeth rattled; and I told her I’d be back.
                  What she needs is to be tamed -- <q>broke</q> to harness; and I’m the little
                  General who can handle the job. You hired me to teach her music -- well, I’m going
                  to stick until I’ve taught her <emph>manners</emph></q>.</p>

            <p><q>Good boy! Hooray! <choice>
                     <sic>Brabo</sic>
                     <corr>Bravo</corr>
                  </choice>!</q> chortles the Major, <q>But how?</q> Jack grins, and pulls the
               volume of THE TAMING OF THE SHREW from his pocket:</p>

            <p><q>See this?</q></p>

            <pb n="14"/>

            <p><q>Yes</q>. The Colonel is caution.</p>

            <p><q>Read the title</q>. He holds the back of the book under the Major’s curious eye,
               as the Major reads. <q>That <choice>
                     <sic>Guy</sic>
                     <corr>guy</corr>
                  </choice> Petrucio had the world’s biggest idea</q>, continues Jack
               enthusiastically, <q>Tame ’em, that’s the stuff. Rough ’em around. Use a mean
                  shoulder, a granite jaw and an iron fist -- the wilder they are the better they
                  love it. Meet me half way, Governor, and I guarantee I’ll have that spicy little
                  Hell cat crawling around on all fours and eating out of my hand</q>.<note
                  type="editorial">Missing ending quotation mark in original.</note></p>

            <p>The Major is the most direct of men -- and the expression in Jack Hemmingway’s eye
               spells expensiveness -- the Major comes tersely to the core of the matter.</p>

            <p><q>How much will it cost - how are you going to do it - and where?</q></p>

            <pb n="15"/>

            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw>

            <p>Jack pulls himself up a chair, seats himself, and leans toward the Major, the epitome
               of concise determination.</p>

            <p><q>Now, by following this---</q></p>

            <p><q>This</q>, he begins, indicating the volume fo the <q>Taming of the Shrew</q>,
                  <q>It will cost something near a hundred thousand. And the scene of action will be
                  first a private car on the C.P.R. and then my <choice>
                     <sic>radium ;ands</sic>
                     <corr>radium; ends</corr>
                  </choice> in North Western Canada</q>.</p>

            <p>Displaying a remarkable lack of curiosity for one of her type and sex, Mrs.
               MacClellan quietly leaves the office -- smiling in keen satisfaction, and closing the
               door of Major MacClellan’s office, leaves the conspirators alone.</p>

            <p>Some weeks later, we find Gloria Glendon speeding through North Western Canada in a
               luxurious private car, accompanied by Miss Farnsworth en route -- supposedly -- to a
               summer vacation in Banff, Canada’s favorite playground. Gloria paces restlessly up
               and down the car, wondering why on earth her fool guardian has taken it into his head
               to send her on such a journey; while Miss Farnsworthy is absorbed in Coue. <q>If you
                  are to drive out fear etc</q>. Suddenly Gloria is concscious that the car is
               slackening speed. She looks out of the window-where a sweeping, panoramic view of the
               majectic Canadian Rockies meets her eye, just as the figure of a roughly dressed man
               on horseback flashes by near the tracks - something in the set of his shoulders seem
               familiar, and irrelevant as it may seem, Gloria thinks of the officioius young man
               who had come supposedly to teach her the piano, had remained only long enough to
               shake her soundly, and had never again returned. Gloria grits her teeth and grinds
               her little heels <pb n="16"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <choice>
                  <sic>Into</sic>
                  <corr>into</corr>
               </choice> the thick carpet on the floor --- the coward!! To take her by surprise that
               way, and then dispapear before she could collect her wits sufficiently to pay him
               back in his own coin.....Merciful Heavens, if she could only get her hands on him!
               Here <choice>
                  <sic>O-</sic>
                  <corr>--</corr>
               </choice> now; the thought was maddening!</p>

            <p>The speed fo the privat ecar grows less and less -- and finally ceases entirely. Miss
               Farnsworth looks inquiringly up from Coue-- and Gloria runs to the front of the
               private car bent upon inquiry -- this desolate spot is certainly not a normal
               stopping place. Reachign the door, Gloria gives an involuntary cry fo surprise and
               concern -- the rest of the train is speeding away and is just in the act of making a
               sharp turn around the mountainside -- disappearing rapidly from sight. Gloria
               realizes with stunning clarity, that her car has been uncoupled from the train and
               she and Miss Farnswroth are stranded -- alone -- in a mountainous wilderness.</p>

            <p>And in a <choice>
                  <sic>drawingroom</sic>
                  <corr>drawing room</corr>
               </choice> compartment in the disappearing train, Mrs. MacClellan and the Major,
               looking out of the window, return the salutation of the man on horseback, who --
               riding past the window of the private car -- has riveted Gloria’s attention. The man,
               a huge, bearded creature in the blue shirt, corduroy trousers, high boots, and broad
               brimmed sombrero, of the Canadian miner or pioneer, smiles brilliantly, showing an
               even row of strong white teeth; and taking a note from his pocket, shoves it through
               the window as he rides neck and neck with the speed of the train; then he pulls his
               horse up sharply, wheels and races back to the abandoned private car.</p>

            <pb n="17"/>

            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw>

            <p>The Major opens the <choice>
                  <sic>note,chuckling</sic>
                  <corr>note, chuckling</corr>
               </choice> as he does so. It reads:</p>

            <p>Come back in a month.....in the meantime the best of good things in Beautiful
               Banff</p>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">Petruchio.</fw>

            <p>From the front door of the private car, Gloria turns angrily to the inquiring Miss
               Farnsworth -- who is still holding the volume by Coue: <q>W-w-w-<choice>
                     <sic>wHat</sic>
                     <corr>what</corr>
                  </choice> ----</q> stammers the companion nervously.</p>

            <p><q>WHAT?</q> snaps Gloria, <q>That’s what I’d like to know -- the rest of the train
                  is speeding away a mile a minute -- and you and I are left behind in this plush
                  covered morgue -- a thousand miles from everything -----</q></p>

            <p>She gets no further, for just then a gutteral masculine voice interrupts her ------ </p>
            <p><q>Oh, no you’re not -- I’m here</q>.</p>

            <p>Gloria turns swiftly -- to perceive the most villainous looking man she has ever
               encountered in her whole life, standing in the doorway of the car -- it is, of
               course, the same man who tossed the note through the <choice>
                  <sic>drawingroom</sic>
                  <corr>drawing room</corr>
               </choice> window of the fast disappearing train -- and Gloria sees, with a shudder,
               that his beard is black and stiff -- at least three quarters of an inch long; that
               his belt is simply bristling with revolvers and knives, and that he carries a
               flexible riding whip in one sinewy hand. Miss Farnsworth, almost unable to believe
               the evidence of her senses, tears her eyes from the figure of the <q>bandit</q> as
               she believes the man to be, and rivets them upon the pages of Coue --- and as her
               knees shake and her lips blanch, she repeats doggedly:</p>

            <p><q>I am not afraid. I am not afraid. I am not afraid</q>. Then <pb n="18"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw> she quietly and quickly faints...pitching
               into an unconscious heap on the floor.</p>

            <p>At odds, always, personally, with Miss Farnswroth, Gloria is solidly with her against
               the enemy. With a cry of alarm she runs to the frail unconcscious figure on the
               floor, lifts her in her arms, then glares up at the intruder:</p>

            <p><q>You brute! You dirty, uncouth, frightful looking beast -- get out! Get out, I
                  say!</q> She screams, torn herself, between wrath and fright. <q>Look what you’ve
                  done!</q> The tears are very near the surface as Gloria fans Miss Farnsworth with
               her tiny pocket handkerchief. Roughly, the bandit pushes Gloria <choice>
                  <sic>aside,lifts</sic>
                  <corr>aside, lifts</corr>
               </choice> Miss Farnsworth back into the chair, and taking a flask from his pocket,
               forces brandy down her throat. Her eyelids flutter -- and seeing this, Gloria makes a
               dive for the car door, and escape -- anywhere, even into the unknown wilderness of
               the Canadian Rockies, in order to put herself out of this terrible looking Bandit’s
               reach. But she hasn’t a chance - an iron hand grasps her wrist, and the bandit smiles
               down upon Gloria with the keenest of satisfaction:</p>

            <p><q>Kick, bite, scratch, snarl scrath!</q> he invites as his smile broadens into a
               grin. <q>I like ’em full of fight -- the tougher they come, the better I’m
                  pleased</q>.</p>

            <p>Gloria gasps incredulously for a moment---and this hesitation is her undoing......the
               bandit grabs her hands, jerks them behind her back, pulls the colored handkerchief
               from his neck, and binds Gloria’s hands securely. She struggles -- but the bandit
               forces her, into a corner, face against the wall -- his shoulder braced against hers
               until the operation is complete; then he swings Gloria over his <pb n="19"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw> shoulder, and carries her from the car. On
               the far side of the train, a littel knot of Indians are waiting, each mounted upon a
               stubby pony -- and led by an aged man called Black Eagle. It is quite evident that
               the Indians are in the bandit’s employ; for, at his order, two of them enter the
               private car, and soon come out carrying Miss Farnsworth...who has retrived Coue, and
               is mumbling to herself dully:</p>

            <p><q>I am not afraid. I am not afriad. I am not afraid</q>.</p>

            <p>The bandit throws Gloria across the front of his saddle -- while the Indians place
               Miss Farnsworth on one of their ponies; and the cavalcade starts away, on a downward
               angle, toward a great canyon beyond the towering mountains; Miss Farnsworth seemingly
               resigns herself to fate -- but Gloria, now recovered from her first stranglign gasp
               of astonishment, kicks and spits and screams and bites like a veritable hellion.
               Holding Gloria firmly in his great left arm -- so that her hysterical struggles are
               absolutely impotent -- the bandit seems to be intesely enjoying the situation; and
               when Gloria, turns with the lightning quickness of a slim green snake to remark
               venemously:</p>

            <p><q>If I could kill you -- I should do so with infinite pleasure</q>.</p>

            <p>The bandit throws back his head and laughs uproariously.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="content">

            <p>In the dining car of the north bound express, en route to Banff, Mrs. MacClellan and
               the Major, sitting on opposite sides of a charmingly appointed table in the dining
               car, are still discussing <pb n="20"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw> the problem of Gloria. Mrs. MacClellan
               consults the daintieset of platinum wrist watches:</p>

            <p><q>Seven o’clock</q>, she remarks speculatively; <q>I wonder where Gloria is eating
                  her dinner!</q></p>

            <p><q>Unless she’s cooked it herself, she isn’t eating at all</q>, assures the Major
               with a keenness of relish that causes Mr. MacClellan the initial instigator of the
               accummulative plot for the taming of Gloria - to squirm uncomfortably. Mrs.
               MacClellan stops eating abruptly, pushes her soup away with sudden aversion, and
               raises slightly uneasy brows.</p>

            <p>And while the <choice>
                  <sic>McClallans</sic>
                  <corr>MacClellans</corr>
               </choice> are speculating as to her condition, Gloria finds herself <choice>
                  <sic>heaching</sic>
                  <corr>reaching</corr>
               </choice> the bottom of the steep incline, still held firmly in the bandit’s arms --
               now they are riding through a narrow pass; then into a blind canyon with endless
               sides of sheer steep rock, so smooth that there is not even a foothold for one who
               might have the courage to scale its walls. suddenly, the bandit loosens his hold; and
               quick as lightning, Gloria is out of his grasp onto the ground. Without looking back
               she runs desperately forward -- searchign for a means of escape; but the sole egress
               from the canyon is the narrow pass throughwhich they have just come -- and this
               remains tenaciously guarded by the smiling bandit, still astride his quivering,
               pawing mount. The bandit makes no attempt to follow Gloria -- merely rolling a
               cigarette with a maddening precision and ease, as though to say: <q>run yourself
                  ragged, you little fool, batter your head against the rocky walls, scream yourself
                  hoarse --- and when you’re through, we’ll talk business</q>. Obligingly, Gloria
               does all of these things; then, her <pb n="21"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw> hands still tied behind her back -- she
               walks slowly, unwillingly forward and faces her captor: </p>

            <p><q>Who are you?</q> she demands with a dangerous calm that simply screams a surging
               tempest within -- and as she looks at the man her eyes are narrowed until the long
               black lashes seem a sharp wire screen.</p>

            <p><q>Who am I?</q> -- and the bandit smiles, bows and introduces himself elaborately;
                  <q>Have you never heard of Mister Petruchio -- at your service, my lady. Just
                  outside the canyon is my camp -- where your estimable companion is now being fed a
                  delicious supper of fruit, coffee, pancakes and bacon. If you like, we shall join
                  her -- on condition, that after you’ve eaten you shall wash the dishes</q>.</p>

            <p>Dishes! Gloria is speechless -- she has heard of the process, but never in her entire
               life has she actually seen it done. From his pocket, the bandit takes a bar of
               chocolate, breaks off a piece and proceeds to eat it with great relish -- entirely
               ignoring Gloria as he does so. Gloria has not eaten since breakfast -- she is hungry,
               damnably hungry. Going closer to the bandit she touches his boot, attracting his
               attention: <q>All right</q>, she agrees, <q>I’ll wash them -- if you’ll show me
                  how</q>. The bandit dismounts, takes a <choice>
                  <sic>villianous</sic>
                  <corr>villainous</corr>
               </choice> looking knife from his belt -- and sharpens it against the rocky wall of
               the canyon, while Gloria watches, fascinated - is she to be killed -- or possibly
               marked with the knife as a rancher uses a branding iron. As the bandit turns toward
               her again, with the knife in his hand, she shrinks from him -- the bandits grasps her
               shoulder, turns her about by force; then he merely cuts through the <pb n="22"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw> handkerchief binding Gloria’s slender
               hands. </p>

            <p><q>Walk!</q> commands the bandit -- pointing toward the path that leads through the
               pass and out of the canyon. After a moment’s hesitation, Gloria <choice>
                  <sic>obeys;the</sic>
                  <corr>obeys; the</corr>
               </choice> bandit follows, leading his horse.</p>
            <milestone unit="section"/>
            <p>Half an hour later, Gloria, Miss Farnsworth and the bandit are sitting around a rough
               table, on which are tin <choice>
                  <sic>dishes,rough</sic>
                  <corr>dishes, rough</corr>
               </choice> knives, forks and spoons, tin cups and the remains of a supper. Miss
               Farnsworth, who has hardly touched her food, watches the bandit with wide, terrified
               eyes -- <choice>
                  <sic>everytime</sic>
                  <corr>every time</corr>
               </choice> he speaks to her she jumps like a frightened <choice>
                  <sic>rabbit,holds</sic>
                  <corr>rabbit, holds</corr>
               </choice> up her hands as though to shield herself from a blow, and stammers an
               inarticulate reply. Gloria, well fed, buoyed up by the confidence of youth and the
               fact that she is still <choice>
                  <sic>unharmed.</sic>
                  <corr>unharmed</corr>
               </choice> is regaining her usual arrogance -- she examines the bandit with open
               contempt, her mouth drawn sharply down at the corners. The bandit wipes his mouth on
               his sleeve, rises from his chair, whistles sharply -- and immediately, two of his
               Indians enter and stand waiting orders. Pointing to Miss Farnsworth the bandit orders
               the Indians to take her to her room, to see that she has everything needed to make
               her comfortable for the night; and then to lock her into the compartment --
               stationing a guard outside of the window. Miss Farnsworth, fortified by emergency,
               finds the courage to speak authoratively. With much of her usual dignity she says
               firmly:</p>

            <p><q>Come, Gloria!</q></p>

            <p>Gloria starts forward -- but the bandit stops her.</p>

            <p><q>The dishes</q>, he reminds her tersely, <q>And after they are washed, I want to
                  talk to you</q>.</p>

            <pb n="23"/>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw>

            <p><q>Dishes!</q> Gloria laughs <choice>
                  <sic>scornfully;</sic>
                  <corr>scornfully; </corr>
               </choice><q>do you think I’d wash those filthy things after an animal like you had
                  eaten from them?</q> The bandit is dangerously quiet:</p>

            <p><q>You gave me your word -- evidently your sense of honor is as faulty as your
                  manners are bad</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Manners -- what do you know about your manners? Who are you, anyway -- and why
                  have you kidnapped us and brought us to this God- <choice>
                     <sic>firsaken</sic>
                     <corr>forsaken</corr>
                  </choice> hole?</q></p>

            <p>The bandit merely points commandingly to the soiled dishes and orders:</p>

            <p><q>Pile them up, carry them into the kitchen -- and if you really don’t know how,
                  I’ll teach you to wash them</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I won’t!</q> defied Gloria, stamping her foot.</p>

            <p><q>Pick them up!</q></p>

            <p><q><emph>NO!</emph></q><note type="editorial">Ending quotation mark missing in
                  original.</note> flames Gloria</p>


            <p>The bandit’s voice drops almsot to a whisper -- and his hand reaches out to grasp the
               handle of his riding whip, where he has hung it against the wall.</p>

            <p><q>Pick them up!</q></p>

            <p>Now the riding whip is direclty in evidence, and there is no doubt as to its imminent
               use -- Gloria’s eyes, usually narrowed when angry, now dilate with fear; but she
               squares her shoulders and stands her ground.</p>


            <p><q>I - won’t - do - it!</q> she repeats in a choking monotone == then she closes her
               eyes and waits for the blow.</p>


            <p>The bandit looking at this beautiful, wholly game, and really helpless girl, lifts
               the whip to strike -- then throws it into a corner. Reaching into his pocket he takes
               out a leather-bound <pb n="24"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">KM</fw> book, opens it and looks earnestly at an
               engraving illustrating the contents - it is a picture of Petruchio, carrying
               Katherine - the shrew, away on his shoulders at theend of the spectacular wwedding.
               The book hurtles into the corner after the whip. Gloria opens her eyes and asks
               breathlessly: </p>

            <pb n="25"/>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw>

            <p><q>If you’re going to use that whip--why don’t you?</q></p>

            <p>The bandit’s answer is to pick Gloria up in his arms, carry her into the
               kitchen--after which he performs the same service for the dinner table, soiled dishes
               and all.</p>

            <p><q>When you’ve washed them all, I’ll let you out</q>, he informs Gloria triumphantly.
               Then he locks the door--stationing a guard outside of the kitchen window, exactly as
               he has done in the case of Miss Farnsworth. Gloria finds herself in the smallest and
               most unkempt room she has ever seen in her <choice>
                  <sic>temptestuous</sic>
                  <corr>tempestuous</corr>
               </choice> young life. The closing of the door has entirely shut out the light. She
               runs to the window--squatting directly in front of it sits a huge impassive Indian.
               Then unaccountably, Gloria is stricken by a consuming fear--an unreasoning,
               unexplainable need for light, companionship--any companionship, even that of the
               great bearded bandit who has kidnapped her, bullied her, and locked her into this
               stifling room. Gloria covers her mouth with both hands, in a futile effort to stifle
               a scream that she knows she must utter--then blindly she runs to the locked door,
               pounds upon it with her white fists until the skin upon them is cut by the rough
               unplaned boards; and at the same time she calls hysterically: <q>Mr Petruchio! Mr
                  Petruchio! Mr Petruchio, please! I’ll wash them if I can, Mr Petruchio--only
                  truly, I don’t know how! I don’t--know--how!</q></p>

            <p>The door opens immediately, the bandit enters with a bright round wicked lantern. He
               smiles in the most friendly of fashions. Going to the sink he places the dishpan
               under the <choice>
                  <sic>fawset</sic>
                  <corr>faucet</corr>
               </choice>, takes a <pb n="26"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw>
               <choice>
                  <sic>dishmop</sic>
                  <corr>dish mop</corr>
               </choice> from a convenient nail and turnign to Gloria with a Chester fieldian bow,
               he suggests gallantly. </p>

            <p><q>Let us proceed</q>.</p>

            <p>Gloria’s eyes hold the bandit’s for a moment--then, her cheeks still wet with tears,
               she finds herself smiling--a smile of half-sheepish admiration--this is the first
               human being who has ever really been able to force her to do something entirely
               against her will. Gingerly, Gloria picks <choice>
                  <sic>up<emph>o</emph>ne</sic>
                  <corr>up one</corr>
               </choice> of the soiled tin plates, gravely she walks to the dishpan; and as the
               bandit begins to demonstrate the gentle art of dishwashing, Gloria’s mind is not on
               the mechanics of this homely art--it is entirely engrossed by an intensive
               examination--and strangely enough, by a lively interest in her remarkable teacher.
               Such shoulders--huge, flexible, yes, handsome shoulders. And what a likeable
               smile--one might almost admire the creature if--if--well, if he were anything but a
               bandit.</p>

            <p><q>Hold the plate in your left hand and swab it off with the mop; then put it under
                  the <choice>
                     <sic>fawset</sic>
                     <corr>faucet</corr>
                  </choice> and rinse off the suds</q>. The bandit’s voice brings Gloria back from
               abstraction on speculation--the next minute she is scrubbing a tin plate with an
               exceedingly efficacious cotton string mop.</p>

            <p>But while Gloria has seemingly capitulated, Miss Farnsworth certainly has not. Once
               Gloria has been taken to the room reserved for her use, the bandit--leaving only a
               guard before the open windows of the rooms occupied by the two women, starts across a
               flat <pb n="27"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw> stony clearing to a place where a deep
               shaft in the ground and a mass of machinery suggests mining operations of an
               extensive sort. The door of a small building opens, and the aged Indian, Black Eagle,
               calls the bandit who passes into the structure, closing the door behind him, leaving,
               uninterrupted the abysmal darkness of the night.</p>

            <p>Once inside, Black Eagle actually beams with excitement--a most unheard of procedure
               for an Indian, and going to a portable safe begins to manipulate the combination. As
               he does so he says jerkily, his utterance handicapped by excitement: </p>

            <p><q>While you go way to New York, we find him, much radium--you tak ’em back, show big
                  bank, they spend much money find more radium. Little Jack Hemmingway--big man now,
                  grow very big rich--Black Eagle much glad</q>.</p>

            <p>And in her room, Miss Farnsworth, working <choice>
                  <sic>dilligently</sic>
                  <corr>diligently</corr>
               </choice> with a hairpin, has managed to pick the very simple lock on her bedroom
               door. Once in the main room of the shack, she finds a revolver, hanging in a holster,
               gets possession of the weapon--and with the gun held nervously before her, peers out
               of the window--a hundred yards away, she sees a bright light shining from a small
               square window--and with visions of a bandit crew engaged in drunken debauchery over a
               bottle of whiskey and a game of cards--she creeps to Gloria’s door and calls
               hoarsely:</p>

            <p><q>Gloria, dear--it is I--Miss Farnsworth. I--I--I’ve got a gun</q>.</p>

            <p>Gloria is immediately alert.</p>

            <pb n="28"/>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw>

            <p><q>What are you going to do with it?</q> asks Gloria from her side of the
                  barrier--<q>And how did you get out?</q></p>

            <p><q>Picked the lock--</q> elucidates Miss Farnsworth--<q>hairpin. Stay where you
                  are--you can’t do anything--yours is short</q>.</p>

            <p>With no more explanation Miss Farnsworth opens the outside door, and with the gun
               still held before her, starts toward the lighted window across the clearing.</p>

            <p>Inside the shack, Black Eagle extinguishes the lamp, then he takes the cloth wrapping
               from a slender glass tube--a brilliant green-white light floods the room, almost
               blinding Jack with its unexpected intensity; then he whoops jubilantly:</p>

            <p><q>Radium--very big much--we find while you go New York</q>, grunts Black Eagle.</p>

            <p><q>Great guns, man--there’s a fortune right there in that tube</q>, exclaims Jack,
               almost unable to believe his good fortune. <q>We’re rich, Eagle--rich, do you
                  hear!</q></p>

            <p>Outside, looking through the window, Miss Farnsworth, the gun still in her hand--and
               shaking violently, sees a clear target in the bandit whom she is seeking--for his
               face is illuminated with uncanny clarity by the radium in the slender tube. Back in
               the main shack, Gloria, after Miss Farnsworth ceased speaking, scoured her brain for
               a means of getting out of her mom. The door resisted her effort to force it open.
               Finally Gloria confined her attention to the squatting Indie stationed outside her
               window--habit immediately <pb n="29"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw> asserting itself, she grabbed the
               nearest missile--which happened to be a heavy china water pitcher, and with the
               perfect accuracy born of long practice, hurled it at the head of the Indian with such
               fore that he rolled over, quite unconscious for several minutes. In this fortunate
               interim, Gloria managed to climb out of the window--and seeing the slim figure of
               Miss Farnsworth, hurrying across the clearing--she followed.</p>

            <p>When Gloria reaches Miss Farnsworth’s side, Miss Farnsworth is at the
               window--watching the bandit as he looks at the brilliant greenish-white tube in Black
               Eagle’s hand. Miss Farnsworth is so engrossed that she has not been aware of Gloria’s
               approach--she still holds the gun in front of her, her hand on the trigger; when
               Gloria speaks, Miss Farnsworth is so terrified that her finger involuntarily pulls
               the trigger. There is a crash of glass as the windowpane shatters, a man’s cry of
               hurt and surprise--then utter blackness. Black Eagle, wary in time of attack, has
               wrapped his blanket about the tube of radium.</p>

            <p>Miss Farnsworth’s first idea, after the shooting, is to find horses and make an
               escape; but Gloria, unable to analyze her own feelings, refuses to move. Something
               strange, stifling, grips her throat; then her brain clears and she is conscious of
               just one driving thought. Suppose <emph>he</emph> had been killed. Xes, this uncouth,
               unshaven barbarian--the thought is too terrible even to contemplate. Shaking off Miss
               Farnsworth’s detaining hand, Gloria makes her way into the tiny building before her,
               calling as she does so: </p>

            <pb n="30"/>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw>

            <p><q>Mr. Petruchio--Mr. Petruchio, are you hurt, Mr. Petruchio?</q></p>

            <p>While Miss Farnsworth, her burst of courage completely in collapse, runs around in
               circles mumbling alternately:</p>

            <p><q>What have I done! What have I done!</q> And again, <q>I am not afraid--I am
                  not--yes, yes, I am--I am afraid, I’m terrified</q>. Then she sinks into a little
               shivering heap, burying her face in her hands.</p>

            <p>In the shack, Black Eagle rekindles the light and Gloria finds the bandit lying on
               the floor--an ugly splotch of blood on his forehead, where Miss Farnsworth’s bullet
               has born across his smooth bronzed skin. Staggering to his feet he laughs in grim
               amusement:</p>

            <p><q>So you tried to shoot me? You told mo, I remember, that you could do so with the
                  greatest of pleasure</q>.</p>

            <p>Gloria’s protest has an accent of horror:</p>

            <p><q>I didn’t, Mr. Petruchio--really, I didn’t--I----</q> Then suddenly Gloria throws
               pretense to the winds. She smiles.</p>


            <p><q>Who are you--and why--why don’t you shave?</q></p>

            <p>For a moment, the bandit considers--then he reaches up to a shelf, finds a pair of
               scissors, and looking into a bit of cracked mirror nailed against the wall, clips
               industriously. Gloria watches this operation with breathless interest, as, little by
               little, the bandit disappears, and in his place emerges a face strangely
               familiar--suddenly it dawns upon her with flashing clarity--the music teacher; and
               she had thought him a coward--afraid to come back, beaten, vanquished by a girl and a
               silver candlestick. Yet--again, this familiar <pb n="31"/>
               <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
               <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw> figure seems less formidable--less awe
               inspiring. Courage returning, Gloria’s eyes narrow--her temper surges, flashes:</p>

            <p><q>What do you mean</q>, she begins shrilly, <q>taking me out of my own private car,
                  bringing me to this frightful place--actually forcing me to wash---</q></p>

            <p>She gets no further, for the erstwhile bandit swings about on his heel; and as he
               faces her, his expression alone is enough to shock Gloria into abrupt silence.</p>

            <p><q>That will be enough from you</q>, he snaps tersely. Then pointing to a tin basin
               on the wall, he continues, <q>take that basin and fill it with water--there’s a punp
                  outside. You’ve asked me to shave and I’m going to accommodate you</q>. Gloria
               gasps--starts to speak--think better of it--then reaches for the basin.</p>

         </div>

         <div type="section">
            <p>Two days later in Banff, Major and Mrs. MacClellan receive the following
               telegram:</p>

            <p>BOTH GLORIA AND RADIUM 100 PERCENT. I’VE SHAVED.</p>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">JACK.</fw>

            <p>For a wedding present to herself, Gloria has Jack’s copy of The Taming of the Shrew
               rebound in the most expensive of tulled leather--and out under the moonlight while
               honeymooning at Banff, she shows the volume to her brand new husband. Pointing up
               toward the glowing grandeur of the harvest moon, Jack Hemmingway turns to Gloria
               Glendon Hemmingway and says sternly:</p>

            <p><q>Look--it is the sun</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Yes, dear</q>, smiles Gloria docilely, <q>it is the sun</q>.</p>

            <pb n="32"/>
            <fw type="continued" place="right">A SAVAGE IN SILKS</fw>
            <fw type="continued" place="left">(GHR)</fw>

            <p><q>What!</q> storms Jack in the most approved Petrucian manner, <q>say you the sun?
                  By the beard of my Grandfather, woman, ’tis the moon!</q></p>

            <p>Then they both laugh in sheer delight; and as Gloria lifts her delicious lips to be
               kissed, she whispers softly:</p>

            <p><q>God bless Mr. <choice><sic>Shakespere</sic><corr>Shakespeare</corr></choice></q>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
