<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Sinners1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sinners</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:124"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-07">Begin transcribing</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2020-05-29">Directed to bibl 124 instead of 123</change><change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2019-08-29">Directed to facs</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl123 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Sinners">
      <pb n="13"/>
      <body>
         <head>Sinners</head>
         <opener>
            <note>The story of a Salvation Army Motherhood.</note>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>
            <byline>Illustrated by L. A. C. Panton</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>Hetty’s baby was born in the Salvation Army Rescue Home of Calgary, Alberta. Dire
               necessity had driven the girl to this last resort, of what she termed <q>lost
                  souls</q>, but when the first days of agony and humiliation had passed, Hetty
               still lay with her face turned stonily to the wall. She kept up this ostentatious
               pose of defiance and scorn for a longer period than most girls of her type, for she
               prided herself upon being <q>above the common girls who go wrong</q>. She, so Hetty
               believed was merely an accident and it was one of the ironies of fate that found her
               here with this despised human driftwood of a Salvation Army Rescue Home. The sights
               and sounds, the rows of beds, the sobbing or shameless girls, coming and going, the
               uncontrolled loudly expressed grief of the miserable mothers who gave up their babies
               for adoption, filled Hetty with aversion. She said to herself that only uncivilized
               and low people abandoned themselves to noisy grief. It was like <q>washing one’s
                  dirty linen in public</q>. She was an English girl, proud of her ability to
               demonstrate reserve even in misery and shame. There was nothing primitive in her.</p>
            <p>And so, with hard eyes staring at the bleak wall, and back turned to other inmates of
               the ward, Hetty sought to work out her poor little philosophy of pride. She believed
               she was immune from such weaknesses as tears. She had seen soldiers grit their teeth
               and bear the bitterest pain. She too, had been a soldier, and she would take her
               punishment <q>like a man</q>.</p>
            <p>But the baby had upset all of her calculations. She had expected to hate it and indeed her first act upon entering the home was to register upon the records that her child would be free for adoption. Now its warm, helpless little body filled her with a wild clamor of foreign <choice>
               <sic>impluses</sic>
            <corr>impulses</corr>
            </choice> and demands provocative of such passionate tears that she bit her lips till they bled and hid her face in the pillow to fight back the stifling sobs that sought for an outlet. </p>
            
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>Before the world—the world as contributed by the nurses and Salvation officers and
               the many young mothers in the ward with her, Hetty still kept up a bold <q>face</q>,
               but when the nurse, a smiling young Salvation Army lieutenant would bring her baby to
               be nursed Hetty, as soon as the woman’s back was turned would drop her pose of
               indifference and slip her arm under the little body and draw her baby close to her
               breast, resting her cheek against the dear, soft, tiny head. When no one was looking,
               she rose upon her elbow, eagerly to study the tiny face, and it seemed to her that
               her baby was the prettiest, the sweetest and the cleverest in the world. Every little
               twitch of its face she imagined to be a smile, and a cry or murmur wrung her heart
               and caused it strange agitation.</p>
            <p>There were girls in that Salvation home from all classes of society. A few indeed
               were from the very lowest strata—street waifs, tarnished outcasts from life’s deep
               gutter, brazen or maudlin according to their natures. There were shop girls and
               factory girls, and girls from the stage; there were girls from respectable homes and
               one tragically young child from a High School. A sad, sad flock of sinners, indeed,
               these young creatures who had passed through the agony of child bearing, but were
               denied the compensating comfort of love and home and a mate to share with them the
               pride and joy of parenthood. Yet trouble sits but lightly on young hearts. These
               girls had their little jokes and even celebrations, and there was something
               approaching real fun and joy in showing and comparing and exclaiming over each
               others’ babies. Merry young laughter rang out through the room when the nick-names
               applied by them to the babies struck their fancy or sense of humor. One of the girls
               had started the habit of nicknaming the babies—<q>Salvation names</q>, and it was
               considered great sport to name a baby according to some characteristic peculiar to
               him. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>Thus <q>Prince</q> was named because of his royal bearing and the lordliness of his
               demanding cry. He was the child of the half breed Indian girl, who had drifted down
               from the Sarcee Reserve to the gay city of Calgary. Proud of her white blood, she had
               sought kinship among her father’s people. Now she was to return to the Reserve with
               this tiny hostage as an emblem of her hunt. Her cheeks were sunk in, her chest had
               narrowed; she coughed incessantly. She was suspected of <q>T.B</q>. that sickness
               once peculiar to the white race and which brings death to the Indian when it touches
               him. Little proud Ivy, as was her name, was going back to her mother’s people to end
               her days. She had that far, far away longing look of one who see across the horizon
               and sense a glimpse of that other land to which sooner or later we are all destined
               to drift. </p>
            <p><q>Flirt</q> was the name applied to the wandering eyed laughing baby of a street
               waif, who calmly proclaimed her ignorance as to who was the father of her child.</p>
            <p><q>Bubbles</q> was the child of the swollen eyed girl, whose tears had never ceased
               to flow since the day she entered the Refuge. Growing, kicking and bubbling, little
               cared happy Bubbles for the tragedy of his life. </p>
            <p><q>Squalls</q> was destined to find a home in a millionaire’s mansion, and himself to
               become a leader of men. He was the child of a still-faced young person, who made no
               secret of her indifference to her child, and awaited with evident impatience the time
               when she might set out again into the world freed of the unwelcome encumbrance. </p>
            <p>There was the <q>Brat</q>, the <q>Cop</q>, <q>Bawls</q>
               <q>Dr. Pills</q>, <q>Chinky</q>, <q>Blacky</q> and other appropriate and often
               ingenious names, but of all the babies in the Refuge, she who came to occupy the very
               center of that sad stage and queened it over all was little <q>Bootie</q>, baby
               language for <q>Beauty</q>, the child of Hetty. From the top of her head, already
               like her mother’s a mass of shining ringlets, her bright blue eyes, and sweet cooing
               mouth and rosy cheeks down to her tiny perfect feet. Hetty’s baby was a morsel of
               loveliness and charm. She was the pride of the Refuge, and indeed there was something
               pathetic in the pride of those girls in the beauty of his baby born in a Salvation
               Army Rescue Home. <q>Bootie’s</q> career in the home had been one of conquest, even
               the smartly stepping Captain Boyce, who had met Hetty’s assumed defiance by quietly
               ignoring her, capitulated before the smiling blue eyes of Hetty’s baby. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section"> 
            <p><choice>
               <sic>Captian</sic>
               <corr>Captain</corr>
            </choice> Boyce was in charge of the Refuge. Under her sheltering wing and into her capable hands came all of these poor broken pieces of human flotsam and jetsam that were cast up from the sick sea of passion and love. She would have preferred to be likened to a shepherd who gathers <choice>
               <sic>iu</sic>
               <corr>in</corr>
           </choice> her ninety and nine lost lambs, but indeed one could not but think of her as some divine Beach Comber, bent on saving and sorting out the poor human wreckage that had been beaten upon the rocks of life. She was a big, bonny Scotch woman, or rather girl, for she was but twenty-eight years old. A trained nurse by profession, after her conversion, she had gone into the army, and her full time and services were devoted gratis, to the cause of caring for the eayward girls of the Home. But her activities did not cease here, for Captain Boyce followed the career, and indeed endeavored to act as a sort of guiding <pb n="15"/> </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
