<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Sinners1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sinners [Part One]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile at Royal Ontario Museum</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:124"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-08-05">added illustrator</change><change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-08-04">proofread</change><change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-08-02">added illustrator</change><change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-07-31">Added instalment number</change><change who="pers:MC1" status="published" when="2020-07-01">Added note about source</change>
         <change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-07">Added transcription</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2020-05-29">Directed to bibl 124 instead of 123</change><change who="pers:MC1" status="empty"  when="2019-08-29">Directed to facs</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl123 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Sinners">
      <pb n="13"/>
      <body>
         <head>Sinners</head>         
         <head>The story of a Salvation Army Motherhood.</head>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>
         <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:LP1">L. A. C. Panton</name></byline>
         
         <div>
            <p>Hetty’s baby was born in the Salvation Army Rescue Home of Calgary, Alberta. Dire necessity had driven the girl to this last resort, of what she termed <q>lost souls</q>, but when the first days of agony and humiliation had passed, Hetty still lay with her face turned stonily to the wall. She kept up this ostentatious pose of defiance and scorn for a longer period than most girls of her type, for she prided herself upon being <q>above the common girls who go wrong</q>. She, so Hetty believed was merely an accident and it was one of the ironies of fate that found her here with this despised human driftwood of a Salvation Army Rescue Home. The sights
and sounds, the rows of beds, the sobbing or shameless girls, coming and going, the uncontrolled loudly expressed grief of the miserable mothers who gave up their babies for adoption, filled Hetty with aversion. She said to herself that only uncivilized and low people abandoned themselves to noisy grief. It was like <q>washing one’s dirty linen in public</q>. She was an English girl, proud of her ability to demonstrate reserve even in misery and shame. There was nothing primitive in her.</p>
          <p>And so, with hard eyes staring at the bleak wall, and back turned to other inmates of
the ward, Hetty sought to work out her poor little philosophy of pride. She believed she was immune from such weaknesses as tears. She had seen soldiers grit their teeth and bear the bitterest pain. She too, had been a soldier, and she would take her
               punishment <q>like a man</q>.</p>
            <p>But the baby had upset all of her calculations. She had expected to hate it and indeed her first act upon entering the home was to register upon the records that her child would be free for adoption. Now its warm, helpless little body filled her with a wild clamor of foreign <choice>
               <sic>impluses</sic>
            <corr>impulses</corr>
            </choice> and demands provocative of such passionate tears that she bit her lips till they bled and hid her face in the pillow to fight back the stifling sobs that sought for an outlet. </p>
            
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>Before the world—the world as contributed by the nurses and Salvation officers and
               the many young mothers in the ward with her, Hetty still kept up a bold <q>face</q>,
               but when the nurse, a smiling young Salvation Army lieutenant would bring her baby to
               be nursed Hetty, as soon as the woman’s back was turned would drop her pose of
               indifference and slip her arm under the little body and draw her baby close to her
               breast, resting her cheek against the dear, soft, tiny head. When no one was looking,
               she rose upon her elbow, eagerly to study the tiny face, and it seemed to her that
               her baby was the prettiest, the sweetest and the cleverest in the world. Every little
               twitch of its face she imagined to be a smile, and a cry or murmur wrung her heart
               and caused it strange agitation.</p>
            <p>There were girls in that Salvation home from all classes of society. A few indeed
               were from the very lowest strata—street waifs, tarnished outcasts from life’s deep
               gutter, brazen or maudlin according to their natures. There were shop girls and
               factory girls, and girls from the stage; there were girls from respectable homes and
               one tragically young child from a High School. A sad, sad flock of sinners, indeed,
               these young creatures who had passed through the agony of child bearing, but were
               denied the compensating comfort of love and home and a mate to share with them the
               pride and joy of parenthood. Yet trouble sits but lightly on young hearts. These
               girls had their little jokes and even celebrations, and there was something
               approaching real fun and joy in showing and comparing and exclaiming over each
               others’ babies. Merry young laughter rang out through the room when the nick-names
               applied by them to the babies struck their fancy or sense of humor. One of the girls
               had started the habit of nicknaming the babies—<q>Salvation names</q>, and it was
               considered great sport to name a baby according to some characteristic peculiar to
               him. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>Thus <q>Prince</q> was named because of his royal bearing and the lordliness of his
               demanding cry. He was the child of the half breed Indian girl, who had drifted down
               from the Sarcee Reserve to the gay city of Calgary. Proud of her white blood, she had
               sought kinship among her father’s people. Now she was to return to the Reserve with
               this tiny hostage as an emblem of her hunt. Her cheeks were sunk in, her chest had
               narrowed; she coughed incessantly. She was suspected of <q>T.B</q>. that sickness
               once peculiar to the white race and which brings death to the Indian when it touches
               him. Little proud Ivy, as was her name, was going back to her mother’s people to end
               her days. She had that far, far away longing look of one who see across the horizon
               and sense a glimpse of that other land to which sooner or later we are all destined
               to drift. </p>
            <p><q>Flirt</q> was the name applied to the wandering eyed laughing baby of a street
               waif, who calmly proclaimed her ignorance as to who was the father of her child.</p>
            <p><q>Bubbles</q> was the child of the swollen eyed girl, whose tears had never ceased
               to flow since the day she entered the Refuge. Growing, kicking and bubbling, little
               cared happy Bubbles for the tragedy of his life. </p>
            <p><q>Squalls</q> was destined to find a home in a millionaire’s mansion, and himself to
               become a leader of men. He was the child of a still-faced young person, who made no
               secret of her indifference to her child, and awaited with evident impatience the time
               when she might set out again into the world freed of the unwelcome encumbrance. </p>
            <p>There was the <q>Brat</q>, the <q>Cop</q>, <q>Bawls</q>
               <q>Dr. Pills</q>, <q>Chinky</q>, <q>Blacky</q> and other appropriate and often
               ingenious names, but of all the babies in the Refuge, she who came to occupy the very
               center of that sad stage and queened it over all was little <q>Bootie</q>, baby
               language for <q>Beauty</q>, the child of Hetty. From the top of her head, already
               like her mother’s a mass of shining ringlets, her bright blue eyes, and sweet cooing
               mouth and rosy cheeks down to her tiny perfect feet. Hetty’s baby was a morsel of
               loveliness and charm. She was the pride of the Refuge, and indeed there was something
               pathetic in the pride of those girls in the beauty of this baby born in a Salvation
               Army Rescue Home. <q>Bootie’s</q> career in the home had been one of conquest, even
               the smartly stepping Captain Boyce, who had met Hetty’s assumed defiance by quietly
               ignoring her, capitulated before the smiling blue eyes of Hetty’s baby. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section"> 
            <p><choice>
                  <sic>Captian</sic>
                  <corr>Captain</corr>
               </choice> Boyce was in charge of the Refuge. Under her sheltering wing and into her
               capable hands came all of these poor broken pieces of human flotsam and jetsam that
               were cast up from the sick sea of passion and love. She would have preferred to be
               likened to a shepherd who gathers <choice>
                  <sic>iu</sic>
                  <corr>in</corr>
               </choice> her ninety and nine lost lambs, but indeed one could not but think of her
               as some divine Beach Comber, bent on saving and sorting out the poor human wreckage
               that had been beaten upon the rocks of life. She was a big, bonny Scotch woman, or
               rather girl, for she was but twenty-eight years old. A trained nurse by profession,
               after her conversion, she had gone into the army, and her full time and services were
               devoted gratis, to the cause of caring for the wayward girls of the Home. But her
               activities did not cease here, for Captain Boyce followed the career, and indeed
               endeavored to act as a sort of guiding <pb n="15"/>Providence to all of her girls
               even after they left the home. Her eyes were a clear blue, with a penetrating light
               that seemed to search to the depths of her pitiful wards. There was something
               peculiarly pure and unswervingly true about her direct gaze. She was fresh and clean
               looking, radiating health physically, mentally and morally. </p>
            <p>She had retained her plain white dress and apron of the graduate nurse, and only her
               blue and scarlet cape and bonnet revealed her as of the Army, and the straps on the
               shoulder of her cape showed that she had risen to the rank of Captain. Her somewhat
               high cheeked bones were rosy and ruddy, and her smooth brown hair was swept back
               crisply from a wide white foreheads. Her hands had that long white look one
               associates with strength and capability. There was nothing flabby or soft about their
               clasp, and many a girl had clung to those hands in the hour of her direct need and
               found strength and courage. </p>
            <p>Though she cherished and comforted her charges and wards, Captain Boyce was no
               sentimental guardian. It was by no means a humble Salvation Lassy, but a cool and
               often belligerent warder who faced the applicants who came to the Refuge bent upon
               securing the unfortunate young mothers as cheap help, or for the purpose of adopting
               the fatherless babes. Searching questions must be answered, the best credentials and
               proof of character furnished before Captain Boyce resigned one of her charged into
               the hands of soliciting strangers. </p>
            <p>Nor was she soft in her attitude towards her <q>sinners</q>;<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No final quotation mark in original.</note> she took them in and
               sheltered and forgave them their sins, but she held up before each girl a stern and
               ruthless ideal of future conduct. She had a loud, inexhaustible vocabulary of
               whipping words, and these she fired at her weeping young sinners, and in the manner
               of the old time preacher, who thundered of damnatic fire and hell, so this Salvation
               captain with one hand dealt punishment and with the other comforted and saved. </p>
            <p>When Hetty <note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><q>Hettie</q> in original.</note>had turned her face to the wall; when she had refused to speak to other
               girls; when she had answered all of the Captain’s questions with defiant
               monosyllables; when for days on end she had kept to her attitude of indifference to
               fellowship or sympathy. Captain Boyce quietly ignored her, but her clear blue eye had
               singled out Hetty as one destined for especial scourging, and she did not fail to
               note that first suggestion of a smile that came to lighten the girl’s woeful young
               face when they told her the name they had given to her child. A few days after that
               Judge Emily Lawson came down to the Refuge bringing with her a ranchman and his wife,
               who, recently bereaved of their own baby sought to soften their hurt by adopting
               another woman’s child.</p>
         </div>
          <div type="section">
             <p>Now Hetty had determined from the first to <q>wash her hands</q> of her infant. In the long days of anguished waiting that had preceded the advent of Bootie, Hetty, like many another girl of her position, had planned a hundred different schemes by which to be rid <sic>in</sic> her child. Indeed she knew that it would be impossible for her to reinstate herself in her own little world or return to her work—she was a stenographer in a large law firm—unless she could find a home for her child. She had used up her scant savings before coming to the Refuge by a prolonged <q>vacation</q>, supposedly in Banff, where she told her employers and associates she had relatives. That her <q>vacation</q> had in reality been spent in a dim hall room of a house on the north side of Calgary was immaterial: she had <q>saved her face</q> in the office, and could probably get her position back, but that hall room had nevertheless cost her the last of her small hoard and the openly hostile attitude of her landlady in the latter days had been the spur which had driven her to the extremity of the Salvation Army. The <q>relatives in Banff</q> were a myth. Poor Hetty had, in fact, no relatives in Canada. She had been one of the army of W.A.A.C. girls that England had sent out to Canada. In Montreal, club women had taken the girls in hand, and those who were not jealously grabbed up for household service were disposed in the various cities. Hetty, who prior to her work had been at a commercial school, was sent out to Alberta, where a position was found for her in the law office of a well-known senator at Ottawa, who maintained his law firm in his native city of Calgary. She, who had passed through the war morally unscathed, <q>Fell</q> in the hysteric joy days that followed the <sic>armistic</sic>. Of the man, father of Bootie, the less said the better. To the weak, deluded and so lonely girl—stranger in a land thousands of miles from her own home and people, who thought of her vaguely as in exile in the vicinity of the North Pole, he had appeared as the magnificent adventure of her life. In the long stifling months that followed the exalted period of blind delirium of supposed love, Hetty still cherished a wild passion for the man who had <q>ruined</q> her. For his sake, because she feared it would mean the loss of the last pinch of sentiment he had for her, she was prepared to sacrifice her child. She had an ignorant girl’s exaggerated notion that the mere knowledge of the existence of her baby would mean the end of things between her and her lover. Bootie was her badge of shame. That oft repeated and favorite axiom of many such as Hetty that <q>the sin lies in being found out</q>, appealed to the girls as aptly fitting her case. She had been very, very careful. No one knew a thing about <q>Bootie</q>—not even the man himself and he least of all must know. She still <choice>
                <sic>desparately</sic>
                <corr>desperately</corr>
                </choice> clung to the hope that he would keep his promise and marry her. Marriage to Hetty, spelled salvation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>Now, suddenly, Hetty <note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><q>Hettie</q></note> found herself fronted with the actual question of the
               disposition of her baby. The ranch people who had come to the Refuge with the woman
               judge, had gone through the nursery, and like everyone else who had seen little
               Bootie, they had fallen captive to the baby’s beauty and charm. They wanted Hetty’s
               baby. Already it was in the hungry arms of the mother who had lost her own.</p>
         
            <p>I think Hetty recognized from the first that sooner or later she would capitulate to
               the Salvation Captain, for there was always an element of fear in her too hostile
               attitude toward Captain Boyce. Now when the latter approached her in the ward, where
               she sat mending sheets and pillow cases, Hetty affected at first not to see her, and
               her slightly turned face stiffened and reddened when Captain Boyce addressed her. She
               kept her head down while the Captain spoke, but when the full import of the words
               began to dawn upon her, her face flashed up with that look of awakening fear. </p>
            <p><q>You listed Booties for adoption, and I have been making inquiries for you, and now
                  Judge Lawson has brought some good people to the Home who—</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hetty <note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><q>Hettie</q></note> began to think of that night when the loud sobbing of the Swedish girl in the
               bed next to her had irritated and terrified her. The Swedish girl’s baby had been put
               out for adoption on that day, and inconsolable, she had cried all of that night.
               Hetty had covered her ears with her hands, but she could not shut out the low animal
               cries of the Swedish mother, and there pierced through her memory certain words heard
               of long ago, as it seemed, in some small English Sunday School. <q>The voice of
                  Rachel crying for her children will not be comforted</q>. She was seized with a
               fit of uncontrollable superstitious terror, for the first time she awoke to the
               poignant realization of what the loss of her child was to mean to her. Her own
               Calvary was at hand. </p>
            <p>Strangely enough, the white face that imagined was so composed, that she flashed up
               Captain Boyce bore a tragic resemblance to that red, swollen mask of the Swedish
               mother, for in both their eyes was the same terror of the mother thing at bay. But
               Hetty was of more valiant flesh than Elsie. She went down smiling, if that twisted
               mockery of a smile might be called such. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            
        
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <p><q>Is there any hurry Captain?</q> she inquired with exaggerated politeness. Her eyes
               were blinking, though she tried to hold them wide open. There were no inclination for
               tears, but she found that she had suddenly gone quite blind. Though she was staring,
               wide-eyed at the Captain, Hetty saw nothing in the world but her own baby’s face, and
               it floated before her like a spirit’s. Nevertheless she kept up her pose of calmness.
                  <q>You see, I am not awfully strong yet, and I thought maybe if you didn’t mind,
                  I’d like to stay here another month. I can afford to pay a little, or I am willing
                  to work for my board—just as you say</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Stay as long as you wish</q>, said the Captain gravely. She removed her gaze from
               the girl’s straining face, and looked far out before her, clearing her husky throat
               and commanding the tremble that <pb n="118"/>came to her voice despite her self control.</p>
            <p><q>But now—about Bootie. You know, sooner or later, she is to be placed for adoption.
                  You so asked when you entered here. We have it on the records, and have been
                  making diligent inquiries in your behalf. Now we always find it best when a child
                  is to be adopted, to get a home and parents for it just as soon as possible. In
                  fact the longer you—we—put off, the harder it is to part with the child. So, after
                  careful search, we have been successful, and a good home is offered to Bootie.
                  Judge Lawson is here now, and we must get the formalities over with</q>. </p>
            <p><q>Formalities</q> repeated Hetty. She had had that word in dictation many times in
               the law office. </p>
            <p><q>Yes, you know you sign certain papers before a judge, renouncing your claim to
                  your child. Then it is in a position to be adopted legally, and receive all the
                  benefit of care and property of the people who take it; in fact, is regarded,
                  legally as their own child. Now, as I know how hard it is for my girls to go to
                  court, I have Judge Lawson—a very fine woman, and one you can trust
                  absolutely—come here personally once a month, or when some special case is to be
                  settled. And she is here to-day; so, if you are ready, my dear, we will have the
                  matter of Bootie cleared up without further delay</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Matter of Bootie</q> repeated Hetty dully. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>Nevertheless she was surprised at her own apparent composure—or what she took to be
               composure. Actually she was able to stand on her feet and follow Captain Boyce across
               the ward and into the office. The woman judge was sitting at a table, but she looked
               up as Hetty followed Captain Boyce into the room, and her penetrating glance fixed
               the girl searchingly. Things began to spin round and round about Hetty. She had seen
               that woman judge before. Yes—it was in the law office where she had worked. She was a
               friend of Hetty’s employers. She knew—Panic seized upon Hetty. A wild impulse to run
               away, to hide her face <choice>
                  <sic>overwhelmned</sic>
                  <corr>overwhelmed</corr>
                  </choice>the miserable girl. Suppose this judge should go
               back to her office and tell them all about her—Hetty. Suppose <emph>he</emph> should find out
               that—<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">Extra final quotation mark in original.</note> </p>
            <p>But the woman judge gave no sign of recognition. She had turned back to the table,
               and now Hetty, sitting opposite a paper they had placed before her. The long index
               finger of the woman judge was pointing to the <choice>
                  <sic>lne</sic>
                  <corr>line</corr>
                  </choice>where Hetty was to sign. This was
               the <q>formality</q>. She heard the voice of the judge saying or reading something to
               her, but things were spinning around so swiftly now and there was such a buzzing in
               Hetty’s ears that she comprehended nothing save that she was to put her name upon
               that paper. She wrote slowly, carefully in that round, childish hand prized by the
               law office. She stopped to blot her name, and then her chair scraped back, and Hetty
               stood on her feet again. All she thought of just then was that it was strange the old
               weakness in her knees that had been there when first she had arisen after her illness
               was back again. She put out her hands as if to feel her way and she swayed from side
               to side as she found her way to the door.</p>
            <p><q>Damn the <emph>man</emph>, say I! <emph>He</emph> should be bung!</q></p>
            <p>Said the Captain:</p>
            <p><q>Hetty’s crucifixion will be her salvation. She will ‘go and sin no more.’</q></p>
            <p>Now for two days and a night Hetty lay in bed, her face turned stonily to that wall,
               rejected all food, speaking to no one, hearing and heeding not the words of
               commiseration and sympathy. Her breasts ached and burned fiercely, for there were no
               hungry baby lips to relieve the pressure. Not alone the mother’s breasts, but every
               inch of the mother’s body, and the heart within, was aching and crying aloud for her
               child; yet hating the world and herself, damning even her God, Hetty crouched up
               against the wall.</p>
            <p>In the middle of the second night, the ward was startled by the piercing cry of
               Hetty. The night nurse, a Salvation Army lieutenant, hurried across the dormitory in
               her felt slippers, and sought to hush the alarm that the girl’s wild outcry had
               raised, but like a lot of children, all of the girls were crying in sympathy with
               Hetty. She had sprung out of her bed, and like one entirely out of her senses the
               crazed child plunged across the room in the direction of the nursery. With her hands
               striking the door flatly, she broke her through, till she came to the crib where
               little Bootie had slept. Here a small black head—the child of a mulatto, made a dark
               patch upon <pb n="120"/>the white pillow. Hetty broke into laughter, desperate, wild laughter. She swayed back and forth, her terrible laughter wrenching hysterically from her tossed back head. A woman in white opened the door of the office, and hurried across the ward. Hetty saw her, and clapping her hand to her mouth, she stifled back her laughter. Like a drowning person who grasps after straws, Hetty dimly saw in the Salvation Captain the emblem of hope. She sprang to meet her, dropped on her knees before her, her frantic arms clasped about and her hands tearing and clutching at the Salvation Captains knees. </p>
            <p><q>Oh Captain, Captain, I’ve changed my mind. I want my baby. I want my baby. I want
                  my baby. Give me my baby!</q>
            </p>
            <p><q>Now Hetty, Hetty, this won’t do at all. Come with me dear—this way—this
               way</q>.</p>
            <p>There were in the captain’s office at the end of the hall, Hetty was on the sofa
               doubled forward, even her bare little feet twitching and showing the anguish that
               wracked her from head to foot. Well that Salvation captain knew the precious value of
               tears, and she prayed that they might come to bring relief to the tortured young
               creature before her; but only the dry gasping tearless sobs were wrenched from the
               heart of Hetty. </p>
            <p><q>Hetty, God sees you. He knows your heart is tender, and He pities you. In His
                  great goodness He is going to bless your dear little baby by giving her a good
                  home and people to love and care for her</q>.</p>
            <p><q>But captain d-dear, I w-want my own baby. I didn’t know what I was doing when I
                  s-s-signed those f-f-f-formalities, and I want my baby, my little, little b-baby!
                  You wouldn’t be so hard to take her from me, w-would you? She’s all, all I’ve got
                  in all this r-r-rotten world!</q></p>
            <p><q>No Hetty dear, I’d be the last to take your baby from you, but you know, you asked
                  us to find a home for her, and the kind people came, and I believe it is God’s way
                  of solving the problem for you and Bootie</q>. </p>
            <p><q>B-but I d-don’t want it solved. I can solve my own problems, and I don’t want any
                  help from God. I d-don’t believe in God anyhow! And if He is a God, He is a cruel
                  God!</q></p>
            <p><q><emph>Hetty</emph>! That is blasphemy!</q> </p>
            <p><q>I don’t care what it is. He didn’t help me before. He won’t help me now. he made
                  the baby come when I didn’t want it, and th-then when it came and I wanted it, He
                  took it away from me. But you won’t be so cruel, will you. You’ll give me my baby
                  back. I am sure you will. You look so g-good and k-kind. You cant refuse me. Oh,
                  say that you will—that you will! Oh, oh, what am I do to, what am I to do?</q></p>
            <p><q>Pray to God to forgive you those wicked words—to forgive you for your sins</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I can’t pray. I’m all frozen up in here. and even if I did pray, no one would hear
                  me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Cry, then, poor lamb, cry! God will see your tears and know them for prayers</q>. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            
        
       
            <p>There was a long silence and then from those wild staring out eyes the great drops
               began to fall down the girl’s thin little face. Back and forth she rocked and she
               thrust out her arms with an eloquent motion and cried:</p>
         
            <p><q>My arms are empty! My arms are empty! Oh my <emph>God!</emph></q></p>
   
            <p>In the silence that again fell after that utterance fell the compassionate voice of
               her friend, the Salvation captain.</p>
            
            <p><q>Hetty, it’s not as if anything bad had happened to Bootie. Suppose she had died,
               like the child of the dear woman who has taken little Bootie. Suppose you had kept
               her, and she had to suffer for your sins, or grew up to do as you have done and—</q></p>
            <p><q>No, no—never, never that</q> cried Hetty. </p>
            <p><q>—but your own example, Hetty</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh captain, I wasn’t so bad as you think. J-just a foolish little flapper, vain,
               silly and weak—I wanted to dance and drink and have pretty c-clothes, and he was—he
               was the big boss of the office—away above me, you understand, and I got dazzled, and
               he was always after me, and I thought—he told me so many times Captain—that he 
                  <emph>loved</emph> me</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh Hetty dear, <emph>that</emph> is not <emph>love</emph>! Love
               cherishes; not destroys</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I believe you now. I trust you. I feel that you will help me. You’ll get me my baby
               back. I am sure you will? You will find a way somehow. I can see how kind you are,
               and if you’ll only give me back Bootie, I’ll be so good you won’t recognize me. I’ll
               do anything in the world you ask me to. I’ll—I’ll go out in the streets with the
               Army. Yes, I will captain, though I used to laugh at the Salvation lassies. I thought
               them jokes. But now the laugh is on me. They can laugh at me</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><q>Oh Hetty, my dear, we are not in the world to laugh at each other, but to help each other, though I’m not going to preach to you now. I’d gladly give you back Bootie if I could, and if you really wanted me to; but after I’ve told you about the people she has gone to, I know you will see it is for her best good, and I know you will think of Bootie first. You are not a selfish girl, and you will think of your child’s future happiness before your own. Now lie down there like a good little girl! There right on that pillow. There, I’ll tuck the cover in about you, and if you’ll keep real quiet, I’ll tell you what I know of the people who have Bootie</q>. </p>
            <p><q>She is a ranchman’s wife, Hetty, a very fine little woman. We investigated them
                  thoroughly, and they have a beautiful home, a ranch of thousands of acres, with
                  big modern buildings and a great many people working for them. Their ranch is
                  right in the foothills of the Rocky mountains, so that they have something
                  beautiful to look at all the time, and you know the poets tell us mountains
                  inspire us to noble thoughts and deeds, so our Bootie will grow up in a clean,
                  fine, beautiful atmosphere. Now won’t be great for her development? <choice>
                     <sic>Then</sic>
                     <corr>Than</corr>
                  </choice>this little woman, who loves her already, has had a great grief and loss.
                  Her own baby has just died, so you see Bootie is going to be doubly loved, both
                  for herself and the dead baby. Now isn’t it better for her to have a fine home and
                  care and be brought up properly, <choice>
                     <sic>then</sic>
                     <corr>than</corr>
                  </choice> to remain with you, and perhaps have to pass through a hand to mouth
                  existence; maybe subjected to poverty and hardship and shame, you have so much to
                  be thankful for Hetty. All babies do not find good homes, but Booties was so
                  pretty. No one could resist her; everyone wanted her that saw her</q>.</p>
            <p>A smile that was strangely pitiful and beautiful lit up Hetty’s wan face. </p>
            <p><q>Ah</q>, she whispered, <q>wasn’t she the prettiest baby ever. Why no one could
                  have believed she was only two months old. Oh her dear little face and her
                  smile—she smiled the very first week, and she knew me so soon and—Oh my little
                  baby—Oh my baby—my—</q>
            </p>
            <p><q>Cry it out Hetty dear. You’ve needed to cry for so long now. one cannot carry a
                  cup brimful</q>.</p>
         </div>
          <div type="section"> 
          
          
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>Hetty’s head had fallen forward. Her hair was bobbed like a child’s, in the prevalent
               mode, but it curled in ringlets about her <choice>
                  <sic>forhead</sic>
                  <corr>forehead</corr>
               </choice> and cheeks and neck. She was pretty
               as her baby and almost as helpless. The captain’s voice above her was beginning to
               sound very far away now to Hetty. It seemed almost as if someone was speaking to her
               in a dream, and assuring her that some day perhaps Bootie would be with her again. It
               was against the rules to give the names and addresses of the people who took the
               babies, but Captain was sure that when Hetty had proven herself a true repentant the
               people who had taken her baby would let her come to their home to see little Bootie.
               With this promise, Hetty’s fingers closed spasmodically upon Captain Boyce’s hands
               and then relaxed their tension. There was complete silence in the room, and Hetty’s
               curls almost hid her face. One arm was thrown up childishly to ward off the light.
               Hetty, the sinner, slept. </p>
            <p>And the Salvation captain, softly releasing her hand from that of the girl lowered
               the light, and withdrew to her desk. She opened a well worn book. Lovingly thumbing
               the pages she came to the passage she sought, and almost unconsciously she read the
               words aloud:</p>
            <p><q>Let him who is without sin among you cast the first stone at her</q>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
