<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="SomeLesserKnown1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some Lesser Known Authors of Alberta</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:RZ1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from the University of Calgary archive</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:288"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="readyForProof">
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2021-11-29" status="readyForProof">Edited and added text to repository.</change>
         <change who="pers:RZ1" when="2021-10-28" status="inProgress">Completed transcription</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-24" status="empty">Added PDF and category references.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-24" status="empty">Created shell from bibl file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:SomeLesserKnown1">
      <pb n="52"/>
      <body>
         <head>Some Lesser Known Canadian Authors</head>
         <opener>
         <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name></byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <div>
            <p>Of all the novels written or being written about Alberta attain publication, we are in the way of becoming an extremely well known part of this old earth of ours. </p>
            <p>Midnapore alone boasts no less than two authors, living within a few miles of each other. John Lloyd, native born son of this province, has done an excellent story in <q>The Stranger</q>. I do not recall the title of Miss Evans’ novel, but I do recall that it was over 150,000 words in length, - the size of about two ordinary novels. The author is a girl in her early 20’s, and it is a credible and clever performance, in spite of loose technique, crudities and faults of digression, etc.
                  If I were a fortune-teller, I would say this girl has a natural gift.</p>
            <p>If I read the signs aright, some Calgary writers are due to make their mark, large or small, in the literary firmament. Especially notable, since her novel, <q>The Judgment of Solomon</q>, took the second prize in the recent national prize novel contest, is Mrs. Floe Jewel Williams of this city. She is analytical, witty and daring. Mrs. Williams has been at the coast all of this summer, engaged upon her second novel.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Charlotte Gordon has already a considerable reputation as a prolific writer of special articles. Recently stories from her pen have been appearing in the London Sphere and the London Graphic. Her story of last winter’s carnival at Banff occupied two pages and was the main feature of a recent issue of the Graphic. She now steps into the limelight with a first novel. It is a beautifully written story concerning the gentlefolk in the ranching country of the Okanagan Valley, and will be published in the coming year.</p>
            <p>Recently The Maple Leaf, official organ of the Canadian clubs, in a prize contest for the best essay upon the subject of Canadian magazines, awarded the first prize to Prof. Austin Bothwell of Regina, and the second to Mrs. Gordon. There were over 700 manuscripts turned in for this contest.</p>
            <p>Book-keeping and accounting may not seem to be especially inspirational employment. However, they failed to extinguish the natural living spark of real literary talent possessed by Mr. Eric Davies, credit man for the Pat Burns company. He has written a thrilling, exciting, romantic, passionate love story of this country. He has an unusual plot and a smooth, quiet style, the very repression of which serves to grip the reader the tighter he climbs from climax to climax. Whether the story will get by the censors - (it has Sheik characteristics!)--remains to be seen. It might very well attain unusual success if published.</p>
            <p>John Main, teacher of mathematics at the East Calgary high school, has written an interesting story concerning the grain game. Its title is <q>The Golden Stream</q>, and it is likely to have serial publication this year in a well known farm magazine. It is not hard to discover in Mr. Main’s hero our own Mr. Wood, of U.F.A. fame.</p>
            <p>Geneva Lent is still in her teens, but Geneva’s talent and ambitions are not <q>teeny</q>. She has written scores of poems and lyrics and songs and short stories. Also she has dished off lightly a couple of full sized novels - mere 60,000 or 100,000 word manuscripts. Watch Geneva! If she can rise above the mountains of impediments that are rolled in the path of the young literary aspirant, she has it in her to go far.</p>
            <p>Clever John Williams, though better known in Calgary for his music and as the author of several books on music, published by Schirmer of New York, has also written several stories. A novel and play are also in process of writing. I had the pleasure of reading one of the wittiest and funniest of comedy scenarios by Mr. Williams, and I expect to see it before long upon the silversheet.</p>
            <p>On a ranch at De Winton, Mrs. Eva Jacobs, the wife of a farmer and mother of several small children, adds to her thousand and one household duties the task-- or, as I think she considers it,-- the diversion of writing a novel concerning Alberta ranch life. Mrs. Jacobs is already quite well known as a writer of short stories and articles. She was the first president of the Calgary Press club.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Waagen, of the Red Cross, has written a novel of old Quebec.</p>
            <p>A boy of fifteen years, whose name I am not at liberty to mention, has written a 50,000-word yarn about a prize fighter, his battles and his loves.</p>
            <p>We look for a new story from Dr. Kerby. In spite of his many duties as principal of Mount Royal College, and a strenuous summer of Chautauqua, the doctor can always be depended upon for a poem or a rattling good story. He is as fresh and ambitious today as, when a zealous and impetuous young <q>parson</q>, he came down the aisle of the Central Methodist church and paused to speak a kind word to the young lady from faraway Sweden, whose lonely state had touched the susceptible heart of the doctor, who had noted and pitied. The lady’s reply to his fatherly request for her address, that he might call upon her, is, in its way, a classic. She replied: <q>No, tank you; I got man</q>. From such material, and other experiences equally interesting, might not Dr. Kerby produce a book of memoirs concerned with this country that would prove a treasure? He has had the experience and he knows how to write.</p>
            <p>And speaking of memoirs. Friends are urging the popular American consul, Mr. S. C. Reat to write a book concerned with his life and adventure in this and other lands. If Mr. Reat should write as he speaks-- and I believe that he can and does-- one of the wittiest and cleverest of books would be the result.</p>   
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
