<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="SomeMotorists1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some Motorists Are Not as Popular with the Farmers as Many of Them Think</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:SC1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from University of British Columbia</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:127"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-07-02">Made note about source</change><change who="pers:SC1" status="inProgress" when="2020-06-12">Begin transcription</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty"  when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty"  when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl127 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Some_Motorists">
      <pb n="28"/>
      <body>
         <head>Some Motorists Are Not as Popular with the Farmers as Many of Them Think</head>
         <head type="subtitle">The Farmers, However, Are Painfully Popular with the Motorists—Many Joy Riders
            Expect Much for Nothing And Believe It Is Conferring a Favor to Land a Hungry
            Carload Into a Farmer’s Dining Room—Some Very Magnificent <q>Tips</q> Are Offered,
            Even to the Extent of Fifty Cents—But the Freckle Faced Boy Refused tThe Dough with
            Scorn.</head>
         <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Reeve</name> (<name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name>)</byline>
         <div>
            <div n="1">
               <p>They come with the first breath of spring, ploughing along the muddy, slippery
                  roads, bent, so they assure us, on <q>making the grade</q> to Banff, but managing
                  generally to get as far as our ranch, kill the engine, burst a tire or run dead
                  out of gasoline. </p>
               <p> </p>
               <p>As the roads dry and the sun of the advancing summer glows upon the land, they
                  come shooting along the main road to Banff, with such alarming speed and
                  frequency, that it is no wonder a number of them manage to spill themselves off at
                  our gates. </p>
               <p> </p>
               <p>Summer, with all its heat and dust, brings them literally by the hundreds. We like
                  to see them roll by and disappear into the foothills of the Rockies, but an
                  astonishing number of these hundreds roll no farther than our doors.</p>
               <p> </p>
               <p>We are painfully popular at this time. The fishing season has opened.</p>
               <p> </p>
               <p>Although the cars en route to Banff lessen in number with the passing of the
                  summer days, they increase so far as those that stop abruptly at the ranch house
                  goes, with no pr4tense now of <q>making the grade</q> to Banff. Lo! the hunter is
                  at hand. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
               <head>Where They Foregather</head>
               <p>Down at the junction of the Ghost and Bow rivers, which bound two sides of our
                  ranch, the mother hoboes love to foregather. Neither tightly closed gate or four
                  lines of barbed wire, daunt these trespassers, who open (but never close) the gate
                  at the bridge, park their cars on the Ghost side under the bridge, and disappear
                  along the banks of that forbidden stream.</p>
               <p>Sometimes tents and camping paraphernalia are set up, either down by the Ghost
                  river or in the pasture above the Bow river, and our motor hobo squats upon the
                  land indefinitely. Very ingenious are some of their camping devices, and when
                  supplies are low and they tire of a fish diet, they beg, borrow and steal from
                  their unwilling hosts. Some of them camp <q>de luxe</q> with electrical
                  contrivances connected with their cars, thermos bottles and other luxurious
                  articles dear to the heart of the modern camper; but for the most part they camp
                  in the rough, and the smoke of their fires curl up from the river, apprizing us of
                  the presence of our uninvited guests, and warning us to be on guard. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
               <head>Soft Spot in His Heart</head>
               <p>Our <q>hands</q> joke about the <q>paper collar dudes</q> in camp, but the boss
                  has a soft spot for all would-be fishermen and hunters. As the days pass, however,
                  and our stock strays forth through the open gates and are sometimes banged by
                  joyriders on the highway; as incipient forest fires are barely nipped in the bud;
                  we begin to feel a measure of irritation and alarm. So we wire the gates and stick
                  up a <q>No Trespass</q> sign. We leave, however, a portion of the land by the
                  bridge, where the aspiring fisherman may angle in peace, and where also, when the
                  season opens, the hunter may have a shot or two at the coy partridge, grouse and
                  prairie chicken that seem to vamp us from every bush. Our good nature meets with a
                  poor reward, and our wrath rises to fever heat, when we discover the wanton
                  cutting of the fences, and narrowly scape being hit by the crazy shooting in
                  pastures and woods where our cattle are grazing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4">
               <head>Delegation of One</head>
               <p>If our delegation is represented by the small boy of the house 9it’s not always
                  convenient to spare <q>hands</q> to go three miles down the road) his reception is
                  not always cordial by these well-meaning and perhaps unconscious incendiaries, bad
                  shots and poor sports—for it is poor sport to fish in streams that a thoughtful
                  government has closed for the best of reasons. Said one <q>big piece of
                  cheese</q>, as the boy described him, when approached by said small boy, and
                  warned that his <q>bonfire</q> was endangering the brush:</p>
               <p><q>Listen to who’s talking now. If you don’t shut your <choice><sic>fact</sic><corr>face</corr></choice>, I’ll throw you<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">The line is duplicated and the sentence is not complete originally</note></q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5">
               <head>The Hobo Beats It</head>
               <p>The boy, disdaining to answer, wrote down the number of the hoboe’s car, stuck his
                  small spurred heels into his horse’s flank, and was off over the hill before the
                  hobo awoke to a realization of possible danger to his precious outfit. From the
                  top of the hill the boy saw him actively at work upon the cut fence and bonfire
                  and before the boy could reach the ranch house the noise of the departing car of
                  the motor hobo was heard loud in the land as he escaped along the road in a cloud
                  of dust.</p>
               <p>So much for the motor hoboes who bear a sort of relationship to sports. We feel
                  for them a certain sympathy, and even liking at times, so long as they close our
                  gates, do no <choice>
                     <sic>wlid</sic>
                     <corr>wild</corr>
                  </choice> shooting near the cattle, fish in the open streams, and do not set our
                  woods on fire. They are part of the <q>game</q> of ranching in this part of the
                  country, and we take their presence among us as philosophically as we do such
                  visitors as the fish and game in season. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6">
               <head>What They Require</head>
               <p>We come now to those who chug up the hill to the ranch house, and proffer their
                  various requests and demands. Experience forces us to regard with suspicion all
                  applicants for shelter, meals, milk, eggs, tools, horses, vegetables, use of
                  telephone, use of verandah for picnic, gasoline and berries. Now the man
                  travelling from Calgary to Banff, knows just how much gasoline, there is Cochrane
                  midway between, where he can fill up. We have had one motor hobo after another,
                  drive up to our door and casually demand gasoline. We’ve had them help themselves
                  to gasoline from the drum outside our garage—the <q>boss</q> being away, and the
                  women of the house uncertain how to measure out gasoline, and the motor hobo
                  assuring us they would be very careful. We have had them procure the gasoline from
                  our <q>hands</q> in our absence, omitting to pay for the same (at a time when
                  gasoline was as high as 60 cents per gallon), but handling a tip to the
                     <q>hand</q>. At 3 in the morning we have been awakened by a joyrider asking for
                  gasoline, his car being stalled down the road, with a party which included girls
                  and men, and if we would but get up and get him some of the desired fluid he would
                  pay us a whole dollar per gallon. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7">
               <head>Not a Garage</head>
               <p>We do not run a public garage, but a cattle ranch. When the farmer hauls out to
                  his ranch at considerable labor and cost, a drum of gasoline, he does it for his
                  own especial use, because he is not near to the sources that supply the
                  joyriders.</p>
               <p>Often the motor hoboes are of the feminine persuasion, and very persuasive they
                  are. With ingratiating smile, they tender their various requests, the commonest
                  ones being a square meal, a harbor for the night, butter and eggs and <q>Could we
                     go into your woods to get raspberries, saskatoons and gooseberries</q>. They
                  have first scouted through said woods, and assured themselves of the presence
                  there of the desired berries, before making the request, which is nearly always
                  granted. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8">
               <head>Here’s a Sweet Sister</head>
               <p>One sunny day an especially blooming type of the female motor hobo species, blew
                  up the hill in a great giddy car, that was brim full of chattering and beveled
                  sister adventurers, and sought to induce us to give them a meal. She seemed to
                  think the request to feed eight extra people on a ranch was a trifling matter,
                  and, in fact, I suspect that at first she thought she was doing us a mighty favor
                  by asking us. We politely returned that we were a private ranch, not a hotel; but
                  if she kept on a bit further she would come to a place where, no doubt, they could
                  get a meal. Our motor hobo, in this instance, was apparently one used to having
                  her own way and would take no refusal. She first flattered (the looks of our ranch
                  and of us); she then endowed us with most charming smiles; she then pathetically
                  told how dogged tired and hot and hungry they all were, and wouldn’t we let them
                  wash up and refresh themselves on the verandah before dinner, etc. she then,
                  lowering her voice, descended to bribery, mentioning the alluring amount she was
                  prepared to pay for a good fare dinner, and, finally, aggravated by our
                  stubborness, she waxes indignant and extremely haughty, and her aside remarks
                  anent <q>Rubes</q> were not good for us to hear. She stated further that she
                  understood it was the custom of the country for the farmers to take in people who
                  were on the road as they were, etc., and suggested that we were outside the breed
                  of those kindly souls who lived according to said rule. We aeulesced in this, and
                  apprized her of the fact that that rule applied to wayfarers, farmers like
                  ourselves; people who were unavoidedly held up or had an accident, and included
                  also the pedestrian tramp, but not the mere motor hobo. We also inquired whether
                  if we drove up to the lady’s house in Calgary with a load of <q>Rubes</q> aboard
                  our Lizzlle if she would trouble even to parley with us on the subject of grub. </p>
               <p>She left our premises in a fine huff, convinced, I am sure, that farmers were not
                  all they aere cracked up to be, but a tight-fisted, mean lot—their women at all
                  events. </p>
               <p>I should not, however, be supposed that we turn such a stony front to all who
                  apply to us for meals and shelter. Far from it. Scarcely a day passes that we do
                  not have a stranger or strangers at our board, and on Sundays, what with our city
                  friends, neighbors and wayfarers, whose request seems really legitimate, we
                  sometimes have much ado to find room for all. Twenty-two and twenty-five at the
                  table is no uncommon occurrence on a Saturday or Sunday. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9">
               <head>Offered a Quarter</head>
            <p>The tipping motor hobo is one of our pet aversions. Perhaps I should say, rather, the
               hobo who offers to tip. Very often when put to the test, said tip calls forth
               explosive chuckles from all hands on the ranch, as for instance: Tendered a whole
               quarter for his dinner by a dapper young <q>hobo</q>, who had rolled up to our gates with
               a henna-haired product of our fair city of Calgary, we smilingly rejected the same,
               but suggested that he might tip our cook as he made his exit through the kitchen. Did
               he follow our suggestion? He did not. And he is only one instance. </p>
            <p>On another occasion, a couple of <q>Yanks</q>, touring en route to Banff and Lake
                  Luoise, buzzed up noisily in their big Cadillac, and spent an hour or so in our
                  garage overhauling their ear. They were departing, waving a friendly farewell,
                  when one, apparently taking pity on us, whispered something to the tother’s ear.
                  Actually those fine men turned back. They hailed us as:</p>
            <p><q>Hi there</q>, which is not our name at all.</p>
               <p>Ignorant of their purpose, we approached the big shining car. With the gracious
                  and benevolent smile of one bestowing a kingdom, one of them leaned out of the car
                  and proffered us a fifty-cent bit. Overcome by this unexpected act of generosity,
                  we grinned and shook our head.</p>
               <p><q>No, thank you. It’s all right</q>.</p>
               <p>At that moment, around the side of the garage appeared our son, aged 12 years old.
                  With the cynical, suspicious and guying eye peculiar to a freckle-faced,
                  <choice>
                     <sic>read</sic>
                     <corr>red</corr>
                  </choice>-haired country lad, who in some way or other has imbibed a wholesale disdain
                  for merely <q>city guys</q>, he was knew by his diabolical expression that he
                  purposed, should I take that fifty cents, forever afterwards tomake me the
                  scornful butt of his gibes and jeers. It so happened that this fine motor hobo
                  perceived our son as soon as we did, and his face clearing, and still benevolent,
                  he held up that coin between thumb and forefinger. The boy, ignoring his
                  suggestive motion, that man descended from his car, and approached said
                  red-headed, freckle-faced overall-clad farmer’s boy. </p>
               <p><q>Here, little boy</q>, said he cheerily, <q>is 50 cents. Your mamma won’t take
                     it. So you run along and buy her a big box of candy and a stick of candy for
                     yourself</q>.</p>
               <p>(I don’t know what kind of candy he expected to buy in such quantity for 50
                  cents.)</p>
               <p>Now, if there is one mortal insult that a 12-year-old boy cannot endure, it is to
                  be addressed as <q>Here, little boy</q>, such language, in his opinion, being more
                  fitted for one of his sex ten years younger. </p>
               <p>The red that spread hotly over our boy’s freckle face forewarned us of what
                  followed, and furthermore an audience had arrived in the shape of sundry fellows
                  who had sauntered over from the corral and the bunk house.</p>
               <p>Said the boy:</p>
               <p><q>I don’t want your d—m dough. Blow it on yourself</q>.</p>
               <p>The man, surprised at this unexpected rejection, pressed the bit of money into the
                  boy’s hand and hastily jumped into his car. The boy, however, pursued him,
                  wrathfully demanding:</p>
               <p><q>Say, do you take me for a bell hop? Here’s your dirty d—m dough back</q>.</p>
               <p>Normally that boy can hit straight and that 50-cent piece should have landed where
                  it was aimed, at the car, but the car was moving with increasing speed, and the
                  coin flew wide of its mark and disappeared into the grass.</p>
               <p>Several hours later, I <choice>
                  <sic>asw</sic>
                  <corr>saw</corr>
                  </choice> the boy on hands and knees, carefully going over the
                  ground, inch by inch. Quite late in the afternoon he came to the house, with a
                  glowing face, and held up triumphantly the scorned piece of <choice>
                     <sic>omne.y</sic>
                     <corr>money</corr>
                   </choice>.</p>
               <p><q>I found it I found <choice>
                  <sic>It</sic>
                  <corr>it.</corr>
               </choice> Hey, mom, can I go over to Morley after the mail? I gotta
                     get something at the store</q>.</p>
               <p>Of other tippers, I might write considerably, especially the ones we pull out of
                  sloughs or up slippery hills. They are fine fellows when our horses are hauling
                  them out of their trouble: but they get down to grim business when the job is
                  done, and hand rattling the small change in pocket, they inquire:</p>
               <p><q>How much for that little distance?</q> ignoring the distance the horses have
                  come from the field, and often the trouble of getting them in, harnessing, etc.
                  Our men charge variously for such jobs, it being the rule of the ranch that they
                  can keep what they get. We had an Irishman who was always satisfied with:</p>
               <p><q>A bit of tobacco, sor</q>.</p>
               <p>And we were overwhelmed with mirth by the canny dealings of a Scotch <q>Yank</q>
                  in our employ. When charged with usury by an indignant complainant, he sulkily
                  justified himself by telling us of a friend of his who made a regular trade of
                  pulling <q>guys</q> out of a muddy hole, that he himself kept greased and well
                  watered. Close at hand, his friend was always there to bargain with the
                  unfortunate motorist when the latter’s car sped heedlessly into the tran set for
                  him. In this special case, however, the biter was finally bitten. A victim having
                  agreed to pay him the exorbitant price of $10 to pull him out of the muddy hole,
                  once on dry land, turned on full speed, tooted his horn and made off merrily and
                  swiftly, returning, however, the following day with a squad that not only patched
                  up that hole efficiently, but pumped the fear of retribution into the soul of the
                  fellow who thought he had secured a corner on this dubious trade. Which all goes
                  to show that there are indeed two sides to every question, and no doubt the
                     <q>motor hobo</q> could tell a story on the farmer that would be better than
                  mine. </p>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
