<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="StarvingAndWriting3">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>First Appearance in New York City</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:229"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Alberta"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-11" status="published">Set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-09" status="readyForProof">Proof completed. Still need to figure out milestones before setting to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-09" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-08-24" status="empty">Created shell from bibl file and
            added PDF.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:StarvingAndWriting3">
      <body>
         <head>First Appearance In New York City</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna (Mrs. Winnifred Reeve)</name>,</byline>
            <byline>Author of <q>A Japanese Nightingale</q>.</byline>
         </opener>
         <div>

            <p>I was eighteen years old. I had received a letter from Mr. Ellery Sedgwick, then
               editor of Frank Leslie’s (now editor of the Atlantic Monthly). Instead of the usual
               rejection slip, he wrote expressing an interest in me, and suggested that I should
               let him see <q>anything else you have written</q>.</p>
            <p>Upon my arrival in New York, I did not wait to secure lodgings. I went straight from
               the train, bag in hand, to Mr. Sedgwick’s office. Having explained to him who I
               was—he appeared to have forgotten that letter he had written me—I said: <q>And you
                  wrote me to let you see anything else I had written, and so…</q></p>
            <p>I opened my bag. He leaped to his feet, threw up his hands, and shouted:</p>
            <p><q>Help! Help!</q></p>
            <p>In rushed half a dozen editors and clerks, and the wild-looking Mr. Sedgwick pointed
               dramatically to that bag of mine, which was brim full to the top with manuscripts.
               With a vague idea that I was about to be arrested, I burst into tears. I bawled as
               hard and heartily as only a husky youngster can, with the result that outrageous
               mirth was checked, and Mr. Sedgwick alternately wringing his hands and running them
               through his hair implored me to stop weeping. He said:</p>
            <p><q>Don’t cry! Don’t cry! Don’t cry like that! Stop it! I’ll buy a story from you if
                  you will. I’ll buy all your stories if you do. There, there, no one’s going to
                  hurt you. Shut up, do!</q></p>
            <p>In later years, when Mr. Sedgwick and I would meet at intervals, he liked to recall
               the several amusing episodes he recalled in my past, and he told our friends that I
               had blackmailed him with tears into buying my first story.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Onoto Watanna</head>
            <p>Montreal can claim to be the birthplace of no more interesting author than Winnifred
               Reeve, nee Winnifred Eaton, who under the pen-name of Onoto Watanna, has written
               sixteen novels, dealing chiefly with Japanese life, one of which, <q>A Japanese
                  Nightingale</q>, has had an immense circulation and was dramatized by Cosmo Gordon
               Lennox for Marie Tempest, while Klaw and Erlanger produced it in New York with an
               all-star cast, headed by Margaret Illington. The play was also published and produced
               in France and Germany. Mrs. Reeve won the $10,000 prize offered by the Chicago
               Tribune for a serial motion play, and has had several of her books transferred to the
               screen. Montreal is introduced in two of her novels, <q>Me</q>, which was run
               anonymously as a serial in the Century Magazine, and <q>Marion Sister of Me</q>,
               which was run anonymously in Hearst’s Magazine.</p>
            <p>During the last five years Mrs. Reeve has been ranching in Alberta, half way between
               Calgary and Banff, where she is secretary and one of the three owners of Pleasant
               Range Stock Farm. She has just completed a new novel, <q>Sunny-San</q>, which will be
               published shortly by the George W. Doran Company, of New York, and is being
               dramatized for play production by Willard Mack, author of <q>Tiger Rose</q>, <q>Kick
                  In</q>, etc.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Reeve’s sister, Ruth Eaton, wrote a book of short stories interpreting the life
               of the Chinese in America, entitled <q>Miss Spring Fragrance</q>, which is a classic
               in this particular field, and was so much appreciated by the Chinese on this
               continent that they erected a monument in her memory when she died. It was published
               by A. C. Maclurg, of Chicago, and is now extremely rare.</p>
            <p>List of novels published: <q>An Old Jinrikisha</q>, serial in Conkey’s Magazine;
                  <q>Miss Nume of Japan</q>, Rand McNally; <q>A Japanese Nightingale</q>, Harper
               &amp; Bros. and serial in Woman’s Home Companion; <q>Wooing of Wistaria</q>, Harper
               &amp; Bros.; <q>Heart of Hyacinth</q>, Harper &amp; Bros. and serial, Harper’s
               Weekly; <q>Love of Azalea</q>, Dodd, Meade &amp; Co. and serial in Bookman;
                  <q>Daughters of Nijo</q>, Macmillan Company; <q>Tama</q>, Harpers; <q>Japanese
                  Blossom</q>, Harpers; <q>Honorable Miss Moonlight</q>, Harpers; <q>Diara of
                  Delia</q>, Saturday Evening Post and Doubleday Page; <q>Me</q>, Anonymous—serial
               in Century Magazine and book; <q>Marion</q>, Anonymous—serial in Hearst’s Magazine
               and book; <q>Miss Spring Morning</q>, serial in Red Book; <q>Lend Me Your Title</q>,
               serial in MacLean’s; <q>Other People’s Troubles</q>, serial in Farm and Ranch.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
