<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="SunnySan6">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sunny-San [Part 5]</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl218"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna, Onoto</name></author>.
                   <publisher ref="org:Sovereign">Sovereign
                     Magazine</publisher>. <title level="a">Sunny-San [Part 5]</title>. <title level="j">Sovereign Magazine</title>, vol. <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>, no. <biblScope unit="issue">31</biblScope>, <date when="1922-05">June 1922</date>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from The Bodleian Library.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovelSerial"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-02-01" status="published">Encoded headings and corrected typo.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="published">Added citation from bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-06-11" status="published">Fixed typo.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-06-02" status="published">Proofed and encoded. Set to published.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-06-02" status="inProgress">Downloaded document from
            Google Drive and converted to TEI.</change>
         <change who="pers:SB2" status="empty" when="2020-08-15">Added brief notes
            statement.</change>
         <change who="pers:SB2" status="empty" when="2020-08-14">Added facsimile.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-31">changed title.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-24">changed title.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-06-30">Added next instalment
            link.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and
            exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl132 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Sunny-San6" prev="doc:SunnySan2" next="doc:SunnySan7">
      <pb n="76"/>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Sunny-San</head>
            <opener>
               <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>
            </opener>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>PROLOGUE</head>
            <p>It was the night of the Festival of the Full Moon, but Hirata, the proprietor of the
               House of a Thousand Joys, was infuriated, for was not Madame Mary Smiles, the famous
               dancer, lying dead among her robes? At her feet knelt her child, crushed and hurt by
               a grief that nothing could assuage, and it was for the sake of her mother’s honour
               that presently she stood a-tiptoe on the tight-rope, laughing at the sea of faces
               round her and throwing her kisses right and left. So charming was she that the Lord
               of Negato, amorous for this lovely child, tossed her a jewel and a handful of coin,
               which she cleverly caught on her fan but, acting under a sudden impish impulse, she
               suddenly threw them in her admirer’s face and, jumping to the ground, vanished into
               the tea-house.</p>
            <p>A party of English students visiting Japan had witnessed this scene and, learning
               that she was to be punished for her slight to the Japanese nobleman, they made a
               sudden raid on the tea-house and carried off the girl before Hirata’s lash could fall
               a second time upon her shoulders.</p>
            <p>These four students and their tutor then decided to adopt Sunny-san, the dancer’s
               child, whose father was a white man. They formed a syndicate, and together raised
               sufficient money to provide for Sunny during her lifetime.</p>
            <p>Soon a time came when the Englishmen had to return to their own country, and they
               regretfully departed, leaving Sunny in charge of a missionary. She begged them to
               take her with them, but the hardest moment came when she said good-bye to Jerry
               Hammond, who had been her faithful champion from the first. However, the ship
               carrying the Englishmen sailed away, and left a sorrowful Sunny languishing in
               Nagasaki.</p>
            <p>As time went on, Sunny’s friends across the sea reached a period where they thought
               of her as a charming and amusing episode of an idyllic summer in Japan. One bleak
               March day, Jerry was surprised to learn, on the telephone, that Sunny-san was in
               London and waiting instructions from the Syndicate. He hastily collected her other
               friends, and while they were discussing position Sunny entered. She had grown to be a
               charming young woman, and her friends, agreeably surprised, cannot do enough for her.
               Jerry cabled to the Professor to return from Canada to take charge of Sunny, but he
               was unable to do so, and she took up her abode in Jerry’s flat.</p>
            <p>Sunny has proposals from Monty, Bobs, and Jinx, but refuses them all. Acting on the
               advice of Hatton, Jerry’s valet, she decides to wait till Leap Year, and then ask
               Jerry to marry her. She learns then that Jerry is already engaged, but he goes home
               to break off his engagement, because he realizes that he loves Sunny. Two days later
               Jerry’s mother and <emph>fiancée</emph> arrive and drive Sunny out of the flat while
               Hatton is in a drunken sleep, and Jerry returns to find her gone.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>CHAPTER XIII</head>
            <p>He shot the questions at her frantically. Mrs. Hammond began to whimper, dabbing at
               her face with her handkerchief.</p>
            <p><q>For heaven’s sake, answer me. What have you done with Sunny?</q></p>
            <p><q>Jerry, how can I tell you? Jerry—Miss Falcon—er, and I—we—we thought it was for
                  your good. I didn’t realise that you c-cared so much about her, and I—and
                  we—Oh-h-h</q>— she broke down crying uncontrolledly—<q>we have driven that poor
                  little girl out—into the streets</q>.</p>
            <p><q>You what? What is that you say?</q></p>
            <p>He stared at his mother with a look of loathing.</p>
            <p><q>Jerry, I thought—we thought her bad and we—</q></p>
            <p><q>Bad! Sunny!  Bad! She didn’t know what the word meant. My
               <emph>God!</emph></q></p>
            <p>He leaped up the stairs, calling the girl’s name aloud, as if to satisfy himself that
               his mother’s tale must surely be false, but her empty room told its own tale, and
               halfway across the gallery he came upon Hatton. He kicked the valet awake, and the
               latter raised up, stuttering and blubbering, and extending with shaking hand the
               letter Sunny had left. The words leaped up at him and smote him to the soul. He did
               not see his mother. He did not hear her cries, imploring him not to go out like that.
               Blindly, his heart on fire, Jerry Hammond dashed out from his studio, and plunged
               into the darkening street, to begin his search for the lost Sunny, who had
               disappeared into that cesspool that is London.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>CHAPTER XIV</head>
            <p>Despite all that money and influence could do to aid in the search of the missing <pb n="77"/> girl, no trace of Sunny had been found since the day she passed through
               the door of the studio apartment and disappeared into the seething throngs
               outside.</p>
            <p>Every policeman, every private detective in the country, aided in that search, keen
               to earn the enormous rewards offered by her friends. Jerry’s entire fortune was at
               the disposal of Scotland Yard. Jinx had instructed them to <q>go the limit</q> as far
               as he was concerned. Bobs, his newspaper instinct keyed up to the highest tension,
               saw in every clue a promise of a solution, and <q>covered</q> the disappearance day
               and night. Young Monty, changed from the cheeriest of medical students to the most
               pessimistic and gloomy, developed a weird passion for the morgue, and spent hours
               hovering about that ghastly part of the hospital.</p>
            <p>The four young men met each night at Jerry’s studio and cast up their barren results.
               Jinx unashamedly and even noisily wept, the big tears splashing down his no longer
               ruddy cheeks. Jinx had honestly loved Sunny, and her loss was the first serious grief
               of his life.</p>
            <p>Monty hugged his head and ruminated over the darkest possibilities. He had suggested
               to the police that they drag certain parts of the Thames, and was indignant when they
               pointed out the impracticability of such a thing. In the spring the river was swollen
               to its highest, and flowing along at a great speed, it would have been impossible to
               find what Monty suggested.</p>
            <p>Jerry, of all her friends, had himself the least under command. He was still nearly
               crazed by the catastrophe, and unable to sleep or rest, taking little or no
               nourishment, frantically going from place to place. In his studio he could not keep
               still an instant, but paced up and down, as if half demented.</p>
            <p>Despite the fact that her son seemed scarcely conscious of her existence and
               practically ignored her, Jerry’s mother continued to remain in the flat, and away
               from the somewhat overpowering influence of his father, she was seeing a new light.
               Many a tear she dropped upon Jerry’s sketch-books, and she suffered the pang of one
               who had had the opportunity to help one she loved, and had withheld that sorely
               needed sympathy. For the first time, too, Jerry’s mother realised his right to choose
               his own love. In their anxiety to select for their son a suitable wife, they had
               overlooked his own wishes in the matter. Now Mrs. Hammond became poignantly aware of
               his deep love for this strange girl from Japan. She began to feel an unconscious
               tenderness toward the absent Sunny, and gradually became acquainted with the girl’s
               nature through the medium of the left behind treasures and friends. Sunny’s little
               mongrel dog, the canaries, the gold fish, the nailed up hole where she had fed the
               mice, her friend the <q>caretaker gentleman</q>, the liftboy, the butcher gentleman,
               the policeman on the beat who had never failed to return Sunny’s smiling greeting
               with a cheery <q>Top o’ the morning to yourself, miss</q>. Hatton—all these revealed
               more plainly than words could have told that hers was a sensitive and rare nature. In
               Hatton’s case, Mrs. Hammond found a problem upon her hands. The unfortunate valet
               blamed himself bitterly for Sunny’s going. He claimed that he had given his solemn
               word of honour to Sunny, and had broken that word, when he should have been there:
                  <q>Like a man, ma’am, hin the place of Mr. ‘Ammond, ma’am, to take care of Miss
                  Sunny</q>.</p>
            <p>Far from reproving the man, the conscience-stricken Mrs. Hammond wept with him, and
               asked timid questions about the absent one.</p>
            <p>After a long, sniffling pause, Hatton said one day:</p>
            <p><q>Begging your pardon, ma’am, I’m thinking that I don’t deserve to work for Mr.
                  ‘Ammond any longer, but I ‘avent the ‘eart to speak to ‘im at this time, and if
                  you’ll be so kind to hexplain things to ‘im, I’ll betake myself to some hother
                  abode</q>.</p>
            <p><q>My good man, I am sure that even Mr. Jerry would not blame you. I am the sole one
                  at fault. I take the full blame. I acknowledge it. I would not have you or anyone
                  else share my guilt, and, Hatton, I <emph>want</emph>  to be punished. Your
                  conscience, I am sure, is clear, but it would make us all very happy, and I am
                  sure it would make—Sunny</q>—she <pb n="78"/> spoke the word
                  hesitatingly—<q>happy, too, if—if—well, if, my good Hatton, you were to turn over
                  a new leaf, and sign the pledge. Drink, I feel sure, is your worst enemy. You must
                  overcome it, Hatton, or it will overcome you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Hi will, ma’am. Hi’ll do that. If you’ll pardon me now, Hi’ll step right out and
                  sign the pledge. I know just where to go, if you’ll pardon me</q>.</p>
            <p>Hatton did know just where to go. He crossed the park to the east side and came to
               the brightly lighted Salvation Army barracks. A meeting was in progress, and a fiery
               tongued young woman was exhorting all the sinners of the world to come to glory.
               Hatton was fascinated by the groans and loud Amens that came from that chorus of
               human wreckage. Pushing nearer to the front, he came under the penetrating eye of the
               Salvation captain. She hailed him as a <q>brother</q>, and there was something so
               unswervingly pure in her direct gaze that it had the effect of magnetising
               Hatton.</p>
            <p>We leave him then, the pledge having been taken, marching forth from the barracks
               with the Salvation Army, his head thrown up, and singing loudly of glory.</p>
            <p>On the third day after the disappearance of Sunny Professor Timothy Barrowes arrived
               in London with the dinornis skeleton of the quaternary period, dug up from the clay
               of the Red Deer cliffs of Canada. This precious find was duly transported to the
               Museum of Natural History, where it was set up by the skilled hands of workmen, who
               were zealots even as the little man who nagged and adjured them as he had the
               excavators on the Red Deer River. So absorbed, in fact, was Professor Barrowes by his
               fascinating employment, that he left his beloved fossil only when the pressing
               necessity of further funds from his friend and financial agent (Jerry had raised the
               money to finance the dinornis) necessitated his calling upon Jerry Hammond, who had
               made no response to his latter telegrams and letters.</p>
            <p>Accordingly Professor Barrowes wended his way from the museum to Jerry’s studio.
               Here, so enthused and happy over the success of his trip, he failed to notice the
               abnormal condition of Jerry, whose listless hot hand dropped from his, and whose eye
               went roving absently above the head of his volubly chattering friend. It was only
               after the restless and continued pacing of the miserable Jerry and the failure to
               respond to questions put to him continued for some time, that Professor Barrowes was
               suddenly apprized that all was not well with his friend. He stopped midway in a long
               speech in which words like Mesozoic, Triassic and Jurassic prevailed and snapped his
               glasses suddenly upon his nose.</p>
            <p><q>Come! Come! What is it? What is the trouble, lad?</q></p>
            <p>A tortured cry broke from Jemmy’s lips.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, for God’s sake, Professor Barrowes, why did you not come when I asked you to?
                     Sunny—<emph>Oh, my God!</emph></q></p>
            <p>Professor Barrowes had Jerry’s hand gripped closely in his own, and the disjointed
               story came out at last.</p>
            <p>Sunny had come! Sunny had gone! He loved Sunny! He could not live without Sunny—but
               Sunny had gone! They had turned her out into the streets—his own mother and Miss
               Falconer.</p>
            <p>For the first time, it may be said, since his discovery of the famous fossil of the
               Red Deer River, Professor Barrowes’s mind left his beloved dinornis. He came back
               solidly to earth, shot back by the calling need of Jerry. Now the man of science was
               wide awake, and an upheaval was taking place within him. The words of his first
               telegram to Jerry rattled through his head just then: <q>The dinornis more important
                  than Sunny</q>. Now as he looked down on the bowed head of the boy for whom he
               cherished almost a father’s love, Professor Barrowes knew that all the dried-up
               fossils of all the ages were as a handful of worthless dust as compared with this
               single living girl.</p>
            <p>By main force Professor Barrowes made Jerry lie down on that couch, and himself
               served him the food humbly prepared by his heartbroken mother, who told Jerry’s
               friend with a quivering lip that she felt sure he would not wish to take it from his
               mother’s hands.</p>
            <p>There was no going out for Jerry on that night. His protestations fell on deaf ears,
                  <pb n="79"/> and as a further precaution, Professor Barrowes secured possession of
               the key of the flat. Only when the professor pointed out to him the fact that a
               breakdown on his part would mean the cessation of his search, would Jerry finally
               submit to the older man taking his place temporarily. And so, at the telephone, which
               rang constantly all of that evening, Professor Barrowes took command. A thousand
               clues were everlastingly turning up. These were turned over to Jinx and Bobs, the
               former flying from one part of the city and country to another in his big car, and
               the latter, with an army of newspaper men helping him, and given full license by his
               paper, influenced by the elder Hammond and Potter. Finally, Professor Barrowes,
               having given certain instructions to turn telephone calls over to Monty in Bobs’
               apartment, sat down to Jerry’s disordered work-table, and glasses perched on the end
               of his nose, he sorted out the disordered mail. The afternoon letters still lay
               unopened, tossed down in despair by Jerry, when he failed to find that characteristic
               writing that he knew was Sunny’s.</p>
            <p>But now Professor Barrowes’ head had suddenly jerked forward. His chin came out
               curiously, and his eyes blinked in amazement behind his glasses. He set them on
               firmer, fiercely, and slowly reread that two-line epistle. The hand holding the paper
               shook, but the eyes behind the glasses were bright.</p>
            <p><q>Jerry, come hither, young man!</q> he growled, his dry old face quivering up with
               something that looked comically like a smile glaring through threatened tears.
                  <q>Read that</q>.</p>
            <p>Across the table Jerry reached over and took the letter from the famous steel magnate
               of London. He read it slowly, dully, and then with a sense as of something breaking
               in his head and heart. Every word of those two lines sank like balm into his
               comprehension and consciousness. Then it seemed that a surge of blood rushed through
               his being, blinding him. The world rocked for Jerry Hammond. He saw a single star
               gleaming in a firmament that was all black. Down into immeasurable depths of space
               sank Jerry Hammond.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>CHAPTER XV</head>
            <p>Sunny, after she left Jerry’s apartment, might be likened to a little wounded wild
               thing, who has trailed off with broken wing. She had never consciously committed a
               wrong act. Motherless, worse than fatherless, young, innocent, lovely, how should she
               fare in a land whose ways were as foreign to that from which she had come as if she
               had been transplanted to a new planet?</p>
            <p>As she turned into the main street, with its overloaded buses, crammed with the
               home-going workers of London, she had no sense of direction and no clear purpose in
               mind. All she felt was that numb sense of pain at her heart and the impulse to get as
               far away as possible from the man she loved. Swept along by a moving, setting throng
               that pressed and pushed and shoved and elbowed by her, Sunny had a sick sense of home
               longing, an inexpressible yearning to escape from all this turmoil and noise, this
               mad rushing and pushing and panting through life that seemed to spell London. She
               sensed the fact that she was in the Land of Barbarians, where everyone was racing and
               leaping and screaming in an hysteria of speed. Noise, noise, incessant noise and
               movement—that was London. No one stopped to think; no polite words were uttered to
               the stranger. It was all a chaos, a madhouse, wherein dark figures rushed by like
               shadows in the night and little children played in the mud of the streets.</p>
            <p>The charming, laughing, pretty days in the shelter of the studio of her friend had
               passed into this nightmare of noise, where all seemed ugly, cruel and sinister. Life
               in London was not the charming kindly thing Sunny had supposed. Beauty indeed she had
               brought in her heart with her, and that, though she knew it not, was why she had seen
               only the beautiful, but now, even for her, it had all changed. She had looked into
               faces full of hatred and malice; she had listened to words that whipped worse than
               the lash of Nirata.</p>
            <p>To Kuonnon, the Goddess of Mercy, in the streets of the European city, the girl of
               Japan sent out her petition:</p>
            <pb n="80"/>
            <p><q>Oh, Kuonnon, sweet Lady of Mercy, permit the spirit of my honourable mother to
                  walk with me through these dark and noisy streets</q>.</p>
            <p>The shining Goddess of Mercy, trailing her robes among the million stars in the
               heavens above, surely heard that tiny petition, for certain it is that something warm
               and comforting swept over the breast of the tired Sunny. We know that faith will
                  <q>remove mountains</q>. Sunny’s faith in her mother’s spirit caused her to feel
               assured that it walked by her side. The Japanese believe that we can think our dead
               alive, and if we are pure and worthy, we may indeed recall them.</p>
            <p>It came to pass, that after many hours that she stopped before a brightly lighted
               window, within which cakes and confections were enticingly displayed, and from the
               cellar of which warm odours of cooking were wafted to the famished girl. Sunny’s
               youth and buoyant health responded to that claim. Her feet, in the unaccustomed
               shoes—in Japan she had worn only sandals and clogs—were sore and extremely weary from
               the long walk, and a sense of intense exhaustion added to that pang of emptiness
               within.</p>
            <p>By the baker’s window, therefore, on the dingy suburban street, leaned Sunny, staring
               in hungrily at the food so near and yet so far away. She asked herself in her quaint
               way:</p>
            <p><q>What I are now to do? My honourable insides are ask for food</q>.</p>
            <p>She answered her own question at once.</p>
            <p><q>I will ask the advice of first person I meet. He will tell me</q>.</p>
            <p>The streets were in a semi-deserted condition, such as follows after the home-going
               throngs have been tucked away into their respective abodes. There was a cessation of
               traffic, only the passing of the trains overhead breaking the hush of early night
               that comes even in the city of London. It was now fifteen minutes to nine, and Sunny
               had had nothing to eat since her scant breakfast.</p>
            <p>Kuonnon, her mother’s spirit, providence—call it what we may—suffered it that the
               first person whom Sunny was destined to meet should be Katy Clarry, a shop girl by
               trade. She was crossing the street, with her few small packages, revealing her
               pitiful night marketing at adjacent small shops, when Sunny accosted her.</p>
            <p><q>Aexcuse me. I lig’ ask you question, please</q>, said Sunny with timid
               politeness.</p>
            <p><q>Whell?</q></p>
            <p>Miss Clarry, her grey, clear eye sweeping the face of Sunny in one comprehensive
               glance that took her <q>number</q>, stopped short at the curb, and waited for the
               question.</p>
            <p><q>I are hungry</q>, said Sunny simply, <q>and I have no money and no house in which
                  to sleep these night. What I can do?</q></p>
            <p><q>Lord!</q> Katy’s grey eyes flew wider. The girl before her seemed as far from
               being a beggar as anyone the east side girl had ever seen. Something in the wistful,
               lovely face looking at her in the dark street tightened that cord that was all mother
               in the breast of Katy Clarry. After a moment:</p>
            <p><q>Are you stoney broke then? Out of work? You don’t look’s if you could be. What you
                  doin’ on the streets? You ain’t—? No, you ain’t. I needn’t insult you by askin’
                  that. Where’s your home, girl?</q></p>
            <p><q>I got no home</q>, said Sunny, in a very faint voice. A subtle feeling was
               stealing over the tired Sunny, and the whiteness of her cheeks, the drooping of her
               eyes, apprised Katy of her condition.</p>
            <p><q>Say, don’t be fallin’ whatever you do. You don’t want no copper to get ‘is hands
                  on you. You come along with me. I ain’t got much, but you’re welcome to share what
                  I got. I’ll take care of you till you get a job. Heh! Get a grip on yourself.
                  There. That’s better. Hold on to me. I’ll put them packages under this arm. We
                  ain’t got far to walk. Steady now. We don’t want no copper to say we’re full,
                  because we ain’t</q>.</p>
            <p>Katy led the trembling Sunny along the dirty, dingy avenue to one of those melancholy
               side streets of the upper east side. They came to a house whose sad exterior
               proclaimed what was within. Here Katy applied her latch key, and in the dark and
               odorous halls they found their way up four flights of stairs. Katy’s room was at the
               far end of a long bare landing, and its dimensions <pb n="81"/> were little more than
               the shining kitchen range of the studio apartment.</p>
            <p>Katy struck a match, lit a kerosene lamp, and attached to the one half-plugged gas
               jet a tube at the end of which was a small gas-ring. Sunny, sitting helplessly on the
               bed, was too dazed and weary to hold her position for long, and at Katy’s sharp:
                  <q>Hi, there, lie down</q>, she subsided back upon the bed, sighing with relief as
               her exhausted body felt the comfort of Katy’s hard little bed. From sundry places
               Katy drew forth a frying pan, a pitcher of water, a tiny kettle and a teapot. She put
               two knives and forks and spoons on the table, two cracked plates and two cups. She
               peeled a single potato, and added it to the two sausages frying on the pan. She
               chattered along as she worked, partly to hide her own feelings, and partly to set the
               girl at her ease. But indeed Sunny was far from feeling an embarrassment such as Katy
               in her place might have felt. The world is full of two kinds of people: those who
               serve, and those who are served, and to the latter family Sunny belonged. Not the
               lazy, wilful parasites of life, but the helpless children, whom we love to care for.
               Katy, glancing with a maternal eye, ever and anon at the so sad and lovely face upon
               her pillow was curiously touched and animated with a desire to help her.</p>
            <p><q>You’re dog-tired, ain’t you? How long you been out of work? I always feel more
                  tired when I’m out o’ work and looking for a job, than when I got one, though it
                  ain’t my idea of a rest exactly to stand on your feet all day long shoving out
                  things you can’t afford to have yourself to folks who mostly just want to look ‘em
                  over. Of course, if I were in one of them big stores up West, I could give a
                  customer the laugh when the bell sounded for closin’, but you can do no such thing
                  here. We’re still in the pioneer stage up here. I expect you’re more used to the
                  Bond Street shops. You look it, but, say, I never got a look in at one of them
                  jobs. They favour educated girls, and I ain’t packed with learning, I can tell
                  you</q>.</p>
            <p>Sunny said:</p>
            <p><q>You loog good to me</q>—a favourite expression of Jerry’s, and something in her
               accent and the earnestness with which she said it warmed Katy, who laughed and
               said:</p>
            <p><q>Oh, go on. I ain’t much on looks neither. There, now. Draw up. Dinner is served.
                  Stay where you are on the bed. Drop your feet over. I ain’t got but the one chair,
                  and I’ll have it meself, thank you, don’t mention it</q>.</p>
            <p>Katy pushed the table beside the bed, drew her own chair to the other side, set the
               kettle on the jet which the frying pan had released and proudly surveyed her
               labour.</p>
            <p><q>Not much, but looks pretty good to me. If there’s one thing I love it is a hot
                  dog</q>.</p>
            <p>She put on Sunny’s plate the largest of the two sausages and three-quarters of the
               potato, cut her a generous slice of bread and poured most of the gravy on her plate,
               saying:</p>
            <p><q>I always say sausage gravy beats anything in the butter line. Tea’ll be done in a
                  minute, dearie. Ain’t got but one burner. Lord, I wisht I had one of them two
                  deckers that you can cook a whole meal at once with. Ever seen ‘em? How’s your
                  dog?</q></p>
            <p><q>Dog?</q></p>
            <p><q>Sausage, dearie?</q></p>
            <p><q>How it is good</q>, said Sunny with simple eloquence. <q>I thang you how
               much</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Don’t mention it. You’re welcome. You’d do the same for me if I was busted. I
                  always say one working girl should help the other when the other is out of work
                  and broke. There’s unity in strength</q>, quoted Katy, with conviction. <q>Have
                  some more—do! Dip your bread in the gravy. Pretty good, ain’t it, if I do say it
                  who shouldn’t</q>.</p>
            <p><q>It mos’ nices’ food are ever taste</q>, declared Sunny earnestly.</p>
            <p>While the tea was going into the cups:</p>
            <p><q>My name’s Katy Clarry. What’s yours?</q> asked Katy, a sense of well-being and
               good humour toward the world flooding her warm being.</p>
            <p><q>Sunny</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Sunny! That’s a queer name. Ain’t it pretty? What’s your other name?</q></p>
            <p><q>Sindicutt</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Sounds kind of foreign. What are <pb n="82"/> you anyway? You ain’t British—at
                  least you don’t look it or talk it</q>, said the native-born American girl with
               scorn. <q>Meaning no offence, you understand, but—well—you just don’t look like the
                  rest of us. You ain’t a Dago or a Sheeny. I can see that, and you ain’t a Hun
                  neither. Are you a Frenchy? You got queer kind of eyes—meaning no offence, for
                  personally I think them lovely, I really do. I seen actresses with no better eyes
                  than you got</q>.</p>
            <p>Katy shot her questions at Sunny, without waiting for an answer. Sunny smiled
               sadly.</p>
            <p><q>Katy, I are sowry thad I am not be English girl. I are born ad Japan—</q></p>
            <p><q><emph>You</emph> ain’t no Chink. You can’t tell me no such thing as that. I wasn’t
                  born yesterday. What are you, anyway? Where do you come from? Are you a royal
                  princess in disguise?</q></p>
            <p><q>No, I are not princess</q>, said Sunny sadly. <q>I not all Japanese, Katy, jos
                  liddle bit. Me? I got three kind of blood on my insides. I sawry thad my ancestors
                  put them there. I are Japanese and Russian and English</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Gee! You’re what we call a mongrel. Meaning no offence. You can’t help yourself.
                  Personally I stand up first for the home-made English article but I ain’t got no
                  prejudice against no one. No one’ll be the wiser. You can trust me not to open my
                  mouth to a living soul about it. What you’ve confided in me about being partly
                  Chink is just as if you had put the inflamnation in a tomb. And it ain’t going to
                  make the least bit of difference between us. Try one of them crackers. Sop it in
                  your tea now you’re done with your gravy. Pretty good, ain’t it?</q></p>
            <p><q>Katy, to-night I are going to tell you some things about me, bi-cause I know you
                  are my good frien’ now forever. I lig’ your kind eye, Katy</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Go on! You’re kiddin’ me, Sunny. If I had eyes like yours, it’d be a different
                  matter. But I like the idea of having you for a friend just the same. I ain’t had
                  a chum since I don’t know when. If you knew what them girls was like in my
                  shop—well, I’m not talkin’ about no one behind their backs, but, say—Sunny, I
                  could tell you a thing or two’d make your hair stand on end. And as for tellin’ me
                  about your own past, say if you’ll tell me yours, I’ll tell you mine. I always say
                  that every girl has some tragedy or other in her life. Mine began in the slums. It
                  ain’t nothing to brag about, but it’s heaven compared with what’s down in my old
                  home. I used to live in that gutter part of the town where God’s good air is even
                  begrudged you, and where all the dirty forriners and Chinks—meanin’ no offence,
                  dearie, and I’ll say for the Chinks, that compared with some of them Russian
                  Jews—you’re Russian too, ain’t you, but I don’t mean no offence! Take it from me,
                  Sunny, some of them forriners—I call them just that to avoid givin’ offence—are
                  just exactly like lice, and the smells down there! Well, the rotten dust got into
                  the lungs and the spine of them all. Father went first. Then mother. Lord only
                  knows how they got it—doctor said it was from the streets, germs that someone
                  maybe dumped out and come flyin’ up into our place that was the only clean spot in
                  the tenement house. I’ll say that for my mother. There was two kids left besides
                  me. I was the oldes’, and not much on age at that, but I got me a job chasin’
                  around for a millinery shop, and I did my best by the kids when I got home nights;
                  but the cards was all stacked against me, Sunny, and when that infantile
                  parallysus come along the first to be took was my baby brother, and me li-little
                  s-sister she come down with it, too, and—Ah-h-h-h—</q></p>
            <p>Katy’s head went down on the table, and she sobbed tempestuously. Sunny, unable to
               speak the words of comfort that welled up in her heart, could only put her arms
               around Katy, and mingle her tears with hers. Katy removed a handkerchief from the top
               of her blouse, dabbed her eyes fiercely, shared the little ball with Sunny, and then
               thrust it down the neck of her blouse again. Bravely she smiled at Sunny again.</p>
            <p><q>There you got the story of the Clarry’s of London. You can’t beat it for—for
                  tragedy, now can you? So spiel away at your own story, Sunny. Don’t spare me,
                  kiddy. I’m braced for anything in this r-rotten world</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>CHAPTER XVI</head>
            <p>It was well for Sunny that her new friend was endowed with a generous and belligerent
               nature. Having secured for Sunny a position at the Bamberger Emporium, Katy’s loyalty
               to her friend was not dampened when on the third day Sunny was summarily discharged.
               Hands on hips, Katy flew furiously to her friend’s defence, and for the benefit of
               her brother and sister workers, she relieved herself loudly of all her pent-up rage
               of the months. In true Union style, Katy marched out with Sunny. The excuse for
               discharging Sunny was that she did not write well enough to fill out the sales slips
               properly. Nasty as the true reason was, there is no occasion to set forth the details
               here.</p>
            <p>Suffice it to say that the two girls, both rosy from excitement and wrath, arm and
               arm marched independently forth from the Emporium, Katy loudly asserting that she
               would sue for her half week’s pay, and Sunny anxiously drawing her along, her breath
               coming and going with the fright she had had.</p>
            <p>Here they were indeed, back in the small ugly room of that fourth floor, sitting, the
               one on the ricketty chair, and the other on the side of the hard bed. But the eyes of
               youth are veiled in sun and rose. They see nor feel not the filth of the world. Sunny
               and Katy, out of a job, with scarcely enough money between them to keep body and soul
               together, were yet able to laugh at each other and exchange jokes over the position
               in which they found themselves.</p>
            <p>After they had <q>chewed the rag</q>, as Katy expressively termed it, for awhile,
               that brisk young person removed her hat, rolled up her sleeves, and declared she
               would do the <q>family wash</q>.</p>
            <p><q>It’s too late now</q>, said Katy, <q>to job hunt this morning. So I’ll do the
                  wash, and you waltz over across the street and do the marketin’. We can boil some
                  of them bones and get a good soup. I always say soup is just as fillin’ as
                  anything else, especially if you put a onion in it, and have a bit of bread to sop
                  it up with, and I got the onion all right. So cheer up, we’ll soon be dead, and
                  the worst is yet to come</q>.</p>
            <p>Sunny was standing now by the bureau. A very thoughtful expression had come to
               Sunny’s face, and she opened the top drawer and drew out her little package.</p>
            <p><q>Katy</q>, she said softly, <q>here are some little thing ad these package, which
                  mebbe it goin’ to help us</q>.</p>
            <p>Sunny was picking at the red silk cord. Lovingly she unwrapped the Japanese paper.
               The touch of her fingers on her mother’s things was a caress and had all the
               reverence that the Japanese child pays in tribute to a departed parent.</p>
            <p><q>These honourable things belong my mother</q>, said Sunny gently. <q>She have give
                  them to me when she know she got die. See, Katy, this are <foreign xml:lang="ja">kakemona</foreign>. It very old, me be one tousan’ year ole. It belong at
                  grade Prince of Satsuma. Thas my mother ancestor. This <foreign xml:lang="ja">kakemona</foreign>, <unclear reason="illegible">he</unclear> are so ole as
                  those ancestor</q>, said Sunny reverently.</p>
            <p><q>Old. I should say it is. Looks as if it belongs in a tomb. You couldn’t pawn
                  nothing like that</q>. What’s that you got there, Sunny?</p>
            <p><q>That are a letter, Katy. My mother gave me those letter. She say that some day
                  mebbe I are need some frien’. Then I must put those letter at post office box, or
                  I must take those letter in my hand to thad man it are write to. He are frien’ to
                  me, my mother have said</q>.</p>
            <p>Katy grabbed the letter, disbelieving her eyes when she read the name inscribed in
               the thin Japanese hand. It was addressed both in English and Japanese, and the name
               was Stephen Holt Wainwright.</p>
            <p><q>Someone hold me up</q>, cried Katy. <q>I’m about to faint dead away</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, Katy, do not be dead away! Oh, Katy, do not do those faint. He are those
                  cracker. I am not so hongry as you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>My Lord! You poor ignorant little kid, don’t you reckernize when a fellow is
                  fainting with pure unadulterated joy? How long have you had that letter?</q></p>
            <p><q>Four year now</q>, said Sunny sadly, thinking of the day when her mother had
               placed it in her hand, and of the look on the face of that mother.</p>
            <p><q>Why did you never mail it?</q></p>
            <p><q>I was await, Katy. I are not need help. I have four and five good frien’ <pb n="84"/> to me then, and I do not need nuther one; but now I are beggar again.
                  I nod got those frien’s no more. I need those other one</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Do you know who this letter is addressed to, dearie?</q></p>
            <p><q>No, Katy, I cannot read so big a name. My mother say he will be frien’ to me
                  always</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Sunny, I pity you for your ignorance, but I don’t hold it against you. You was
                  born that way. Why a child could read that name. Goodness knows I never got far,
                  yet I <emph>hope</emph>  I’m able to read that. It says as plain as the nose on
                  your face, Sunny: Stephen Holt Wainwright. Now that’s the name of one of the
                  biggest guns in the country. He’s a financier, or was and is, and he’s so rich
                  that he has to hire twenty or fifty cashiers to count his income that rolls in
                  upon him. If you weren’t so ignorant, Sunny, you’d a read about him in the paper.
                  Gee! his picture’s in nearly every day, and pictures of his luxurious home and
                  yacht and horses and wife. They call him ‘The Man of Steel,’ because he owns most
                  of the steel in the world, and because he’s got a mug—a face—on him like a steel
                  trap. That’s what I’ve heard and read, though I’ve never met the gentleman. I
                  expect to, however, very soon, seeing he’s a friend of yours</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Katy, this letter are written by my mother ad the Japanese language. Mebbe those
                  Fin-an-cier kinnod read them. What I shall do?</q></p>
            <p><q>What you shall do, baby mine? Did you think I was goin’ to let precious freight
                  like that go into any post box. Perish the idea, lovey. You and me are going to
                  waltz downtown to his office, and we ain’t going to do no walking, what’s more.
                  The Tube for little us. Get your hat on now, and don’t answer back
               neither</q>.</p>
            <p>On the way downstairs she gave a final stern order to Sunny.</p>
            <p>Laughing merrily the two girls, with music in their souls, danced up the street,
               their empty stomachs and their lost jobs forgotten. When they reached the Subway,
               Katy seized Sunny’s hand, and they raced down the steps just as the South Ferry train
               pulled in.</p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>CHAPTER XVII</head>
            <p>That was a long and exciting ride for Sunny. Above the roar of the rushing train Katy
               shouted in her ear. Perfectly at home in the Tube, Katy did not let a little thing
               like mere noise deter the steady flow of her tongue. The gist of her remarks came
               always back to what Sunny was to do when they arrived; how she was to look; how
               speak. She was to bear in mind that she was going into the presence of a great man,
               and she was to be neither too fresh nor yet too humble. Englishmen, high and low, so
               Katy averred, liked folks that had a kick to them, but not too much of a kick.</p>
            <p>Sunny was to make application in both their names. If there were no vacancies in the
               financier’s office, then she would delicately suggest that the financier could make
               such a vacancy. Such things were done within Katy’s own experience.</p>
            <p>Katy had no difficulty in locating the monstrous office building, and she led Sunny
               along to the elevator with the experienced air. Sunny held tight to her arm as they
               made the breathless ascent.</p>
            <p>It was noon hour, and Katy and Sunny followed several girls returning from lunch,
               through the main entrance of the offices.</p>
            <p>A girl at a desk in the reception hall stopped them from penetrating farther into the
               offices by calling out:</p>
            <p><q>No admission there. Who do you want to see? Name, please</q>.</p>
            <p>Katy swung around on her heel, and recognising a kindred spirit in the girl at the
               desk, she favoured her with an equally haughty and glassy stare. Then in a very
               superior voice, Katy replied:</p>
            <p><q>We are friends of the Financier. Kindly announce us, if you please</q>.</p>
            <p>A grin slipped over the face of the maiden at the desk, and she shoved a pad of paper
               toward Katy.</p>
            <p>Opposite the word <q>Name</q> on the pad, Katy wrote, <q>Miss Sindicutt</q>. Opposite
               the word: <q>Business</q> she wrote <q>Private and personal and intimate</q>.</p>
            <p>The girl at the desk glanced amusedly at the pad, tore the first sheet off, pushed a
               button which summoned an office boy, to whom she handed the slip of paper. With one
               eye turned appraisingly upon <pb n="85"/> the girls, he went off backwards,
               whistling, and disappeared through the little swinging gate that opened apparently
               into the great offices beyond.</p>
            <p><q>I beg your pardon?</q> said Katy to the girl at the desk.</p>
            <p><q>I didn’t say nothing</q>, returned the surprised maiden.</p>
            <p><q>I thought you said ‘Be seated.’ I will, thank you. Don’t mention it</q>—and Katy
               grinned with malicious politeness on the discomfited young person, who patted her
               coiffure with assumed disdain.</p>
            <p>Katy meanwhile disposed herself on the long bench, drew Sunny down beside her, and
               proceeded to scrutinise and comment on all passers through the main reception hall
               into the offices within.</p>
            <p>A man had come into the reception room from the main entrance. He started to cross
               the room directly to the little swinging door, then stopped to speak to a clerk at a
               wicket window. Something about the sternness of his look, an air savouring almost of
               austerity aroused the imp in Katy.</p>
            <p><q>Well, look who’s here</q>, she whispered behind her hand to Sunny. <q>Now watch
                  little Katy</q>.</p>
            <p>As the man turned from the window, and proceeded toward the door, Katy shot out her
               foot, and the man abstractedly stumbled against it. He looked down at the girl,
               impudently staring him out of countenance, and frowned at her exaggerated:</p>
            <p><q>I <emph>beg</emph> your pardon!</q></p>
            <p>Then his glance turning irritably from Katy, rested upon Sunny’s slightly shocked
               face. He stopped abruptly, standing perfectly still for a moment, staring down at the
               girl. Then, with a muttered apology, Mr. Wainwright turned and went swiftly through
               the swinging door.</p>
            <p><q>Well, of <emph>all</emph> the nerve!</q> said Katy. Then to the girl at the
               desk:</p>
            <p><q>Who was his nibs?</q></p>
            <p><q>Why, your friend, of course. I’m surprised you didn’t recognise him</q>, returned
               the girl sweetly.</p>
            <p><q>Him—Mr. Wainwright</q>.</p>
            <p>The boy had returned, and thrusting his head over the short gate sang out:</p>
            <p><q>This way, please, la-adies!</q></p>
            <p>Katy and Sunny followed the boy across an office where many girls and men were
               working at desks. At a door marked <q>Miss Hollowell, Private</q>, the boy knocked. A
               voice within bade him <q>Come in</q>, and the two girls were admitted.</p>
            <p>Miss Hollowell, a clear-eyed young woman of the clean-cut modern type of the
               efficient woman executive, looked up from her work and favoured them with a pleasant
               smile.</p>
            <p><q>What can I do for you?</q> The question was directed at Katy, but her trained eye
               went from Katy to Sunny, and there remained in speculative inquiry.</p>
            <p><q>We have come to call upon the Financier</q>, said Katy, <q>on important and
                  private business</q>.</p>
            <p>Miss Hollowell smiled indulgently at Katy’s words.</p>
            <p><q><emph>I</emph> see. Well now, I’ll speak for Mr. Wainwright. What can we do for
                  you?</q></p>
            <p><q>Nothing. <emph>You</emph> can’t do nothing</q>, said Katy. She was not to be
               beguiled by the smile of this superior young person. <q>My friend here—Miss
                  Sindicutt—has a personal letter for Financier Wainwright, and she’s takin’ my
                  advice not to let it out of her hands into any, but his</q>.</p>
            <p><q>I’m awfully sorry, because Mr. Wainwright is very busy, and can’t possibly see
                  you. I believe I will answer the purpose as well. I’m Mr. Wainwright’s
                  secretary</q>.</p>
            <p><q>We don’t want to speak to no secretary</q>, said Katy.</p>
            <p>Miss Hollowell laughed.</p>
            <p><q>Oh, very well then. Perhaps some other time, but we’re especially busy to-day, so
                  I’m going to ask you to excuse us. <emph>Good</emph>-day</q>.</p>
            <p>She turned back to the papers on her desk, her pencil poised above a sheet of
               estimates.</p>
            <p>Katy pushed Sunny forward, and in dumb show signified that she should speak. Miss
               Hollowell glanced up and regarded the girl with singular attention. Something in the
               expression, something in the back of the secretary’s mind that concerned Japan, which
               this strange girl had now <pb n="86"/> mentioned caused her to wait quietly for her
               to finish the sentence. Sunny held out the letter, and Miss Hollowell saw that fine
               script upon the envelope, with the Japanese letters down the side.</p>
            <p><q>This are a letter from Japan</q>, said Sunny. <q>If you please I will lig’ to give
                  those to Fin—Thad is so big a name for me to say</q>. The last was spoken
               apologetically and brought a sympathetic smile from Miss Hollowell.</p>
            <p><q>Can’t I read it. I’m sure I can give you what information you want as well as Mr.
                  Wainwright can</q>.</p>
            <p><q>It are wrote in Japanese</q>, said Sunny. <q>You cannot read that same.
                     <emph>Please</emph> you let me take it to the gentleman</q>.</p>
            <p>Miss Hollowell, with a smile, arose at that plea. She crossed the room and tapped on
               the door bearing the Senator’s name.</p>
            <p>Even in a city where offices of the magnates are sometimes as sumptuously furnished
               as drawing-rooms, the great room of Mr. Wainwright was distinctive. The floor was
               strewn with priceless Persian and Chinese rugs, which harmonised with the remarkable
               walls, panelled half way up with mahogany, the upper part of which was hung with
               masterpieces of the famous painters, whose work the steel magnate especially
               patronised. Stephen Wainwright was seated at a big mahogany desk table, that was at
               the far end of the room. He was not working. His elbows on the desk, he seemed to be
               staring out before him in a mood of strange abstraction. His face, somewhat stony in
               expression, with straight grey eyes that had a curious trick when turned on one of
               seeming to pin themselves in an appraising stare; his iron grey hair and the grey
               suit which he invariably wore had given him the name of <q>The Man of Steel</q>. Miss
               Hollowell, with her slightly professional smile, laid the slip of paper on the desk
               before him.</p>
            <p><q>A Miss Sindicutt. She has a letter for you—a letter from Japan she says. She
                  wishes to deliver it in person</q>.</p>
            <p>At the word <q>Japan</q> he came slightly out of his abstraction, stared at the slip
               of paper, and shook his head.</p>
            <p><q>Don’t know the name</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Yes, I knew you didn’t; but, still, I think I’d see her if I were you</q>.</p>
            <p><q>Very well. Send her in</q>.</p>
            <p>Miss Hollowell at the door nodded brightly to Sunny, but stayed Katy, who
               triumphantly was pushing forward.</p>
            <p><q>Sorry, but Mr. Wainwright will see just Miss Sindicutt alone</q>.</p>
            <p>Sunny went in alone. She crossed the room hesitantly and stood by the desk of the
               steel magnate, waiting for him to speak to her. He remained unmoving, half turned
               about in his seat, staring stolidly at the girl before him. If a ghost had arisen
               suddenly in his path, Senator Wainwright could not have felt a greater agitation.
               After a long pause, he found his voice, murmuring:</p>
            <p><q>I beg your pardon. Be seated, please</q>.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="paratext">
            <p><emph>Another instalment of this novel will appear in the next issue of the Sovereign
                  Magazine.</emph></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>