<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Tama1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tama</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl135"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Watanna,
                           Onoto</name></author>. <title level="m">Tama</title>. Illustrated by
                           <author role="illustrator"><name ref="pers:GK1">Genjiro
                           Kataoka</name></author>. <publisher ref="org:Harper">Harper and
                           Brothers</publisher>, <date when="1910">1910</date>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from the Thomas Fisher Canadiana Collection on the
                           Internet Archive.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySourcePublished" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovel"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-09-27" status="published">Notes and translations under
            review by Yuki Matsumoto.</change>
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-09-21" status="readyForProof">Proof in progress. I do not
            know Japanese, so all editorial notes under resp=pers:LW1 are based on online research
            and may be incorrect.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2022-04-30">Added facsimile.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and
            exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl135 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Tama1">
      <pb n="frontcover"/>
      <body>
         <head>Tama</head>
         <note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Some Japanese words and phrases may not yet be
            translated with an accompanying editorial note. This is an ongoing process.</note>
         <pb n="0"/>
         <head>Tama</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>
            <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:GK1">Genjiro Kataoka</name></byline>
         </opener>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>I</head>
            <p>Fukui was in an unwonted state of excitement. For days the people had talked of but
               one event. Even the small boys, perilously astraddle the bamboo poles, the scullery
               wenches of the kitchen, the very mendicants of the street, the highest and lowest of
               the citizens of Fukui talked of the coming of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >O-Tojin-san</foreign> (Honorable Mr. Foreigner).<note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">The prefix <q>O-</q> is a Japanese honorific denoting respect.
                     <q>Tojin</q> translates to <q>foreigner</q>. When acting as a suffix following
                  a person’s name, <q>-san</q> is a Japanese honourific that is used to address
                  someone respectfully. Although it is translated in the text as <q>Mr</q>.,
                     <q>-san</q> is a gender neutral honorific.</note></p>

            <p>For at last the exalted <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign><note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">Eaton likely means <q>Daimyo</q>, a powerful land-owning Japanese
                  feudal lord. This mistake occurs throughout the text and will be kept in its
                  original form.</note> of the province had acceded to the pleadings and eager
               demands of the students of the university, and, at <pb n="2"/> great expense and
               trouble, a foreign professor had been imported.</p>

            <p>Signs of preparation were everywhere visible. Vigorous housecleaning was evidence.
               The professional storytellers, who took the place of newspapers in these days, reaped
               small fortune in their halls. Some of them opened booths on the streets and regaled
               their auditors with strange accounts of America and its people.</p>

            <p>Already the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s house and household had been
               chosen for him, from the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer and
               the four <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign><note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">Samourai were part of the warrior caste in Japan and had political
                  power until the Meiji Restoration.</note> body-guard, who were to protect him from
               any possible <foreign xml:lang="ja"
               >Jo-i</foreign><!-- *Cannot confirm what this translates to in Japanese --> (foreign
               hater), down to his body-servant.</p>

            <p>An enormous old historical <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> (mansion),<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"><q>Shiro</q> refers to a Japanese castle.</note>
               two hundred and seven years old, was assigned as his residence, and was now
               undergoing certain remarkable changes. For heavy <pb n="3"/> woollen carpets, with
               flowers and figured designs, were being nailed down over the ancient matting in the
               chief rooms. Strange articles of furniture, massive and heavy as iron, were pushed
               into the great chambers, under the supervising hand of a dapper, rosy-cheeked young
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> who was to serve as interpreter to the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>. His name was Genji Negato, and he had
               already lived among foreigners in the cities of Tokyo and Yokohama. He spoke the
               English language very well indeed, and his knowledge of the white man and his ways
               was extraordinary.</p>

            <p>Now, as he ordered this or that article set in place, his full red lips curled
               smilingly under his little bristly mustache. He called the servants in one by one,
               lecturing each in turn in regard to his especial duties. Incidentally, he regaled
               them with <pb n="4"/> tales of the habits and desires of the white man.</p>

            <p>Food sufficient for six ordinary mortals must be prepared for his individual
               consumption. Raw meat and game, slightly scorched before fire, were essential. A
               never-failing spring of what the original American had aptly called <q>fire-water</q>
               must be constantly flowing at and between meals and day and night. Such was the
               thirst of the white man. Brooms must be in readiness to follow the trail of the dust
               and mud-laden boots of the professor, since he would not remove them even in the
               house. Finally, his supreme favor could be won by having at hand always the sweetest
               and prettiest maidens to entertain and caress him. And so on through a strange
               list.</p>

            <p>If the students of the college where the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               was to teach were <pb n="5"/> elated at the prospect of his coming, their joy was
               hardly shared by his household. It was in a flutter of excited fear. Even the stolid,
               impassive-faced <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> guard discussed in
               undertones among themselves the degrading service to which they were reduced in these
               degenerate days. To guard the body of a mere <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>!
               Well, such was the will of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> of
                  Echizen,<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Echizen is a city in the prefecture
                  of Fukui.</note> and a <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> is the right hand
               of his Prince. His <choice>
                  <sic>the</sic>
                  <corr>is the</corr>
               </choice> task to obey even the caprice of his lord, or take his own life in
               preference to service too far beneath his honor.</p>

            <p>In the humbler regions of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign>, however, the
               servants discussed the matter less pessimistically. Some rumor of the generosity and
               wealth of foreigners had floated across the vague tide of gossip. Anyhow, the
               preparations for his coming went blithely on here, and already odors of vigorous <pb
                  n="6"/> advance cooking were being wafted from the kitchen regions, warming and
               savoring the great chambers, and awakening into noisy life the vast army of rats and
               bats which had long made their homes in the eaves and rafters of the old deserted
               mansion, now for the first time in years to be occupied by a tenant.</p>

            <p>Everything was quite in readiness when the cook’s wife’s baby’s nurse (for his entire
               family were, of course, also domiciled in the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign>)
               missed a portion of her rice. She had turned about to give better attention to master
                  baby<foreign xml:lang="ja">-san</foreign>, when, so she averred, a <q>white
                  hand</q> reached out of nowhere and seized the remnants of her supper. She ran
               squealing with her tale to her mistress, who, in turn, rushed with it to her lord,
               the cook. He put aside his apron and sought Genji Negato, who solemnly called a
               council of war. <pb n="7"/> To the four <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>
               guard the entire household looked for a solution and ending of the impending
               trouble.</p>

            <p>Measures should be taken at once, it was unanimously decided. It would be to their
               Prince’s everlasting disgrace should the exalted foreign devil also become a victim
               of the dreaded Fox Woman of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign>,<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"><q>Yama</q> means <q>mountain</q>.</note> for,
               undoubtedly, this mischievous and irrepressible sprite of the mountains was at her
               tricks again. In the names, therefore, of the august <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>, nay, in the very name of the Imperial <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Daimio</foreign> of Echizen, it was the duty of the honorable <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> to spare in no wise the witch should she be
               caught trespassing upon the estate of the Prince’s guest and protege.</p>

            <p>They fell to telling weird tales of the latest doings of the fox-woman. A
                  Tsuruga<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Tsuruga is a city in the prefecture
                  of Fukui.</note> child had followed the witch-girl <pb n="8"/> into the mountains,
               believing her glittering hair to be the rays of the sun, and stretching out his tiny
               hands to touch and hold it. To propitiate the dread creature, the parents had set out
               daily food at the foot of the mountains, and thus, for a time at least, the hunger of
               the fox-woman had been satisfied, but the child had never been the same again,
               fretting and crying constantly for the <q>Sun Lady</q>. As its peevishness continued,
               the parents revenged themselves upon its abductor, and ceased to set out the nightly
               repast, bravely facing down their fear of the witch’s certain anger and
               retaliation.</p>

            <p>Since then she had been forced to seek her sustenance elsewhere. A basket of fish
               disappeared overnight from a vendor’s locked stand. A bag of rice was found on the
               mountainside of the river, as if the thief, finding <pb n="9"/> it too heavy, had
               dropped it in her flight.</p>

            <p>And now—could it be possible that the most distinguished (though augustly degraded)
               guest Fukui had known in years was to suffer by the depredations of the
               fox-woman?</p>

            <p><foreign xml:lang="ja">Samourai</foreign> Iroka voted in favor of killing the witch
               outright. But not by the means of his own personal sword, for he was unmarried and
               had no descendants to pray for his soul should it be forced to pass along on a
               journey.</p>

            <p><foreign xml:lang="ja">Samourai</foreign> Asado feared for the safety of his wife and
               family in the event of his honorable sword being stained by the blood of the
               witch-girl. Once a similar goblin had torn the head and arms from the body of a
               sleeping babe, in revenge for the mere pin-prick of a <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >samourai</foreign> sword.</p>

            <p><foreign xml:lang="ja">Samourai</foreign> Hirata suggested referring <pb n="10"/> the
               matter to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> himself; but was urged against
               this by the others, for was not the fox-woman the one black blot upon the escutcheon
               of their exalted Prince, seeing she was indeed, and alas! of his own blood?</p>

            <p>Finally, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Samourai</foreign> Numura, an ancient, grizzled
               warrior of the most stolid common sense, gruffly insisted that the matter was the
               affair of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> himself; and from him alone
               should they receive commands upon the matter. It was agreed, therefore, that they
               should wait for the coming of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. Out of
               his vaunted western wisdom certainly should he be able to suggest the solution of the
               problem.</p>

            <p>And, in the Season of Greatest Cold, while the snow whirled in feathery flakes over
               all the Province of Echizen, and the winds blew in laughing, <pb n="11"/> whispering
               murmurs through the glistening camphor and pine trees, across the sacred bosom of
               Lake Biwa, and over the snow-crowned mountains between, the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> came to Fukui, the <q>Well of Blessing</q>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>II</head>

            <p>The room was so large that even with the seven lighted <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >andon</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">An <q>andon</q> is a
                  traditional Japanese paper lantern.</note> and the three ancient <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja"
               >takahiras</foreign><!-- *Cannot confirm what this translates to in Japanese. Seems to just be a last name. -->
               glimmering dully where they hung from the raftered ceiling overhead, it was chiefly
               in shadow. Set at intervals against the sliding walls were a few large pieces of
               heavy black-walnut furniture, grotesque objects in the otherwise completely empty
               chamber. The room itself was cold, but a <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >kotatsu</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>kotatsu</q> is a
                  blanket-covered table frame over a heat source.</note> in the centre of the room
               had been filled with live coals, and over this the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> crouched. He sat upon the floor, close to the fire-frame, his
               knees drawn up, his hands encircling them.</p>
            <pb n="13"/>

            <p>After a long and tortuous journey over land and water, by boat, by horse, by <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">kurumma</foreign>,<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"
                     ><q>kurumma</q> means <q>car</q>.</note> and often on foot—a never-ending,
               long-winding, cold journey, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was at
               last at home! This was Fukui, where he had contracted to live for seven years of his
               life; this vast, empty, bleak mansion was his house.</p>

            <p>He had started upon the journey with an alert and quickened pulse, and an ardent
               ambition to serve, to raise up, to love this strange people to whom he had pledged
               himself. A short sojourn was made in Tokio and Kioto—days of sheer delight in a
               charms one with intoxicated. Then, leaving the open ports, under the escort sent by
               the Prince of Echizen, he had taken finally that plunge into the great unknown
               country itself, where only half a dozen foreigners had been before him.<pb n="14"
               /></p>

            <p>The journey had been one of many weeks. Crossing waters in a fragile craft, which
               tossed and heaved with every tide, he had come to know the true meaning of the
               Japanese saying that <q>a sea voyage is an inch of hell</q>.</p>

            <p>For days his party had been snow-bound on a desolate mountain, far from even the
               smallest village or town, and, when finally they had issued forth, it was only to
               encounter new perils, in savage-souled <foreign xml:lang="ja">ronins</foreign><note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>ronin</q> is a samourai without a
                  master.</note> who hung about the vicinity of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>’s party, their narrow, wicked eyes intent upon his
               destruction. How many white men before him had started upon a similar journey, in
               other provinces of Japan, and met the then common fate—a stab in the back, or in the
               dark! And the punishments, the indemnities, the humiliations forced upon the
               government by the foreigners, but added to <pb n="15"/> the hatred and malice of the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Jo-i</foreign> (foreign haters).</p>

            <p>But the Prince of Echizen was of the most enlightened school. No foreign teacher or
               guest within his province should suffer the smallest hurt! His edicts in the matter
               were so emphatic that they reached even the humblest of the citizens, and the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, did he but know it, was practically
               immune from attack. Indeed, his pilgrimage was in the nature of one of triumph.
               Whatever their inner feelings toward the intruder, the people met him with smiles and
               expressions of welcome. Every little town and hamlet sent to him on its outskirts
               deputations of high officials. There had been feasts here and banquets there, and
               always and everywhere about him he saw the same brown face, the same glittering eye,
               the same elusive smile.<pb n="16"/></p>

            <p>Now the last <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s officer was gone, the last
               officious minister of his Prince had chanted his singsong poem of welcome, and the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was alone!</p>

            <p>Even the individual members of his household had dispersed. They had come in one by
               one in solemn procession, led by the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> guard,
               who, as they prostrated themselves, sucked in their breath fiercely, expelling it in
               long, sibilant hisses. The cook, his assistants, and wife and family formed a small
               procession of their own, one behind the other, executing a series of such comical
               bows and bobs that the stern lips of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               had softened in spite of himself, particularly so, when the tiniest one, a toddling
               baby no more than two years old, had solemnly brought its diminutive shaven pate to
               the floor, and had almost capsized <pb n="17"/> in a somersault in its efforts to
               emulate its elders’ politeness.</p>

            <p>Now the weary, half-closed eyes of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               were seeing other faces, his mind travelling backward over other scenes, very far
               away. He saw a great, green campus, overshadowed by towering elms. Bright-eyed,
               white-skinned boys were singing huskily as they swept across the lawns into the tall
               stone buildings, which seemed to smile at them with maternal indulgence. The <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was seated at a desk, looking across at that sea
               of boyish faces. Strange how they had repulsed him; how he had even felt a bitterness
               that was almost hatred for them in that other time and place! And now! Now he caught
               himself thinking of them with a tenderness which almost stifled.</p>

            <p>Then the jaded mind of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> wandered out
               into another scene <pb n="18"/> of the past, and out of a longer, darker memory a
               woman’s cold, unsmiling face mocked him.</p>

            <p><q>Marry you!</q> she had cried, and not even her native courtesy could suppress the
               note of horror in her voice. <q>Oh—h!</q> she had cried out, covering her eyes
               shudderingly, <q>if you could but—see—yourself!</q></p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> had indeed seen himself that night.
               Glaring back at him in a tragic grimness his own fearful face had looked at him from
               the mirror. Not that he had not known the blight upon him; but he had been dull,
               stupid, slow to realize its full horror.</p>

            <p>Time was when the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was as other men,
               smooth-skinned, level-eyed, very good to look upon. But in a God and Man forsaken
               little town crushed between the mountains and the sea, a young and ardent doctor <pb
                  n="19"/> of long ago had given himself up to a sublime heroism. Shoulder to
               shoulder with a few—one or two only beside himself—they had fought the plague of
               smallpox. From this fight the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> had emerged
               marked! With the optimism and blindness of youth, however, he had gone back to the
               woman he loved, and she had struck at him!</p>

            <p>There is a Japanese proverb which says: <q>The tongue three inches long can kill a
                  man six feet tall</q>. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> thought of
               this now. A woman’s tongue, the mere brutal smiting of her words, had wrought a
               curious effect upon his entire life. From that time on he had avoided women as he had
               not a vile plague. He led the life of an ascetic, wrapped in his books and sciences,
               making few friends, avoiding others, with the sensitive fear upon him that the whole
                  <pb n="20"/> world avoided and shrank also from him. And while still a young man
               under forty—they had named him <q>Old Grind</q> at the university.</p>

            <p>Then upon him suddenly had come a new upheaval, a pent-up, passionate longing to
               break away from the dull hopeless treadmill to which he seemed bound.</p>


            <p><q>Old Grind!</q> So age was to be clapped upon him while the vital fires of youth
               still throbbed in an agony in his blood. There was a new life, an exhilarating, more
               inspiring life to be led, out in that old-new world across the seas! It beckoned to
               those of adventurous souls and those who were weary of a drowsy, torpid existence,
               wherein hope of a new dawn had vanished beyond memory. The <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> panted for this new life. He wanted to swing his arms in a
               wilder world, to breathe less vitiated <pb n="21"/> air, to feel himself alive again!
               He had made of himself, for half a lifetime, a mummy for the sake of a woman he had
               not even really loved. It was fantastic!</p>

            <p>Out of this curious rebellion against Fate which had swept upon him like a tidal
               wave, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> had broken his bonds.</p>

            <p>He was in the strange wild land he had yearned for, strange faces peered at him
               askance, and strange gods mocked him from their temples with their sphinx-like
               impenetrability. And he crouched, shivering, over a <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >kotatsu</foreign> in a great, historical <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >yashiki</foreign>,<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"><q>Yashiki</q> means
                     <q>house</q>.</note> cold and empty as a very mausoleum, and the strong man
               within him recognized and fought the weakness come upon him—the aching, longing,
               praying, for the mere sight of a white, familiar face!</p>

            <p>So still was the night, even the <pb n="22"/> glide of a <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >gaki</foreign> (spirit)<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Gaki are known as
                     <q>hungry ghosts</q> who died while suffering.</note> across the cracking snow
               without must have been heard. A breeze just trembled through the frost-incrusted
               bough of a camphor-tree, and it bristled and broke, the twigs snapping and bouncing
               down on the frozen ground beneath.</p>

            <p>Something crept out of the shadows of the woods at the foot of the mountains, leaped
               like a fawn across the wide arm of the castle moat, and slid over the grounds between
               it and the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> Matsuhaira. An army of crows which
               lodged in the attic of a dilapidated ruin of what had once been a <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">go-down</foreign> (treasure-house) suddenly began to flap their
               wings, calling to each other querulously and making short, futile, terrified flights.
               A rat fled from the <foreign xml:lang="ja">go-down</foreign> interior and scuttled
               across to the kitchen in the rear of the mansion, and the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>
               <pb n="23"/> raised a startled face, listening to a new sound.</p>

            <p>It was as if one without were tapping or scratching ever so faintly upon the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">amado</foreign> (winter walls).<note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1"><q>Amado</q> can be more accurately translated to a horizontally
                  sliding storm shutter.</note> He did not move, but fastened his gaze upon the
               point whence he had fancied the sound proceeded. Now it came from another direction
               and tapped lightly, timidly again, as a child might have done.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> came to his feet with a bound. He
               flung wide the screens of his chamber, now on this side, now on that, and now those
               opening upon the grounds. Not a soul was visible. Nothing but the white, still snow,
               glittering like silver under the moonrays. He looked up at the outjutting eaves, felt
               along them with his hand, though a curious instinct told him insistently that the
               touch upon his screens had been <pb n="24"/> intelligent and human. Slowly he drew
               them into place again, and, as he did so, a voice, low as a sigh, called to him
               across the bleak snow:</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">To-o—jin-san! To-o-o-jin—san! To-o-o-jin—san!
                     To-o-o—!</foreign></q></p>

            <p><foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>! That was the name he had heard
               everywhere. The one they had given him. Someone was calling him, wanted him, needed
               him, perhaps!</p>

            <p>It was a step only down to the gardens below. He took it at a leap, crossed the
               intervening lawn and plunged into the wooded grove beyond. On and on he followed the
               sound of the voice, still sighing across to him, now pleading, now wistful, now wild
               and now—mocking, with the tone of a teasing sprite which laughed through a veil of
               tears.</p>

            <p>Suddenly he stopped, white-lipped. He had been within a step of the but <pb n="25"/>
               half-frozen moat. One more, and he would have plunged into it. A shuddering sense of
               horror, of shock, seized him, and held him there rooted to the spot, bewildered,
               stunned, his ears still strained listening to the drifting voice, which had vanished
               across the heights and lost itself in the white looming shadows of the mountains.<pb
                  n="26"/></p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>III</head>

            <p><q>Your excellency, though he live a million honorable years, could not estimate the
                  augustly degraded chagrin experienced by my exalted Prince in my humble and
                  servile person</q>.</p>

            <p>So spoke the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer, through the
               interpreter, Genji Negato.</p>

            <p>The American held his shaking hands over the replenished <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >kotatsu</foreign> as the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s officer,
               hastily summoned by the guard, set himself the distasteful task of explaining to him
               the existence of the fox-woman.</p>

            <p>A fox-woman, so he explained solemnly, was a female human being into whose body the
               soul of a fox had entered. In Japanese mythology <pb n="27"/> the fox occupies an
               important position, and the fox-woman is a creature greatly to be feared. Her face
               and form, so said the Japanese, were of a marvellous whiteness and a beauty so
               dazzling that a mortal must cover his eyes to escape blindness. Her hair resembled
               the sunrays, so bright and glittering its color and effect. Gifted with this beauty
               of face and form, but devoid of soul, she had but one ruling and controlling
               ambition. She spent her days and nights lurking about the mountain passes, behind and
               within rocks and caves, luring men—aye, and women and children, too!—to
               destruction.</p>

            <p>Something in the half-skeptical smile on the taciturn face of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> stopped the officer’s recital. His expression
               became troubled, revealing a sensitive pride unduly wounded. Plainly the foreign
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sensei</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A
                     <q>sensei</q> is a teacher.</note>
               <pb n="28"/> looked upon his explanations in the light of a fairy-tale.</p>

            <p><q>Your excellency disbelieves our legend of the fox-woman?</q> he queried
               courteously.</p>

            <p><q>Legends</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> slowly, <q>belong
                  to literature, and are tales to charm and beguile adults and deceive children. In
                  the West we no longer heed them. We name them superstitions, and we’ve burned out
                  our superstitions as we did our witches in the early days</q>.</p>

            <p>The Japanese sat up stiffly, and in the chilly room he waved his fan regularly to and
               fro.</p>

            <p><q>You deny the existence of spirits in the West?</q></p>

            <p><q>At least we do not create them out of our fancy or thought</q>, said the American
               gravely.</p>

            <p>The officer said vehemently:</p>

            <p><q>They exist actively in Japan, <pb n="29"/> honorable sir. Though you ignore them,
                  they will force themselves upon you—as to-night, excellency!</q></p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> frowned slightly. Then, thoughtfully,
               he emptied his pipe on the old bronze <foreign xml:lang="ja">hibachi</foreign>.<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>hibachi</q> is a brazier for burning
                  charcoal.</note></p>

            <p><q>You wish me to believe that my visitor to-night was a—spirit?</q></p>

            <p><q>She was worse</q>, said the officer earnestly, <q>for she was invested with at
                  least the form of a human being</q>.</p>

            <p><q>How do you know she is not human?</q></p>

            <p>It was the Japanese’s turn to frown. His narrow eyes drew sternly together. His voice
               was stubborn. He spoke as if determined to justify some indisputable course he had
               taken.</p>

            <p><q>She is unlike us in any way, exalted sir. No human being ever was created with
                  such fiendish beauty. Her acts are those of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >gaki</foreign>, moreover. She is mischievous, impish, <pb n="30"/> wicked,
                  delighting as much in torturing and frightening the poor as well as the rich,
                  little children as well as their elders. The birds of the air come at her calling
                  and follow her whithersoever she bids them. Degraded dogs and cats, forlorn beasts
                  of the mountains and the forests are her body-guard, defying mere human beings to
                  molest or take her. Her home is among the tombs of <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon
                     Sha</foreign>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Eaton may mean
                        <q>shogun</q>, military commanders who ruled Japan, instead of <q>Sho
                        Kon</q>.</note> She is of the Temple Tokiwa, long forsaken of men and
                  accursed by the gods</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> raised himself with a show of more
               interest.</p>

            <p><q>A temple housing your dreaded fox-woman!</q> he exclaimed, whimsically.</p>

            <p><q>Yes, alas so, excellency</q>, admitted the Japanese miserably. <q>Her mother was
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Nii no Ama</foreign> (noble nun of second rank) and kin
                  to our august <pb n="31"/> Prince. She broke her vows to the Lord Buddha,
                  desecrated and disgraced his temple. The gods visited their wrath upon her
                  offspring. They gave it a body only—no soul, save that of the fox. She is beyond
                  the pale, honored sir, and no clean being may look upon or touch her</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, sitting up erectly now, was holding
               his lower lip thoughtfully between thumb and forefinger.</p>

            <p><q>Your fox-woman then is some sort of outcast, who has lived all her life avoided by
                  her kind?</q></p>

            <p><q>She had the company of her degraded parents</q>, said the officer gruffly,
                  <q>until she was the age of ten. Then a zealous band of former <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Danka</foreign> (parishioners)<note type="editorial"
                     resp="pers:LW1">The danka system required households to be affiliated and
                     registered with a Buddhist temple. Affiliates of a temple are called
                        <q>danka</q>.</note> assaulted the temple by fire and sword. The parents of
                  the fox-woman met a deserved death, being literally torn to pieces before <pb
                     n="32"/> the very altar of Great <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shaka</foreign><note
                     type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">The Buddha is known as <q>Shaka</q> in
                     Japanese.</note> himself</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s officer paused, his little black eyes
               glittering with a fanatical light. Then the exhilaration dropped from his voice.</p>

            <p><q>But the ways of the Lord Buddha are strange. How could the devoted <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Danka</foreign> conceive that <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shaka</foreign> would turn his wrath upon them also, for thus scorching his
                  altar with unclean blood. Since the Restoration, excellency, our city’s history
                  has been one of blood and poverty. Some assert the province is doomed. Others,
                  more optimistic, that it is but passing through its new birth pains, and that, as
                  of old, its history will be glorious</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> puffed at his relighted pipe in
               meditative silence. Then, very quietly, he asked:</p>

            <p><q>Do you lay the misfortunes of <pb n="33"/> your province upon this fox-woman, as
                  you call her?</q></p>

            <p><q>Aye!</q> said the officer almost fiercely. <q>The hand of Fate fell heaviest upon
                  us after the assassination of the intruder. We have never recovered from the
                  humiliations heaped upon us by—the countries of the West. The bombardment of
                  beloved Kagoshima<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Kagoshima is the capital
                     of Kagoshima Prefecture.</note> by the allied forces of the western nations
                  followed almost instantly after the death by violence of—</q></p>

            <p>He stopped abruptly, and coughed in gruff alarm behind his now sheltering fan. He had
               been upon the verge of telling what had been forbidden.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> looked puzzled, baffled.</p>

            <p><q>I do not see the connection</q>, he said.</p>

            <p><q>Yet—it is so</q>, said the Japanese <pb n="34"/> vaguely, shifting his eyes from
               the averted faces of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> guard.</p>

            <p>Said the American forcefully:</p>

            <p><q>It seems to me an amazing thing that to-day when you are frankly hoping to join
                  the nations of enlightenment, you still give yourselves up to barbarous
                  persecution because of what, after all, is nothing but a legend fit for children
                  only. For my part, I intend to sweep from my house vigorously the absurd belief I
                  find actually seated on my hearth-stone</q>.</p>

            <p>The Japanese said solemnly:</p>

            <p><q>There are several things in life it is impossible to do, exalted sir. We cannot
                  throw a stone to the sun, or scatter a fog with a fan. We cannot build a bridge to
                  the clouds. With this little hand I cannot dip up the ocean. We bow to the
                  elevated wisdom of the West your excellency has come to teach us in <pb n="35"/>
                  honorable chemistry and physics, but, though we humbly solicit pardon for thus
                  stating, there is nothing your augustness can tell us of our own—and
               knowledge</q>.</p>

            <p>He made a slight, stiff sign to his attendants and they assisted him to arise. The
               American stood up also. He was smiling grimly.</p>

            <p><q>When the snows melt</q>, he said, <q>I shall ask for guides of your excellency,
                  and personally make a pilgrimage to the lair of this dreaded fox-woman of the
                  mountains</q>.</p>

            <p>At that the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s officer’s face distinctly
               paled. His impassive features were anxious, troubled.</p>

            <p><q>What does your augustness seek to do?—regenerate one without a soul?</q></p>

            <p><q>I wish merely to see her. She must be an interesting specimen—of her kind</q>.</p>
            <pb n="36"/>

            <p><q>‘Making an idol does not give it a soul,’</q> quoted the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Daimio</foreign>’s officer solemnly. <q>Honored sir, a snake has its charm to
                  some, and the vampire is kin to the snake. In Japan we believe the fox-woman one
                  form of vampire. Condescend, exalted sir, to beware</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> laughed shortly, contemptuously. He
               was a man of gigantic stature, and as he stood there towering above his gleaming-eyed
               visitor there was something about his attitude careless, indifferent, fearless, and
               beyond the understanding of the Oriental. With a morbid recollection of specific
               instructions from his Prince, the officer restrained his fingers, turned almost
               automatically toward the two short swords hanging at his side.</p>

            <p><q>It is my duty, excellent sir</q>, he said with forced courtesy, <q>to convince you
                  of the danger wherewith <pb n="37"/> you seek to play. Condescend to permit the
                  humble one once again to be seated</q>.</p>

            <p><q>By all means</q>, said the American, hospitably, and, in a moment, they were back
               seated upon their respective mats, their pipes refilled at the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >hibachi</foreign>.</p>
            <pb n="38"/>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>IV</head>
            <p><q>You have stated, honored sir, that the Fox-Woman of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Yama</foreign> is but a superstition worthy of a child, and you have laughed,
                  Mr. sir, at the possibility of danger from proximity with the forsaken creature.
                  Thus spoke and laughed another before your time in Fukui. We of Echizen do not
                  forget the very recent fate of Gihei Matsuyama</q>.</p>

            <p><q>And pray who was Gihei Matsuyama, and what was his fate?</q> asked the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, good-humoredly.</p>

            <p>The fanatical fire was back in the eyes of the officer. He had thrust forward his
               thin, yellow face and was regarding the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               with an almost <pb n="39"/> venomous glance. His words, however, were pacific, and,
               as he talked, the American showed a greater interest with every moment.</p>

            <p><q>We sent seven of our youths to the universities of the West. They were chosen from
                  the most intelligent and noblest of our families. Gihei Matsuyama was one of
                  these, and in him we had particular interest, for he was of Fukui. After two
                  years’ sojourn in Europe he returned for service in <foreign xml:lang="ja">Dai
                     Nippon</foreign>,<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"><q>Dai Nippon</q>
                     translates to <q>Greater Japan</q>. <q>大日本帝國</q> or <q><foreign xml:lang="ja"
                           >Dai Nippon Teikoku</foreign></q> refers to <q>the Empire of
                     Japan</q>.</note> and we gave him a position of honor and housed him in an
                  honorable <foreign xml:lang="ja">yashiki</foreign> hard by Atago <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign></q>.</p>

            <p><q>As a youth—as a child, he had known the story of the fox-woman. His honorable sire
                  and other male kin had participated in the slaughter of the parents of the
                  creature. Now with this new wisdom he had acquired in the West, as fresh as
                  new-spread <pb n="40"/> varnish upon him, Gihei laughed to scorn the stories of
                  her fiendish origin, and boasted he would dissipate them as the air does the
                  steam. Making a bold and ingenuous wager that he would enslave the sprite, he set
                  himself the task of tracking her. Unaided by even the counsel of the priests of
                  neighboring temples, he blithely followed the trail of the witch over the river,
                  through the woods and mountains and in and out of the cemeteries, until he had
                  driven her to her final refuge—the Temple of Tokiwa, wherein no man had stepped
                  since the accursed blood spilt before the eye of the eternal Lord</q>.</p>

            <p>Here the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer reverently bowed to
               the floor, ere he continued his narrative, his eyes gleaming more fiercely as he
               proceeded.</p>

            <p><q>As he hesitated upon the threshold <pb n="41"/>, divided between a desire to
                  penetrate its mysteries, and an instinct which peremptorily bade him depart, she
                  came forth from the temple doors dancing, as the nuns of old danced for the gods,
                  with her wild, unbound hair outmatching the sun, and her hungry, vivid, smiling
                  lips scarlet as the deadly poppy. He, having looked upon her face, became blinded
                  to all else on earth. Infatuated and maddened, he sought to touch, to seize the
                  creature, when she fled suddenly before him, mocking him with the silver laughter
                  of the sea-siren and hiding her face in the glimmering veil of her hair</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Thus they sped on, she ever before him, with her luring hair streaming like a
                  gilded cloud in the wind, springing as lightly as a breeze from rock to rock, over
                  brooks and slender streams that melted in between,<pb n="42"/> up this cliff and
                  down that dell and through this valley, on and on she led the infatuated
                  seeker</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Suddenly, while his dazzled eyes were fastened solely upon her, and he reached
                  forth a hand to seize her, she darted like a nymph over some unseen chasm of the
                  mountains. He stumbled in her tracks, reached out vainly to seize her, saw not the
                  gulf at his feet, and plunged headlong down into the abyss</q>.</p>

            <p>The mask-like face of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s officer quivered.
               He wiped his face with a hand that shook visibly. Then, rejecting his breath in that
               hissing fashion so peculiar to the Japanese, he added fiercely:</p>

            <p><q>This, honorable sir, is the story of Gihei Matsuyama and the Fox-Woman of Atago
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign>. It belongs not to the lips only of the
                  children, as you name them, but is true, well-authenticated <pb n="43"/> history,
                  which any one in Fukui can prove to you</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was silenced. He had followed the
               officer’s story with unabated interest. He had no word now in defense of this
               Japanese Lorelei. His voice was grave, stern:</p>

            <p><q>What did she do—when the boy disappeared?</q></p>

            <p><q>There are different stories, honored sir. Some say she not even stopped in her
                  flight. Others that she came of nights and hung over the edges of the chasm,
                  shrouding her mouth in her hands and calling to her victim beneath as if she had
                  the power to lure him back. But we have no certain version of this part of the
                  tragedy. For the first part, we have the tale, four times repeated, from the
                  body-servants of Gihei Matsuyama, who dutifully had followed their master upon his
                  wild quest</q>.</p>
            <pb n="44"/>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer arose and made several
               profound obeisances to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. His face had
               resumed its immobile melancholy. As he was backing formally toward the exit, bowing
               at every step, the American suddenly remembered his name. He took a step toward him,
               his hand impetuously outstretched:</p>

            <p><q>Pardon me, the boy you speak of was—near and dear to you, was he not?</q></p>

            <p>Slowly the officer raised his head. Not a quiver broke the stony impassivity of his
               face. His eyes met the Tojin’s blankly:</p>

            <p><q>He was—my son!</q> he said.</p>
            <pb n="45"/>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>V</head>
            <p>The sense of discouragement and gloom which had seemed to take full hold upon the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> on his first night in Fukui was, after
               all, but temporary. He awoke the following morning, feeling refreshed and
               invigorated. The sun was pouring into his room, gilding even the farthest corner with
               a friendly touch. He jumped out of bed, donned a warm bath-robe and shoved his feet
               into fur slippers. Crossing the room in a few quick strides, he threw open one of the
               latticed sliding doors.</p>

            <p>It was a clear, cold day, but the snow, enshrouding trees and ground, glistened with
               the warm sun upon it. <pb n="46"/> The army of crows on the roof of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">go-down</foreign> were chattering and fighting among themselves like
               magpies, and a monkey, swinging by one foot from a camphor bough, shook its fist
               playfully in his direction, screwing up its face in apparent derision.</p>

            <p>From the direction of the narrow river, which threaded its ribbon-like way in the
               valley below, a rollicking voice was heard in song, and, presently, the owner of the
               voice climbed up the crest of the slope, skirted the sunken garden hard by the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s windows and moved across the lawns
               toward the kitchen regions in the rear. She was a great, fat girl, whose enormous,
               muscular arms were balancing on either side huge pails of water. As she waddled
               along, wheezing and singing, she resembled, to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>’s humorous sense, a bag of jelly, her bosoms and thighs
               shaking <pb n="47"/> at every step, her fat soft cheeks keeping time in unison. Close
               upon her heels, and, himself carrying two smaller pails of water, the cook’s
               diminutive heir toddled solemnly after her.</p>

            <p>It was he who first perceived the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> at the
               opened door, and he promptly dropped his pails upon the serving-maid’s heels, causing
               her to kick backward in squalling alarm as the cold water splashed about her bare
               legs and drenched her scanty skirts. Doubtless she would have punished her small
               charge, had she not at this juncture also perceived the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign>. Her thick red lips fell instantly agape. She stared at him in a
               stunned wonder. Then her knees began to wobble, and she attempted to make an
               obeisance. With every kowtow she essayed, the waters from her pails bounced up <pb
                  n="48"/> and merrily splashed her. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               burst into hearty laughter, and after a moment maid and youngster joined in his
               mirth. They then scuttled off like a pair of panic-stricken rats, their shining, wet
               heels flashing like snowballs in the sun behind them.</p>

            <p>This simple domestic incident put the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> into
               an excellent humor at once. As he looked after the comical pair, and then turned back
               to gaze, entranced, at the magnificent view on all sides of him, his garden exquisite
               even in its winter dress, he marveled at his gloom of the previous night. Then his
               glance went upward, traveled across the pure blue sky, and rested upon the snowy
               bosoms of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign> and Hakusan.<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Hakusan is a city in Ishikawa Prefecture, but
                  Eaton appears to be referring to Mount Hakusan specifically.</note> Suddenly he
               thought of the fox-woman. There was something chill, forbidding, sinister in those
               great, beautiful <pb n="49"/> mountains of snow, looming out there in the sunny sky.
               He pictured this forsaken creature threading her bleak way under the towering
               frost-incrusted pines. The gloom of the previous night fell upon him again like a
               shadow. Shivering, he went indoors, snapping the closed latticed doors behind
               him.</p>

            <p>A fine horse had been provided for the American teacher, and he rode abroad through
               the streets of Fukui, under an escort sent by the Prince of Echizen himself.
               Everywhere the friendly and curious citizens ran out to see the white-faced teacher,
               and bows and smiles were the general rule on all sides.</p>

            <p>Occasionally, however, he met the scowling, threatening glance of some roving
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>, who, the interpreter explained, under
               the new order of things, was out of office and consequently <pb n="50"/> a <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">ronin</foreign>. It was one of the unfortunate effects of the
               Restoration that so many men of the sword, who had previously been supported by the
               people as retainers in the service of princely houses, now found themselves without
               aristocratic employment, and, too proud to turn to trade, or other equally debasing
               labor, they wandered about the provinces, voicing their discontent of the order of
               things, picking quarrels on the slightest provocation, and prophesying dread things
               for the empire when it should fall under the dominion and patronage of the nations of
               the West. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">ronins</foreign> were all <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Jo-i</foreign> (foreign haters), and they alone the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> need fear. Happily the Prince of Echizen had furnished an
               adequate guard for his protection, and the students of the college, themselves
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>, or sons of <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >samourai</foreign>, were <pb n="51"/> all pledged to protect the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> from harm.</p>

            <p>Presently they arrived at the school, an enormous building, once the citadel of the
               Castle, and here nine hundred students received the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> with a veritable ovation.</p>

            <p>As he stood straightly before them, looking across at that sea of bright friendly
               faces, is it any wonder he recalled another scene in America, so similar, yet
               dissimilar, and that his heart went out yearningly to the youths facing him?</p>

            <p>These intelligent, eager-faced boys were looking to him to guide and lead them. And,
               in turn, already they had pledged themselves to be his vital friends and allies. He
               felt emboldened, courageous, proud, elated. Not for a moment would he have retraced
               his steps to that other land he had regretted.</p>
            <pb n="52"/>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>VI</head>
            <p>In the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s absence several aggravating
               accidents had happened in his house. While little Taro, the cook’s youngest child,
               was sitting on the doorstep in the sun, nibbling on a <foreign xml:lang="ja">sammari
                  sembei</foreign> (thunder cake),<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"
                     ><q>Senbei</q> is a rice cracker. Eaton may be referring to <q>Zarame
                     senbei</q> which is a sugarcoated senbei.</note> suddenly from behind an
               adjacent pine-tree the fox-woman had appeared, and before the frightened child could
               open its mouth to scream she had pounced upon him, nipped the cake cleanly from his
               hand and was off.</p>

            <p>The child’s nurse (who was none other than the fat wench of the morning), who adored
               her charge, and had already herself suffered at the hands of the mountain witch, <pb
                  n="53"/> rushed out valiantly at the child’s loud cry of alarm. Her fury getting
               the better of her fear, she started in pursuit of their tormentor.</p>

            <p>The latter she discovered serenely seated upon the topmost bough of a bamboo-tree,
               where she was demolishing the rice cracknel at her leisure. From this perch she threw
               white pebbles, with which her sleeves seemed loaded, down upon the head of the irate
               Obun, and while the latter was execrating her and calling upon <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Ema</foreign> (the Lord of Hell)<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Eaton is
                  referring to <q>Emma-ō</q>, the Japanese name for the Buddhist god of the
                  underworld.</note> to come to her assistance the fox-woman slid down the bamboo
               trunk so swiftly and so silently she was beside the terrified serving-maid before the
               latter knew. She felt her arms caught in a sudden squeezing grip. Sharp fingers sank
               into her thick, fat flesh, crept up along her arms to her shoulders, nipped at her
               breast, her neck, her <pb n="54"/> cheeks, her great muscular legs, and with a last
               vicious tweak at her nose, the fox-woman had again vanished.</p>

            <p>The kitchen was in an uproar, the cook’s wife in hysterics, and Obun herself reduced
               to such a state of stunned terror it was impossible to get her to stir from a corner
               of the kitchen whither she had fled like a whipped dog for refuge.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, as master of the house, was besought
               to lend his honorable assistance and advice. He ordered that Obun be brought before
               him.</p>

            <p>After some delay there was a sound as of scuffling and shoving in the hall, and
               presently the perspiring face of the cook was seen through the parted screens. He was
               pushing something which looked like a great soft ball along before him, and, in turn,
               ordering and pleading with the object in <pb n="55"/> question to stand upon its feet
               and help itself. He was assisted in his pushing endeavors by a small army of lesser
               menials of the kitchen, who took turns in pushing and shoving the unwilling Obun into
               the presence of her dread master, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>.
               Presently she was at his feet, her face hidden on the floor.</p>

            <p><q>Come, come!</q> said he, suppressing his inclination to laugh. <q>Stand up, my
                  good girl</q>.</p>

            <p>This was translated in sharp peremptory tones by his interpreter:</p>

            <p><q>Thou worm of a slattern! Rise to thy degraded and filthy feet. How dare thee bring
                  agitation into the chamber of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Guai-koku-jin</foreign>
                  [outside countryman] guest and protege of His Imperial Highness the terrible
                  Prince of Echizen</q>.</p>

            <p>Whereupon Obun came tremblingly to her feet, and shaking from head <pb n="56"/> to
               foot, raised a pair of eyes that rolled with terror to the face of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. What she saw there must have reassured her. The
               rugged features of the giant foreigner were softened humorously. In the keen gray
               eyes bent upon her she saw nothing but kindness and understanding. Instantly she
               began to whimper, like a great baby unexpectedly comforted.</p>

            <p><q>You are in trouble, my good girl</q>, said the Tojin, in his deep, kindly voice.
                  <q>Pray tell me what ails you</q>.</p>

            <p>And the interpreter translated:</p>

            <p><q>Repeat to your terrible and inflexible master the incidents of the morning, and
                  arouse not his dreadful wrath with vain exaggerations and lies</q>.</p>

            <p>She opened her lips to speak, encouraged by his smile, closed them again, and mutely
               uncovered first <pb n="57"/> her arms, then her neck, and finally her great soft
               breast.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, his brows now drawn in a slight frown
               together, examined the girl’s wounds, and with the quick eye of a surgeon instantly
               perceived their nature. She had been pinched sharply by little relentless fingers
               which had evidently flown with lightning swiftness from one portion of the hapless
               maid’s body to the other, and finally with a last mischievous tweak had left their
               mark upon the round bit of putty which served Obun for a nose. The <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> whistled under his breath. Obun had certainly
               been the victim of a most curious and spiteful antagonist.</p>

            <p>He gave some brief directions for healing the wounds, and then turning gravely to his
               interpreter admonished his servants for their excitement and foolish fears.</p>
            <pb n="58"/>

            <p>Undoubtedly, Obun had got the worst of her fight with this fox-woman, as they chose
               to name her; but probably, had she not permitted herself to be overcome with fears,
               she might have left her own mark upon her assailant also. It was vain and foolish to
               regard this troublesome one who annoyed them so often in the light of a spirit or
               witch or ghost, as they believed her to be. There were no such things in the
               world.</p>

            <p>The interpreter repeated these instructions with personal embellishments, and the
               little army of servitors with sidelong glances of wonder and awe at their master
               sucked in and expelled their breaths, and, with final servile bumping of heads to the
               floor, retreated kitchenward.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> remained for a moment apparently
               plunged in puzzled thought. Suddenly he turned toward <pb n="59"/> his interpreter,
               who was regarding him with popping eyes of interest. Indeed no move, no word, no
               action of the white man escaped the notice of Genji Negato, who found him an object
               of absorbing interest and wonder. His manner of eating, his manner of sleeping, his
               manner of thinking, talking—all things about him, were a source of wonder and
               entertainment to the young <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>, who was more
               than satisfied with this interesting position he had obtained.</p>

            <p><q>Genji</q> now said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> abruptly, <q>you
                  have seen something of the world. At all events you have lived in the open ports
                  among people of other lands. You speak English excellently and must have read
                  considerably. Tell me what is your opinion of this fox-woman?</q></p>

            <p>Genji Negato was all flattered smiles. He drew up his well-groomed <pb n="60"/>
               shoulders in a profound French shrug.</p>

            <p><q>It would give me supreme pleasure to agree with your excellency</q>, he said
               ambiguously, and smiled apologetically.</p>

            <p><q>I see</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, <q>you, too!
                  Why?</q></p>

            <p>The stiff expression on the interpreter’s face relaxed. In a blurt of confidence he
               said:</p>

            <p><q>I have felt the fox-woman’s touch also, honored sir</q>, and blushed like a boy at
               the admission.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was smiling broadly.</p>

            <p><q>Ah! When?</q></p>

            <p><q>The first night in your service, excellency—a month before your coming</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Indeed. Tell me about it</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I was changing duty with <foreign xml:lang="ja">Samourai</foreign> Hirata. As a
                  large amount of provisions had been put in the storerooms <pb n="61"/> it was
                  necessary to mount guard at various points of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shiro</foreign> and the grounds. I was assigned by the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Daimio</foreign>’s officer to the lodge gates, and there, to my humiliating
                  condemnation be it said, I fell asleep. I carried with me a box containing my
                  rations for the night, and this was strapped upon my back. I am addicted to
                  sleeping on my honorable belly, which your excellency is aware is the proper
                  position for all sleeping animals—to which kingdom I unworthily belong</q>.</p>

            <p><q>While I slept, I dreamed I was climbing down a mountain-side when suddenly an
                  avalanche of rock and earth swooped down upon my defenseless back, pinioning me to
                  the ground with the excess of its weight. I sought to throw off the burden,
                  shaking my shoulders from side to side, and as I cast back my hands, <pb n="62"/>
                  the better to seize it, something caught them in a quick, elastic grip. I rolled
                  over bodily, and, as I opened my eyes, perceived the fox-woman leaning over me.
                  She had cut loose the straps of my luncheon-box and was drawing it from under my
                  back when, with a cry of rage, I caught her by the shoulders and pulled her down
                  upon me in a vise-like grip. The blood rushed to her unearthly white face, her
                  piercing wild eyes blazed upon mine till my own eyeballs felt afflicted as if with
                  fire. I felt her breath, sweet as the Spring, coming yet nearer and nearer to my
                  face. I was like one inebriated by <foreign xml:lang="ja">sake</foreign>,<note
                     type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Sake is a Japanese alcohol.</note> with but
                  one impulse, one desire, to feel the actual touch of her unhuman face against my
                  own. As finally we touched cheek to cheek, honored excellency, my fingers released
                  their grip. Just as they did <pb n="63"/> so a sharp pain stabbed me in the cheek.
                  Before I could regain my wits the witch was gone</q>.</p>

            <p>He passed his hand nervously across his cheek.</p>

            <p><q>For weeks afterward my face was marked with the imprint of teeth sharp as a
                  marmoset’s, your excellency</q>.</p>

            <p><q>And the luncheon?</q> queried the American, smiling in spite of himself.</p>

            <p><q>Gone, too</q>, said the interpreter, aggrievedly.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> laughed. </p>

            <p><q>What a curiously greedy elf it is! All its expeditions among mere mortals seem to
                  be solely for the purpose of food-getting</q>.</p>

            <p>Genji opened his little black eyes with an expression of surprise.</p>

            <p><q>But that is natural. Even a fox-woman needs sustenance</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Come to think of it, a fox-woman has the body of a human?</q></p>
            <pb n="64"/>

            <p><q>Certainly</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Then why not make proper provision, and thus protect yourselves from her
                  pilfering?</q></p>

            <p><q>Your excellency forgets that the fox-woman’s origin is malign. No clean Japanese
                  would undertake to nourish an evil spirit. The priests of our temples give us
                  certain charms which protect us, to a certain extent, and we heed their advice,
                  which is ever to avoid and forsake her</q>.</p>
            <pb n="65"/>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>VII</head>
            <p>They had told the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> in Tokyo that he was to
               be the first white man to set foot upon Echizen soil since that historical period
               when the Jesuit fathers in the sixteenth century had come near to Christianizing the
               nation. The subsequent edicts which expelled all foreigners from the empire and made
               the study of Christianity a crime to be punished with fire, crucifixion or torture,
               had had their due effect. All this was long before the coming of the Tojin, however,
               and Japan had broken its hermit-like seclusion, and now was fearfully and curiously
               holding out a grudging hand to the Western <pb n="66"/> nations pressing her on all
               sides. The foreigner was already a familiar figure in the open ports, but so far, in
               the interior at least, no white faces were to be seen. It was therefore with
               amazement that the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> first discovered signs
               that one of his race had lived recently in Fukui before him.</p>

            <p>It was in the Season of Rain-water, the end of February, a dreary period, when the
               inexhaustible store of drizzling gray rain dribbled unceasingly from the skies. To
               break up the monotony and depression of the period he had undertaken, with three
               favorite students, a short pilgrimage up the Winged Foot River for the purpose of
               examining a cave at the base of the mountains wherein, they said, had once been a
               curious image. The country people had believed it to be <pb n="67"/> the image of
               Buddha’s mother, with her babe in her arms, and pilgrimages were made from all parts
               of the county because of its supposed healing abilities.</p>

            <p>As the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> examined the cave, with the
               interest and eagerness of the born scientist and archaeologist, the youths explained
               to him the fate of the image in question. A learned Bonze of the Nichiren sect had
               recognized it as an image of the <q>Criminal Faith</q> and, in an excess of rage, had
               broken it into fragments.</p>

            <p>Over the entrance of the cave a large board was nailed, and on this was emblazoned
               the same notice the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> had seen wherever he had
               travelled—in every city, town or hamlet, at every entrance to temple or palace,
               roadside or mountain-pass. He had often inquired what the notice was, but his
               questions had always <pb n="68"/>been politely evaded, and once he was somewhat
               curtly told it was simply one of the laws of old Japan, now rapidly becoming
               obsolete. Now he turned abruptly upon the young students, who were all deeply devoted
               to him, and imbued with the new spirit and thirst for knowledge sweeping like a fever
               over all the empire. They, at least, would answer him.</p>

            <p><q>Higo, just what is this notice? Translate it for me, will you not?</q> for the
               three youths accompanying him spoke the English language with fluency.</p>

            <p>Higo replied with a slight flush of embarrassment:</p>

            <p><q>It simply refers to the Criminal God, your excellency</q>.</p>

            <p><q>The Criminal God? You are very vague</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Condescend to pardon the allusion, honored <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >sensei</foreign></q>, said the <pb n="69"/> boy, apologetically. <q>To-day, we
                  are ready to repel all such unworthy references to your exalted nation’s
               faith</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Indeed</q>, put in earnest-eyed Junzo, <q>we are not prepared to name any religion
                  or god criminal. Our august Emperor has set us a divine example, since he has
                  honorably thrown open the doors to any and all sects, however odious</q>.</p>

            <p><q>And for my part</q>, contributed Nunuki in his brusque and somewhat surly manner,
                  <q>I agree with our ancient philosopher: Dogma is a box in which small minds are
                  kept</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Dogma is a form of superstition</q>, said Junzo, <q>and superstition awakens the
                  meaner, crueler passions. Do you not agree with me, honored <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >sensei</foreign>?</q></p>

            <p>But the latter, his brows drawn in puzzled wonderment, was examining <pb n="70"/>
               something which had been cut into the wood of the board on which the notice
               appeared.</p>

            <p><q>What—</q> he began, when in a singsong voice, after a slight shrug of his
               shoulders, Higo began translating the text:</p>

            <p><q>It reads thus, honored teacher: ‘The evil sect called Christians is strictly
                  prohibited. Suspicious persons should be reported to proper officers and rewards
                  given,’ but be not afraid</q>, he added hastily, <q>for it is an old law, and even
                  if still in force to-day your excellency is exempt</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I am trying to decipher what is written under it—in English!</q> said the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> slowly. He took out and applied a magnifying
               glass to the board.</p>

            <p>A swift, oblique look passed from one student to the other; but when <pb n="71"/> the
               American turned toward them for enlightenment, their faces were as impassive as their
               feudal ancestors.</p>


            <p><q>It appears to me</q>, said he, thoughtfully, <q>as though some one had cut words
                  into the woodwork, and that—there are marks as if an attempt had been made to blot
                  out the words. Now let us see: On this—Thomas Mor—18—’ is recent—within the last
                  ten years!</q></p>

            <p>He turned about in a state of intense excitement. Something in the averted faces of
               his companions increased his curiosity and suspicions. Ere he could frame another
               question, Nunuki spoke up abruptly:</p>

            <p><q>It is well you should know the truth, Mr. Teacher. A <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Guai-koku-jin</foreign> [outside countryman] lived in Fukui before your
                  time</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Recently?</q> demanded the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> eagerly.</p>
            <pb n="72"/>

            <p><q>Seven years since</q>, said the boy shortly.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> drew a great breath. His eyes kindled.
               He looked wonderfully pleased.</p>

            <p><q>Then that is why some of you students speak English so creditably?</q></p>

            <p><q>No, teacher. Many of us studied in Yokohama. Many have learned by the book alone.
                  After the coming of your exalted Lord Perry, it became the chief ambition of all
                  thoughtful men of the New Japan to learn the English language and its
               sciences</q>.</p>

            <p>Higo volunteered the above information, but the gruff Nunuki quickly followed
               him:</p>

            <p><q>Be not deceived, excellent <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign>, in regard to
                  the <foreign xml:lang="ja">baku</foreign> [fool]<note type="editorial"
                     resp="pers:LW1"><q>Fool</q> can be romanized in English as <q>baka</q>.
                        <q>Baku</q> are known as supernatural beings in Japanese folklore.</note>
                  who was here before you. He was not like you, honored sir</q>.</p>

            <p><q>No? What was he, then?</q></p>
            <pb n="73"/>

            <p><q>He was—<foreign xml:lang="ja">damyuraisu</foreign></q>, blurted the boy
               angrily.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> burst into laughter. It was a
               colloquial word well known in the open ports, and was applied to the foreign sailor
               of whatever nationality. It was the Japanization of the sailor’s favorite expression:
                  <q>Damn your eyes</q>.</p>

            <p>Suddenly his face went grave, remembering how the sailors of the white nations had
               misrepresented their nations! How, in a constant condition of drunkenness, they
               rioted around the open ports. The gravity in his face was reflected in that of the
               students.</p>

            <p><q>It is a subject</q>, said Junzo gently, <q>ignored by common consent in Fukui,
                  because it is painful to our <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>. He was the
                  fellow’s patron and protector till the time when the honorable beast betrayed him.
                  Pray <pb n="74"/> thee, honored <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign></q>, he
               added almost pleadingly, <q>do not seek to know further in the matter</q>.</p>

            <p><q>At least tell me what became of him</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Your excellency’s honored feet are surely tired. Your honorable insides must be
                  entirely empty. Food is good in that event. Let us call the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >kurumma</foreign></q>.</p>

            <p>They were moving along the road toward the waiting vehicles, which were to carry them
               back to the little boat that had brought them down the river. It was indeed chilly
               and dreary, and their rubber-coats and hats of straw were dripping. The <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, his arm linked in that of the gentle Junzo,
               cast a look back at the dimly shadowed mountains, and, as he did so, the boy dreamily
               remarked:</p>

            <p><q>The Fox-Woman of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign> will find wet passage
                  back to <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon Sha</foreign>
                  <pb n="75"/> this night. It is said the streams and rivers are all billowing over,
                  and not even a sprite may spring across them</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Have no fear</q>, said Nunuki gruffly, looking back over his shoulder. <q>The
                  fox-woman will find wings suitable to her degraded feet. She’ll not lack the
                  shelter so illy deserved</q>.</p>

            <p>The words were so brutal, the tone of the boy so full of animus and hatred that the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> stopped abruptly. He laid a firm,
               kindly hand on either lad’s shoulder.</p>

            <p><q>Who was it spoke this afternoon of superstitions engendered by a fanatical
                  dogma?</q></p>

            <p>For a moment neither of the students answered, then growlingly Nunuki snarled:</p>

            <p><q>It is hard to spit against the wind. Facts cannot be altered</q>.</p>
            <pb n="76"/>

            <p><q>By facts—you mean the fox-woman?</q></p>

            <p><q>Her origin, learned sir. It is impossible for the offspring of so vile a union to
                  be otherwise than unclean, as says the law</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> said solemnly, his hand emphasizing
               with its pressure on their shoulders his words:</p>

            <p><q>I know nothing of her origin, but to quote a favorite proverb of your own Japan,
                  remember: ‘The lotus springs from the mud!’</q></p>

            <p>The Japanese were silenced, deeply moved.</p>
            <pb n="77"/>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>VIII</head>
            <p>It became common knowledge in Fukui that the fox-woman had taken up her residence on
               the Matsudaira estate. The palace grounds covered nearly twenty acres, and were
               surrounded like a veritable wall on all sides of the estate by smaller buildings,
               which had once housed the retainers of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>,
               but which had not been occupied for years and were in a dishevelled and forlorn
               condition of ruin and decay. Two of these dwellings had been put in order, and these
               were occupied by the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> guard, the aged
               gateman who guarded the road leading to the mansion and the family of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s <pb n="78"/> interpreter, who, himself,
               however, had an apartment in the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign>.</p>

            <p>It was, therefore, quite possible for the fox-woman to find lodging in almost any of
               the remaining structures, and she could, if she desired, move from one to the other,
               and when unduly pressed, return to her old refuge of the woods and foothills of the
               mountains that bounded them on two sides of the estate.</p>

            <p>More than one of the household had thought they had seen and recognized her. On a
               still, hazy night, when the golden moon barely showed an inquiring face in promise of
               the summer nights to come, Genji Negato had shown her to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >samourai</foreign> guard. Just a white, fleeting face glimmering out like that of
               some hunted thing between the slender, towering trunks of a grove of bamboo. A moment
               only under the <pb n="79"/> streak of moonbeam, and then it had vanished like a mist
               at twilight.</p>

            <p>Was it a dream, they asked themselves, or indeed a manifestation of the just anger of
               the Buddha for sins committed in a former state. Were they henceforth to be harassed,
               goblin-haunted?</p>

            <p>And in the dawn, before the sun had barely shown its first glimmer of light across
               the eastern sky—in the misty, dewy, clammy dawn—the maid Obun had again come face to
               face with her.</p>

            <p>Obun was bent upon her usual task of the morning, the bringing of water from the pond
               to the house. Her eyes were swollen with sleep, she yawned cavernously, and as she
               stooped to dip the first of the pails into the water, something stirred the other
               side the pond, and she looked across to gaze, with fascinated eyes, <pb n="80"/> at
               the fox-woman, whose long, sunlit hair dripped in and out among the lotus and the
               water-lilies, as if she bathed it in their perfumed purity. Through this dripping
               veil of hair her face gleamed whitely. Her lips fell apart as though she listened,
               her eyes were startled, wild, and looked not at but through and beyond the dumbstruck
               serving-maid as though she saw her not at all. Slowly, stealthily, the fox-woman came
               to her feet, still with that weird, seeking, listening look upon her face, and thus
               with backward, shivering glances, she retreated to the bamboo grove.</p>

            <p>To his own amused dismay, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> found
               himself constantly on the watch for her. He had never seen the witch, but he had
               heard and felt her. She crept upon him in the evenings when he strolled about his
               garden, and she seemed to follow his <pb n="81"/> footsteps with the stealthiness of
               a wildcat, disappearing as fleetly as the wind at his mere turning.</p>

            <p>He was aware of her constant nearness if he merely stepped out of his house. Once
               when something brushed his cheek he was startled to find himself believing at once
               that it was she who had touched him. He plunged into the brush at his side, and, in
               the dark, thrust back the branches of the low-growing trees and bushes only to find
               himself up to his knees in water where he had stepped unawares into an overgrown
               rookery and fish-pond. As he floundered helplessly about he heard her softly laughing
               in a weird, mocking voice, which nevertheless seemed to overrun with tears.</p>

            <p>Holding his breath unconsciously he found himself straining his ears to listen to the
               sound, which indeed was <pb n="82"/> so faint a whisper of a laugh he could have
               believed he dreamed it.</p>

            <p>Sometimes as he drove abroad through the country she called to him from behind
               sheltering hillocks, and sometimes it seemed her voice floated down to him from some
               height—some giant tree-top, heavyladen with foliage; for it was the time of <q>Little
                  Plenty</q> (May) and all the land was green and warm.</p>

            <p>He found himself listening for her call—stopping, waiting for it, and returning with
               a sense of bitter disappointment when he heard it not. The servants gossiped, the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> whispered among themselves. They said
               the fox-woman had put a spell upon him. Genji Negato repeated this to him, and was
               rewarded by a look of startled contempt and anger.</p>

            <p><q>Spell!</q> The man of science repelled the very thought; but he began <pb n="83"/>
               to avoid the mountain-sides of his estate, and turned in preference to the
               river-road, whither she could not follow unless she revealed herself.</p>

            <p>Late that month, with no advance warning of its coming, whatever, a typhoon swept
               venomously across the province, leaving in its wake a shattering storm that shook and
               beat upon the aged <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> for a day and night; and,
               in the night, one encountered the shadow of the fox-woman in the great deserted halls
               of the Matsuhaira mansion.</p>

            <p>A wildly shrieking housemaid, calling <q><foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Hotogoroshi</foreign>!</q> (murder) at the top of her voice, gave the alarm, and
               from all parts of the palace the menials scuttled like frightened rats, taking refuge
               in the great kitchen in the rear.</p>

            <p>Even Genji Negato, with blanched face and shaking knees, followed the <pb n="84"/>
               last agitated <foreign xml:lang="ja">obi</foreign><note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">An <q>obi</q> is a belt.</note> into this dubious shelter. Here
               fortifying himself with heavier, if not trustier, implements than his swords he
               recovered his wits sufficiently to attempt to rally the panic-stricken army of
               servitors. Each in turn was ordered, urged, besought to go to the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s apartment. It was dastardly, so he averred, to
               leave the foreigner alone to face the unknown peril menacing him. For plain it was to
               be seen that she who had hitherto confined her malign activities to the large
               outdoors, had stepped at last across the threshold of the doomed palace. Undoubtedly,
               the typhoon which had crushed half the city so cruelly had been summoned by the witch
               in token of her power over them. Something horrible, sinister, was about to happen.
               Who could tell exactly what; but the signs were evil, evil!</p>
            <pb n="85"/>

            <p>He forgot the difference in his state and rank to these creatures of the kitchen, and
               found himself confiding to them his worst fears.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> slept from north to south, the
               position proper for a corpse alone! Genji Negato had pleaded with him to change, but
               the foreigner had laughed and insisted it was the true, scientific position, from
               pole to pole, in harmony with the electric currents of the atmosphere.</p>

            <p>The night before all four of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> guard had
               heard the plaintive howling of a dog; an owl was seen black athwart the moon; a
               tailless cat fled under the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Uki</foreign> (goblin-tree). The
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> had dutifully reported all these
               happenings to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, and now, when the blow
               seemed about to fall upon him, this stalwart guard, provided by their <pb n="86"/>
               prince, were sleeping comfortably in their <foreign xml:lang="ja">yashiki</foreign>
               on the very edge of the estate. It was the workings of the gods!</p>

            <p>Goto, the cook, found his fluttering tongue.</p>

            <p><q>This very morning</q>, said he, <q>trod thrice upon an egg-shell</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I miserably entangled my <foreign xml:lang="ja">obi</foreign> when dressing</q>,
               said another.</p>

            <p><q>And I, alas! bit my tongue when eating. My mistress said it was a sign some one
                  begrudged me my food. Who indeed but this spiteful fiend of the mountains?</q></p>

            <p>><q>Twice this week</q>, wailed the cook’s wife, <q>little Taro broke his chopsticks
                  when eating</q>.</p>

            <p>She fell to sobbing violently into her sleeve.</p>

            <p><q>Condescend to hush!</q> said Genji Negato. <q>Remaining silent is good</q>. The
               interpreter’s yellow face had <pb n="87"/> turned ashen, his hair appeared to stand
               almost on end, as he listened with suspended breathing.</p>

            <p>Outside the wild rain beat against the wind-swept trees, and dashed peltingly against
               the ancient <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign>. Jagged flashes of lightning
               zigzagged across the skies showing clearly through the walls, though the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">amado</foreign> were in place. It was not, however, to the sound of
               the tempest that the interpreter was giving ear. Somewhere within the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> itself new sounds were heard. It was as if a wind
               passed along the great halls and corridors and close upon its soft-footed flight
               there dashed something heavy, pursuing.</p>

            <p>Suddenly the main sliding screen or door, which led into the halls, fell inward with
               a crash. Over it something bounded like a ball of fiery light, passed through the
               kitchen <pb n="88"/> swift as a lightning flash and shot out into the storm, letting
               in a gust of rain and wind and thunder through the shaking doors.</p>

            <p>A moment later only, and panting like an animal in the chase, the great <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> burst into the chamber. He stopped short, staring as
               if confounded at the group shuddering against the farthermost wall. Slowly his gray
               face relaxed its tension. He tried to speak normally, but in spite of himself his
               voice shook, though his words were terse, commanding.</p>

            <p><q>There is nothing to be afraid of</q>, he said. <q>Translate that, if you please,
                  to the servants</q>, he sternly ordered his interpreter.</p>

            <p>The latter’s teeth were chattering. He could barely speak.</p>

            <p><q>Your excellency —you yourself have seen—</q></p>

            <p><q>I saw nothing</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>,<pb n="89"
               /> doggedly, <q>save the figure of a —woman!</q></p>

            <p><q>A woman!</q> cried the interpreter, almost in tears at the evident stubbornness of
               this fool-white-man. <q>Ah, most high-up sir, would you have condescended pursuit of
                  a mere female creature?</q></p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> looked care-worn, haggard, as if he
               struggled within himself. His deep, stern voice quivered in spite of himself.</p>

            <p><q>She was pressed against my wall, and fled fleetly as a wild thing when I threw the
                  doors open. The halls were unlighted. I could barely see her. My eyes were dazzled
                  at the sudden darkness. I may have been mistaken. And yet —and yet —it seemed to
                  me— her hair was <emph>gold!</emph></q></p>
            <pb n="90"/>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">

            <head>IX</head>

            <p><q>I am determined to satisfy my call it curiosity if you will—in regard to this
                  fox-woman</q>, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> told the three
               students who were his almost constant companions outside the school.</p>

            <p><q>I can get no help whatever from my servants and less from the guard. Genji Negato
                  is worse than a woman, and the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s officer
                  has point blank refused to give me a guide to direct me to her home on Atago
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign></q>.</p>

            <p>He paused and looked at the embarrassed faces of the students. They were devoted to
               him he knew, eager to serve and please him; yet even <pb n="91"/> they, sons of the
               new, sane Japan, feared the fox-woman. He was determined to win them over. </p>

            <p><q>So I want your help, Junzo, and yours, and yours, Nunuki and Higo. You can help me
                  if you will</q>.</p>

            <p><q>In what way?</q> demanded Nunuki cautiously. </p>

            <p><q>In any way you wish. Devise some scheme to trap this creature of the
               mountains</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Can we trap the north wind when it raves over the wilderness? Can we trap even the
                  gentlest zephyr when it dances across sunlit paths?</q> asked Junzo,
               wistfully.</p>

            <p><q>But the fox-woman is neither the rough north wind, nor the playful zephyr of the
                  south. She has a physical body, which even you will admit. The wildest thing of
                  the wildest forest can be caught</q>, and he added, half under his breath <q>and
                  tamed</q><pb n="92"/> Higo was considering, his young patrician face very
               thoughtful and intent; but Junzo with a burst of boyish pity put his hand timidly,
               affectionately into that of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>’s. </p>

            <p><q>Ah, dear <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign></q>, he said, <q>you are
                  tortured, obsessed by this wretched witch. She has put her evil spell upon
               you</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Nonsense</q>, said his teacher, almost roughly, releasing his hand. <q>This is not
                  helping me, Junzo</q>.</p>

            <p><q>But you have never heard the story of Chuguro. It happened in Yedo, many years
                  ago, your excellency. He was in the service of a <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Hatamoto</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>hatamoto</q> was
                     a high-ranking samourai employed by a daimyo.</note> named Suzuki, and seemed
                  like any other contented and healthy <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >ashigaru</foreign>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">An <q>ashigaru</q>
                     was a foot soldier in feudal Japan.</note> Then came a time when his comrades
                  missed him in the night, and they would not again see him till just before the
                  dawn, when he would creep back to his quarters <pb n="93"/> looking very strange
                  and white and exhausted. He became weaker and weaker from day to day, and at last
                  was unable to leave his couch at all, though he pleaded and begged to be carried
                  to the foot of a little bridge not far from the main gateway. But his friends were
                  obdurate. They called in a great Chinese surgeon, who made an examination of the
                  dying man and declared his veins had been literally drained dry of blood! All
                  declared it was the fox-woman; but the Chinese doctor said:’It was a frog, which
                  took to the soldier’s eyes the form of a woman’</q>. The boy paused, eying his
               teacher wistfully. <q>It is only a legend you will say, <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >sensei</foreign>, but I beseech thee, honored sir, to avoid contact with even
                  a stray fly, a spider, any crawling thing that may beat its way into your <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">yashiki</foreign>. Who knows what form this dreadful <pb n="94"/>
                  fox-woman may take to lure you</q>.</p>

            <p>Higo broke in impatiently: </p>

            <p><q>If indeed our <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign> is tortured, why waste words
                  on idle tales of the past? It is our duty to conceive some sensible scheme by
                  which to rid his excellency of the torture</q>.</p>

            <p>He began to talk swiftly and eagerly to his friends in Japanese, and gradually their
               resisting and doubting faces changed. With boy-like zeal they discussed the adventure
               proposed by Higo. Then the latter turned abruptly back to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>. </p>

            <p><q>You will permit us free access to your grounds at all and any hours?</q></p>

            <p><q>Most certainly. I will so instruct the gateman</q>.</p>

            <p><q>And, if necessary, we may call upon the guard for assistance?</q> The <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> slightly smiled.</p>
            <pb n="95"/>

            <p><q>Come now, surely you don’t anticipate so hard a task?</q></p>

            <p><q>We cannot tell. Even the guard may prove insufficient, but with <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Shaka</foreign>’s aid we may succeed!</q></p>

            <p>A look of alarm came to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s face.</p>

            <p><q>I wish no harm whatever to befall her. If you can surprise her upon one of her
                  nightly peregrinations in our neighborhood, and induce her gently but firmly to
                  accompany you, it will be gratifying. Once brought face to face with other
                  people—for I am convinced she is the same as we are—I hope to be able to lay this
                  bugaboo of a fox-woman</q>.</p>

            <p><q>As for that, impossible to say</q>, said Higo vaguely. <q>Now sinking, now
                  floating, thus is life says the poet. If disaster befall us in the undertaking it
                  will be as decreed of the gods. All things are beforehand ordained</q><pb n="96"
               /></p>

            <p><q>You anticipate hazard in the adventure?</q></p>

            <p><q>We would not attempt it otherwise</q>, proudly asserted Nunuki, his hand
               unconsciously caressing his sword-hilt, for these boy-<foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >samourai</foreign> all wore the sword. Higo indeed was of a princely house, and
               kin to Echizen himself.</p>

            <p>As the American looked at them, nerving themselves thus bravely for an encounter
               which to them at least was a deadly one, he suddenly thought of that frail, fleeing
               shadow which had gone before him in the gloom of the unlighted halls, and,
               unconsciously, he smiled. Why, boys as they were, any one of them could surely have
               crushed her between the palms of his sinewy young hands. If there were a real risk to
               run, he knew he would be the first to thrust himself in their way. But no! The
               undertaking <pb n="97"/> was <choice>
                  <sic>worth while</sic>
                  <corr>worthwhile</corr>
               </choice>, necessary, indeed, if only for the purpose of demonstrating the
               foolishness and cruelty of superstition. Even the melancholy tones of his favorite
               pupil, chanting almost monotonously the Buddhist text:</p>

            <p><q>Brief is the time of pleasure, and quickly turns to pain, and whatsoever is born
                  must necessarily die</q>, failed to move him. </p>

            <p>Young heroic fatalists! His heart went out to them overwhelmingly.</p>
            <pb n="98"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>X</head>
            <p>They had dug a trench hard by the castle moat. Over this they spread a net made of
               stout hempen rope, the edges of which were threaded in and out with elastic of great
               strength. This was stretched out and pinned, not too firmly, till it encircled and
               covered the pit. Then the sod and leaves and flower petals were carefully, though
               thinly, replaced, and the trap was ready for the Fox-Woman of Atago <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign>.</p>

            <p>Over all the Matsuhaira <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> a tense, silent
               excitement pervaded. Though the students had worked in secret, swiftly and silently
               on a dusky, rainy night, when their prey <pb n="99"/> would not be likely to be
               abroad, nevertheless no smallest menial on the place but knew that measures had been
               taken to entrap the fox-woman. They shivered deliciously over the dreadful prospect,
               for dire things had been promised them by the too garrulous Genji Negato, should any
               slightest inkling of the plans leak out from the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Shiro</foreign> itself.</p>

            <p>Even the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, who had been kept in complete
               ignorance of the actual methods they had taken to entrap her, was affected by that
               nameless feeling of uneasiness and unquiet, of repressed excitement and strained
               fear, which animated every other individual of his household.</p>

            <p>Throughout the evening he paced his great chamber in a moody, wretched silence. The
               sense of aloneness, of homesickness that sometimes came upon him in this land, seemed
                  <pb n="100"/> somehow this night to be deeper, more depressing. For days, indeed,
               he had been affected by a feeling of impending gloom and disaster. He had been
               restless, dissatisfied, nervous—unconsciously listening and waiting for something he
               seemed to expect was about to happen. Now he found himself analyzing this sick sense
               of depression which had pervaded his whole being these latter days, and seemed to
               reach its culmination on this silent night.</p>

            <p>Was it something in the look or tone of a student who recalled one of his own people,
               or was it the letters that had come to him from across the seas that made him realize
               they had cared for him more in that other country than he had realized? No—he faced
               the situation. This was not what had awakened the fever within him. <pb n="101"/> It
               was something deeper, something very beautiful and mystic. It was the golden hair of
               this Japanese Lorelei which had ensnared his longing! He could not banish its
               glitter, its <q>sun</q> as they called it here, its wild appeal from his mind. What
               was this creature of the mountains then, whom the gentlest of people had outcast? And
               what was this spell they said she had cast upon him ? The words seized upon his
               fancy, writhed his lips into a tortured smile. He, whom a mere woman had scorned,
               under the spell of a witch—a wild creature of these Japanese mountains whose face he
               had never even seen! It was preposterous—fantastic! And yet!</p>

            <p>The blood forsook his face, his lips. For days, for weeks, aye, for months he had
               thought of little else. Through half the luminous nights he had <pb n="102"/> watched
               and waited for her—had sought her desperately, hungrily. Day and night he had been
               waiting for her—waiting and listening, always listening, for that appealing voice of
               mockery and anguish that called to him insistently—to him alone! What mad fancies
               were these that had woven themselves like a subtle spider’s web into his clear, sane
               mind? It was the country, the people! He was in a land of gods and spirits!</p>

            <p>The night was very still and humid. The rain was gone, but its wet touch still clung
               in the air and was moist upon the grass and trees. The <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >shoji</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>shoji</q> is a
                  Japanese screen divider of latticed paper.</note> of the chamber had been removed
               entirely on the garden side, so that he practically was out-of-doors in an open
               pavilion or verandah. He could see the moon-tipped branches of the trees under whose
               shade myriad fireflies flickered in and out, rivalling <pb n="103"/> the distant
               stars above them in brilliancy. </p>

            <p>A cherry grove, from which blew fairy flakes, like confetti at a carnival, was at the
               extremity of the garden, and ever and anon a shower of these dancing - petals blew
               into his apartment, giving it an almost festive air. Great drifts of them lay in the
               corners of the room, like snow, and upon his couch, his tables, chairs and other
               furnishings, marking them with a white touch. In the shadow of a bamboo grove an
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">uguisu</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">The
                     <q>uguisu</q> is also known as the <q>Japanese bush warbler</q>.</note>
               thrilled forth its liquid song, and the wind-bells on the eaves tinkled musically
               back and forth in a faint breeze, as if in unison with the song of the wood-bird. </p>

            <p>From across the mountains came the gentle booming of the temple bells, telling the
               hour of the night, and, as if they were a signal listened for, the fox-woman crept
               out of the <pb n="104"/> dense bamboo grove and felt her way among the shadows till
               she came to the brink of the castle moat. Along its edge she wended her fleet,
               cautious way, till she came to a narrow wing, and over this she stepped silently. In
               the vague light of the moon, she seemed indeed a wraith, in her clinging gown of
               white, enshrouded in the wild veil of her hair. On and on she moved, as though she
               travelled over known and familiar paths. </p>

            <p>Suddenly, piercingly, in the still moonlight sounded the cry of the fox-woman, and,
               as suddenly, a silence fell, still as death itself. It was as if every living thing
               had paused to listen to that appealing cry of agony and terror. </p>

            <p>Silence! No one stirring. No one breathing. </p>

            <p>Then, as if brought violently into <pb n="105"/> life, the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> bounded to his feet, and in the light of the swinging
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">takahiras</foreign>, for a moment his great form loomed up
               menacingly. From all parts of the estate now came the sound of movement, and he saw
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> guard, their gleaming swords drawn
               fully and flashing eerily in the moonlight, charge down blindly in the direction of
               the cry. Within the woods came the sound of battle, the rumble of men’s savage,
               triumphant voices—a wild stirring and crying, and then again—the silence! </p>

            <p>Presently from out the brush they came, bearing their burden—stalwart men of war, all
               with their hands upon her. Out along the whitewashed paths, across the green-clipped
               lawns and through the garden of fragrant, blowing flowers they carried the fox-woman
               into the cherry-petalled chamber <pb n="106"/> of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>. There they set her down, still entangled, like a wild beast
               of the woods, in the net they had made to snare her. </p>

            <p>Unmoving she lay, as one indeed in whom life was extinct; but when the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> moved with an impulse of passionate yearning
               toward her, the boy Junzo, who loved him, sprang in his path. </p>

            <q>Touch her not, beloved <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign>! She is accursed,
               unclean!</q>

            <p>He put the boy roughly, savagely aside, and in a moment was kneeling above her. It
               was the task of a minute to cut free the bonds that bound her. Still she did not
               move. With hands that trembled in spite of themselves, gently, softly, he put back
               from her face the glittering veil of her hair, and as he did so his heart came up in
               his throat in a great, suffocating bound—for the face he <pb n="107"/> uncovered was
               that of a white woman! </p>

            <p>So perfect, so exquisite the small, sensitive face, he could only gaze upon it
               spell-bound. The great purple eyes, wide open, and shadowed with their long, gilded
               lashes; the thin little nose; the lips red as a new blown rose, and as sweet! —and
               crowning it all, the golden glory of her hair. </p>

            <p>In this land where only the brown face and densely black hair and eyes had been known
               for centuries, was it strange that this creature of the mountains seemed as of
               another world—a sprite indeed. This persecuted, hunted creature, whom they had
               trapped with ropes, as the hunter does the wild animals of the forests; this fragile,
               trembling, quivering little child—of his own skin and blood this was the fox-woman!
                  <pb n="108"/> She spoke not at all, though her wide-open eyes never moved from the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>’s face. Something in their glassy stare,
               their curious look as of a mist before them, brought an exclamation to his lips. He
               bent nearer to her, looked deeply, keenly into those unflickering eyes, and an
               imprecation swept his lips. </p>

            <p><q>And blind! My God!</q> he cried. </p>

            <p>As if his voice had moved her spirit into a sudden life, the fox-woman stirred
               soundlessly as a cat would have done. Suddenly she leaped blindly in the face of the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>. He stood unmoving, a great stolid wall
               against which she might hurl her puny strength in vain. </p>

            <p>Presently, gasping, exhausted, she drew backward, her fluttering hands crushed upon
               her heart as if to stop its frantic beating. A sound that had the vaguest, most
               piteous of <pb n="109"/> human notes came from the fox-woman’s lips, and suddenly,
               with the motion of a lost child in despair, she buried her face in the fragile
               shelter of her hands. </p>
            <pb n="110"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XI</head>

            <p>She was the daughter of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">damyuraisu</foreign> (foreign
               sailor) and of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Nii-no-ama</foreign> (Noble Nun of second
               rank). Bit by bit he drew forth her history from the students, who remained with him
               throughout the night. There was little enough they could tell him, beyond the fact of
               her parentage. Her father had betrayed his friend and benefactor, an Echizen prince;
               her mother had broken her vows to the Lord Buddha. And the creature herself! Now the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> could see for himself that the tales
               told about her were by no means chimerical. </p>

            <p>She was free to go, for he had cut <pb n="111"/> the ropes that bound her. Though
               blind, she could have found any exit of the chamber unaided. She made not the
               slightest move to go. Crouched back there against the farthest wall she stayed, with
               her wild flushed face peering out from between her parted hair, the eyes wide open,
               unblinking, scarcely moving. If she understood what they spoke, she made no sign; yet
               her face had a strained, listening look—as though she heard strange sounds that both
               baffled and troubled her. </p>

            <p>The dawn crept into the chamber, murky and sunless, and found them still there on
               guard as it were, with the distance of almost the entire room between them and the
               fox-woman, but watching her with unabated emotion. It was the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> who at last approached her. She sensed his coming and shrank
               back farther, if <pb n="112"/> that were possible against the wall. Now he stood
               directly before her, studying her in a profound silence. </p>

            <p>Slowly, cautiously she raised herself to her knees, and then to her feet. Now she
               stood fairly facing him, her back against the wall. A thin, searching little hand
               felt blindly before her, touched him. With a quick, animated movement her fingers now
               flew from his hand, up along his arm and shoulder, paused upon his pitted cheek,
               moved to his lips and rested there, soft as a feather, fragrant as a flower. </p>

            <p>Never in all the days of his life had he looked upon such a face as hers. Every
               quivering, sensitive feature seemed alive with the quickened, subtle sense of the
               blind. Even the little feeling fingers, how mortally alive they were, as they swept
               with their light, electrical touch across him!</p>
            <pb n="113"/>

            <p>When he put his great, firm hands upon her shoulders, he felt the shock, the
               startling tremble that agitated her. She stood poised for flight, uncertain, fearful,
               with the wild defiance of her nature only in part checked; but as his deep,
               compassionate voice addressed her, she became gradually passive and very still.</p>

            <p><q>You may not understand my words</q>, he said, <q>but you will their meaning. I
                  want to help you. I am your friend</q>.</p>

            <p>Her eyes became curiously blue, and the misty look faded like a shadow from their
               depths. Across the tremulous, scarlet lips a smile crept like the dawn. She moved a
               step nearer to him, and as he regarded her, fascinated, thrilled, the student, Junzo,
               broke the spell of silence. He had thrust himself forward with an impetuous,
               imploring motion.</p>
            <pb n="114"/>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Sensei</foreign>!—honored sir, teacher—!</q></p>

            <p>She turned her head craftily in the direction of the new voice, then slowly back to
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. There was a low, accusing note in her
               voice:</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">To-o-jin-san!</foreign> Thou too!</q> she said.</p>
            <pb n="115"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XII</head>

            <p>The Palace Matsuhaira, wherein the courteous Prince of Echizen had housed the foreign
               teacher, had lost all but two of its tenants. The odorous kitchens where but lately
               the army of servants had happily and noisily labored were now quite empty. So were
               the vast, cool halls, and the great, bare chambers. Like an army of rats, one and
               all, they had deserted the place, leaving the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> alone, save for that unseen one, who alternatively teased and
               entreated him.</p>

            <p>Even the faithful students, who had brought about her capture, had ceased to visit
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign>, having vainly implored the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> to <pb n="116"/> abandon the place. With a grim
               and stubborn patience, he kept doggedly to the course he had set himself.</p>

            <p>All over the house he found traces of her. Now she had slept in this chamber, now in
               that. Here she had prepared her diminutive, stolen meal of fruit, honey, and
               rice.</p>

            <p>He was aware of her constant nearness, and had he so desired, at almost any moment,
               he could have again seen her; but he was taking a more subtle means this time to
               entrap her. She must come forth of her own free will; then he would know he had her
               confidence, that she knew him for a friend. He found himself talking to her,
               sometimes sternly, in the chiding, coaxing tone one uses to a child. He would move
               from screen to screen as he talked, until he knew behind which one she <pb n="117"/>
               pressed; but he made no effort to force her from her hiding-place.</p>

            <p>Never a word would she speak in response until he was seated far removed from the
               sheltering screens, then she would begin reiterating the one appealing, accusing
               sentence:</p>

            <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, thou too! thou too!</q>

            <p>It was as if she knew no other words of her father’s language. He pondered their
               meaning. What was it she asked of him? Of what accused and reproached him? Did she
               hold him responsible for the manner of her capture—its cruelty ? He told her in slow,
               forceful words that he had known nothing of this, and waited in anxiety for some word
               or sound from her to indicate that at least she understood. She only laughed, that
               soft, mocking, tremulous little laugh with its inner sound of tears.</p>

            <p>The burning, humid days of June <pb n="118"/> slipped by on drowsy wing. School was
               closed for the season, and the foreign <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign> was at
               liberty to travel if he wished upon his vacation. The <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >samourai</foreign> body-guard were anxious to attend him upon any expedition that
               would take them away from the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign>. Genji Negato
               was available, outside the place. Every cringing, fearful, cowardly servant, who
               still drew wages from the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer, was
               anxious again to serve him. They made up deputations and committees, which fearfully
               approached the mansion, and threw their messages in little balls that pelted against
               the paper summer walls of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign> and pierced
               their way into the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s apartment. And still
               not once did he venture forth. </p>

            <p>Every sliding door and screen he had himself put in place. He did not <pb n="119"/>
               venture outside the house, even to step into the grounds. And a strange restless
               rumor began to float about the little town below, which told of the spell which
               chained the white man. </p>

            <p>Meanwhile within the mansion itself, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               was winning a strange victory. Timidly, like a fascinated wild bird, now approaching,
               now retreating, nearer and yet nearer, had come the fox-woman. There came a day when,
               though he did not turn to look at her, fearing instantly to lose her, she stood at
               last revealed. Only a few paces from him, there of her own free will, timorous,
               trembling, but unafraid. </p>

            <p>Her name was <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tama</foreign> (Jewel).<note type="editorial"
                  resp="pers:LW1">The word <q>tama</q> has multiple meanings, including
                  <q>jewel</q>. It is also associated with mythological figures and foxes.</note>
               She told it to him voluntarily, her hand upon her breast. He had not even asked her,
               nor did he by the slightest motion reveal the eager emotion her <pb n="120"/> words
               aroused when he found they were spoken in his own tongue. Haltingly, uncertainly,
               like a child for the first time feeling for its words, she essayed to speak.</p>

            <p><q>I am Tama</q>, softly she said, and then, as if enchanted by her ability to speak
               actual words to one who might hear and understand, she lapsed into excited, trembling
               speech, wholly unintelligible to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, for
               it was a medley of both her father and her mother tongue, neither of which she could
               properly speak.</p>

            <p>Suddenly she stopped abruptly, as if affrighted by her own bravado, and her fears
               again besetting her panically she retreated behind the screens. For the rest of that
               day, as least, he saw nothing further of her. But he was well pleased with matters as
               they were. It was worth <pb n="121"/> waiting for this, he told himself. As he paced
               his chamber, he made no effort to curb the exhilarating excitement that pervaded his
               whole being. </p>
            <pb n="122"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XIII</head>
            <p>Two days later she again came forth from her hiding-place. He had been aware of her
               hovering nearness all through the morning, but made no effort to induce her to come
               to him. One may entrap a wild bird; one cannot make it sing. He knew the course he
               was taking with her was right; he was exuberantly, boyishly happy at its evident
               success.</p>

            <p>Shyly, trustingly, of her own free will, again she had come to him. On the sensitive
               questioning face there was scarcely a trace of the wild, impish defiance that had
               seemed on that first day its only expression. She even smiled tentatively, pleadingly
                  <pb n="123"/>, as though she sought in this wise to win his approval. He spoke to
               her quietly, as though her presence there were but natural:</p>

            <p><q>Won’t you be seated?</q> he said.</p>

            <p>She hesitated a moment, sat a moment, rose to her knees uncertainly, and gradually
               subsided to the mat. Her face was down-drooped, the little white hands folded meekly
               in her lap.</p>

            <p><q>You are not Japanese</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>,
               gently. It was a simple, clear statement. If she understood anything of his language,
               it would be plain to her what he meant. A marvellous flush spread over her eager
               little face. The humid, misty eyes were clear as blue-bells now. A sound like an
               excited sob, half laugh, escaped her.</p>

            <p><q>Nipponese?</q> she said. <q>No—me? I am—<foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >To-o-jin-san!</foreign></q></p>
            <pb n="124"/>

            <p>Her hands went out to him in a sudden impulsive action. She moved on her knees nearer
               to him.</p>

            <p><q>Ah</q>, she cried, <q>speag those words of my father! Thas—beautiful!</q></p>

            <p>He was deeply moved, and took the little hands closely in his own. They were soft and
               small, clinging and confiding as a child’s. How they trembled and fluttered at first;
               then rested still, as if with a joyous new confidence. </p>

            <p>He could not bear to look at her beseeching face. In all the days of her life he knew
               he was the first she had not held at bay. She knew mankind only as creatures of prey.
               Was this the mocking sprite of the mountains, who even when entangled in the ropes of
               the hunter had fought so desperately, so savagely? What could he say to her, what
               words of <pb n="125"/> assurance that would penetrate her full understanding? As he
               pondered the matter, he saw the startled change that swept suddenly across her face.
               The hands in his own grew tense, rigid, clung to his own in a passionate frenzy of
               fear. </p>

            <p><q>You are afraid of something? What is it?</q></p>

            <p>The old hunted, listening look was upon her face again. She was shivering, trembling
               violently. Her voice came in a whispering gasp:</p>

            <p><q>I hear—those sound!</q> she said, her head uplifted.</p>

            <p>Only a lazy breeze was stirring, and moving the wind-bells to and fro. Suddenly he
               saw the silhouetted shadow on the <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign> wall. It
               moved silently, cautiously. Then the screens were slid soundlessly open, and the
               student Junzo appeared. For a moment he remained staring down upon <pb n="126"/>
               them, his young face becoming gray and stern.</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Sensei</foreign>! Then it is true</q> he burst out, and the
               look of despair on his face deepened.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> arose to his full gigantic height. His
               hand fell like a heavy weight upon the shoulder of the youth. His voice was rough,
               commanding.</p>

            <p><q>Look at this child, Takemoto Junzo. What is there you see in her to fear—to
                  hate?</q></p>

            <p><q>Ah, you, beloved <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign></q>, cried the boy
               passionately, <q>are bewitched, enchanted. Do I not see with my honorable eyes the
                  change that has befallen you? It is spoken of all over Fukui that you are in the
                  toils of this siren. I could not longer bear it, and, against my honorable
                  parent’s stern command, I came here to see for myself. Alas, it is too true! You
                  are bewitched, obsessed!</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="127"/>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> curbed his temper. His voice, though
               stern, was calm, as though he sought to humor the boy.</p>

            <p><q>What is the change you observe in me then?</q></p>

            <p><q>Your eyes are weak and soft like the dove’s. There is a melting, tender look unfit
                  for man upon your face. Your voice is gentle, like unto a woman’s. It is as if—as
                  if—the enamored weakness of a love possessed you!</q></p>

            <p><q>A love!</q> repeated the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, as though the
               very word were new to him. Suddenly a look of anguish came into his face, giving it a
               poignant, withering expression.</p>

            <p>The fox-woman had crept softly across the room. Now she leaned upon the farthest
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign>, her head lifted in a dreaming trance.</p>

            <p><q>Leave this accursed place with <pb n="128"/> me to-day</q>, urged the boy
               entreatingly. <q>My honorable father will gladly receive you as our honored guest.
                  Throw off the burden of this foul witch of the mountains. She can only soil your
                  excellency, and Fukui is prepared to mete out to her at last her proper
               fate</q>.</p>

            <p><q>I am a white man</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> slowly,
               in a deadly voice, and never had his student seen such an expression upon his face
               before. <q>As such I protect, not abandon, the women of my race. It will not be well
                  for Fukui if harm comes to either me, your guest and teacher, or to her, whom I
                  choose to befriend</q>.</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Sayonara</foreign>,<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"
                        ><q>Sayonara</q> means <q>farewell forever</q>. It is a final goodbye spoken
                     to a person one does not expect to see again.</note> then, excellent <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign></q>, said the boy brokenly, <q>I have done my
                  best</q>.</p>

            <p>As he pushed back the doors, the fox-woman glided soundlessly across his path. The
               boy found himself <pb n="129"/> looking directly into that shining face that had
               distracted all who had gazed upon it. Breathing heavily, almost as if he sobbed, he
               drew backward from her, his young face drawn and shaken. She spoke not at all, though
               she touched him with a timid, questioning hand. Something in the expression of the
               upturned face, in the tears that stood like dew in the wide, sightless eyes, aroused
               a new strangling emotion in the Japanese youth—reached at last his innermost sense of
               chivalry. He threw up his arm, with a sudden motion almost as of defense. Then,
               without a word or look backward, he jumped into the garden below, and fled along its
               paths. </p>
            <pb n="130"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XIV</head>

            <p>The days stole by with light tread. Without the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Shiro</foreign> Matsuhaira events of great national import were taking place.
               Fukui was disrupted, torn by the new tide of events that was to alter its destiny,
               for the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yaku doshi</foreign> (evil years)<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"><q>Yakudoshi</q> are years in life that are
                  believed to be unlucky in Japanese tradition.</note> were again upon them.</p>

            <p>No longer were the provinces to be ruled by individual princes, for one and all had
               come under the dominion of the Emperor.</p>

            <p>People were packing their household goods in haste and wending their ambitious ways
               toward the greater cities. In a single month Fukui lost half its population, and
               those left behind seemed to move about the <pb n="131"/> affairs of life as if in a
               dream, from which presently they would awake.</p>

            <p>Thus the political upheaval served for a time, at least, to distract the people’s
               mind from the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> and the fox-woman. It was but a
               temporary distraction. A whispering, sinister voice was at work. It ran in and out
               the houses of Fukui, and breathed its suggestive message to the disaffected,
               impoverished ones, and pointed out the cause of the calamity that had befallen them;
               for so sudden and drastic a change of government was bound to react disastrously upon
               the people at first, no matter how fortunate its ultimate end. The people of Fukui,
               like those of other feudal strongholds, were at present feeling only the first
               blighting, threatening touch of coming poverty.</p>

            <p>For hundreds of years the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> and their
               families had been dependent <pb n="132"/> aristocrats, who shared the rich fortunes
               of their lords. Now they found themselves suddenly thrust out of service; in the same
               position as the despised merchant or farmer, forced to seek employment no matter how
               repugnant or menial. Many of them chose what they considered the noblest and most
               heroic solution of the problem—<foreign xml:lang="ja">suppuku</foreign><note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">Eaton is referring to <q>seppuku</q>, a Japanese
                  ritualistic suicide that was originally reserved for samourai.</note>! The entire
               destruction of themselves and families. Many sought the larger cities intent on
               obtaining lucrative positions under the new government; many families were reduced to
               the direst poverty, and became dependents upon their own servants and trades
               people.</p>

            <p>Fukui had known the noblest of princes, and it was with a feeling of despairing
               confidence that the people awaited his return from Tokio. He was high in the councils
               of the Imperial Government. He could and <pb n="133"/> would—he must do much to save
               his beloved province from disaster. So they waited patiently, helplessly. Hope is at
               best but the comforter of despair, and as the days passed drearily by a new feeling
               took its place. </p>

            <p>A sullen, rebellious hatred for the white nations who had brought this new state of
               affairs about—a murderous, resentful impulse of revenge. It was the same feeling that
               had animated the misguided patriots of Satsuma, when they fought the allied fleet at
               Kagoshima, but it was uglier, meaner, for its force was directed upon two
               individuals, who, to the Fukui mind, represented the detested nations of the West.
               One of these, so Fukui firmly believed, was directly responsible for the disaster.
               She, the accursed outcast, who had descended from the mountains and taken up her <pb
                  n="134"/> abode in their very midst; who had laid her spell upon the great
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, who had been their friend! </p>

            <p>Many a <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>’s itching hand crept stealthily to
               the forbidden sword, for, by the new law, they were not permitted to wear the sword,
               as he measured his misfortunes through the blighting nearness of the fox-woman. Many
               a distracted mother crooned a promise to her sleeping babe that the dread <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja"
               >gagama</foreign><!-- *Cannot confirm what this translates to in Japanese -->
               (goblin) of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign> that had menaced them for so
               long was at last to be extinguished.</p>
            <p>And meanwhile, in the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> Matsuhaira, another kind
               of dream was unfolding its rose-lined wings. </p>
            <pb n="135"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XV</head>

            <p><q>To what are you listening, Tama?</q></p>

            <p>He had come upon her pressed closely against a latticed screen, whose opening looked
               out upon the river leading to the city below. She started at his coming, and turned
               toward him, her back against the screen.</p>

            <p><q>I listen to the noise of thad river</q>, she said, and there was a conciliating,
               pleading note in her voice.</p>

            <p><q>You cannot hear the river from here. It is very shallow—barely stirs. There is
                  something else you are listening to?</q></p>

            <p><q>It is the <foreign xml:lang="ja">uguisu</foreign></q>, she said quickly, <pb
                  n="136"/> as though she sought to disarm his fears. <q>It no longer sings,
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. I listen for hees voice
               again</q>.</p>

            <p><q>It never sang, my child, save at night. What is it that troubles you? You seem
                  always to be listening, waiting—so fearfully—so anxiously. You are afraid of
                  something. Tell me what it is?</q></p>

            <p>His deep, lowered voice was as caressing and tender as a mother’s. She faltered,
               turned from him. Her voice overran with vague sighs.</p>

            <p><q>I hear even those mos’ sof of honorable whisper. I hear some noise of—trobble! I
                  am afraid—for you—kind <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign></q>.</p>

            <p><q>For me! I am amply protected here in Fukui. I have a body-guard of <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>, besides Genji Negato, who will come back
                  quickly enough when he has mastered his foolish fears</q>.</p>
            <pb n="137"/>

            <p><q>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> gone</q>, she said, simply.</p>

            <p>He was silent a moment, realizing there was nothing to be gained by attempting to
               deceive her. How, when or where she learned of these matters he never knew; but she
               knew perhaps more than he did of what was happening in Fukui.</p>

            <p><q>Even if it is so</q>, he finally said, <q>and the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samourai</foreign> too are gone, you have nothing to fear. Less than a week
                  ago a courier brought word to me from Tokio.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"
                     >Eaton is likely referring to <q>Tokyo</q>.</note> I am expecting friends in
                  Fukui very shortly now</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Frien?</q> she repeated wistfully, <q>Like unto you, kind <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Tojin-san</foreign>?</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes—white men, and Japanese, too, for that matter. I have good friends in Tokio.
                  They are coming here to see you, my child</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Alas!</q> she said, shrinking slightly from him, <q>Why do they come?</q></p>
            <pb n="138"/>

            <p><q>I asked them to come</q>, he said, very gravely. <q>I feel I am right, and that by
                  a simple operation we will be able to make you see, as other people do, my
                  child</q>.</p>

            <p>The word appeared to trouble her.</p>

            <p><q>I see already, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign></q>, she said.</p>

            <p><q>What do you see, Tama?</q> he asked her huskily.</p>

            <p>The words came floodingly, tumultuously to her lips. The misty eyes were blue as the
               sea and as beautiful.</p>

            <p><q>I see thee, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. Thou art beautiful ad my
                  sight, lig’ unto the gods</q>.</p>

            <p>A look of suffering left its mark upon the face of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign>. He gazed at the kindling face of the girl before him, and the
               old strangling, yearning emotion swept over him.</p>

            <p><q>Give me more sight—if it is your honorable wish</q>, she said, <q>bud <pb n="139"
                  /> already I see—I know!</q> She pressed her fingers impetuously to her eyes.</p>

            <p><q>I see the light—the dark. It is a worl’ of shadows on my eyes, and shadows are
                  lig’ unto our dream mos’ beautiful of all!</q></p>

            <p>His voice was firm, almost solemn.</p>

            <p><q>You have been wandering around in a black wilderness all of your life; you do not
                  know what it is, my poor little one, to see the sun! But, with God’s good help, I
                  am going to lead you out of the wilderness—into the light!</q></p>

            <p><q>You are the light!</q> she said, throbbingly, and slipped to her knees, putting
               her face against his hand. Something bounded against the wall and came whistling
               through the <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign>. It grazed the cheek of the
               kneeling fox-woman, and imbedded itself against the woodwork of the opposite wall.
               She put up her hand <pb n="140"/> with a quick, startled movement, but though she
               turned a questioning, fearful face upon the great <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign>, she could not see how deathly white he had become. He bent
               suddenly above her.</p>

            <p><q>Make me a promise. Repeat after me, that no matter what might befall us, you will
                  remain with me—you will not desert me!</q></p>

            <p>With her face pressed against his hand, her eyes fervently closed, she repeated the
               words as a veritable prayer.</p>
            <pb n="141"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XVI</head>
            <p>In the sunken garden directly beneath his rooms he saw that sinister thing below,
               waiting in a throbbing silence. It seemed as if his gardens were alive with them. Who
               had summoned them? For what were they waiting?</p>

            <p>From his elevation above them he spoke, his clear voice booming out above their
               heads.</p>

            <p><q>Genji Negato, I desire your services</q>.</p>

            <p>From somewhere in the shadows the voice of the interpreter came back at him like a
               cold slap in the face.</p>

            <p><q>When the evil spirit of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign> shall have
                  left the abode of the <pb n="142"/> exalted <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Tojin-san</foreign>, Genji Negato will humbly return for service</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>’s incisive, perfectly controlled voice
               continued coldly:</p>

            <p><q>By command of the Prince of Echizen you are in my service. In his name, I order
                  you to control your foolish fears, or take the consequences of your Prince’s
                  displeasure</q>.</p>

            <p>A strange voice, rumbling, sneering, responded to this statement. Like a flash, upon
               the retort, came the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>’s ringing order to the
               interpreter:</p>

            <p><q>Translate the words just spoken, if you please</q>.</p>

            <p><q>He says, your excellency, that the Prince of Echizen has been summarily called to
                  Tokio. If the new law is indeed enforced he may not return</q>.</p>

            <p>For a moment the far-seeing mind <pb n="143"/> of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign> staggered before this appalling news, which, if true, meant the
               possibility of his being suddenly cast adrift and left to protect himself from the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Jo-i</foreign> menace, against which Echizen himself had
               taken such precautions in his behalf. While his mind revolved all the possible perils
               of his position, a new voice sprang ringingly out of the shadows of his garden—a
               boy’s clear, unfaltering voice with its reassuring note of loyalty and affection.</p>

            <p><q>Beloved <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign>, we, your students, offer
                  ourselves in place of your guard</q>.</p>

            <p><q>What may babes know of a sword’s honor?</q> snarled the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >samourai</foreign>, who had already spoken. <q>What strength may the foreign
                  devil lean on for his new support?</q> he demanded with cutting sarcasm.</p>

            <p>The burly laugh that followed was suddenly stopped, as the student <pb n="144"/> Higo
               flung himself defiantly before them all.</p>

            <p><q>I, Higo, kin of your absent Prince, will answer you. There are nine hundred
                  students, <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> themselves, and sons of a
                  thousand <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> before them. All of these are
                  loyal to our teacher. They will protect and fight for him, if necessary</q>.</p>

            <p>Now the answering voice snarled merely in explanation.</p>

            <p><q>Who spoke of harm to your <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign>? It is not him
                  we seek. We have come for the Fox-Woman of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Yama</foreign>, who blights our fortunes, who brings sickness, poverty, and
                  disaster upon our ancestors and our children, and whose doom has been spoken by
                  Fukui. You have trapped her, young sirs of the college, like any other female
                  beast of the woods. Let older, more experienced hands finish your honorable work.
                     <pb n="145"/> There are those of us whose hands performed a like service upon
                  the debased parents of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">gagama</foreign>, and whose
                  palms itch now to mingle her blood with her sire’s. Let but the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> eject this siren of the mountains, and we
                  will be satisfied</q>. </p>

            <p><q>It cannot be done</q>, frantically cried the boy Junzo. <q>I myself have touched
                  the wretched, helpless one, and, as the gods in heaven hear me, she is but—human,
                  as ourselves!</q></p>

            <p>A roar of derision greeted the boy’s passionate outcry, and there was a concerted
               movement toward where the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> stood towering
               above them, his arms crossed, his keen, stern eyes regarding them piercingly.</p>

            <p>Some one pushed forward the interpreter, and the craven, agitated fellow now faced
               his master. He made several ineffectual efforts to speak, gulped at the lump which
               rose persistently <pb n="146"/> in his throat. Before him loomed the grim, sardonic
               face of this west countryman he had always inwardly feared and respected; behind him
               the rabble of dissatisfied ronin. </p>

            <p>Gasping, trembling, he repeated to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> the
               verdict of the mob. They called upon him to deliver into their hands the fox-woman.
               Failing to do that, they would storm the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> and
               take her by force. Whiningly, pleadingly, he begged his master to hurl from his house
               the wretched spirit he was harboring. </p>

            <p>To this demand the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> returned slowly, as
               though he carefully chose his words, that if one hair upon the head of the one he
               protected were touched, the whole Fukui should feel a vengeance such as never had
               befallen it before. He, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>—a citizen of a
               mightier country than this—was the guest of one of their <pb n="147"/> princes. Not
               alone his friends at home, but those here—the very Emperor himself, who had pledged
               himself publicly to uphold the new enlightened laws, borrowed from the West—would
               avenge insult and wrong done to him—the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>. </p>

            <p>His answer, translated by Negato, raised a turmoil of angry discussion, and that one
               who seemed to be the leader of the company, sprang headlong forward, as if to show
               the way to those who hesitated. He climbed half-way up the steps to where the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> stood, and quick as a cat drew forward his
               swords. </p>

            <p>Every eye was turned upon the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. He was
               standing tautly erect, his heavy, pugnacious chin thrust out. As the sword of the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> touched him he drew slightly backward,
               then with a swift, merciless bound sprang headlong upon his assailant, <pb n="148"/>
               his great white fists flashing more vividly than the steel had done. Backward went
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>, his swords flying out of either hand.
               Without a cry, he fell upon the grass path beneath. </p>

            <p>And the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was back in his place, facing
               them, waiting for them, calm, still unmoved, but very terrible and mighty to look
               upon. </p>

            <p>In the deadly silence that followed, the student Nunuki passed the castle gates,
               followed by his valiant, stalwart little army of fellow-students. They moved in a
               line steadily onward, spread out on all sides and completely surrounded the house of
               the Tojin. </p>

            <p>Ere the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign> could realize it they found
               themselves encircled by an army four times their own in number. Their leader lay
               before them, unmoving; and above them <pb n="149"/> towered the grim, terrible figure
               of this west-countryman, who represented in his gigantic person all the power and
               strength they had come to know and superstitiously believe belonged to the West. </p>

            <p>One by one, they moved toward the gates, broke into smaller groups, passing the long
               line of student warriors without a word or sign of war. </p>

            <p>Presently the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> moved a step lower down into the
               garden. He stood a moment, staring frowningly at the still form lying at his feet.
               Then slowly, unwillingly he stooped, and turned it over. A deep breath escaped him.
               For a moment things swam dazedly before him, for the white, agonized face upturned
               was that of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer, the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Samourai</foreign> Gihei Matsuyama! </p>
            <pb n="150"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XVII</head>
            <p>As a mother seeks a lost child, so the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               frantically scoured every nook and corner of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Shiro</foreign> Matsuhaira for the fox-woman.</p>

            <p>In the interval in which he had faced that threatening, blood-hungry mob, she had
               gone! He was torn with sick forebodings of the fate that might have befallen her.
               That she had gone of her own free will, he could not believe—no, not after the
               promise she had made him! </p>

            <p>And so, with his wound untended, his brain swimming in vertigo, he staggered from
               room to room, until the morning dawned dim and gray, <pb n="151"/> and the sun crept
               over the horizon with its bright, hard eye. </p>

            <p>Wild and haggard-eyed, shaking as though he were afflicted with ague, he came finally
               back to his own chamber. Here his students awaited him, eager to show him their
               goodwill, to congratulate him and gossip over the certain punishment that would
               overtake those who had molested him. But he heard no word that they spoke, and
               presently they seemed to realize that something was wrong with the great <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>, and they drew apart, whispering, and regarding him
               with awed glances. </p>

            <p>The maid, Obun, snivelling and shaking with fear, crept into the vast, deserted
               kitchen and fell to putting it in order. In another wing of the house the voice of
               the lately craven Genji Negato was heard, and out along the road, loaded down with
                  <pb n="152"/> their belongings, trailed the little caravan of menials, creeping
               humbly back to their old employment. </p>

            <p>Oh, these were dark, impoverished days for Fukui! Who could refuse remunerative
               employment such as this ? The honorably enlightened students of the university had
               vanquished the disgruntled, fighting ones <foreign xml:lang="ja">samourai</foreign>
               Matsuyama, their leader, was desperately sick, shorn of his power, and deserted even
               by his friends.</p>

            <p>And the fox-woman was gone! No one knew how or when she had gone. They told, in
               whispers, of her ghostly vanishing, and some said the bottomless lake of Matsuhaira,
               with its white, chilly lotus, held a secret all its own. But <q>The Lotus tells no
                  tales</q>, as the proverb has it, and how should they know, and why should they
               care whether the fiendish <foreign xml:lang="ja">gagama</foreign>, <pb n="153"/> who
               had haunted their master for so long, floated beneath the smiling water-flowers or
               not? </p>

            <p>They gathered together, these gabbling, faithless servants, and discussed ways and
               means to propitiate the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. Following the
               lead of Genji Negato, finally, they took their courage into their hands and came to
               his apartment. Barely had they entered the room, however, ere they fled again. </p>

            <p>One look only at the distorted face was enough. Like a pack of startled sheep they
               turned tail and fled from his presence, leaving him once more alone, pacing and
               repacing, with staggering, irregular steps, the floor, crunching his great hands
               together as if in some mortal agony. </p>

            <p>What weakness was this that robbed him of his manhood! What anguish that pierced to
               his very <pb n="154"/> marrow? Was this what the son of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Daimio</foreign>’s high officer had endured when he had followed the fox-woman
               out into the mountains? Persistently, dazedly he thought of Gihei Matsuyama, and he
               asked himself repeatedly why—why? Suddenly it was clear—he knew why. He had killed
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer ! With his own mighty
               hands he had killed the father of Gihei Matsuyama! </p>

            <p>A Chinese doctor, brought by the students Junzo and Higo, examined him at a safe
               distance, and he said the foreign <foreign xml:lang="ja">sensei</foreign> was
               afflicted with a malady of the brain. </p>

            <p>Outside in the summer gardens, serious-eyed, grave-faced boys looked at each other
               with startled glances, and in the city people were telling in the streets of the
               dreadful punishments certain to be meted out to those who had molested the guest of
                  <pb n="155"/> their absent Prince; for word had, at last, come from Tokio that he
               had started on his way back to Fukui. </p>

            <p>The day with its sun and fragrance passed away unseen to the great, blank-minded
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>. But when the night came, with a whispering
               breeze about the ancient Matsuhaira, he raised a listening head. </p>

            <p>As on that first night in Fukui, plainly, distinctly he heard the fluttering, human
               knocking upon his <foreign xml:lang="ja">shoji</foreign>. Holding his breath,
               treading on tiptoe, he found his way to the doors, drew them apart and looked out
               into the dusky woods beyond. Howhisears tingled now, straining for that old caressing
               call: </p>

            <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">T-o-o—jin-san! Too-jin-san!</foreign></q>

            <p>Gently, softly, wooingly, he answered the fox-woman, breathing her name into the
               still air about him:</p>

            <q>Tama! Tama!</q>
            <pb n="156"/>

            <p>And, as on that other night, again he dropped down into the garden. Over the
               green-clipped lawn he went, across the wing of the moat, into the bamboo grove, and
               on and on into the beckoning, luring woods of Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Yama</foreign>.</p>
            <pb n="157"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XVIII</head>
            <p>To awaken on an afternoon in summer upon a bed of moss and fragrant leaves; to rest
               tired, aching eyes upon a clear, pale sky, which smiled divinely through interlacing
               boughs of towering pines and hemlocks; to hear the whistling calls of the wood-birds;
               the murmuring, sobbing laughter of some fairy brooklet close at hand; to feel the
               touch of a fugitive gentle breeze upon one’s brow—this was the fate of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>! </p>

            <p>For how long he could not have told he lay unmoving, staring dreamily at the sky
               above him, a sense of contentment, of rest, of comfort — <pb n="158"/> such as one
               might feel after a long, exhausting race, permeating his whole being. </p>

            <p>Then suddenly upon his consciousness there stole another sense—the dim, exquisite
               feeling of a loved presence close at hand, and he raised himself slowly, weakly upon
               his elbow. It was like music in his ears, that faint, caressing voice he had listened <choice>
                  <sic>for for</sic>
                  <corr>for</corr>
               </choice> so many days:</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">To-o-jin-san! Goran nasai!</foreign></q> (august glance
                  deign).<note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1"><q>Goran nasai</q> translates to
                     <q>please look</q></note></p>

            <p>She was kneeling by his side, her questioning, wistful face hovering above his own;
               her soft, timid little fingers touching his brow, his eyes, his lips. </p>

            <p>He felt himself falling backward again, as if in some delicious swoon, from which
               there could be no awakening. Then like the dimly remembered scenes of a vague dream,
               he seemed <pb n="159"/> to recall a time wherein he had wandered through some
               unending woods, seeking, seeking! Now the dream had ended in this—this that was part
               of the dream itself! </p>


            <p>She stirred ever so slightly, and as if he feared she might vanish by her mere
               stirring, he reached up the great, once mighty arms, and sought to envelop her within
               them. </p>

            <p>Her hair had the odor of the pine woods; upon her lips there was the breath of some
               sweet incense. She remained passive within his grasp, but presently her voice, with
               its tremulous tone of tears, broke the spell between them—reached him with the gentle
               appeal of a child distressed. </p>

            <p><q>Honorable water good for thirsty throat</q>, she said.</p>

            <p>Now he released her, and she drew back to find the little cup beside her. <pb n="160"
               /> He let her raise his head and bring the cup to his lips, and with his eyes still
               hungrily upon her he drank the water.</p>

            <p>He was content merely to gaze at her, though it troubled him that she no longer
               smiled. She said in a very stricken voice:</p>

            <p><q>August food also good for <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. Bud, alas! I
                  god nudding bud rice! Thas good enough for Tama bud nod for you, <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign></q>.</p>

            <p>Even in his weakness he laughed joyously at the mere notion of food fit for her being
               unfit for him, and at the sound of his low laughter her face lighted up
               wonderfully.</p>

            <p><q>You gittin’ better!</q> she exclaimed. <q>Now I bring you thad rice joyously. Too
                  bad—bud thas all I got! I go ad grade temple at top those hill. Priest too fat run
                  quick to catch at me</q>. She laughed with an element of her old mischievous
               defiance.</p>
            <pb n="161"/>

            <p>As he did not speak, too intent upon gazing at and marveling on the fairness of her
               face, her expression changed to one of melting anxiety.</p>

            <p><q>I am lig’ unto those foolish <foreign xml:lang="ja">karasu</foreign> [crow], who
                  mek chatter all thad time. Condescend forgive me, <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Tojin-san</foreign>. I nod speag agin mebbe for—for twenty hour—vacs?</q></p>

            <p>No one had ever kissed her hands before. The sound, the touch aroused her wonder, her
               apprehension. She drew her hands instinctively from his, and for a moment held them
               up before her, almost as if she looked at them. Then with an impetuous, laughing
               little sob she thrust them back upon him:</p>

            <p><q>Do agin ad my hands, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>! I lig’ those</q>,
               she said.</p>

            <p>It was not alone the pallor of bodily illness, but of some mental pain that <pb
                  n="162"/> swept over his face, as he set the little hands back into her lap,
               reverently, gently.</p>

            <p>Later, when strengthened with the simple meal she made for him, she told him how the
               night before she had come upon him in the Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign>
               woods. It was but two days since the terrible events at the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Shiro</foreign> had driven them both forth into this enchanted wilderness. He had
               been ill but a night; yet it seemed to him many days. </p>

            <p>No, she had not heard him calling her, nor had she called him. This, too, was part of
               the dream; but something louder than any human cry had reached her in her
               hiding-place in the mountains, the intuitive, certain sense of the blind. She had
               retraced her steps down the mountain-side, and had gone cautiously seeking in the
               woods for him; and <pb n="163"/> the gods had guided her aright. Ah! to his very
               feet. </p>

            <p>She humbly begged him to pardon her for leaving him; but she had thought this was the
               only way she could save him from those who hated her. Now—now she wished to repeat
               the prayer and promise she had made him down in the old <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Shiro</foreign>. Never again would she desert him. She would always abide by his
               side. She humbly entreated that he would permit her to remain with him, even if she
               must follow him throughout the world as a slave, the meekest and lowliest of
               servants. </p>

            <p>He did not reply, so obsessed was he still with the vision of her loveliness.
               Throughout the golden afternoon he lay there watching her every little movement, her
               slightest change of expression; thrilling under the touch of her hands, the sound of
               her <pb n="164"/> voice; obeying her slightest request; permitting her to serve him
               as if he were a babe and she his mother. </p>

            <p>Gradually the murmuring of the crickets in the grass, the soft chirping of the birds,
               even the babbling of the brook, the sighing of the gentle breezes seemed to soften
               their tone to one concerted murmuring lullaby. A veil crept gently over the sky,
               shutting out the sun and its light. </p>

            <p>She put a pillow of pine needles beneath his head, and she covered him over with a
               downy, silken mantle that smelled of temple incense and was gorgeous beyond words
               with the golden embroidery of some sacred order. </p>

            <p>And presently as he drowsed deliciously under the warm fragrant silk, he felt her
               stirring at his feet, <pb n="165"/> and her tired little voice came whispering to him
               as if from very far away: </p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Sayonara, Tojin-san! Imadzuka!</foreign></q> (Now we
               rest).</p>
            <pb n="166"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XIX</head>

            <p>One does not always count the gilded days of summer in the mountains. It might have
               been a month, a week, or a few days in which the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign> and the fox-woman wandered over Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Yama</foreign>. But the season of Little Heat passed into that of the Great Heat,
               and they did not know it. </p>

            <p>The mountains were cool; there was a green wonder world about them. Soft shadows
               flickered across the sun-burned paths; intangible breezes fanned them with their
               scented breaths. They trod a carpeted paradise that was all beauty, all harmony. They
               felt like the <pb n="167"/> birds which blew over them, or came shyly, timorously at
               her calling to share her morsel of rice and berries. </p>

            <p>Even had he desired to do so, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> could not
               have found his way back to the city. Seven-eighths of the province is mountain land,
               and she had led him over paths she alone knew, and indeed had made—narrow, hidden
               little paths that traced their unending way in and out the densest portion of the
               wooded mountains. </p>

            <p>They passed no humblest lodge, no smallest temple even, though he knew that there
               were many in the mountains, and the music of their bells reached them at times like
               the tingling call of a familiar voice very far away. </p>

            <p>She knew every secret corner of the mountains. The purest springs, hidden pools and
               lakelets, caves of unbelievable <pb n="168"/> wonder and beauty, she showed now to
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>. </p>

            <p>Clouds of sacred pigeons followed her as if they knew her. They were of her own
               Temple Tokiwa, she told him, and were part of her heritage from the ancestors of her
               mother who had founded the temple. She knew them all—every single bird, so she told
               him proudly; knew, too, why they were wandering thus far from home. They were seeking
               her, their guardian, who had been gone for so many, many days. </p>

            <p>For the first time she recoiled from him when he suggested that they utilize the
               birds for food. Up till then they had depended entirely upon the seemingly
               inexhaustible stores of rice she seemed to have hidden in a hundred different places
               in the mountains, and upon the fish trapped in the streams, the fruit and <pb n="169"
               /> wild vegetables which were plentiful enough. She had never dreamed of the pigeons
               as an addition to their diet, and her expression was quite tragic and piteous. </p>

            <p><q>They are of the temple</q>, reverently she said. <q>The gods love them, and I—I
                  may not eat the forbidden meat</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Forbidden meat?</q></p>

            <p>She looked at him timidly with a new expression in her face. It was as if a flame had
               crept into her eyes and set its touch upon her lips. She had crossed her hands upon
               her bosom.</p>

            <p><q>I, too, am <foreign xml:lang="ja">Ni-no ama</foreign>, like unto my mother</q>,
               she softly said. <q>For both our sin I got mek thad atonement unto Buddha!</q></p>

            <p>He regarded her in a spellbound silence. There was something about her words, her
               actions, withal their <pb n="170"/> simplicity, that held a sacredness. She, against
               whom the hostile hands of an entire Buddhist community had been raised, a priestess
               of the Buddha! It was impossible, preposterous! She had been but a child when her
               parents were killed. What could they have taught her thus early ? </p>

            <p>She seemed to realize from his silence his doubts, and suddenly she stepped back,
               raising her hands high above her head, bringing the tips of the fingers together. A
               moment she stood with her face upraised, her eyes closed. </p>

            <p><q>For you, oh <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, I will danze! It is as my
                  mother have tich me the danze for the gods. <foreign xml:lang="ja">Haiken
                     suru</foreign>!</q> (Adoringly look). </p>

            <p>From side to side she swayed, her small, exquisite hands moving in the languorous
               motions of the dance. <pb n="171"/> Never in even the greatest temples of Kioto or
               Nikko had he seen a priestess perform as she was doing. He thought of the glittering
               robes of the hundred nuns chanting their splendid ritual before some gorgeous altar,
               of their impassive, stony faces, their ebony hair, their narrow, inscrutable eyes.
               But she, with her unbound hair of gold, her bosom and face of snow! </p>

            <p>Yes, they were right, they of Fukui! She was an incarnation of the Sun Goddess,
               tripping like the Spring upon the earth, and inspiring in the hearts and eyes of all
               who saw her sensations of adoration, and of those who dared not look, of fear—fear
               and hatred! </p>

            <p>She had stolen the face and vestments of the goddess, so they had said; but her soul
               was that of a fox!</p>

            <p>There burst upon him suddenly a <pb n="172"/> realization of the impassable gulf
               between them, and with the knowledge came an overwhelming sense of revolution, the
               mad, irresistible passion of the primitive man who knows only his desires. </p>

            <p>But a moment later she was at his feet, her pure, trusting face smiling appealingly
               up at him. </p>
            <pb n="173"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XX</head>
            <p>Now came the Season of White Dew. The days were unbelievably beautiful. The first
               russet touch of the autumn barely cast its shadow upon the green about them, the
               yellow tints of leaf and flower mellowed into a dull crimson glory. </p>

            <p>But the nights turned chill, and in the early mornings there was the heavy print of
               the frosted dew upon the ground.</p>

            <p>Unconsciously they quickened their lagging footsteps, and turned into shorter paths
               that would bring them sooner to <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon Sha</foreign>, the
               cemetery of <q>Soul Beckoning Rest</q>, which was to be the end of their journey.
               This <pb n="174"/> was her home, so she said—the gardens of the temples of her
               ancestors. Only a few hill-lengths from the cemetery was the Temple Tokiwa, deserted,
               almost in ruins, but—her home! </p>

            <p>There her parents had lived—and died! Here she had been happy in her solitary
               childhood, hidden and sheltered by fearful but loving parents. Here her mother had
               taught her to dance for the gods and entreat them with her prayers; here her father
               had told her of another God, another heaven. After her parents were gone, the aged
               temple had been her only sure place of refuge, a sanctuary wherein even the stoutest
               of hunters dared not penetrate; for the wrathful gods still stared with their
               dreadful eyes upon the affronted altar, and at the very portals the demons <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Ni-o</foreign>, guarding the sacred <pb n="175"/> gates, might no
               longer be propitiated. </p>

            <p>Now confidently, happily, with the pride of a child thither she was leading the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>, eager to show him this beautiful shelter
               she wished to share with him forever. But, ah! how sweet had been the mountain paths
               this summer, and why need they hasten? The restless, vindictive little city was very
               far away, and the fox-woman trod upon territory all her own, hers by right of every
               instinct, and by the very law of the land, did she but know it, which made her proper
               heir to her ancestors’ property.</p>

            <p>Now they were very near to the temple, and soon she would spread forth her arms and
               say to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>: </p>

            <p><q>Behold, dear exalted one, here is my honorable home. Condescend to step upon its
                  floor</q>.</p>

            <p>And in her mind she fancied the face of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>
               would shine with a great light of happiness.</p>

            <p>Now he said to her dreamily, as he followed her through a shadowy bypath which crept
               into a sunlit forest of dripping willow-trees:</p>

            <p><q>Someday I shall awake. It cannot be true that I am here with you alone in these
                  wild mountains, wandering along in this aimless bliss!</q></p>

            <p>Because she put back her hand, and he took it perforce in his own, he continued in
               his low, wooing voice:</p>

            <p><q>And when I wake, little Tama, I will know the truth of what you once said to me:
                  that our dreams are the most beautiful of all</q>.</p>

            <p>She stopped and turned back to him, with the tall foliage and grass almost burying
               her in its thickness: </p>

            <pb n="177"/>

            <p><q>You god no udder dream more beautiful?</q> she questioned wistfully.</p>

            <p><q>No other</q>, he answered softly. <q>Have you?</q></p>

            <p><q>No. This is mos’ bes’ dream of all—jost be lone wiz you ad those mountains! Thas
                  bes’ dream in all the whole worl’, <foreign xml:lang="ja"
               >Tojin-san</foreign>!</q></p>

            <p>In the silence that fell between them, and as he still clasped her hands, a momentary
               shadow flitted across her face, and she stood wide-eyed, as though she saw a
               vision.</p>

            <p><q>Alas!</q> she said in such a mournful tone: <q>Dreams like unto thad mist. Now
                  here so sweet, so—so beyond our touch. Next hour gone—gone perhaps foraever! Nod
                  even the gods know where they gone!</q></p>

            <p>He scarcely knew his own voice, so full of a deep encompassing tenderness and
               yearning was it:</p>

            <p><q>Our dream is to be different from others</q>, he said solemnly. <q>It will never
                  end. Not for a lifetime, little Tama!</q></p>

            <p><q>It surely goin’ last foraever ad this worl’?</q> she asked with sceptical
               wistfulness.</p>

            <p><q>If you wish it</q>, said he huskily.</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p>When the sun was dipping down in the west, and but half its red face showed above the
               shadowy hills of Hakusan, the fox-woman felt the fears seize her in their throttling
               grip again. </p>

            <p>She stood like one under some spell, her back against the trunk of a giant oak, her
               hair like a veritable aureole above her. </p>

            <p>Down in a little ravine, but a few feet from where she stood, the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was gathering dried sticks to build their
               evening fire. She could hear him as he moved from point to <pb n="179"/> point.
               Sometimes he whistled softly to himself, sometimes hummed vague snatches of song. </p>

            <p>Farther away—at a distance beyond her sight, even if she could have seen—she knew,
               with that intuitive certainty of the blind, that others were passing over their
               tracks. </p>

            <p>Her hand sought her heart, and clung to it, as if to stop its beating. Fear lent
               sudden wings to her feet, as with a little gasping cry she fled downward to the
               hollow where the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> labored. She was beside him
               before he had heard or seen her, and now in surprise he looked at her white little
               face of anguish. </p>

            <p><q>Tama!</q></p>

            <p><q>You speag right</q>, she said, and could not smile with her white lips so
               tremulous, <q>thas only—beautiful dream. Thad mist gone—away!</q></p>

            <p><q>Dream! No, it’s a beautiful reality. <pb n="180"/>We are here, together, and
                  nothing in the world shall ever tear us apart again</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Nothing in the worl’</q>, she repeated.</p>

            <p>Suddenly she covered her eyes, as if the light pained them. From behind her little
               sheltering hands came her voice, still with that note of pleading terror:</p>

            <p><q>They come—tear you ’way from me now, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>!
                  All the way how many miles I kinnod say—I see them! In my heart I know! Ad my ears
                  I hear! Those feet—ah, cannot you hear them also, kind <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Tojin-san</foreign>? Listen!</q></p>

            <p>She put up her hands, and they stood in a silence, straining for the sound that only
               she could hear, or believed she did.</p>

            <p>He knew she was right. Her instinctive sense was keener than mere <pb n="181"/>sight.
               Simply, with a tender strength that could not be resisted, he took her little hand in
               his.</p>

            <p><q>Come, Tama. We must reach <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon Sha</foreign>
                  to-night</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Yaes</q>, she murmured, and now there was a note of plaintive weariness in her
               voice. <q>I thought she said the gods were good, an’ that perhaps they goin’ forgit
                  us here in those mountains</q>.</p>

            <p>She sighed and moved along step by step beside him.</p>

            <p><q>Now I know</q>, she said, <q>I god new visitor ad my heart!</q></p>

            <p><q>What is it, little Tama?</q></p>

            <p><q>Fear</q>, she said, <q>—for you!</q></p>

            <p><q>What blessed nonsense!</q></p>

            <p><q>You are <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>, like unto my father</q>, she said,
               in a voice of anguish, <q>and oh, all those days my life how I kin forgit what happen
                  unto my father!</q></p>

            <p><q>That was many years ago</q>, he said. <q>It is a New Japan we live in to-day, and
                  I have friends—even in Fukui!</q></p>
            <pb n="183"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXI</head>

            <p>A <choice>
                  <sic>NEW</sic>
                  <corr>new</corr>
               </choice> impulse drew them now more closely together. Side by side, pressed closely
               to each other, they travelled swiftly toward <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon
                  Sha</foreign>. They dared not wait to eat, to sleep, to rest but a moment, and the
               night found them still moving onward.</p>

            <p>They spoke scarcely at all to each other; but she rested like a child in the curve of
               his arm, her head against his breast. Once she sighed, ever so faintly—a little
               breath of weariness that escaped her almost unconsciously. </p>

            <p>Instantly he stopped, lifted her face in his hands, and, in the dark woods, anxiously
               examined it.</p>
            <pb n="184"/>

            <p><q>You are crying, Tama</q>.</p>

            <p><q>No-o</q>, she said.</p>

            <p><q>But your face is wet</q>.</p>

            <p><q>It is the dew upon my face</q>, she said.</p>

            <p>Again they moved onward. About them towered the giant trees, silhouetted against the
               starlit skies. Sometimes as the ascent became more steep, they clung to outjutting
               shrubs and bushes, and once when he fancied her footsteps slightly dragged, he lifted
               her bodily in his arms and carried her for a space. But she begged to be permitted to
               walk. There was still a great distance to go. He must not be hampered by her burden.
               She wished to help—not hinder him.</p>

            <p>The night grew more still, and a penetrating chill descended about them. He drew off
               his coat, to put about her; but she showed him where <pb n="185"/> she had strapped
               to her back, with the string of her <foreign xml:lang="ja">obi</foreign>, the quilt.
               He had thought it part of her sash, and was all compunction that he had permitted her
               to carry even so slight a load. She laughed in her little tremulous way, and
               challenged him to untie the knot. In the dark his big, clumsy fingers picked at it in
               vain. Again she laughed, caressingly, with a teasing tenderness, and she drew the
               little bundle round in front. It fell at her feet in a soft, silken heap.</p>

            <p>He was for wrapping it several times around her; but she insisted she would not
               proceed even the fraction of a step unless he shared the quilt with her. And so, his
               arm again about her, under the down-padded temple quilt, they moved along in the
               chilly darkness, defying with the new warmth of their hearts and bodies the cold of
               the autumn night.</p>
            <pb n="186"/>
            <p>Thus all night long they travelled, their feet moving mechanically, but never
               unwillingly, pausing not at all to look backward over the paths they had followed,
               but pressing steadily onward toward their goal. And the first pale streak of dawn
               found them climbing up the last height, within the very sight of <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon Sha</foreign>. </p>
            <pb n="187"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXII</head>

            <p>As the laggard sun crept stealthily out of the east, a vision of extraordinary
               loveliness burst upon them. There, within but the length of a single hill and field
               from them, the ragged peaks of the old Temple Tokiwa raised a lordly head above the
               sun-flecked pines. </p>

            <p>Stripped of its wealth, but not its beauty, showing the ravages of fire and assault
               upon its burnished walls, deserted, falling to the decay of neglected age, it was
               more compellingly majestic than any of the famous structures the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> had seen.</p>

            <p>The approach was over terraces made of countless stone steps, many <pb n="188"/> of
               them now loose and entirely overgrown with grass and weeds. </p>

            <p>The pagoda was of seven stories, its crimson eaves still fringed with shattered
               wind-bells. </p>

            <p>A swarm of pigeons flew about its eaves and roof, and came to meet them in a voluble,
               almost intelligent cloud. She ran to meet them, holding out her arms and calling and
               chirping to them. Dipping into her long sleeves, she brought up handfuls of the rice
               she had not forgotten to bring with her, and threw it generously among them. They
               pecked at her hand, seeking scoldingly for the food, and sprang upon her shoulders,
               her head, her hands. Presently, chidingly, she drove them off, shaking her sleeves at
               them and waving them back. </p>

            <p>Now she drew the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> into the temple, pushing back
               its rusty doors with a careful hand.</p>
            <pb n="189"/>

            <p>He was struck with the empty majesty of the interior. It had been stripped of all its
               treasures, save the great stone images, which still sat inscrutably upon their
               thrones. </p>

            <p>The altar was devoid of vestments no twinkling lights or swinging censers burned
               their incense for the delectation of the gods; yet the penetrating odor of sandalwood
               and the dim fragrance of <foreign xml:lang="ja">umegaku</foreign> and the pine seemed
               to cling about the very air. </p>

            <p>By the great main altar, the hideous old god Bunzura glared at them from beneath his
               sleepy eyelids, resting fatuously upon his haunches. Before him was the bar where
               once thousands of slips of paper containing written prayers, were tied. Now it was
               entirely stripped and glittered up in the face of the god in a mocking irony.</p>
            <pb n="190"/>

            <p>Tama moved softly by the image, pausing only to put her hand upon its knee, caressing
               it gently, as if with a conciliating, loving pat. It was evident she did not stand in
               awe of the gods. She had been born among them; knew them as part of her own silent
               family, exiled like herself upon the mountains. </p>

            <p>She even put her cheek against the head of a peculiarly sinister-looking image, who
               was attended by three smaller gods. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>
               recognized the group. They were in every Buddhist temple. Ema, the Lord of Hell, with
               his assistant torturers, one of which wielded a sword, one a pen, and one a priest’s
               staff. </p>

            <p>Now she made her first prostration, bowing lowly, and slipping devoutly to her knees.
               She was in a little alcove wherein no image whatever was to be seen.</p>
            <pb n="191"/>

            <p>As he stood wondering why she should choose this empty corner for her prayers, he
               perceived upon the wall a curious print or scroll. It was a faded paper chromo,
               apparently many years old, the picture upon it almost obliterated, the ends of the
               paper showing charred marks where it must have once started to burn. </p>

            <p>A curious sensation stirred within the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>, such a
               feeling as one might only know when in a land of gods one sees for the first time an
               emblem or a token of one’s own true God; for the tattered, shabby scroll upon the
               wall was a picture of the Christ! </p>

            <p>She seemed to sense his emotion and excitement, and, still kneeling, raised a pair of
               smiling eyes: </p>

            <p><q>It is my father’s God</q>, she said. <q>To him, mos’ of all, I speag me my
                  petitions</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Why to him?</q> he asked, deeply moved.</p>

            <p><q>Because</q>, she answered simply, <q>he, too, lig’me, knew trobble. Thas why I
                  speag to him my heart—account I know he—listen!</q></p>
            <pb n="193"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXIII</head>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> took what measures he could for their
               future protection. An exploration throughout the seven-storied pagoda brought to
               light some old weapons—a rifle and a sword, once evidently her father’s. They were
               out of date, and in bad condition, but better than nothing, he decided.</p>

            <p>As she had shown him a small exit in the rear, of which the outside of the pagoda
               gave no inkling, he decided to barricade the main entrance. This he did, after a
               gigantic effort, by piling several of the images before it until they effectually
               blocked the entrance. As their faces were turned <pb n="194"/> outward he surmised
               their weird effect upon the marauders when, after forcing the doors, they should find
               themselves fronted with so formidable a guard as these. </p>

            <p>No one, so she said, had stepped across the threshold since that frightful day when,
               in their fanatical hatred, the <foreign xml:lang="ja">danka</foreign> had murdered
               her parents. </p>

            <p>She had always been kept hidden in one of the upper stories of the pagoda, and at
               this time no one had seen her save her parents. </p>

            <p>On that day she had fled to the very roof in her first impulse of mortal terror; but
               even from there, with her ears covered by her hands, she had heard the cries of her
               father and her mother, and the wild, brutal, triumphant shouting of those who had
               killed them. </p>

            <p>A strange sense of quiet came suddenly upon her. She crept stealthily, <pb n="195"/>
               but fearlessly, back down the seven stories of the pagoda, and opened the great doors
               that gave ingress to the temple. There for the first time the people of Fukui saw
               her, standing like a flame upon the altar of the great <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Shaka</foreign>, whither she had leaped from the door in a single bound. </p>

            <p>Her hair was more glittering than the altar itself; her eyes, her skin were of a
               color no man in Fukui had ever seen before. She seemed to their dazzled eyes a
               vengeful spirit, whom the Lord Buddha had uplifted. They stood as if petrified,
               staring at her as she swayed before them on the very lap of the god. Then, with a
               concerted cry of superstitious fear and horror, they slunk from the temple, leaving
               her alone with her dead! </p>

            <p>As the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> looked about the great chamber, he felt
               himself almost unconsciously <pb n="196"/> rehearsing that grim scene of the past. He
               knew why her hand had been set against the whole world, why she had terrified and
               defied her tormentors. Even now, as she repeated the tale to him her face was white
               and fixed. </p>

            <p><q>Now you know</q>, she said, <q>why I am call the fox-woman! Perhaps thas true
                  ’bout me. Mebbe I am <foreign xml:lang="ja">gagama</foreign>!</q></p>

            <p><q>You are not</q>, he said, <q>even in spite of them</q>.</p>

            <p>She was silent, staring out before her in some abstracted trance. Suddenly she
               sighed:</p>

            <p><q>I nod lig’ udder people! Thas bedder nod come near unto me. I mek the trobble, and
                  sometimes—the death for those who seek me! Down in Fukui perhaps already they have
                  tol’ you of thad—Gihei Matsuyama?</q></p>

            <pb n="197"/>

            <p><q>They told me</q>, he said, <q>but I do not believe them</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Thas true</q>, she said, and there was a plaintive note of weariness in her voice.
                  <q>He cum lig’ unto a storm that fall down from those sky wiz no warning. When I
                  am come from my door, he there to await me. He speag my name sof—kind—lig’ you,
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>! No one ever speag unto me lig’ thad
                  before. No! They bud cry to me those name and curse and throw the stone upon me!
                  Bud he! he speag lig’ you augustness</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Ad firs’ my heart stan’ still—it ’fraid. I thing of my father—my mother, and I am
                  ’fraid he come kill me also. Then again he speag my name sof and kind, an’ I say
                  ad my heart: ‘Thas god come veesit me!’ An’ so—an’ so—for him I mek the sacred
                  danze. But when I am through, I know I mek meestake—thas nod <pb n="198"/>god ad
                  all! Thas jost man from Fukui!</q></p>

            <p><q>Then my heart laugh wizin me, and my feet carry me quick across those mountain. I
                  loog nod bag, though I hear his voice, for I am thad ’fraid agin. I know nod why,
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign></q>.</p>

            <p>Her voice faltered. She went a timid step nearer to him, touched his hand
               questioningly with her own.</p>

            <p><q>The blind see wiz one thousand inner eye, bud, ah, alas! they see nod also for
                  another. How could I know thad the foolish one would nod loog upon his
               steps?</q></p>

            <p>She shuddered and covered her face with her little shaking hands.</p>

            <p><q>How many days I waiting ad thad pool—jos’ waiting, <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Tojin-san</foreign>, wiz the hope that mebbe some day he goin’ come bag out
                  those water</q>.</p>

            <p><q>You must never think of it again</q>, <pb n="199"/>he said. <q>You were entirely
                  blameless</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Sometime I thing</q>, she went on wistfully, <q>thad mebbe those Fukui people
                  right, an me?—I am truly a fox-woman. For see what trobble, what—death I mek for
                  those who see me. Even for you, kind <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>,
                  alas! I mus’ bring you those pain!</q></p>

            <p><q>No—that is not so</q>, he said.</p>

            <p><q>I know nod when or how firs’ I have hear of your comin’. They talk of nothing else
                  at Fukui, an* I am always listen, though they see me nod. Something tell me, when
                  you come all those worl’ goin’ change for me! Trias* why I wait, wait, all thad
                  winter for your comin’</q>.</p>

            <p>A smile, wistful, yet joyous, crept over her lips.</p>

            <p><q>You din know</q>, she said, <q>thad firs’ day in Fukui, thad I too am ad <pb
                     n="200"/>your house to welcome you. Bud me? I am nod wizin thad house. I am out
                  in thad snow. I kinnod speag unto you lig’ those others. I may nod even touch you
                  honorable hand. Bud all same I know you are <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign>—lig’ unto my father! Oh, how glad—how joy I am! Though my feet,
                  my hand, my nose, my honorable ears perish wiz those cold, still I am wait for
                  you. When all those honorable exalted ones gone—then—then I, too, call you name!
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">To-o-jin-san!</foreign></q></p>

            <p>She made a little shivering motion.</p>

            <q>Bud suppose I bring you also thad—thad death?</q>

            <p><q>There is nothing to fear</q>, he said steadily, <q>and if there were, I am strong
                  enough to face any peril with you at my side!</q></p>

            <p><q>Oh, my mind travel bag on thad past! I hear again my father’s voice—my mother’s
                  cry! I am toaching <pb n="201"/> their beloved body. I am tek them in thad black
                  night unto the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sho Kon Sha</foreign>, and wiz these liddle
                  hands, all alone, I am put them in their—grave! <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Tojin-san</foreign>! Ah-h!</q></p>

            <p>She hid her face against his arm.</p>

            <p><q>If they should do to you the same!</q> she said.</p>

            <p><q>For myself I have no fear</q>, he said. </p>

            <p><q>Why nod leave me now?</q> she urged. <q>Go bag alone down those mountain. No one
                  speag hard to you who so moch mek respect. Wiz me there is moch trobble, an’ mebbe
                  worse!</q></p>

            <p><q>Without you</q>, he said, <q>there is more trouble, and a deep pain—an aching void
                  that could never again be filled. With you here alone, cut off from all the world,
                  holding your little hands in my own, looking into your face, why, even facing
                  death, I am <pb n="202"/> content—happier than I had ever dreamed it possible to
                  be</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Thas beautiful word you speag</q>, she said. <q>Bud if the gods—</q></p>

            <p>She folded her hands across her breast and closed her eyes in prayer.</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Temmei itashikata kore maku!</foreign></q> she whispered
               lowly. (From the decree of heaven there is no escape.)</p>
            <pb n="203"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXIV</head>

            <p>The rapping on the temple doors was not loud or menacing, but it was insistent,
               questioning. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> drew the fox-woman to the
               winding staircase which led up the seven stories to the tower above. </p>

            <p>Once before Tama had been sent up yonder. Then she had gone willingly, even
               frantically. Now she made no movement up the stairs. Instead, she turned her back
               upon them, and faced the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> fairly. Upon her face
               a smile shone luminously as a star. Simply, steadily, she laid her hands in those of
               the man. </p>

            <p>For a moment he held them in his own, his eyes fixed yearningly upon <pb n="204"/>
               her face, and even while the knocks resounded louder upon the door the clouds cleared
               from his mind. </p>

            <p>Looking into those uplifted, adoring eyes he forgot all else. A sound that was half a
               sob, half a passionate cry escaped him. He reached out irresistibly and took her into
               his arms. For the first time his lips hungrily, passionately found her own, and clung
               in a kiss that over all the years of a lifetime neither he nor she might ever forget.
               They saw nothing, heard nothing, felt only that close, encompassing embrace that made
               them one indeed. </p>

            <p>Then upon their dream at last broke the lowly calling, almost whispering voice of the
               one without. They drew apart, though their eyes and hands still clung unconsciously
               together.</p>

            <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Sensei. Sensei! Sensei!</foreign></q>
            <pb n="205"/>

            <p>It was the voice of the student, Junzo! With a low cry, the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign> was at the doors, wrenching and tearing the great images away
               with the strength of a veritable giant. At last the doors were reached, and these in
               turn thrust aside.</p>

            <p>There, with their anxious, faithful young faces pale with apprehension in regard to
               his fate, were his three loyal boys, Junzo, Higo, and Nunuki. They fell literally
               upon him with tears and shouts of joy. They devoured him with their youthful
               embraces. Higo clung to one hand, Junzo to the other; and at the back of him Nunuki
               hovered, seeking to examine the wound upon his neck where the sword of the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign>’s high officer had pierced. It was healed, so well
               had the fox-woman cared for it.</p>

            <p>Now, step by step, slowly, uncertainly, <pb n="206"/> she crept toward them,
               white-faced, wild-eyed, every nerve in her thrilling, and reaching out blindly for
               the arms that had held her, the lips that had clung to her own. But she stopped with
               her tragic little face clasped on either side with her hands as the joyous voices of
               the students reached her. They were telling the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign> of the coming of his friends to Fukui; of the return of the
               Echizen Prince; of the punishments to be meted out to those who had attacked him; the
               rewards for those who had defended. </p>

            <p><q>Even we</q>, said Higo, with boyish pride, <q>are to have our due reward, for we
                  have honorably been chosen as the body-guard of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Be-koku-jin</foreign> (American), who has come to Fukui to minister to the
                  unfortunate one, and to take her, if your excellency is willing, to the
                  capital</q>.</p>

            <p><q>The unfortunate one?</q> repeated the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>
               dully. <q>To whom do you refer?</q></p>

            <p>The boys stared at him in round-eyed amazement.</p>

            <p><q>The fox-woman of course! Who else? That unfortunate one to whom the whole heart of
                  Fukui had melted like the snows of her native mountains in the Spring. It was the
                  work of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> himself that had accomplished
                  the miracle; for he had pointed out to them all the absurdity, the wrong of the
                  ancient superstition, which had been kept alive chiefly throughout the years by
                  the hatred of those who were ignorant or fanatic</q>.</p>

            <p>Now the Prince himself was convinced a wrong had been committed, and Fukui was taking
               its cue from him. The friend of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> coming at
               such a time had also had its effect upon the people; and now the remorseful ones were
               prepared to atone for the past if that were possible. It was the suggestion of the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign>, however, that the girl should be
               taken out of Fukui.</p>

            <p>Her history had created a sensation among her father’s race in Tokio, and there they
               were eager, anxious to receive her among them. But it was for the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> alone to say. The change of heart in Fukui was
               complete. There was nothing further to fear.</p>

            <p><q>Even I</q>, said Nunuki with Spartan-like courage, <q>am prepared to look upon
                  her. We have learned from the tongue of our own Prince and from the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> that many females of your race have her
                  skin and hair and eye-color. Is it not so, honored teacher?</q></p>

            <p>But the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> was silent. His face had turned
               strangely gray; his arms hung limply by his side. He was staring out before him
               fixedly as though he saw a vision.</p>
            <pb n="210"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXV</head>

            <p><q>Bud speag to me as before! Touch me wiz those hands—those lips! Adoringly look
                  upon me! My honorable heart and body are cold. Condescend to warm them!</q></p>

            <p>She had followed him down a declivity, unmindful of the students who pressed with
               their grave, wondering young faces closely about her.</p>

            <p>She could not understand why now no longer she might travel beside him, his
               sheltering arm supporting her; why she might not even take his hand, or rest her wet
               cheek against his sleeve. In the three days they had been upon the journey back to
               Fukui, he had seemed to avoid her, almost as if he feared her.</p>

            <p>Once he tried to explain, stupidly, and with a forced coldness.</p>

            <p><q>Things were very different now. When alone, they were like lost children and the
                  silent woods and mountains had put strange dreams and fancies into their heads, so
                  that they had wandered along in a blind, gilded delirium. Now they had awakened.
                  They must go back to the city, where they would be like other people, and where,
                  shortly, their ways must separate. It was for her good. She would understand some
                  day</q>.</p>

            <p><q>She must forget the mountain days, or think of them only as a dream that had
                  vanished, as she herself had predicted it would, like the mist</q>.</p>

            <p>She was very stupid, very stubborn, pathetically dense. She did not wish their paths
               to separate—she would <pb n="212"/> not have it so. No, though they tore her from him
               by force. She would return to him. Did he not recall the words he had spoken when he
               declared the dream would never end unless she wished it. She did not wish it. She
               never would. Patiently, persistently she entreated him, until he was beside himself
               and felt his strength of mind weakening, and in desperation turned to his students
               for help. He bade them explain to her more clearly than he could do the new life she
               was soon to lead—of the change in fortunes that had come to her. </p>

            <p>Manfully, but in the bungling, uncertain language of boys they tried to obey him. The
               unfortunate one, as unconsciously they called her, was soon to see, promised the
               gentle Junzo. There was to be an honorable operation upon her eyes. These <pb n="213"
               /> western wizards of science, said the Japanese student, had given sight to hundreds
               in their own land. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>, himself once a doctor,
               had diagnosed her trouble as an invisible cataract of a congenital nature, not
               uncommon nor difficult of removal. He had sent for a great and eminent surgeon who
               was sojourning in the capital. He had come all the way to Fukui, at the bidding of
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>. He was a miracle-worker, whose fame
               encircled the globe, said the boy with a kindling eye. </p>

            <p>A hundred friends awaited her in Tokio, so Higo courteously informed her. They were
               eager and anxious to receive her—Japanese as well as foreigners. To them Tama was to
               be sent; for Fukui had been unkind to her, and she would be happier away from it. She
               would understand by-and-by, they promised her. </p>
            <pb n="214"/>

            <p>She listened patiently, but densely, as if what they told her but half reached her
               understanding. That she was to be sent away into some distant country—very far from
               the Temple Tokiwa and Atago <foreign xml:lang="ja">Yama</foreign>—an immeasurable
               distance away from the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>—this alone she
               comprehended. </p>

            <p>Her mother had taught her that the life of a Buddhist nun must be one long act of
               expiation for sins and faults committed in some former state. She tried dazedly to
               conceive of the terrible crimes of which she must have once been guilty that now she
               was to be punished so dreadfully and she reached out blindly for the only comfort
               possible for her in the world now—the voice, the touch of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>. who had held her in his arms! </p>

            <p>They travelled by the public roads <pb n="215"/> of the mountain that she had so
               carefully avoided. They passed the nights as guests of the priests of the mountain
               temples, who read the letters of the Prince of Echizen, which the students proudly
               exhibited, and with courteous and profound obeisances welcomed the travellers, even
               regarding the fox-woman with eyes that were more speculative than resentful. Perhaps
               they alone of Echizen had best understood this little creature who had lived among
               them, yet beyond their pale, for so long; for though they had not sought her, neither
               had they persecuted her, as they could readily have done. Indeed for years she had
               practically subsisted upon the food she surreptitiously obtained from the temples
               some of which was unostentatiously placed as if prepared for her. </p>

            <p>The journey back to Fukui was <pb n="216"/> long and tortuous. Summer was gone
               completely. The days were cold; wind and rain came about them and drove them
               constantly into refuges of one sort and another; but after many days they came at
               last to the foot-hills of the mountains, passed through these into the pine woods,
               through bamboo groves and camphor groves, till they came to the Winged Foot River,
               which brought them to their destination. </p>
            <pb n="217"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXVI</head>

            <p>The last courteous and obsequious emissary of the Prince of Echizen had bowed himself
               out of the apartment of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, having
               sonorously delivered the speeches of regret of their master. </p>

            <p>The room was piled with the rich gifts sent by the now soon departing Prince, who was
               to take office directly under his imperial master. Now he was sojourning in Echizen
               merely for the purpose of setting his affairs in order, and to do what lay in his
               power to set his former vassals in the new path they were to follow. Because he was
               the soul of chivalry and of justice, he was righting the wrong <pb n="218"/> and
               slight paid to the foreigner he had himself invited to his province. </p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> was inexpressibly weary. One deputation
               after another of the citizens of Fukui had been arriving all day. They had commenced
               coming before daybreak, for the earlier a Japanese makes a call the greater he
               expresses his respect.</p>

            <p>Delegations from the college presented petitions asking him to continue in Fukui,
               despite the change of government, and promising to make his stay there as happy and
               prosperous as lay within their power. He listened to them all a bit grimly, making no
               effort to emulate their politeness. Through the new interpreter who had entered his
               service, he merely signified that he would take the matter under consideration. It
               could not be decided at once.</p>
            <pb n="219"/>

            <p>At last he found himself alone with the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign>,
               as they called his American friend, who was in fact what the Japanese youth had said,
               an eminent surgeon, with whom the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign> had once
               been associated. </p>

            <p>He was a small, but very dignified and important individual, whose most noticeable
               features were his bright eyes, which twinkled incongruously beneath a pair of fierce
               and uncompromising eyebrows. In his well-fitting English clothes he was as out of
               place in the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>’s great chamber as was the
               awkward furniture the deluded Genji Negato had chosen for his master. </p>

            <p>Now he wandered about the room examining this and that article, and fingering the
               gifts brought by the Japanese with anticipatory fingers. His eyes, however, turned
               constantly toward his friend, who, now that they <pb n="220"/> were for the first
               time alone together, had nothing to say.</p>

            <p>The American surgeon was blessed with more than an ordinary intelligence, and he had
               learned a great deal from the students. A man seemingly absolutely wrapped up in his
               work, he had for years secretly cherished what he had become to believe was
               positively a vice. He was in fact as sentimental as a girl. When supposedly he was
               deeply engrossed in the study of some scientific work, locked in his study with stern
               orders without that on no account was he to be disturbed, he was in fact reading some
               love-story—or some romance of adventure usually enjoyed by very youthful persons. </p>

            <p>Now he felt himself, as it were, part of a moving captivating drama cut out of life
               itself. No written page <pb n="221"/> had ever absorbed him quite like this
               love-story of the fox-woman and his friend the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>.</p>

            <p>There was something appallingly tragic in that little listening, waiting figure
               crouching there in the hall against the Tojin’s door! The Bekoku-jin knew very well
               indeed what it was this forlorn little creature of the mountains wanted; he knew,
               too, why it was that the Tojin believed he could not give it to her. </p>

            <p>He had come to Fukui chiefly because he had been unable to resist the lure of the
               story of the fox-woman as the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> had written
               it to him. Now here he had stumbled upon a more entrancing story still. </p>

            <p>He looked at his friend with his bright, clear eyes, and it occurred to him that
               there was something wonderfully attractive about the man’s face, grim and stony as
               was its <pb n="222"/> expression, marked and marred as were the features. The mouth
               was that of the revolutionist, grim, unyielding, almost bitter; but the eyes were
               those of the poet, full of vague dreams and tenderness. The <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Be-koku-jin</foreign>, assuming his most professional and uninterested manner,
               drew up a chair before his friend, and settled his plump little body comfortably into
               its depths. </p>

            <p><q>What are your plans?</q> he asked abruptly.</p>

            <p>The other did not look up.</p>

            <p><q>That depends on you</q>, he said quietly.</p>

            <p><q>Your refusal or acceptance of the position here depends on me?</q></p>

            <p><q>Absolutely</q>.</p>

            <p><q>What do you mean?</q></p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> leaned forward in his chair. His eyes
               were no longer dull, there was a flame behind them.</p>

            <p><q>If you are successful—I remain here, in Fukui</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Ah. Er—you mean as regards the operation?</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> regarded the tips of his fingers,
               which he had brought precisely together, reflectively. He purposely avoided the
               other’s almost pleading glance. He cleared his throat gruffly, and frowned as he
               crossed and recrossed his legs.</p>

            <p><q>Why stay in any event?</q> he demanded shortly, and put up his hand before the
               other could answer. <q>Your attitude is sentimental moonshine. You have nothing to
                  fear—even if the operation is successful. I don’t agree with—er—what you have upon
                  your mind</q>.</p>

            <p><q>That is because you do not understand</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign> wearily. <q>She is indeed what these people have imagined her—a
                  creature almost of another world. She has lived only in her exquisite imagination,
                  and because she is so beautiful and good and pure, to her all things too are fair.
                  I was the first to treat her humanly. She has made me something in her mind’s eye
                  that it is preposterous even to think of. To her I—think of it!—am a thing of
                  beauty—a flawless, perfect god!</q></p>

            <p>He glared in a fierce sort of anguish at his friend, then stood up suddenly and began
               pacing the floor in long irregular strides, to bring up suddenly again before the
               other.</p>

            <p><q>I do not wish her to see me—at all! It will not be necessary. I ask you to take
                  her for me to Tokio. There my sister will meet you, and take her with her to
                  America</q>. He smiled for the first time. <q>At least I can do that for her. I
                  claimed the right to care for her, and refused even the smallest help from Echizen
                  and others. I have means—other than my work; and what I have will be hers. I want
                  no one else to do for her</q>, he added jealously. <q>I can give her everything
                  she needs or may want</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> was still studying his finger-tips,
               and there was a curious expression upon his face. Suddenly he looked up directly at
               the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>.</p>

            <p><q>Why have the operation?</q></p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> had turned very pale, but his voice
               was steady and strong.</p>

            <p><q>I have been through all that, my friend—have wrestled, tortured my very soul
                  threshing it out. That’s the solution of a coward. I am a man!</q></p>

            <p>Said the other:</p>

            <p><q>I decline to perform the operation</q>.</p>

            <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> stared at him as if he could not
               believe his ears. Then he brought his hand so heavily down upon the other’s shoulder
               that the smaller man jumped under the touch.</p>

            <p><q>You prefer to leave it to my bungling hands? Is that what you came to Fukui to
                  tell me?</q></p>

            <p><q>As I said</q>, said the other, wincing still under the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign>’s hand, <q>in any event you exaggerate the effect upon her. Just
                  as you say—you are a man!</q></p>

            <p>He stood up abruptly.</p>

            <p><q>You will do it?</q> demanded the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>
               hoarsely.</p>

            <p><q>Yes</q>, said the other, blinking angrily, <q>I suppose I must</q>.</p>

            <p>He glared for a moment at his friend and then for the first time permitted himself to
               show some emotion in his voice and expression:</p>

            <p><q>We’ll fight it out between us. Sight or no sight, I know you will be the same to
                  her!</q></p>

            <p><q>It is not alone my physical deformity</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign>, steadily, <q>but the fact that I am old enough to be her father.
                  I have no longer the splendid courage of youth to take her in spite of my
                  misfortune. ‘Old Grind,’ that was what they called me, even in America!</q></p>

            <p><q>Stuff!</q> grunted the other. <q>‘Old Bones’ was the affectionate term applied to
                  me. At this rate, you’ll put us in our dotage. A man under forty is in his best
                  youth. I never felt younger in my life!</q> he snorted indignantly.</p>

            <p><q>But she is only a child</q>, said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin</foreign>
               softly, <q>—a child in years—and in heart!</q></p>

            <p><q>If you could see her</q>, said the other, with intense earnestness, <q>as I have
                  had occasion to since last night, you would say differently. Child! why, man, she
                  is a suffering, neglected, forsaken little woman! Open your door to her. Don’t let
                  her think it as stony as your heart!</q></p>
            <pb n="229"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXVII</head>

            <p><q>Tama!</q> He opened the sliding doors at last. She did not stand, even when he
               spoke to her, but with a mute, wordless sob moved a pace nearer to him on her knees,
               and put her head submissively at his feet.</p>

            <p>He stooped above her, his face working, his hands trembling. Gently he lifted her to
               her feet, only to release her instantly.</p>

            <p><q>Stand there</q>, he said, <q>while I speak to you. You must do whatever the
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> wishes of you. He tells me you
                  have resisted his attempts to help you. If I tell you it is my wish, my very dear
                  wish, you will go with him, will you not?</q></p>

            <p>She had put out her hands in the old blind way, and would have found him had he not
               stepped back soundlessly as she approached him. She sighed in her distress, sighed
               and sobbed, like a tortured child. As he looked at her he felt his resolve, far from
               weakening, becoming even more fixed. He would not have her this way, blind in mind
               and in sight. She must know the truth.</p>

            <p><q>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> will help you, Tama. Soon you are
                  going to see, and then things will appear very differently to you. What you
                  believe now to be beautiful may prove to be otherwise. For example</q>, he
               continued steadily, <q>you believe me other than I am in fact. My face is horrible.
                  It may even frighten you, as it did another woman once!</q></p>

            <p>A hush fell between them. Her eyes, very wide and dark, were fixed upon his face,
               almost as though they were endowed with sight.</p>

            <p><q>Though all keep dark forever and my eyes, still I would know your face—and—my
                  heart!</q> she said.</p>

            <p><q>If you could really see—</q> he murmured hoarsely, almost imploringly.</p>

            <p><q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>!</q> she said, <q>though all the worl’
                  come before my eyes, I would know you only! I would follow you—yaes to thad worl’s
                  end—if you bud would permit me</q>.</p>

            <p>He made a motion toward her, and with that smile still upon her face she went blindly
               to meet him; but as quickly he had drawn back again, and a moment later turned
               desperately toward the doors. She heard him slide them open, felt the cold draught of
               air enter; then they closed again, and she heard only the sound of his steps as he
               passed along the paths.</p>
            <pb n="232"/>

            <p>She stood unmoving, listening until even the faintest sound of him was gone. Then
               suddenly she ran forward, feeling her way with her hands till she came to his chair.
               Upon her knees she sank, sighing, sobbing, and buried her face upon her arms in the
               lap of the chair. Here the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> found her,
               sleeping her first sleep in many, many days, exhausted, but with a strange look of
               peace upon her face at last! </p>
            <pb n="233"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXVIII</head>

            <p>The whole of the city of Fukui had turned forth into its streets. Jostling, pushing,
               shoving each other aside they elbowed their way to the front. Children were raised to
               the shoulders of parents, boys climbed upon roofs and poles and trees to see the
               spectacle. </p>

            <p>The runners could hardly make a passageway through the throngs; but there was no
               disorder, nor the slightest trace of antagonism, as the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >norimono</foreign><note type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>norimon</q> is a
                  Japanese carriage carried by people.</note> passed slowly down the streets. A
               respectful silence—a silence that had in it an element of torturing remorse more than
               curiosity—fell upon the throng.</p>
            <pb n="234"/>

            <p>The bamboo hangings had been drawn back from the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >norimon</foreign>, for it was the desire of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign> that all of Fukui might see the fox-woman themselves, see and
               judge what manner of creature was this they had outcast and persecuted through all
               her short life. </p>

            <p>Beside the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign>, who had performed the
               miracle upon her eyes, she sat, her face white as snow, her wide, dazzled eyes gazing
               bewilderedly about her, as if she were but half conscious of what she saw, but half
               comprehended its meaning. They had confined most of her golden hair in some
               shimmering gray veil that floated about her like a cloud, but little moist curls
               clung about her brow and blew from beneath the veil in tender, kissing tendrils about
               her cheeks.</p>

            <p>At her feet, with her fascinated, infatuated eyes pinned upon her <pb n="235"/> face,
               crouched the maid Obun, who was pledged to her service by the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin-san</foreign>. The carriage was full of flowers that those friendly
               inclined had sent her, and the white hands of the fox-woman now aimlessly held a
               sheaf of poems and of love-letters penned her by ardent and impetuous youths, who
               found their warm hearts and imaginations suddenly fired by her appealing history and
               beauty. </p>

            <p>She spoke not at all, neither to answer the occasional word of reassurance from the
                  <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign>, nor the sometimes sobbing utterances
               of Obun, who seemed to find in her triumphal progress through the city an occasion
               for tears. </p>

            <p>It grew darker, the air chillier. It was the Season of Cold Dew, when even the last
               gasping, fading beauty of the autumn ceased to appeal.</p>
            <pb n="236"/>

            <p>As the cortege reached the city’s limits the crowds following gradually drew back,
               and as it passed out into the great road whereon they were to travel on the long
               journey, the last of the followers departed. </p>

            <p>Besides the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> and the maid Obun there were
               three students, proudly acting as body-guard. Several dozen bearers and servants also
               accompanied the party. No halt was made until the last rays of the setting sun had
               disappeared entirely from the sky. Then the runners rested, and the <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign> alighting walked with his head bent, his hands
               behind him, as if plunged in some troubled thought. The students drew together in a
               whispering group and watched the famous surgeon, or threw furtive glances in the
               direction of the fox-woman, whom none of them, as <pb n="237"/> yet, had found the
               courage to look upon unmoved. </p>

            <p>She was sitting upright in her <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimon</foreign>. The veil had
               blown back partly from her head, and her hair shone like the moon above her. Obun
               entreated her to rest, and when she received no response, herself drew the hangings
               about them, and prepared the carriage for the night. As if she had been a child, she
               laid the fox-woman down among the quilts, and then herself crept under the covers,
               falling into a heavy sleep which lasted without a break the long night through as
               jerking, swinging, tossing on high upon the shoulders of the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >kurumaya</foreign> they travelled on and on toward Tokio. </p>
            <pb n="238"/>
         </div>

         <div type="chapter">
            <head>XXIX</head>
            <p>In the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shiro</foreign> Matsuhaira the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Tojin</foreign> sat alone. They had taken away the untasted meal upon the trays;
               his pipe lay unlit upon the <foreign xml:lang="ja">hibachi</foreign>; upon a table
               hard by his American mail and papers lay untouched, unopened. He sat staring at
               something he held in his hands. It was no larger than his hand, worn, ragged, and
               soiled a little sandal of straw! This was all he had left of her. She had passed out
               of his life as completely as the mist vanishes into the clouds. </p>

            <p>What were her thoughts now, he wondered dully—now that she knew! He had seen her but
               once, after the operation. She had come like a <pb n="239"/> shadowy little spirit
               into his chamber; and she had said nothing at all; had merely looked at him out of
               her wide, hungry eyes. As silently as she had come, so she had gone! Passively,
               obediently she had gone with the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign>. This
               was what he had wished, had required of her. Then why this aching, harrowing sense of
               anguish ? </p>

            <p>He closed his eyes, and gave himself up to the last luxury left him the casting of
               his mind adrift upon a sea of memories, wherein he might recall her as she had been,
               see her again pressed against his side, breathe the dear fragrance of her hair, hear
               the music of her voice. </p>

            <p>Outside the wind was whistling and moaning through the leafless gardens, and a rain
               began to fall, pelting against his shutters, dripping in melancholy splashes from the
               eaves. How <pb n="240"/> barren, how God-forsaken seemed this <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                  >Yashiki</foreign> of feudal days! He recalled his first night in this same
               chamber. How cold it had been, how penetratingly desolate! </p>

            <p>Now the winter was coming again. Soon the white snow would wrap its icy shroud about
               the Palace Matsuhaira, and there would be a silence a silence less bearable than the
               grave —out there on those mountains of snow. </p>

            <p>But the people of Fukui would come to him daily with their problems, their ambitions,
               and questions; and they would look to him as a guide and supporter along the new
               glittering road they wished to tread; for the fever of the New Japan was animating
               the entire nation, and Fukui had caught the epidemic. And they would bestow honors
               and favors upon the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign>, fame and riches, too;
               for <pb n="241"/> at the period of the rebirth of a nation its teachers become its
               prophets—its leaders! Yes, there was such a career to his hand as he could never have
               attained in that other land, whither they were taking the fox-woman now. It was this,
               had said the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Be-koku-jin</foreign>, which must be his solace,
               his comfort. </p>

            <p>He stood up unsteadily, his hand resting upon the table. Someone had knocked upon his
               door. He smiled, in the old grim, bitter way. </p>

            <p>He could not be tricked by his imagination again. She was very far away by now, miles
               from Fukui, for it was past midnight, and her cortege would take an unbroken course
               toward the great highway which eventually would lead them to the metropolis. </p>

            <p>But the knocking was repeated, softly, gently, a sound such as a little <pb n="242"/>
               timid bird in the wet night might have made in beating its wings upon the wall. </p>

            <p>He heard the soft moving of the doors, and still he did not stir. </p>

            <p>Now she stood between them, her eyes fully upon him, drawing, compelling his gaze.
               Upon her vivid, passionate little face there was, at last, that look of peace and
               rest that comes to one upon a journey’s end. </p>

            <p>The water dripped from her <foreign xml:lang="ja">haori</foreign>,<note
                  type="editorial" resp="pers:LW1">A <q>haori</q> is a traditional jacket worn over
                  a kimono.</note> and clung in glittering drops upon her hair, her lashes. He could
               not even speak her name. </p>

            <p>He could only gaze at her entranced, as at that other time when he had come to
               consciousness within the woods, and had found her face hovering like a spirit’s above
               his own.</p>

            <p>She said as if answering the question he could not speak: <q>Yaes—it is I—<foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">To-o-jin-san!</foreign></q></p>
            <pb n="243"/>

            <p>With a motion, inexpressibly sweet, she put out her little hands, just as she had
               done ere she could see, and a beseeching, quivering little smile was on her lips.</p>

            <p><q>In the honorable wet dark—all those way—I have come bag to you, kind <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san!</foreign></q></p>

            <p>His voice shook so that he did not recognize it as his own.</p>

            <p><q>You found your way—</q></p>

            <p><q>Wiz these my eyes closed</q>, she said, <q>ad udder end those whole worl’—tha’s
                  same thing <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tojin-san</foreign> I find way bag unto
               you!</q></p>

            <p><q>Why?</q> he demanded with a rough passion that yet tore and intoxicated him.</p>

            <p>She reached out her arms to him yearningly, pleadingly.</p>

            <p><q>Tek me ad you arms again!</q> she said. <q>Toach me on my lips wiz yours. I will
                  tell you—then!</q></p>

            <pb n="244"/>

            <p>His last reserve was gone; he had no wish to hold it. Subtly, irresistibly, she had
               drawn him to her; now he had taken her back into his arms.</p>

            <p>He felt her little fingers, as of old, passing across his face until they found his
               lips, and there she placed her own. </p>
         </div>

         <trailer>THE END</trailer>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
<!-- Curly apostrophe ’ -->
