<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WhenChristmasCame1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>When Christmas Came to Fukui</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:YM1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:KSN1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:PB1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</repository>
                  <idno>7.13</idno>
                  <idno type="UofC">CU111948553</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <bibl xml:id="bibl244"><author><name ref="pers:WE1">Anonymous</name></author>.
                           <title level="a">When Christmas Came to Fukui</title>. ms., <date
                           notBefore="1917" notAfter="1935">1917-1935</date>, <distributor
                           ref="org:WERFonds">Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</distributor>,
                           <idno>7.13</idno>.</bibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Facsimile retrieved from Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at University of
                           Calgary.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <!--Add other editions of this text using a bibl element with a target pointing to its bibl-->
                     <!--
                        <bibl target="bibl:ABCD1"/>
                        <bibl><distributor/>, <idno/></bibl>
                     -->
                  </surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreShortStory"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docPrimarySourceMS"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-09-23" status="published">Transcribed, proofed, and encoded.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2024-01-05" status="empty">Adding document from 2023 Calgary
            Transcribe-a-thon.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-11-23" status="empty">Added citation from
            bibliography.xml to <gi>sourceDesc</gi> using utilities/msdesc.xsl.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2023-04-02" status="empty">Adding <gi>relatedItem</gi>s and
               <gi>notesStmt</gi>.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" when="2022-03-12" status="empty">Added catREF info.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-07-30" status="empty">Created shell from bibl
            file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:WhenChristmasCame1">
      <pb n="frontcover"/>
      <body>
         <head>WHEN CHRISTMAS CAME TO FUKUI</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>by</byline>
            <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">ONOTO WATANNA</name></byline>
         </opener>
         <milestone unit="section"/>
         <p>Address</p>
         <p>Mrs. Francis F. Reeve, </p>
         <p>109--14th. St. N.W.,</p>
         <p>Calgary, Alta. Canada.</p>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <div type="content">
            <head>WHEN CHRISTMAS CAME TO FUKUI</head>
            <opener>
               <byline>by</byline>
               <byline><name ref="pers:WE1">ONOTO WATANNA</name></byline>
               <byline>Author of <q>A Japanese Nightingale</q> &amp;c.</byline>
            </opener>
            <p>Winter had come early to Fukui this year, and although it was still December, a month
               of comparative warmth, the little city was wrapped in a dense snow storm. To the girl
               at the glass window of the <q>foreign</q> house, the people seemed to blow along the
               street as helplessly as the snowflakes. Their shoulders hunched, <del>their</del>
               hands drawn up in the sleeves, they were mutely before the driving wind, one
               shivering word coming from between <del>the their</del> chattering teeth as they
               greeted each other: <q><foreign xml:lang="ja">Samui! Samui!</foreign></q> (Cold!
               Cold!) </p>

            <p>And it was cold indeed, penetratingly, wretchedly cold! So thought the girl at the
               window, as she looked at her own blue hands, and turned her back suddenly upon the
               street, as if to shut out the frigid symbol of the implacable season. </p>

            <p>It was cold, too, indoors, and especially in this great empty chamber, which was all
               her own. They had promised her so many things, she recalled with a suffocating sense
               of bitterness and rebellion. Only the glittering, ice-coated panes of glass were
               there to remind her at least, that they had striven to redeem these promises. The
               Mission was poor--she had known this from the first. Those glass panes represented a
               concession and even sacrifice.</p>

            <pb n="2"/>

            <p>How desireable, how charming, the life had seemed to her but such a short time since.
               What had wrought then this wretched change, she asked herself, and piteously answered
               that it was the cruel cold. It had frozen her very soul. She moved about the room,
               wringing her hands unconsciously. They <del>too</del>felt like small blocks of ice. </p>

            <p> There was no fire in the room, save that contained in a diminutive <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja">kotatsu</foreign>, scarcely more than a small pan with a couple of
               live coals in it, whose warmth one could not adequately feel unless one crept under a
               quilt thrown over the fire frame.</p>

            <p>At home there had been a mother, a father, brothers, sisters, and many other
               relatives and dear friends. They had made her pathway very cheery and rosy. She had
               left them for this! Her mind wandered with a persistent anguish to the little circle
               she knew was gathered this very night about the home hearth. A sense of desolation,
               of unutterable loneliness swept away her last effort at self control. She threw
               herself down by the <foreign xml:lang="ja">kotatsu</foreign>, dragged the quilt
               wildly above her shivering little body, and there with her face buried in her hands,
               the sobs burst from her unchecked. </p>

            <p> How long she wept, she could not have told. She become aware, with a sudden sense of
               half fright, half anger, that someone had intruded, and, no doubt, had witnessed her
               grief. Her orders had been emphatic that her privacy was to be respected. Now,
               without knocking, someone had dared to enter her room, on this night she had claimed
               as all her own, this Christmas Eve, which she <del>only</del> alone in all this snow
               wrapped city--so she told her-self fiercely--- could <del>understand</del> appreciate
               and love!</p>

            <pb n="3"/>

            <p>She had the cynicism of the disillusioned younger missionary, who finds the first
               fruits of his labor returned to him spoiled and scorned. Of all the fifty inmates of
               the school, not one, <del>she was assured,</del> was there for love of her religion.
               This, she was sure of now, despite <del>of</del> those who the most loudly and
               vigorously protested their <q>conversion</q>. Only that morning, one of her most
               hopeful pupils, a boy named Gonji, eagerly desirous of obtaining a bit of money for
               some obscure purpose, and unable to move her by entirety or guile, had finally
               fervently offered: <q>For ten yen me goee to church aevly Thundy. For fifteen yen, me
                  lubbee Jesus!</q></p>

            <p> With passionate vehemence the girl had assured her own weary heart that she alone
               would feel and understand the Spirit of Christmas. She had shared her all with them;
               but this she now wanted, demanded, hugged to herself---just to be alone, on this
               great day adored by her own beloved people for centuries. And now! </p>

            <p> She put back the quilt from her head, cautiously <choice>
                  <sic>noiselessl</sic>
                  <corr>noiseless.</corr>
               </choice> Then as silently, she sat up. A hard look crept into the girl’s young face;
               into her eyes a curious wrathful excitement blazed. Suddenly she sprang to her <choice>
                  <sic>feet.</sic>
                  <corr>feet</corr>
               </choice> and in the moment <del>sprang</del> seized by the neck of her <foreign
                  xml:lang="ja"><choice>
                     <sic>kimona</sic>
                     <corr>kimono</corr>
                  </choice></foreign> the Japanese girl crouching behind her trunk.</p>

            <p>To strike a native servant, or even a pupil, was no uncommon thing among foreigners
               at this time; but if any one had suggested to Miss Ellison this method of
               chastisement, she would have repelled the idea with indignation and horror. Now, as
               she held the trembling girl with one hand, she brought the other <pb n="4"/> swiftly
               forward in a resounding slap.</p>

            <p><q>You thief!</q> she cried breathlessly. <q>Oh-h! You wicked thief!</q></p>

            <p> Words failed her further She could only stare at the Japanese girl with wide,
               blazing eyes, trembling and quivering from head to foot. But she was conscious too of
               another sense, oddly enough one of strange relief, as if the explosion of her hand
               against the yielding cheek of the Japanese girl had acted as a veritable tonic upon
               her overcharged nerves. </p>

            <p>She began to search her, dipping down into the long sleeves, which were quite empty.
               Her hands, since the shock of that single slap, felt weak as a child’s or a sick
               woman’s, and her effort to drag the silk stocking which Yone still desperately clung
               to from her was futile. Miss Ellison abandoned the effort, and <del>shooov</del>
               pushed the Japanese girl toward the doors. </p>

            <p><q>Dr. Masters shall know of this!</q> she cried shrilly. <q>Oh, <del>yo</del> you
                  may be very sure of that. Go---go-- out of my room, quickly! And never let me see
                  you face again!</q>
            </p>

            <p>Alone, she looked about her. The excitement had put new energy and warmth into her,
               but it had added more fire to her bitterness, her anger, her resentment. She put both
               her weak little hands over her heart, as if to stop its passionate beating.</p>

            <p>Yone! <emph>His</emph> precious discovery--the sole redeeming hope of the mission.
               Yone! Whose soft, prayerful, sweet voice, with its pleading entreaty for more blessed
               light, whose wistful eyes and quivering lips had betrayed to him---so he had averred
               with such kindling eyes--- a rare and sensitive soul. Yone--- a thief! What would he
               say to that?</p>

            <p>Miss Ellison felt a <del>strange</del> sense of wild elation at the <pb n="5"/> proof
               of Yone’s defection. She could have cried from sheer joy, from pure relief. Never
               again would he sound the praises of this small white sepulchre! Never again need she
               chide herself for her seeming coldness to this girl.</p>

            <p>Following this savage sense of elation, the reaction was a pitiful one. A pinched,
               tragic look crept slowly across the girl’s face, giving it a peculiarly firghtened,
               suffering expression. She knew very well why she was glad of the wickedness of Yone.
               She loved Dr. Masters. It was like a mad illness--this love that had taken possession
               of her heart, here in this <q>heathen</q> land, where she and he had seemed to her
               sometimes like shipwrecked sailors upon a strange coast. Their very isolation had
               drawn them the closer together. Their interests had been of a mutual kind, their
               ideals the same; they were struggling toward the same goal. She knew that she
                  <del>had</del> loved him that very first moment when she <del>had</del> looked
               into his eager face, as he smiled across at her in the midst of that motley crowd of
               little Japanese people in the mission house. For love knows not Time. It wells up in
               the human breast like the titanic waves of the mighty ocean, which may not be beaten
               down. It had raised this girl to abnormal heights, only to drop her, as she feared
               into abysmal depths.</p>

            <p>Life had been desireable, so absolutely a thing of sun and glory while he was there
               in Fukui, working shoulder to shoulder beside her, teaching, leading, helping
               her---she, who was to take his place. Then he had gone, ---gone to another field of
               labor---and everything had turned black and hateful. This land of unending interest,
               of scenes of surpassing beauty was nothing but the home of the heathen, the savage,
                     <del><unclear>kind</unclear> to the <pb n="6"/>beasts,</del> whose impulses
               were no purer, no higher than animals, and whom it were vain and futile to dream of
               uplifting. She had missed her vocation. She was adrift here, a martyr to a girl’s
               first emotional impulse. Miss Ellison was very very young.</p>

            <p>She wrote to Dr. Masters. He had been transferred to Tokyo, and was in charge of a
               large church there. How glad she had been of this wonderful advancement for him, and
               how her heart had throbbed under the silent parting clasp of his hand, a pressure
               which seemed to reassure her that soon they would be together again. That was more
               than a month since, and he had not replied to her letter! He had written to Yone!
               Miss Ellison’s half closed eyes recalled with a poignant sense of agony the girl’s
               confusion and alarm, when she had come upon her with the letter. Yone had thrust it
               into the bosom of her <foreign xml:lang="ja"><choice>
                     <sic>kimona</sic>
                     <corr>kimono</corr>
                  </choice></foreign>, without reading or showing one word of it to her, whom she
               professed to love! Very well, then. Her turn had come. She would write another letter
               to Yone’s Friend.</p>

            <p>The pen point broke against the paper. She tore the sheet across. No! She would not,
               could not write. It did not matter. Nothing -- nothing in the whole wide world
               mattered now. She hated him no longer, just as she loved him no longer, she told
               herself calmly. Nor was Yone still odious to her. Indeed she regretted her impetuous
               brutality. Nothing, nothing mattered, save that this was Christmas Eve, and at home,
               in her faraway beloved, homely, beautiful Michigan, they were thinking of her
               tonight, and praying for her, sending out upon the silent air myriad beautiful
               thoughts and hopes to bless and elevate her. They had asked her to keep the Christmas
               with them over the distance of land and water between them. So she <pb n="7"/>
               would--Ah, she would! She would transport her yearning heart <choice>
                  <sic>bac back</sic>
                  <corr>back</corr>
               </choice> to the dear homeland, and they must feel that she was indeed <choice>
                  <sic>a among</sic>
                  <corr>among</corr>
               </choice> them again--she, whose heart had been so very sore, and who had let the
               cold of this cheerless place wither her heart.</p>

            <p>Her tired head dropped downward to her arms, and fell like a crushed flower upon
               them.</p>

            <milestone unit="line"/>

            <p/>


            <pb n="9"/>
            <note>Page 9 is labelled as page 8 in original.</note>

            <p> She made no sound, and beyond the widening her eyes, one could not have seen a
               change in her. But her bosom went up and down like a little wave upon a small
               restless sea, and presently her hand stole slowly to her throat. The she closed her
               eyes, as one may do when he prays. </p>

            <p> From behind a folded screen, the small, no longer sad or wistful face of Yone,
               showed. Her dimples glimmered like stars in her cheeks. Never had she appeared so
               pretty and charming, as demurely she pronounced the Japanese formal first words of
               greeting. </p>

            <p><q>I pray thee to excuse my rudeness the last time we met!</q></p>

            <p><q>Yone, dear!</q></p>

            <p> Miss Ellison was holding out her arms; but Yone was unused to embraces. After a very
               deep and profound courtesy, a forehead barely escaping bumping on the mats, she said
               shyly: <q>No doubt your graciousness desires to know who are the honorable humble
                  gift givers?</q>
            </p>

            <p> Turning bashfully toward the long silken stocking, which she had taken from Miss
               Ellison’s trunk, and which now hung in a prominent place in the room, she said:
                  <q>This, respectable teacher, is full of nize gifts from insignificant school.
                  See! They are of Americazan make. Those degraded boy, Gonji, buy same in
               Tokyo</q>. </p>

            <p> Miss Ellison remembered Gonji’s fervent appeals for <pb n="10"/>money, and his
               ingenuous bribe to <q>lubbee Jesus</q> if she would but lend a few yen to him. She
               thought of the severe scolding and lecture with which she had answered his request.
               She had accused him of desiring the money for gambling purposes. </p>

            <p>
               <q>This</q> continued Yone, with sparkling eyes, <q>is a box of honorable choculut
                  Americazen candy. It is my gift to your graciousness. Mees Ellison, me—I have ask
                  that Dr. Master buy that same candy for me at you magnificent country</q>. </p>

            <p> Still Miss Ellison’s tongue failed her. She knew that Yone must have skimped and
               saved for months out of her small earnings in order to buy this Christmass gift. The
               lump in her throat could not be controlled. It threatened to choke her. Tears
               splashed in a shower down her face, but she did not attempt to hide them. </p>

            <p>
               <q>This</q> went on the soft-voiced Yone, and now she turned joyfully to the proud
               little fir tree which literally dripped with ornaments never before probably hung
               upon a Christmass tree, <q>This be the gift of Nishimura Taro <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >sama</foreign></q><note resp="pers:LW1"><q>Sama</q> is the most formal
                  Japanese honourific.</note>. A faint blush dyed the Japanese girl’s cheeks, but
               her eyes smiled straight into the American girl’s. <q>With his honorable hands he
                  have cut down those tree at those mountain and on those unworthy back he have
                  carry him to the honorable house of your graciousnes</q>.</p>

            <p><q>Taro! He---why, he is in Tokyo--Dr. Master’s assistant!</q></p>

            <p>Yone laughed, her pretty dimples all abroad again, and then childishly she clapped
               her hands. As if ashamed of this display of feelings, she then very humbly prostrated
               herself, and when she had <choice>
                  <sic>bumbed</sic>
                  <corr>bumped</corr>
               </choice> her forehead several times on the mat, she looked up, still smiling, and
               said:</p>

            <pb n="11"/>

            <p><q>Taro got obey those order from hees boss----</q> using a forbidden word, and being
               unchided for it<choice><sic>--</sic><corr>.</corr></choice></p>

            <p><q>You mean Dr. <choice>
                     <sic>Masters’</sic>
                     <corr>Master’s</corr>
                  </choice> told him to---come---here?</q></p>

            <p>Yone looked at Miss Ellison, and a very sweet expression was in her shy eyes as she
               answered:</p>

            <p><q>Mees Ellison, he <emph>bring</emph> him here!</q></p>

            <p><q>Please d-don’t----</q> began Miss Ellison, but Yone was still smiling in that soft
               caressing way, just like a little kitten waiting to be stroked. Up and down she
               nodded her shining black head.</p>

            <p><q>Those Dr. Master bring also <emph>hees</emph> gift to you, Mees Ellison</q>. With
               a motion of triumph and pride, Yone jumped to her feet, swept aside a sheltering
               screen, and exposed to the view of the bedazzled teacher a great black stove, through whose open bars a
               ruddy fire blazed and crackled . It was the secret of the magical warmth of the room.
               The Japanese girl looked at it reverently, and then she said: <q>Dr Master say thad
                  Americazan stove jos lig’ jewel ad Japan, and thas <emph>hees<del>s</del></emph>
                  gift unto you!</q></p>

            <p>Miss Ellison stretched out her hands toward it. She was crying, in spite of the smile
               that had been for some time trying to force its way through her tears.</p>

            <p><q>If you only knew what that meant!</q> she said.</p>

            <p><q>It take many long day and moach work carry thad iron over those mountain</q> said
               Yone gently, <q>but Dr. Master, he say thad thas no madder, account thas grade labor
                  --of love!</q></p>
            <note>Missing closing quotation marks in original.</note>

            <p>Something rustled in the bosom of Yone’s <foreign xml:lang="ja"><choice>
                     <sic>kimona</sic>
                     <corr>kimono</corr>
                  </choice></foreign>, as she laid her hand upon it. She drew out a little crumpled
               sheet of <pb n="12"/>
               <choice>
                  <sic>pap paper</sic>
                  <corr>paper</corr>
               </choice> and put into the hands of her teacher.</p>

            <p><q>Thas hees ledder</q> she said. <q>Pray you read ’bout thad grade secret for
                  you</q>.</p>

            <p>Their heads were together, the gold one nestling to the black, and they drew apart
               only at the <del>sou</del> sound of voices in the adjoinng room.</p>

            <p>Said Yone:</p>

            <p><q>Thas hees voice---my Taro<foreign xml:lang="ja">-sama</foreign>’s</q></p>

            <p><q>And <emph>his</emph>!</q> said the other girl in a happy sob.</p>

            <p><q>We vaery loggy</q> said Yone. <q>We got lots nise presents at those school, an’ we
                  got something more bes’ still. You know whas those?</q></p>

            <p>There was a deep note of solemnity in the voice of the missionary as she answered: <q><choice><sic>Its</sic><corr>It’s</corr></choice> what Christ gave us as our <choice><sic>imortal</sic><corr>immortal</corr></choice> birthright, Yone---Love divine!</q></p>


















         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
<!-- Curly apostrophe ’ -->
