<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WillardMack1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Willard Mack to Collaborate With Mrs. Frances Reeve</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:KL1"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreader</resp>
               <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>Facsimile retrieved from University of British Columbia Library</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:210"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNF"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Hollywood"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:LW1" when="2022-05-06" status="published">Proof completed and set to
            published.</change>
         <change who="pers:KL1" when="2021-10-28" status="inProgress">Started transcribing.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2020-07-01">Added note about source.</change>
         <change who="pers:MC1" status="empty" when="2019-08-28">directed to facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and
            exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography
            entry bibl210 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text facs="facs:Willard_Mack_to_Collaborate">
      <pb n="4"/>
      <body>
         <head>Willard Mack to Collaborate With Mrs. Frances Reeve</head>
         <head type="subtitle">Authoress Is Known to Reading Public As <q><name ref="pers:WE1"
                  >Onotowatanna</name></q>
            <name ref="pers:WE1">Mrs. Reeve</name> Says Canada Has Not Attempted to Conserve Cream
            of Natural Resources—The Authors of the Country</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Mrs. Frances Reeve</name></byline>
         </opener>
         <div>
            <p>Canada has no more talented son than Willard Mack, poet, author, playwright and
               actor. Born in Morrisburg, Ontario, (his father was also born in Canada), he is
               essentially a product of our Canada, although his greatest success was achieved in
               the United States.</p>

            <p>Scarcely a season passes in New York without a Willard Mack play, and very often two
               or three plays. He has been associated with David Belasco for years. This versatile
               Canadian author has had one success after another, his <q>Tiger Rose</q>, being one
               of the phenomenal record runs on Broadway. Alberta was chosen as the scene of this
               typically Canadian play. Now Mack is back again with us, <q>rooting</q> for more
               material to show upon the stage and screen Canada <q>as is</q>. He comes back to us
               with no head swollen by his successes abroad and in the States, but, like a truly big
               man, simple, modest and making light of his own achievements, eager to learn from
               others, and to give a helping shoulder.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Local Collaboration</head>
               <p>It is notable that one of his first acts upon arrival in Calgary was to get in
                  touch with Calgary’s author, Ralph Kendal, with whom he is collaborating upon a
                  play of the North West Mounted Police. He will also do a play with another
                  Canadian author, <name ref="pers:WE1">Mrs. Francis Reeve (Onoto
                     Watanna)</name>.</p>
               <p>Mr. Mack knows this part of Canada well. To use his own recent phrase: <q>I speak
                     your language</q>. His father is a well known rancher of Rosebud, owner of the
                     <q>McC</q> ranch. Mr. Mack has pioneered and ranched himself; has been all over
                  the Peace River country and farther northwest. He has herded cattle and raised
                  crops in Alberta.</p>

               <p>We are at present taking a sort of census of Canadian authors. For the first time,
                  under the inspiration of the recently formed Canadian Authors’ League, we are
                     <q>taking the number</q> of our own talent. The result of the research has been
                  proven fascinating and astonishing. We did not know we possessed such valuable and
                  brilliant material. We had come almost to believe that such luminaries as Basil
                  King, Arthur Stringer, Willard Mack and many others equally talented and
                  celebrated belonged to the U.S.A. We have in the past boomed our natural
                  resources, oil, iron, coal, agriculture. We have fought for tariffs to protect our
                  manufacturers, and out of the overwhelming generosity of the public heart we have
                  even patronized and conciliated the farmer; but how have we treated our authors
                  and artists? These, the very cream of our natural resources we have not attempted
                  to conserve; indeed we have in the past literally driven them into the open arms
                  of the U.S. Whenever a Canadian author attains eminence in the States, he is
                  instantly heralded there as an American product. We should not be filched of our
                  purest gold—our dreamers, who in all time, have been esteemed a nation’s pride.
                  They are as truly a country’s natural resources as are its minerals.</p>

               <p>The purely Canadian Authors’ League is in a way a test that we are able to walk
                  without the crutch of the States. It should have the heart-felt support and
                  sympathy of all Canadians.</p>

               <p>Here then is Willard Mack back in Canada, genial, big and friendly, and still
                  loving every inch of his native land. We cannot keep him with us, it is true, for
                  he is not merely a local celebrity, but we can show in some way that we are proud
                  of him and like him as much as he does us.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
