<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WooingOfWistaria14">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Wooing of Wistaria</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:197"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovel"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" when="2020-08-17" status="inProgress">Begin transcribing and proofreading</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-06-14" status="empty">Changed id from WooingOfWistaria12 to WooingOfWistaria14.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-08-23">Added facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl197 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <head>The Wooing of Wistaria</head>
        
         <head type="subtitle">A Love Story of Japan</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>     
         </opener>
         <div type="content">
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>When after a life that had never lacked variety the Lady Wistaria came to the
                  years of <choice>
                     <sic>tranquillity</sic>
                     <corr>tranquility</corr>
                  </choice>, she was wont to say, with the philosophy that follows dangerous times:
                     <q>No one, man or maid, ever really began to live before the time to which the
                     first memory reverts</q>.</p>
               <p>The first recollection of the Lady Wistaria goes back to an earlier childhood than
                  that of most mortals. This she ascribed to its terrible and awful import. She
                  could scarcely do more than move with the uncertain direction of babyhood, when<pb n="2"/>her father, always now in her memory as gaunt, lean, haggard, tall, had
                  taken her upon a long journey. They had travelled partly by <foreign xml:lang="ja">kurumaya</foreign>, and, towards the end, on foot. That is, her father had
                  walked, carry8ing her on high in his arms. </p>
               <p>When they halted at Yedo they stood amid a vast concourse of people, who remained
                  silent and respectful against the background of the buildings, while in the centre
                  of the road marched steadily and pompously a great glittering pageant.</p>
               <p>Wisteria had clapped her hands with glee and delight at the mass of color, the
                  glimmer of shield and breastplate, the prancing, snorting horses. But her father
                  suddenly had raised an enormous hand and in a moment had stopped her delight.
                  Wisteria lapsed into an acute silence.</p>
               <p>Instantly she was awakened from her painful apathy by her father, who moved her
                  higher in his arms, and turned her head slowly about with one hand, while with the
                  other he pointed to a shining personage reclining in a palanquin borne high on the
                  shoulders of ten stout-legged attendants.</p>
               <p><q>My daughter</q>, said her father’s hollow voice in her ear, <q>yonder rides the
                     man who killed your mother. It is through his crime that you are orphaned and
                     have no mother to care for you and love you. Look at him well! Hush! Do not
                     weep or shake with <pb n="3"/>fear, but turn your eyes upon him. Look at him!
                     Look! Look! Yonder rides your mother’s murderer. Do not forget his face as long
                     as you live. It is your duty to remember it!</q></p>
               <p>Whereupon Wistaria, who, in obedience to her father’s commands, had stared with
                  wide eyes fixedly at the reclining noble, set up a most extraordinary cry. It was
                  unlike that of a little child—a wild, wailing shriek, so weird and piteous that
                  the bystanders started in horror and fear. The noble raised himself lazily on his
                  elbow, starting across the heads of all, until his eyes rested upon the man with
                  the child held on high. He fell back with an uneasy shrug of the shoulders. </p>
               <p>That was the Lady Wistaria’s oldest memory. There were others, but none so vivid
                  as this, the first of all. Even later, when she had ceased to be a child, she had
                  been unable to pierce the mystery of her father’s life, or indeed her own.</p>
               <p> One half of her earlier years had been spent in a small, whitewashed cottage,
                  built on the crest of a little wind-blown hill, far enough removed from the
                  dwellings in the village below to be entirely cut off from them.</p>
               <p>There was a touch of the uncanny and weird about the little village, whose slender
                  streets, ascending and descending, zigzagging up and down, disappeared among
                  hillocks <pb n="4"/> and bluffs, though built in reality in the hollow outskirts
                  of a flourishing city at the foot of a small chain of mountains. Through the land
                  here was green and beautiful at all times of the year, there came no one from the
                  great city beyond to this solitary settlement, whose inhabitants bore the impress
                  of toil, pain, and oppression.</p>
               <p>Why her father, who, she had been told, was of noble blood, resided here on this
                  hilltop, isolated even from the strange people who dwelt in the silent village
                  below, the Lady Wistaria had never learned. When she had questioned her uncle and
                  aunt, she had been frigidly informed that curiosity and inquisitiveness were
                  degrading traits, which a maiden should strive with all her strength to overcome.
                  Neither did she ask her father, who, taciturn and cold during her brief residence
                  each year in his house, gave her no opportunity for winning his confidence. His
                  love Wistaria had never dreamed of possessing. </p>
               <p>Nevertheless, whenever she went to her father’s house, a wistful longing and
                  yearning for him possessed her whole being, and when she departed she would hide
                  her face in her sleeve, weeping silently, not knowing why she should weep, and
                  scarcely conscious of the fact that she wept for lack of her father’s love.</p>
               <p> In her father’s house there were no servants, <pb n="5"/> no maids, no
                  attendants—only one weazened, blind, and infinitely old woman, who wept tears from
                  her sightless eyes upon her arrival, who sang and crooned to her at night in a
                  sobbing, sighing voice, that was as sweet and pure as a girl’s.</p>
               <p>She addressed the old woman as <q>Madame Mume</q>, and preserved always towards
                  her the reserved and dignified attitude of the mistress to the maid. Yet her
                  father addressed her as <q>Mother</q>. Wisteria knew the old woman was not his
                  mother, and she could not believe she was even akin to them; for had she not
                  always been taught that the family from which she was descended was one of the
                  oldest and noblest in Japan, while old Madame Mume, though gentle and good, wore
                  the garb of the poor <foreign xml:lang="ja">heimin</foreign>.</p>
               <p> The other half of her childhood had been spent at the home of her uncle. Here
                  were countless retainers and servants, besides a host of <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, petty vassals, soldiers, peasants, and citizens, who lived
                  upon his land and owed their direct allegiance to him. </p>
               <p> The garden walls surrounding her uncle’s palace were tall and of massive
                  structure, built of solid stone. Its gates were guarded by handsome, bold <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> clad in thick armor. The steel upon their
                  breasts and shoulders glistened with a sinister sheen, and beneath their blazing
                  helmets fierce eyes burned out their unswerving allegiance and <pb n="6"/> loyalty
                  to their lord and their scorn and defiance of all his enemies. Their coats, all
                  emblazoned and embroidered with golden dragons, bore two crests, that of the
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> Iyesada, and that of the powerful
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> under whom they served, the Lord of
                  Catzu, uncle of the Lady Wistaria. </p>
               <p> Here in her uncle’s palace, Wistaria was watched over, cared for, nurtured, and
                  refined. Lackeys and servants were about her on all sides, ready to spring to her
                  service. As a child she had attended a private school, kept by an old <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, where with half a dozen other little girls she
                  had squatted on small, padded mats before writing-tables but twelve inches high,
                  and had been taught the intricacies of the language. Two gorgeously liveried
                  attendants always accompanied her to and from the school-house, carrying her
                  books, her writing-box, her keeling-cushion, and her little table. </p>
               <p>When she grew older she attended the elementary school. After she had left this, a
                  silent woman of perfect manners and exquisite appearance had come to her uncle’s
                  palace and attached herself entirely to her. With the coming of this governess,
                  wisteria ceased to pay her annual visits to her father’s house. He himself came to
                  the palace instead, once every year. Upon these occasions Wistaria was brought
                  into his presence. He would put a few stern questions to her <pb n="7"/>
                  concerning her knowledge of her duty to her parents, to which Wistaria would
                  respond with expressions of filial submission to his will in all things.</p>
               <p>From the governess, Wistaria learned the elegancies of conversation and how to act
                  on meeting great personages at court. She had even been drilled in certain graces
                  which should not fail to enchain her lover, when he, the proper one, should be
                  chosen for her. </p>
               <p>Now that she had reached the age of fifteen years, this perfect person had
                  departed from the palace to teach maidens of younger years. The Lady Wistaria had
                  arrived at an age when she could be said to have been graduated from her
                  governess’s hands as competent to pass the rest of her life without further
                  instruction, save that constant restraint exercised over her by her aunt, the Lady
                  Evening Glory of Catzu.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>II</head>
               <p>The education of a Japanese maid is not alone a matter of cultivating the mind; it
                  is an actual <choice>
                     <sic>moulding</sic>
                     <corr>molding</corr>
                  </choice> of her whole character. The average girl under such discipline succumbs
                  to the hereditary instinct of implicit obedience to her dictators, and becomes
                  like unto their conception of what she would be. But the Lady Wistaria was not an
                  average girl. That is the reason her appearance at the court of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> in Yedo created a <choice>
                     <sic>furore</sic>
                     <corr>furor</corr>
                  </choice>. Her fresh, young beauty, her grace and bewitch-<pb n="9"/>ing charm,
                  were a revelation to the jaded court.</p>
               <p>The Lady Evening Glory, who had spent years of thought and preparation for this
                  event, had warned her repeatedly that upon such an auspicious occasion she was to
                  tread across the vast hall with downcast eyes and an attitude of graceful
                  humility. She was on no account to look about her. While all eyes might gaze upon
                  her, she must see no one. And this is how the Lady Wistaria carried out her
                  instructions.</p>
               <p>When first she began the slow parade towards the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>’s throne, my lady’s head was drooped in the correct pose,
                  with her eyes modestly downcast. She had proceeded but a few paces, however, when
                  she was thrilled by the intuition that the spectacle was worthy of any sacrifice
                  necessary to see it. Her small head began to erect itself. Her eyes, wide open,
                  with one great sweep viewed the splendor of the picture—the graceful courtiers,
                  the lovely women in their costumes of the sun. A sharp pinch upon the arm brought
                  her back to the exacting presence of the Lady Evening Glory beside her. Down
                  drooped her head again. Gradually the eyelids fluttered. My lady peeped!</p>
               <p>There was a low murmur throughout the hall. The waving of fans ceased a space. The
                  Lady Evening Glory recognizsed the significance of that murmur, and then the <pb n="10"/> hush that ensued. A tremendous fluttering pride arose in her bosom.
                  Her experience of many years assured her that her niece’s beauty was compelling
                  its splendid tribute.</p>
               <p>Then the Lady Wistaria was presented to the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>. Her prostration was made with inimitable grace. Her beauty
                  and charm called forth words of praise from the Shogun himself to her uncle.</p>
               <p>A young noble, more daring and ardent than all the others, separated himself from
                  the assembled company, and, crossing to where the Lady Wistaria stood, kissed a
                  hyacinth and dropped it at the girl’s feet.</p>
               <p>The Lady Evening Glory could have shrieked aloud with fury at the action of her
                  niece, due solely to her innocence. She had no thought whence it had come. A
                  flower in her path was not something she could tread upon, or even pass by. There
                  in the centre of the gorgeous hall she stooped tenderly and picked up the pleading
                  flower.</p>
               <p><q>Wild girl!</q> cried her aunt, in a suffocating whisper.</p>
               <p> Wisteria started with a little cry of genuine dismay. She had forgotten in one
                  moment the instruction of years. In her confusion she stopped short in her
                  progress across the hall. As if impelled by some great subtle force within her,
                  helplessly the Lady Wistaria raised her eyes. They gazed immediately into the
                  depths of another pair, afire with an <pb n="11"/> awakening passion. The next
                  moment the young girl had blushed, red as the tints a masterful sun throws to
                  coquetting clouds at sunset. </p>
               <p>All the journey through, to their temporary palace in Yedo, her aunt abused the
                  Lady Wistaria. The training of years wasted! Ingratitude was the basest of crimes!
                  Was this the way she repaid her aunt’s labor and kindness? Well, back to Catzu
                  they should go. It would be unsafe to remain longer in the capital. Certainly her
                  niece had much to learn before she could continue in Yedo longer than a day.</p>
               <p>The Lady Wistaria sat back in her palanquin, pouting. What, to be taken from the
                  gay capital one day after arriving—before she had had the chance to meet or even
                  speak to any one! Oh! it was cruel, and she the most stupid of maidens not to have
                  comported herself correctly at her presentation! </p>
               <p><q>Dearest, my lady aunt</q>, said she, <q>pray you, do let us continue in the
                     capital for the season</q>.</p>
               <p><q>What! And be laughed at by the whole court for our shocking and magnificently
                     bad manners? People will declare that you have been reared in the fields with
                     the peasants</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Do not, I beg, blame me for an accident, dear, my honorable aunt. It was not,
                     in truth, my own fault</q>.</p>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p><q>Indeed!</q></p>
               <p><q>Indeed, I do assure you it was the fault of that honorably silly
                  flower</q>.</p>
               <p><q>TSHH!</q></p>
               <p><q>And of that magnificent and augustly handsome courtier who dropped it</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Dropped it! My lady niece, I saw the impudent fellow throw it at your
                  feet!</q></p>
               <p><q>What! You saw! Oh, my aunt, then it is you who are jointly guilty with
                  me!</q></p>
               <p><q>What is that?</q> cried the aunt, angrily.</p>
               <p><q>Why, my lady, your honorable eyes were improper also</q>.</p>
               <p>The Lady Evening Glory turned an offended shoulder.</p>
               <p><q>We will start to-morrow for home</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, my lady!</q></p>
               <p><q>I have spoken</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But, dear aunt—</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>Will you condescend to tell me, girl, who is guarding, thou or I?</q></p>
               <p>With the Lady Evening Glory, <q>thou</q> was the end of discussion.</p>
               <p>The following day, therefore, the returning cortège set out for Catzu. As fortune
                  would have it, the Lady Evening Glory travelled in her own train, while her niece
                  had also her personal retinue about her. Consequently the journey was joyous for
                  the Lady Wistaria.</p>
               <p>When first the cortège began to move through the city a strange little procession
                  followed in its wake. It was made up of the love-<pb n="13"/> sick suitors, who,
                  having but once gazed upon the beauty of the Lady Wistaria, wished to serve and
                  follow her to the end of the world. The following was quite large when the cortège
                  started. A number dropped off as they reached the city limits, then gradually the
                  hopeless and disappointed swains with drooping heads turned back to Yedo, there to
                  dream of the vision of a day, but to dream hopelessly. </p>
               <p>Wherever the Lady Wistaria’s personal train travelled there lay scattered upon the
                  ground, and blowing in the air above and about her, tiny bits of white or
                  delicately tinted and perfumed paper. They were, alas! The love-letters and poems
                  penned by the ardent lovers, which the hard-hearted lady, tearing into
                  infinitesimal bits, had saucily tossed to the winds. It was thus she tossed their
                  love from her, she would have them believe. </p>
               <p>Hopeless, and finally indignant, therefore, backward turned these erstwhile
                  hopeful suitors. </p>
               <p>Sir Genji, the big <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, who had especial
                  charge of Wistaria’s train, reported to her, with a smile of satisfaction, that
                  she would suffer no further annoyance, as all save one of her suitors had finally
                  retreated. </p>
               <p><q>Bring closer your honorable head</q>, said the lady to Genji, who strode beside
                  her <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimono</foreign>, ever and anon ordering and,
                  scolding the runners.</p>
               <p>He brought his ear closer to the girl’s lips.<pb n="14"/> She leaned over and
                  whispered, while a pale pink flush came, fled, and grew and deepened again in her
                  face.</p>
               <p><q>Tell me</q>, said she, <q>which of the honorably bold and silly cavaliers is it
                     that remains?</q></p>
               <p><q>The one, my lady, who, not content with despatching his love-letters and tokens
                     to you by underlings, has had the august impertinence to deliver them himself
                     in person</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Yes—ye-es—of course</q>, said Wistaria, blushing deliciously, <q>and that was
                     honorably right. Fo you not think so, my brave Genji?</q></p>
               <p><q>Perhaps</q>, admitted the astute <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>,
                  frowning at the same time upon a portion of the parade belonging to the Lady
                  Evening Glory. Wisteria laughed with infinite relish. </p>
               <p><q>Well</q>, she said, <q>if my honorable aunt or august uncle were to learn of
                     his boldness, I fear me they would command that the curtains of my
                     insignificant <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimon</foreign> be drawn so tightly that
                     I should surely suffocate</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Fear not</q>, said Genji, <q>I shall take immediate measures to prevent such an
                     occurrence, my lady</q>.</p>
               <p>Wisteria pouted, and frowned as heavily as it is possible for bright eyes and rosy
                  lips to do. She toyed with her fan, opening and closing it several times.</p>
               <p><q>You are honorably over-zealous, Sir Genji</q>, she said. </p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p><q>My lady</q>, he replied, <q>know you aught of this stranger?</q></p>
               <p><q>He has a pretty grace</q>, said Wistaria, <q>and the bearing of one of noble
                     rank. Have you not noted, Sir Genji, the beauty and richness of his magnificent
                     attire?</q></p>
               <p><q>I have, my lady. It is of that attire I would speak</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Do so at once, then</q>.</p>
               <p><q>It is the attire, my lady, of the Mori family</q>.</p>
               <p><q>The Mori! What! Our honorably hostile neighbors?</q></p>
               <p><q>Exactly</q>, said Genji.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, dear!</q> murmured Wistaria, as she sank back in her cushions in troubled
                  thought. After a moment her little black head again appeared.</p>
               <p><q>Gen</q>, she cried, <q>come hither once more</q>.</p>
               <p><q>My lady?</q></p>
               <p><q>A little closer, if you please. So! Know you not, Sir Gen, that my lady aunt,
                     and indeed also my own august father, once served this odious Mori
                  prince?</q></p>
               <p><q>I have herd so, my lady</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Well, then, truly <emph>all</emph> of the members of this honorable clan cannot
                     be augustly bad!</q></p>
               <p>Sir Genji could not restrain a smile.</p>
               <p><q>Indeed, my lady, this Choshui people have many worthy and admirable
                     qualities</q>.</p>
               <p><q>You are a very clever fellow, my dear Sir Gen</q>, said Wistaria, smiling
                  engagingly <pb n="16"/>now, <q>and I shall bespeak you to my honorable uncle. And
                     now—now—if you would really wish to serve me, do you pray show some
                     kindness—some little insignificant courtesy to this unfortunate Mori courtier.
                     Perhaps he may have some good attributes</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Undoubtedly, my lady</q>.</p>
               <p><q>And do be careful to allow my lady aunt to know naught concerning him, for she,
                     having come from this Mori, is actually more sour against them than we, you and
                     I, Sir Gen, who have not indeed</q>.</p>
               <p>Just then my lady heard a familiar tramp to the left of her <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimono</foreign>. There were but few horses in the cortège, and most of them
                  had gone ahead with her father’s <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>.
                  Consequently the beat of a horse’s hoofs was plainly to be heard. The Lady
                  Wistaria wavered between lying back in her carriage and drawing about her
                  discreetly the curtains, or sitting up and feigning indifference to the horseman. </p>
               <p>The rider had fallen into a slow trot behind her <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimono</foreign>, and seemed to be making no effort either to overtake or
                  ride beside her. For the space of a few minutes the Lady Wistaria, with a bright,
                  expectant red spot in either cheek, waited for some sign on the part of the rider.
                  His stubborn continuance in the background at first thrilled, then irritated, and
                  finally distracted her. My lady put her shining little head out of the vehicle,<pb n="17"/>then, leaning quite far out, she looked backward. Instantly the rider
                  spurred his horse forward. In a flash his hitherto melancholy face became luminous
                  with hope. A moment later he was beside the lady’s <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimono</foreign>. Before her officious maid had time to draw the curtains a
                  love-letter had fallen into my lady’s lap. </p>
               <p>It was possibly the fiftieth appeal he had penned to her. Hitherto he had born the
                  bitter chagrin of seeing the torn bits of paper fall from a little hand that
                  parted the silken curtains of her gilded norimono and scattered them to the
                  winds.</p>
               <p>The lover rode within sight of his mistress’s palanquin until the first gray
                  darkness of approaching night crept like an immense cloud over the heaven, chasing
                  away the enchanting rosy tints that the departing sun had left behind. </p>
               <p>Undaunted by the fact that his letter received no response, encouraged rather by
                  the fact that it had not shared the fate of its predecessors, the lover now set
                  himself to the task of composing more ardent and flowery epistles. What time was
                  not occupied in eagerly watching for the smallest glimpse of the little head to
                  appear was spent in writing to her. He wrote his love-letters and poems with a
                  shaking hand even while his horse carried him onward. He wrote them by the light
                  of the moon when the train halted<pb n="18"/>for the night. He wrote them in the
                  early dawn before the cortège had awakened. And he delivered them at all hours,
                  whenever he could obtain opportunity.</p>
               <p>Though the Lady Wistaria by this time must have acquired a goodly quantity of
                  useless literature, she took no measure to relieve herself of the burdensome
                  baggage. Nevertheless the lover began to despair. A few hours before they reached
                  her uncle’s province but into the very grounds surrounding his palace—into the
                  palace itself if necessary. He besought her that she would send him one small word
                  of favor.</p>
               <p>He waited in impatient excitement for a response to this last fervid appeal. He
                  felt sure she must at least deign to express her wish in the matter. But when they
                  reached the province he saw her carried across the borders without having given
                  him one sign or token.</p>
               <p>In his despair he dismounted, and was divided between returning to Yedo or
                  continuing his hopeless quest.</p>
               <p>As he remained plunged in his gloomy reflections and uncertainty of purpose, an
                  enormous <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> touched him sharply upon the
                  arm. In his irritation he was about to<pb n="19"/>resent the fellow’s familiarity,
                  when he perceived a little roll of rice-paper protruding from his sleeve.
                  Stealthily the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> reached out his arm to the
                  lover. The latter seized the scroll eagerly. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="20"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>III</head>
               <p>The palace, and indeed the whole domain of the Lord Catzu, presented the
                  appearance of being constantly armed as though for attack, a not uncommon thing in
                  the latter days of feudalism. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> had been
                  artful in his disposal of the various lords of the provinces. Families attached
                  personally to him were stationed in provinces lying between those administered by
                  families friendly to the Emperor. Thus none of the Emperor’s friends could meet to
                  revolt against the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>.</p>
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p>So it happened that while the Lord Catzu was one of the most intimate and
                  confidential of the advisers of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>, his
                  neighbor, the old Prince Mori, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> of the
                  province of Choshui, desired to see the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Mikado</foreign>
                  once more, the real, instead of the nominal, ruler of Japan.</p>
               <p>Consequently the two neighboring clans, while displaying extravagant courtesy
                  towards each other in public, were in reality unfriendly. Only during that portion
                  of the year when the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>’s edict ordered a
                  Yedo residence for all <foreign xml:lang="ja">daimios</foreign>, did the lords of
                  the provinces meet one another, and that under the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shogun</foreign>’s eyes in his Yedo seat of government. In the capital they
                  simulated suavity and cordiality, but once back at their provincial capitals they
                  preserved towards each other an attitude of polite defiance which made all
                  intercourse between them impossible save that of the sword, when their respective
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> and vassals, coming in contact with
                  one another, fought out their lords’ political differences. </p>
               <p>Imbittering still more the feeling existing naturally between the Mori and Catzu
                  clans, there was a personal element in the situation. When Catzu had first been
                  made lord of the province he had met on a visit to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shogun</foreign>’s Yedo court the Lady Evening Glory, whose brother and
                  guardian (she being an orphan) was a young <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samurai</foreign> in the service of the <pb n="22"/> Prince Mori. Having
                  fallen a victim to the lady’s beauty and charms, the lord of Catzu was determined
                  to have her for wife despite the opposition of the Mori Prince. Bold, brave,
                  fearless, and with a grand contempt for the power of his rival, the Lord Catzu had
                  carried off the fair lady from his neighbor’s dominions, though it was generally
                  understood that both the lady herself and her <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samurai</foreign> brought lent their assistance to the young lord. The young
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, incurring thereby the deep
                  displeasure and enmity of his Prince, was deprived of his title and estates and
                  sent into exile upon the first convenient pretext. Strange talks told without
                  shadow of authority diversified the nature of the crime for which the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> had been exiled, but the two lords remained
                  silent. All who had been concerned in the affair were commanded to the same
                  silence by the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>.</p>
               <p>Whatever were the many reasons responsible for the constant attitude of antagonism
                  of these two clans towards each other, the lords carefully guarded their
                  lands—more aces—with all the rigor of a fortress prepared for the fiercest
                  onslaught. Seemingly unapproachable and impenetrable as were the grounds of the
                  Catzu palace, yet there must have existed at some spot in their watchful walls a
                  vulnerable point, the heel of the stone Achilles. </p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>A courtier, by his dress and demeanor plainly a member of the Mori household,
                  lingered in the private gardens of the palace. The day had long since folded its
                  wings of light, but an early March moon was enveloping the land in an ethereal
                  glow. The courtier remained under the friendly shadow of a grove of pine-trees.
                  His eyes were cast upon the stately Catzu <foreign xml:lang="ja">shiro</foreign>
                  (palace). It seemed as though the moon-rays had singled out the graceful old
                  castle and was bathing it tenderly in a halo of soft light.</p>
               <p>It was cold, not bitterly so, but sharply chill, as it is at night betwixt the
                  winter and the spring. But unconscious of the chill, erect and graceful, the
                  courtier leaned against a tree-trunk, ih sarms crossed over his breast, his eyes
                  full of moist sentiment, drinking in the beauty of the night scene, which had an
                  added enchantment for him, a man in love.</p>
               <p>All about him, before, behind, and around him, graceful pine-trees raised their
                  slender, pointed heads up to the silver light. In the distance, like a strange,
                  white mirage set in the moonlit sky, a snow-capped mountain seemed hung as in
                  mid-air. The grass beneath his feet was young and intensely soft, with dewy
                  moisture upon it.</p>
               <p> A nightingale on the tip of a tall bamboo sang with such passionate sweetness
                  that it brought the lover out from the shelter of the shadow. Quivering with
                  emotion, his<pb n="24"/>soul responding and vibrating to the song of love, he
                  strode into the light of the moon. Unmindful of the danger of his exposure to
                  possible observation, he drew forth from the bosom of his <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >haori</foreign> a little roll of rice-paper. Once more he read it through, and
                  yet once again. </p>
               <p><q>MY LORD,—I write this augustly insignificant letter to you, trusting that your
                     health is good. Also the health of all your honorable relatives and
                     ancestors</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation mark in
                     original</note></p>
               <p><q>I have received your most honorably magnificent compliments. Accept my humblest
                     thanks</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation mark in
                     original</note></p>
               <p><q>Now I design to write unto you, beseeching you to abandon so foolhardy a
                     purpose as to follow me to my uncle’s home. I would feign warn you that my
                     uncle’s home. I would feign warn you that my uncle’s guards are fierce and
                     ofttimes cruel, and to one wearing the garb of a hostile clan, I fear they
                     would show no mercy. Therefore I beseech you, do you pray abandon your
                     honorable purpose</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation
                     mark in original</note></p>
               <p><q>Also condescend to permit me to add, that if you must indeed truly attempt so
                     hazardous an undertaking, I would beg to inform you, that though the grounds
                     are surrounded by such great walls that I fear me not even a tailless cat might
                     climb them, and also the gates are guarded by the fiercest <foreign
                        xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, nevertheless, on the south there is a small
                     river. Mayhap you will hire a boat. Then do you come up this honorable river,
                     keeping close to the shore, and I do assure you that you will discover a break
                     in the south wall, which leads into the gardens surrounding the palace</q>.
                     <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation mark in
                  original</note></p>
               <p><q>My lord, my uncle’s guards are not so vigilant <pb n="25"/>before sunrise, as I
                     myself have ofttimes remarked when I have arisen early of a morning and have
                     looked from my casement, which is also on the south side of the palace, facing
                     the river and the outlet thereto</q>.</p>
               <div>
                  <p>The nightingale paused in its song, and then broke out again, its long,
                     piercing trill filling the night.</p>
                  <p>The lover returned to the shelter of the pine grove, and, throwing himself upon
                     the grass, drew his cape close about him. Leaning his head upon his hand, he
                     gave himself up to his dreams. </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="26"/>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>IV</head>
                  <p>The Lady Wistaria arose with the sun. without waiting to pin back the long,
                     silken hair which hung like a cloud of lacquer about her, she stole softly to
                     the casement of her chamber.</p>
                  <p>The perfume which stole up to her was sweeter and stronger far than that wafted
                     from the trees laden with the dews of the early morning. Yet the trees were
                     bare of blossoms and would not bloom for a month to come. Nevertheless the
                     ledge of Wistaria’s casement was piled with the living spring blossoms <pb
                        n="27"/> of plum and cherry. She could not but caress them with her hands,
                     her lips, her eyes, her burning cheeks. With little, trembling hands she
                     searched among them and found what she sought—a scroll—a narrow, thin,
                     wonderful scroll, long, yet only a few inches in width, with golden borders
                     down the sides, and the faint, exquisite tracings of birds and flowers
                     intertwined among the words that leaped up at her almost as though they had
                     spoken. It was a poem to her—her grace, beauty, modesty, loveliness, its
                     theme:</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>A stately <foreign xml:lang="ja">shiro</foreign> was her home;</l>
                           <l>In royal halls she shone most fair,</l>
                           <l>From tiny feet to golden comb,</l>
                           <l>In her sweet life what is my share?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                     <note type="editorial" resp="pers:SC1">No end quotation mark in original</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Oh, lovely maid, my moon thou art;</l>
                           <l>O Fuji san, thou hast my heart!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>There were many other verses, but the Lady Wistaria was too much moved to have
                     either the vision or the mind to read beyond the first stanza. As became her
                     rank and the painful tuition of years, she should have pushed very deliberately
                     the flowers from her sill and torn the scroll into ragged pieces, a
                     chastisement prescribed by every etiquette for the temerity of a presumptuous
                     lover. </p>
                  <p>But the Lady Wistaria did nothing of the sort. She gathered the flowers
                     tenderly and took them in. Then she came back to the <pb n="28"/> casement,
                     and, learning far out, gazed with piercing wistfulness out into the little
                     garden below. For some minutes she waited, the patience of her caste fading
                     away gradually into that of the impatience of her sex.</p>
                  <p>A voice beneath her casement! She leaned farther over. A young man’s eager,
                     glowing face smiled up at her like the rising sun. Again the Lady Wistaria
                     forgot the training of years. Her trembling voice floated down to him:</p>
                  <p><q>Pray you do consider the perils in which you place yourself</q>, she
                     implored.</p>
                  <p><q>I would pass through all the perils of hell so I might reach you in the
                        end</q>, he fervidly whispered back. </p>
                  <p><q>Oh, my lord, look yonder! See, the sun is pushing its way upward above the
                        mountains and the hill-tops. Do you not know that soon my uncle’s guards
                        will pass this way?</q>
                  </p>
                  <p><q>Under the heavens there is nothing in all this wide world worthy as a gift
                        for you, dear lady. That you have deigned to accept my honorable flowers and
                        my abominably constructed poem has given me such strength that I am prepared
                        to fight a whole army of guards. Ay! And to give up readily, too, my
                        life</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>And if you love me</q>, she replied, <q>you will guard with all your
                        strength that life which you are so recklessly exposing to danger</q>.</p>
                  <pb n="29"/>
                  <p><q>Ah, sweetest lady, can it be true then that you condescend to take some
                        concern in my insignificant existence?</q></p>
                  <p>She made no response other than to pluck from the climbing wine about her
                     casement one little half-brown leaf and drop it at his feet.</p>
                  <p>As he stooped to pick up the leaf a form interposed itself, and a half-grown
                     man looked him steadily in the face. With a little cry the Lady Wistaria
                     vanished from her casement.</p>
                  <p>Meanwhile the intruder, instead of being the aggressor, was defending himself
                     against the flashing blade of the infuriated lover. Too proud to call for aid,
                     the youth opposed to the lover found himself outmatched before the skill and
                     fire of the other. So thinking caution better than valor, he flung his sword at
                     the feet of the lover. The latter, picking it up by the middle, returned it to
                     his opponent with a low bow of utmost grace. Then with one hand on his hip and
                     the othr holding his sword, he addressed the youth.</p>
                  <p><q>Thy name?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Catzu Toro. And thine?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Too insignificant to be spoken before one who bears so great a name as
                        thine</q>, returned the other, bowing with satirical grace.</p>
                  <p><q>How is that?</q> cried Catzu Toro— <q>insignificant? What, one in thy garb
                        and with thy skill of swordsmanship?</q></p>
                  <pb n="30"/>
                  <p>The victorious one, shrugging his shoulders imperceptibly, again bowed with a
                     smile of disclaimer. </p>
                  <p><q>May I be permitted</q>, he said, <q>to put one question to you, my lord, and
                        then I am perfectly prepared to give myself up to your father’s guards,
                        though not, I promise you, without a struggle, which I doubt not your
                        vassals will long remember</q>. And her blithely bent the blade of his sword
                     with his two hands.</p>
                  <p><q>Nay, then</q>, cried the youth, impetuously, <q>You do me injustice. I am
                        ready to swear protection to one who has acted so bravely as thou. But a
                        question for a question, is not that fair?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Assuredly</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Very well, then. You serve the Prince of Mori?</q></p>
                  <p><q>In a very humble capacity</q>, returned the other, guardedly.</p>
                  <p><q>In what capacity?</q> inquired the young Toro, quickly.</p>
                  <p><q>Ah, that is two questions, and you have not even deigned to listen to my
                        one</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Speak</q>, said the youth, curbing his curiosity and impatience.</p>
                  <p><q>The Lady Wistaria—she is your sister?</q></p>
                  <p><q>My cousin</q>, answered the other, briefly. </p>
                  <p><q>Will you tell me how it is possible for one unfortunately attached to an
                        unfriendly clan to pay court to your cousin?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Two questions, that!</q> exclaimed Toro, <pb n="31"/> promptly, whereat they
                     both laughed, their friendship growing in proportion to their good-humor.</p>
                  <p><q>Now</q>, said Toro, <q>I will answer whatever questions you may put to me,
                        if you in return will only satisfy my mind concerning certain matters which
                        I am perishing to know</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>A fair exchange! Good!</q></p>
                  <p><q>Then</q>, said Toro, unloosening his own cape from his hips, <q>pray throw
                        this about you, for I fear you will be observed by my father’s samurai. Even
                        my presence</q>, he added, with a sigh, <q>could hardly protect you, for I,
                        alas! am under age</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Is it possible?</q> said the stranger, with such affected surprise that the
                     boy flushed with delight.</p>
                  <p><q>Now, my lord</q>—he hesitated, doubtfully, as though hoping the other would
                     supply the name—<q>now, my lord, let me explain to you why I truly sympathize
                        with you in your love for one who must seem impossible</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Not impossible</q>, corrected the lover, softly, thinking tenderly of the
                     Lady Wistaria’s fears for him.</p>
                  <p><q>I, too</q>, confessed Toro, <q>am in the same plight</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>What!</q> cried the lover, in dismay; <q>you also adore the lady?</q></p>
                  <p><q>No</q>, replied Toro, shaking his head with sad melancholy; <q>but I have
                        conceived the <pb n="32"/>most hopeless attachment for a lady whom I may
                        never dream of winning</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Then I am much mistaken in you. I thought, my lord, that you were not only a
                        brave man, but a daring knight</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>But you cannot conceive of the extremity of my case</q>, cried the youth,
                     piteously, <q>for consider: the lady I love not only belongs to our rival clan,
                        but is already betrothed</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Well, but betrothals have been broken before, my lord, and the days of
                        romance and adventure are not altogether dead in the land</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Ah, yes, that is true, but my rival is not only more powerful, but in every
                        respect more prepossessing and attractive</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Indeed? Well, all this interests me very much. Still, I must say, my lord,
                        that though I am in the service of the Mori, I have not seen the knight or
                        courtier who could probe so formidable a rival to you, either in graces or
                        rank—for are you not the son of the great lord of this province?</q></p>
                  <p><q>And has not our neighboring lord a son also?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Wh—what!</q> cried the stranger, darting backward as though the youth had
                     dealt him a sharp and unexpected blow; then scanning the other’s face closely,
                        <q>You do not mean—the Prince--?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Yes—the Prince Keiki. That swaggering, bragging, noisy roustabout, who bears
                        so many cognomens</q>. </p>
                  <pb n="33"/>
                  <p><q>Hum!</q> said the other. <q>They call him the Prince Kei—, truly—</q>
                  </p>
                  <p><q>Yes</q>, said the youth, jealously, <q>and also ‘<foreign xml:lang="ja"
                           >Hikal – Keiki – no – Kimi</foreign>’ (the Shining Prince Keiki)</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>You have told me strange news indeed</q>, said the Mori courtier. <q>I did
                        not know of the betrothal of our Prince. It is very sad, truly</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Sad! To be betrothed to the Princess Hollyhock sad?</q></p>
                  <p><q>For you, my lord</q>, replied the other, with a slight smile.</p>
                  <p>Toro doubled his hands spasmodically as he frowned with the fierceness of a
                        <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, that the other might not observe
                     the soft moisture of a woman in his eyes.</p>
                  <p><q>Now let me tell you a secret</q>, said the stranger, touching his arm with
                     confidential sympathy. <q>Upon my word, the Princess Hollyhock is not betrothed
                        to the Prince Keiki</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>My lord, you do not say so! Are you sure?</q></p>
                  <p><q>As sure as I am that I am here now</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Oh, the gods themselves must have sent you hither!</q> cried the youth.
                        <q>Will you not accept my protection and constant aid in your suit for my
                        cousin?</q></p>
                  <p><q>You are more generous than—</q></p>
                  <p><q>Your Prince, you would say</q>, interrupted Toro, bitterly. </p>
                  <pb n="34"/>
                  <p><q>—than the gods, I was about to remark</q>, said the other, gravely. <q>Now
                        let us form a compact. You on your side with promise me protection and aid
                        here on your estates, and I will swear to you that you shall win and wed the
                        Princess Hollyhock</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>I have a small house yonder, my lord</q>, cried the impulsive youth,
                     excitedly. <q>It is kept by my old nurse. Come you with me thither. I shall
                        lend you whatever clothes you may require and you shall remain here as long
                        as you wish. I will introduce you to my family as a friend—a student from my
                        own university in Kummommotta. Then you can make suit to Wistaria, and,
                        having oce wed her, who can separate you, let me ask?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Not the gods themselves, I swear!</q> cried the other. </p>
                  <p><q>And your name—what shall I call you?</q></p>
                  <p>The courtier hesitated for the first time.</p>
                  <p><q>My name is insignificant. It is a Mori name, and therefore dangerous in your
                        province</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>You must assume another, then</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Hum! Well, what would you suggest, my lord?</q></p>
                  <p><q>How will Shioshio Shawtaro do?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Not at all. It has a trading sound</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Ho! ho! How about Taketomi Tokioshi?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Too imperious</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Fujita Gemba?</q></p>
                  <pb n="35"/>
                  <p><q>No, no</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Then do you choose yourself</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>My lord, waiving aside all our political differences, do you not think it
                        would be loyal for me to take the name of one of my own people?</q></p>
                  <p><q>What, a Mori name? you are very droll, my lord. Why not keep your own name,
                        then?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Ah, but it is not the Mori family name I wish to assume, but a
                     surname</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>It might be dangerous</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Oh, not without the family name and title attached. Suppose I take the name
                        of Keiki?</q></p>
                  <p><q>What! The name of my rival!</q></p>
                  <p><q>My prince, my lord</q>, said the other, bowing deeply. </p>
                  <p><q>Nevertheless my rival</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Not at all; and if he were so, why not grant him this little honor, seeing
                        you are to worst him in the suit for the lady?</q></p>
                  <p><q>That is true</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>The name will sound vastly different with another family name attached.
                        Suppose I assume the name of Tominaga Keiki? That is somewhat different from
                        Mori Keiki, is it not?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Somewhat</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Then Keiki is my name</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Kei— Very well. Let it be so</q>.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="36"/>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>V</head>
                  <p>The Lord of Catzu received his son’s friend with hospitality dictated by his
                     fat and good-humored nature, beseeching him to consider the Catzu possessions
                     as his own. Keiki (as he had called himself), on fire to make use of the
                     advantage he had now gained at the outset, was met by two unexpected
                     obstacles.</p>
                  <p>In the first place, the Lady Wistaria was hedged about by an almost
                     insurmountable wall of etiquette and form. Though the lover blessed all the
                     gods for the privilege of being in <pb n="37"/> her presence each day, yet,
                     impetuous, warm-blooded, and ardent, he could not but chafe at the distance and
                     the silence which seemed impassable between them. </p>
                  <p>Wisteria, he thought, might just as well have been a twinkling star in the
                     heavens above him as to be placed at one end of the guest room, her lips sealed
                     in maidenly silence, while at the other end, in the place of honor, must sit
                     he, the august guest, inwardly the burning lover. Between them interposed her
                     honorable relatives and certain members of her uncle’s household, separating
                     the lovers with their extravagant politeness and words of gracious compliment
                     and hospitability. </p>
                  <p>In the second place, the pilot upon whom he had relied for safe conduct through
                     the icy forms which kept him from his mistress had deserted him perfidiously.
                     Toro, the reckless and foolhardy, his imagination fed by the daring and
                     sang-froid of the Mori clansman, his own heart aflame with as deep a passion as
                     his friend’s, had borrowed his dress and departed for Choshui, there to risk
                     all chance of danger with the bravery, but without, alas! the wit, of the Mori
                     courtier. </p>
                  <p>To offset these two hardships, the lovers saw a gift sent by the gods in the
                     indisposition of the Lady Evening Glory. After the long and tedious journey
                     from the capital, the lady, who was of a delicate constitution, retired to her
                     apartments with a malady of the <pb n="38"/>head and tooth. In point of fact,
                     the Lady Evening Glory suffered from neuralgia. The lovers prayed that her
                     illness might be long and lingering, though Wistaria, having besought her to
                     keep to her bed as long as possible that relapse might be avoided, tempered her
                     prayer with a petition to her favorite god that her aunt’s illness might be
                     unattended with pain.</p>
                  <p>With the Lady Evening Glory, the vigilant mentor of Wistaria, safely out of the
                     way, the girl found no cause for despair. This was the reason she returned her
                     lover’s pleading and ofttimes reproachful glances with smiles, which, but for
                     the joy of seeing them, he would have thought heartless. The joy of Wistaria’s
                     smile almost compensated for the pain of her lover’s poignant surmise that her
                     heart had no pity for the woes of her adorer. </p>
                  <p>And, indeed, at this time there was little else in the girl’s heart save a
                     singing joy, a rippling flutter of new emotions and thrills, which she, too
                     innocent as yet to recognize their full import, cared only to welcome with
                     delight, to encourage, to foster and enjoy to the uttermost.</p>
                  <p>Between Wistaria and her uncle there was utmost confidence and love. The young
                     girl occupied that place in his heart which would have been held by the
                     daughter denied him by the gods. The mantling flush, the ever-shining eyes, now
                     bright with joy that would <pb n="39"/> overflow, now moist with the unbidden
                     tears that spring to the eyes when the heart is disturbed with an emotion more
                     sweet than expression; these—the change which young love alone can produce in a
                     maiden—he was quick to perceive. </p>
                  <p>The Lord Catzu’s own marriage had been most romantic, and if his lady had lived
                     down frigidly to the world, her husband at least had retained his sentimental
                     remembrance of the adventurous escapades attending it. </p>
                  <p>Such were the opportunities of life to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                        >daimio</foreign> of a province at peace that, to all outward appearances,
                     Catzu was too indolent, too listlessly, luxuriously lazy and preoccupied with
                     his own pleasures to observe his niece’s condition of heart. But the Lord
                     Catzu, with all his placidity, was astute. Beneath his lazy eyelids his own
                     small eyes missed little that passed before him.</p>
                  <p>In fact, it was not long before he became aware of the attachment between the
                     young people. The courtier, he knew, bore an assumed name, for Toro had labored
                     with awkwardness when he endeavored to invent a lineage for the friend whose
                     appearance at the Catzu palace without the customary retinue of servants or
                     retainers had convinced its lord that he had discovered a tinge of that
                     delightful mystery which but added to the favor of the unknown in the eyes of
                     the sentimental Lord of Catzu. In addition, it was <pb n="40"/> the mode for
                     young nobles of the realm to undertake courtship over an assumed name, so that
                     an air of romance might be lento their love affair. As to the young man’s rank
                     there could be no question, since his manners and breeding, his grace of person
                     and charm of speech, were caste characteristic. Looking secretly with high
                     favor upon the young man, Caztu considered how he might aid the lovers. </p>
                  <p>Slothful and deliberate in all he undertook, Catzu might provoke impatience,
                     but his gradual accomplishment of his ends was gratifying. Just as he took his
                     time in the serious business of life, so was he leisurely in the pursuit of his
                     pleasures. As a consequence the lovers for a time were kept in an agony of
                     waiting and suspense.</p>
                  <p>Keiki, maddened and irritated by the constant presence of the smiling Lord
                     Catzu, who in his opinion stood between him and his heart’s desire, once more
                     fell to writing imploring letters and poems to the Lady Wistaria which made up
                     in epithets of endearment what they lacked in rhetoric. He prayed her to find
                     some means by which he might be with her alone, if only for a fraction of a
                     minute. The one word <q>Patience</q>, written upon a little china plate, so
                     minutely that he could scarcely decipher it, was the reply brought by the Lord
                     Catzu, with the information that the Lady Wistaria her-<pb n="41"/>self had
                     painted the plate for their august guest.</p>
                  <p>Meanwhile Catzu, cognizant of every sigh, every appealing expression, every
                     significant motion, laid his plans carefully for the impatient suitor’s
                     happiness. Certainly within the walls of the palace itself there was no hope of
                     solitude for the lovers. Pretexts for out-door pleasure-parties were never
                     wanting in the warmer season. Local fêtes, the birth of each new flower, family
                     events—all these were sufficient invitation in themselves for such convivial
                     parties as delighted the soul of the lord of Catzu, and could not have failed
                     in their chance opportunity for dual solitude.</p>
                  <p>At this time of the year, alas! there was neither snow nor moon nor flowers to
                     serve a pretext. A series of heavy rainfalls, most distressing and persistent,
                     was the only fugitive before approaching spring. Yet even the rain-gods have a
                     limit to their tears, and, after all, the rains preceding the first month of
                     spring are ofttimes the very means by which the land is cleansed ere it bursts
                     into beauty and bud.</p>
                  <p>Not so interminable as it seemed to them was the lovers’ waiting. Three short
                     days—yet how long!—and then the sun which had struggled for ascendency over the
                     troubled heavens rose up proudly triumphant. The thunders retreated into
                     tremulous growls of defeat; the gray-black clouds rolled away <pb n="42"
                     />before the blinding flashes of the sun-rays, flitting like ghosts before the
                     dawn. An immense rainbow, spanning the entire heavens, sprang out of the skies,
                     a signal of the sun-god’s victory. </p>
                  <p>What mattered it that the land was barren as yet of flowers? The grass was
                     green and the trees almost bursting in effort of emulation. Catzu, having
                     satisfied himself that the moisture on the grass was but the dew of spring,
                     forthwith devised a small party. it consisted of his lady niece and the august
                     guest of the household, who was graciously entreated to accompany them, and who
                     accepted with an alacrity almost lacking courtesy. </p>
                  <p>With but two attendants, the party set out from the palace. Taking a small
                     boat, they made a swift pilgrimage up the graceful river to a small island
                     where a picturesque tea-house and gardens, with twenty charming <foreign
                        xml:lang="ja">geishas</foreign>, made a fairyland for lovers. </p>
                  <p>To receive so early and unheralded a visit from the august lord of the province
                     threw the <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign> into a delighted panic of
                     excitement. Their attendants were seen rushing hither and thither throughout
                     the place, hastily making it suitable for the reception of the exalted
                     guests.</p>
                  <p>Hastening down to the beach, the chief <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign> herself apologized for the
                     island’s condition. The Lord of Catzu went to meet her. For his guest to be
                     received without <pb n="43"/>preparation, he explained to Keiki, would be
                     unfitting. Consequently he begged him to remain on the beach, while he himself
                     proceeded with the chief <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign> to the tea-house to issue instruction. </p>
                  <p>The stolid and indifferent lackeys who had attended the party returned to the
                     boat, where they fell into conversation with the oarsmen. </p>
                  <p>At last the lovers were alone.</p>
                  <p>For a long moment Keiki and Wistaria looked into each other’s eyes. They were
                     safe from all observation, for the gardens, and indeed the whole island, was of
                     that rock-and-pebble-built variety favored by the Japanese. Behind and around
                     them they were screened by quaint, grotesque rocks of natural form and immense
                     size, carried from a mountain to this tiny island, placed there in miniature to
                     simulate nature.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheless Keiki, the impatient and ardent, now at the crucial moment, had
                     naught to say. He had confessed his love in his letters; she had admitted
                     tacitly her own. Still they did not embrace, or even touch each other. Culture
                     is strong in Japan, where also is the fire of love. So these two but looked
                     into each other’s faces, all their hearts’ eloquent passion in their eyes.
                     Wistaria’s eyes did not fall before his tender gaze. Only a rose-red flush
                     crept softly like a magic glow over the oval of her cheeks, tingeing <pb n="44"
                     />her little chin while accentuating her brow’s whiteness.</p>
                  <p>Without a word her lover dropped upon one knee, lifted the long sleeve of her
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">kimono</foreign>, and buried his face within its fabric. </p>
                  <p>Five minutes later, hand in hand, they were standing on the same spot. They
                     were watching the river, swollen by recent rains, as it burst over the rocks
                     beyond, bounding down the river-bed, rolling swiftly along, twisting, curving,
                     and winding about the sinuous form of the island’s shore, holding it in the
                     grudging love of the water for the land. The water was blue-green in color,
                     save where the sunbeams reflected its own light in glistening gleams of
                     quicksilver, ever moving, ever playing, while the shores on either side threw
                     shadows of their trees and rocks upon it. As it ran busily, merrily along, now
                     and then lapping the shore and leaping to their very feet, it seemed a living
                     thing which babbled and laughed with an inward knowledge of their joy, and also
                     sighed and wailed with a prophetic undercurrent of coming woe.</p>
                  <p>The touch of their hands close clasped together made them tremble and quiver.
                     Their eyes met to droop away and meet again in the vivid recognition of their
                     own innocent happiness. They could not speak, because their hearts had laid
                     claim to their lips and sealed them in a golden silence. </p>
                  <pb n="45"/>
          
               <p>Then, after a long interval, Keiki found his voice. If he spoke of the flowing
                  river at their feet, it was not the river itself that absorbed his mind, but
                  because in it, as in all things beautiful in life, he now saw reflected the image
                  of his beloved.</p>
               <p><q>The honorable river</q>, he said, <q>flow high at this season, but before the summer
                  dies it will be but a thin line, very still, very quiet</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Yes</q>, said Wistaria, tremulously, <q>but the lotus will spring up in its honorable
                  waters, and if the river should continue to rise and rush onward like this, I fear
                  me the water-flowers would perish and the noise of its ceaseless flow would drown
                  the voices of the birds, which make the summer speak</q>.</p>
               <p><q>That is true</q>, said Keiki, <q>but when the summer passes then the flowers must
                  still die, and we may no longer hear the singing of the birds. Then still the
                  river will be silent and motionless—perhaps dead</q>.</p>
               <p>Keiki signed with the moodiness of love attained. A gentle depression stole from
                  him to the Lady Wistaria.</p>
               <p><q>Alas! my lord</q>, she murmured; <q>it is so with all things in life that are
                  beautiful. They vanish and die like the flowers of summer</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Then</q>, said Keiki, <q>swear by the god of the sea, by whose waters we now stand,
                  that our love shall never die, and that for the time of this life, and the next,
                  and as <pb n="46"/>many after as may come, you will be my flower wife, and take me for
                  your husband</q>.</p>
               <p><q>By all the eight million gods of heaven, and by the god of the sea, I swear</q>,
                  said Wistaria. </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="47"/>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>VI</head>
                  <p>The air was balmy, the sky of a cerulean blue, the Dewdrop gardens were sweet
                     with a strange charm and mystery all their own. Pebbles, sand, and stone, were
                     cunningly displayed and mingled to create the illusion of an approach to a
                     giant sea. In themselves the wonderous rocks were so fashioned as to form a
                     landscape wherein neither foliage, trees, nor flowers were necessary. Small,
                     grotesque bridges, made of rare rocks in their natural form, undefeated by
                     hammer or chisel, spanned the miniature <pb n="48"/> 
                  rivers, which, snakelike, crept and threaded their way in and out of the rock
                     island. Suddenly appearing caverns yawed wide agape, only to show on closer
                     approach that they were naught but gigantic rocks, hollow within. </p>
                  <p>Though the gardens were bare of foliage, yet the spot shone out like a jewel
                     set in a magic river. Here was the perfection of art, that art so complete that
                     without the very things of nature which seem necessary to a landscape, the
                     cunning hand of man had fashioned the like out of the hard and jagged substance
                     of stone and rock. And in this the hand of the Creator had aided, since the
                     very rocks which formed this precious and priceless island, the pride and
                     wealth of the lord of Catzu, had been untouched by the tool of the artisan,
                     for, having been gathered together from all parts of the country, they were
                     planted in their natural form upon this island jewel.</p>
                  <p>Across the narrow river the shores were green, while beyond the silent surface
                     of the moats the granite walls of the Catzu palace rose to a height, white and
                     stately, tipped with golden towers and peaks that were taller than the cedars
                     and the pines centuries old. </p>
                  <p>A stir of expectation thrilled the Dewdrop tea-house, and then a clear, shrill
                     voice cried aloud:</p>
                  <p><q>The Lady Wistaria passes into the honorable hall</q>.</p>
                 <pb n="49"/>
                  <p>The twenty <foreign xml:lang="ja">geishas</foreign> prostrated themselves at my lady’s feet. Gracefully she
                     returned their courtesy, begging that they would serve her and her august
                     guest, the Lord Tominaga Keiki, with refreshment.</p>
                  <p>The <foreign xml:lang="ja">geishas</foreign>, at this period in history occupying a high and dignified position
                     in society, expressed their wish to serve their lady for the rest of their
                     lives.</p>
                  <p>They brough the lovers fresh fruit, shining and luscious, and drink from a well
                     of sweetest and purest water. Humbly apologizing for the honorable meanness of
                     the refreshment, the chief <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign> prayed that they would condescend to pardon
                     her, for not even in her dreams had she imagined that the gods would favor her
                     so soon in the season with such august guests.</p>
                  <p>But the lovers only smiled benevolently upon her, and insisted that never, no,
                     never in all the honorable days of their lives, had they been blessed with more
                     gracious refreshment. Whereat the <foreign xml:lang="ja">geisha</foreign>, with many low, grateful obeisances,
                     retired. </p>
                  <p>The lovers signed as in one breath.</p>
                  <p><q>Once more alone</q>, said Keiki, blissfully reaching over the little table
                     and laying his own hands softly upon those of the girl. <q>How gracious the
                        gods!</q></p>
                  <p><q>Of a truth</q>, said Wistaria, smiling up at him; <q>we must repay the
                        gods</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>We must, indeed. What shall we do? <pb n="50"/> Build a thousand temples
                        to—well, which one?</q></p>
                  <p><q>I consider!</q> quoth Wistaria, thinking very seriously. Then, suddenly,
                     with a little, silvery laugh: <q>I have it. Let us deify my own august uncle.
                        Is he not the god who befriends us?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Not consciously</q>, said Keiki, <q>for I doubt not my Lord of Catzu would
                        fume and curse me roundly did he know I took advantage of his honorable
                        disposition to sleep</q>.</p>
                  <p>Wistaria laughed softly.</p>
                  <p><q>Now I am quite ready to swear</q>, she said, <q>that of late my honorable
                        uncle is perfectly conscious when he sleeps</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Pray tell me</q>, cried Keiki, starting.</p>
                  <p>The girl nodded merrily.</p>
                  <p><q>Will you tell me, then, how it is possible for one to fall asleep in a
                        small, rocking boat? Could you or I do so, my Lord Keiki?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Oh, not you or I; but your honorable uncle is divinely lethargic</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Then, my lord, he is but lately afflicted</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>But I do not understand, then—you cannot mean—Oh no, it could hardly be
                        so!</q></p>
                  <p><q>And why not, my lord? To me it seems that even the gods must needs favor
                        you, much more than an honorable mortal</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Your uncle favor me! It cannot be possible</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>It is possible. It is so</q>.</p>
                  <pb n="51"/>
                  <p><q>But he has been acquainted with me only for the past six days</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>And does it take a year for favor to grow, when love—</q>
                  </p>
                  <p><q>Awakens in a day—an hour</q>, finished Keiki, rapturously. <q>No, I can see
                        how it is possible, but I could not at once realize my good-fortune.
                        Moreover—</q></p>
                  <p>Suddenly he broke off as a melancholy shadow crept across his brow, troubling
                     his eyes. In a sudden depression he bent forward.</p>
                  <p><q>My lord is trouble? Speak to me quickly</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Troubled? Yes, that is so</q>, Keiki sighed.</p>
                  <p><q>Then do, I pray you, speak your trouble to me</q>, said Wistaria.
                     Immediately she threw herself at his feet, resting her hands upon his knees and
                     raising her face upward to his. Keiki took her face in his hands. He looked
                     deep into her love-lit eyes.</p>
                  <p><q>Yes, I will tell you, little Wistaria</q>, he said, <q>though I fear you are
                        already acquainted with my secret</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>I am not, indeed</q>, she denied.</p>
                  <p><q>You do not know</q>, he asked, sadly, <q>that I am of the Mori clan?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Of the Mori clan! And is that all that troubles you, my lord?</q></p>
                  <p><q>And is not that sufficiently serious?</q></p>
                  <p><q>No</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>But surely you must be aware of the feud existing between the Mori and Catzu
                        clans?</q></p>
                  <pb n="52"/>
                  <p><q>My lord, you and I do not constitute the Mori and Catzu clans</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>You and I</q>, he repeated, slowly, <q>do not constitute the Mori and Catzu
                        clans</q>. Then, after a silent moment: <q>Alas, my lady, I fear we
                     do!</q></p>
                  <p>Wisteria snatched her hands quickly from his and arose. Certainly he could not
                     love her, she thought, if he allowed so small a thing as that to distress
                     him.</p>
                  <p><q>If that be so—if that is what you think, my lord, deign to inform me why you
                        have condescended to make suit to me?</q></p>
                  <p><q>I was forced to make my suit in secret</q>, he said, almost bitterly.</p>
                  <p><q>But your love is honest, is it not?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Oh, my glower-girl, can you ask that?</q></p>
                  <p>She was contrite in a moment. Once more she was at his feet, kneeling, and
                     pressing both his hands with her little, slender, nervous fingers.</p>
                  <p><q>Nay, then, do no look so sad, my Keiki. It troubles me that you should allow
                        so silly a thing as the differences of our respective clans even for a
                        fraction of a moment to come between us</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>They cannot truly come between us</q>, was his fervid reply, <q>for no power
                        on earth can actually separate us now. are we not sworn to each other for
                        all time—for all eternity?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Then why be so sad? You, who are so <pb n="53"/>brave, cannot fear the dangers
                        that may beset our union</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>No, no, it is not that. But—I sigh for the tears of others—our honorable
                        ancestors and parents</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Then do cease to sign at once, if you please. Why, it is not such a terrible
                     crime to marry a Mori, surely!</q></p>
                  <p><q>No, I hope not</q>, said Keiki, smiling now. </p>
                  <p><q>No, indeed, for my own honorable uncle committed that same fault</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Fault?</q></p>
                  <p><q>And I believe that if we were to go to him, and tell him the honorable
                        truth, he would gladly assist us</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Not if he knew all</q>, said Keiki, sadly. <q>No, he must know nothing
                        yet</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Indeed</q>, said Wistaria, <q>I did not know the feeling of the mori was so
                        bitter against us, and I do assure you that in Catzu the prejudice exists
                        not so much against your clan, as against your lord and prince</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Alas, that is too true!</q> answered Keiki, half under his breath.</p>
                  <p><q>Well, a courtier’s loyalty to his Prince need not at all be shaken if he
                        marry the insignificant niece of a rival clan, my own honorable father was
                        of that very clan himself. Know you not that, my lord?</q></p>
                  <p>Keiki groaned suddenly. Whereat the girl placed her hands on his shoulders and
                     forced him to look into her eyes. </p>
                <pb n="54"/>
            
              
                  <p><q>My lord</q>, she said, <q>do you know aught of my father’s history?</q></p>
                  <p>Slowly Keiki drew himself up from her clinging hands. Placing one arm close
                     about her, he drew her to his breast.</p>
                  <p><q>Let us no longer talk of these distressful matters</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Nay, I have asked you a question. Do, I beseech you, answer me</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>What can I say?</q> His voice was very low.</p>
                  <p><q>Tell me of my father—pray tell me</q>, she implored, almost piteously.</p>
                  <p><q>Of your father? But surely I can tell you nothing that you do not already
                        know?</q></p>
                  <p><q>I know naught of my father, save that he was a Choshui samurai, and for some
                        honorable offence was banished by that wicked and cruel Prince of
                     Mori</q>.</p>
                  <p>Keiki was silent.</p>
                  <p><q>I have questioned every one about me—my uncle, his samurai, the very
                        servants about the castle—but none will make answer to me, whether from
                        ignorance or by command of those in authority over them, I know not. Do you,
                        then, my lover, answer me</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>My little flower-girl, I do not know the offence of your honorable father,
                        nor do I know why or wherefore he was sent into exile. I was but a child of
                        five when this penalty came upon him</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Then wherefore di you tremble and turn <pb n="55"/>away your eyes when I spoke
                        of my honorable parent?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Because I know that injury of some sort was wrought against your honorable
                        parent by my—by the Mori, and since then so implacable an enmity exists
                        between our families that nothing but blood alone can ever wipe away the
                        stain. Think, then, of the wrong I do your father in loving his own
                        daughter!</q></p>
                  <p><q>No, no—dear Keiki—it is no wrong, I do assure you. If there be a feud
                        existing between my father and the Mori Prince, truly you and I, who are
                        innocent, cannot be implicated in any way, and, indeed, it is not as if I
                        were about to wed one of the Mori family itself, but—</q></p>
                  <p><q>In that case</q>, he interrupted, quickly, <q>if I were indeed of this Mori
                        family, what then?</q></p>
                  <p>For a moment the girl recoiled, shrinking backward, and regarded him with
                     frightened, shocked eves.</p>
                  <p><q>That—would—be—impossible</q>, she said, and she shivered with
                     apprehension.</p>
                  <p><q>If it were possible?</q> said the lover, hoarsely.</p>
                  <p><q>It could not be</q>, she insisted, <q>for the Mori princes are proud and
                        ill-favored, while you—</q></p>
                  <p><q>While I?</q></p>
                  <p><q>—You are more beautiful than the sun-god</q>.</p>
                  
                  
                  <pb n="56"/>
                  <p><q>But you have not answered me. Suppose it were—Prince Keiki, the heir of
                        Mori, who wooed you?</q></p>
                  <p><q>I cannot, my lord. Oh, the Prince is otherwise occupied than in wandering
                        with love</q>, replied Wistaria, smiling at the thought. <q>Why, he is the
                        head of a wicked party of Imperialists, I have ofttimes heard my uncle
                        declare, and is the most cunning and base fermenter of intrigue against our
                        august Shogun in the whole empire. Indeed, he has no time or inclination for
                        dallying with love</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>But—if I were indeed he, what then?</q></p>
                  <p><q>Why, then—then</q>, said the girl, slowly rising, and regarding him with
                     shining eyes, <q>then still I would say, ‘Take me.’ What have we to do with the
                        quarrels of our ancestors, the wrongs or the rights of our honorable
                        parents? You and I are under the sheltering wings of the god of love. We
                        recognize no law of country, lord, or kindred. Let us go into the mountains
                        together and find refuge in a cottage where we can live and love in
                        peace</q>.</p>
                  <p><q>Oh, thou dear one!</q> he cried.</p>
                  <p><q>But why suggest such a horrible possibility?</q> she continued, tremulously.
                        <q>Thou art not that base and traitorous Prince? Thou art—</q></p>
                  <p><q>Thy love! That is all</q>, he said.</p>
                 
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
