<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WooingOfWistaria14">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Wooing of Wistaria</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:197"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovel"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" when="2020-08-17" status="inProgress">Begin transcribing and proofreading</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-06-14" status="empty">Changed id from WooingOfWistaria12 to WooingOfWistaria14.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-08-23">Added facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl197 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <head>The Wooing of Wistaria</head>
        
         <head type="subtitle">A Love Story of Japan</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>     
         </opener>
         <div type="content">
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>When after a life that had never lacked variety the Lady Wistaria came to the
                  years of <choice>
                     <sic>tranquillity</sic>
                     <corr>tranquility</corr>
                  </choice>, she was wont to say, with the philosophy that follows dangerous times:
                     <q>No one, man or maid, ever really began to live before the time to which the
                     first memory reverts</q>.</p>
               <p>The first recollection of the Lady Wistaria goes back to an earlier childhood than
                  that of most mortals. This she ascribed to its terrible and awful import. She
                  could scarcely do more than move with the uncertain direction of babyhood, when<pb
                     n="2"/>her father, always now in her memory as gaunt, lean, haggard, tall, had
                  taken her upon a long journey. They had travelled partly by <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >kurumaya</foreign>, and, towards the end, on foot. That is, her father had
                  walked, carry8ing her on high in his arms. </p>
               <p>When they halted at Yedo they stood amid a vast concourse of people, who remained
                  silent and respectful against the background of the buildings, while in the centre
                  of the road marched steadily and pompously a great glittering pageant.</p>
               <p>Wisteria had clapped her hands with glee and delight at the mass of color, the
                  glimmer of shield and breastplate, the prancing, snorting horses. But her father
                  suddenly had raised an enormous hand and in a moment had stopped her delight.
                  Wisteria lapsed into an acute silence.</p>
               <p>Instantly she was awakened from her painful apathy by her father, who moved her
                  higher in his arms, and turned her head slowly about with one hand, while with the
                  other he pointed to a shining personage reclining in a palanquin borne high on the
                  shoulders of ten stout-legged attendants.</p>
               <p><q>My daughter</q>, said her father’s hollow voice in her ear, <q>yonder rides the
                     man who killed your mother. It is through his crime that you are orphaned and
                     have no mother to care for you and love you. Look at him well! Hush! Do not
                     weep or shake with <pb n="3"/>fear, but turn your eyes upon him. Look at him!
                     Look! Look! Yonder rides your mother’s murderer. Do not forget his face as long
                     as you live. It is your duty to remember it!</q></p>
               <p>Whereupon Wistaria, who, in obedience to her father’s commands, had stared with
                  wide eyes fixedly at the reclining noble, set up a most extraordinary cry. It was
                  unlike that of a little child—a wild, wailing shriek, so weird and piteous that
                  the bystanders started in horror and fear. The noble raised himself lazily on his
                  elbow, starting across the heads of all, until his eyes rested upon the man with
                  the child held on high. He fell back with an uneasy shrug of the shoulders. </p>
               <p>That was the Lady Wistaria’s oldest memory. There were others, but none so vivid
                  as this, the first of all. Even later, when she had ceased to be a child, she had
                  been unable to pierce the mystery of her father’s life, or indeed her own.</p>
               <p> One half of her earlier years had been spent in a small, whitewashed cottage,
                  built on the crest of a little wind-blown hill, far enough removed from the
                  dwellings in the village below to be entirely cut off from them.</p>
               <p>There was a touch of the uncanny and weird about the little village, whose slender
                  streets, ascending and descending, zigzagging up and down, disappeared among
                  hillocks <pb n="4"/> and bluffs, though built in reality in the hollow outskirts
                  of a flourishing city at the foot of a small chain of mountains. Through the land
                  here was green and beautiful at all times of the year, there came no one from the
                  great city beyond to this solitary settlement, whose inhabitants bore the impress
                  of toil, pain, and oppression.</p>
               <p>Why her father, who, she had been told, was of noble blood, resided here on this
                  hilltop, isolated even from the strange people who dwelt in the silent village
                  below, the Lady Wistaria had never learned. When she had questioned her uncle and
                  aunt, she had been frigidly informed that curiosity and inquisitiveness were
                  degrading traits, which a maiden should strive with all her strength to overcome.
                  Neither did she ask her father, who, taciturn and cold during her brief residence
                  each year in his house, gave her no opportunity for winning his confidence. His
                  love Wistaria had never dreamed of possessing. </p>
               <p>Nevertheless, whenever she went to her father’s house, a wistful longing and
                  yearning for him possessed her whole being, and when she departed she would hide
                  her face in her sleeve, weeping silently, not knowing why she should weep, and
                  scarcely conscious of the fact that she wept for lack of her father’s love.</p>
               <p> In her father’s house there were no servants, <pb n="5"/> no maids, no
                  attendants—only one weazened, blind, and infinitely old woman, who wept tears from
                  her sightless eyes upon her arrival, who sang and crooned to her at night in a
                  sobbing, sighing voice, that was as sweet and pure as a girl’s.</p>
               <p>She addressed the old woman as <q>Madame Mume</q>, and preserved always towards
                  her the reserved and dignified attitude of the mistress to the maid. Yet her
                  father addressed her as <q>Mother</q>. Wisteria knew the old woman was not his
                  mother, and she could not believe she was even akin to them; for had she not
                  always been taught that the family from which she was descended was one of the
                  oldest and noblest in Japan, while old Madame Mume, though gentle and good, wore
                  the garb of the poor <foreign xml:lang="ja">heimin</foreign>.</p>
               <p> The other half of her childhood had been spent at the home of her uncle. Here
                  were countless retainers and servants, besides a host of <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samurai</foreign>, petty vassals, soldiers, peasants, and citizens, who lived
                  upon his land and owed their direct allegiance to him. </p>
               <p> The garden walls surrounding her uncle’s palace were tall and of massive
                  structure, built of solid stone. Its gates were guarded by handsome, bold <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> clad in thick armor. The steel upon their
                  breasts and shoulders glistened with a sinister sheen, and beneath their blazing
                  helmets fierce eyes burned out their unswerving allegiance and <pb n="6"/> loyalty
                  to their lord and their scorn and defiance of all his enemies. Their coats, all
                  emblazoned and embroidered with golden dragons, bore two crests, that of the
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> Iyesada, and that of the powerful
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> under whom they served, the Lord of
                  Catzu, uncle of the Lady Wistaria. </p>
               <p> Here in her uncle’s palace, Wistaria was watched over, cared for, nurtured, and
                  refined. Lackeys and servants were about her on all sides, ready to spring to her
                  service. As a child she had attended a private school, kept by an old <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, where with half a dozen other little girls she
                  had squatted on small, padded mats before writing-tables but twelve inches high,
                  and had been taught the intricacies of the language. Two gorgeously liveried
                  attendants always accompanied her to and from the school-house, carrying her
                  books, her writing-box, her keeling-cushion, and her little table. </p>
               <p>When she grew older she attended the elementary school. After she had left this, a
                  silent woman of perfect manners and exquisite appearance had come to her uncle’s
                  palace and attached herself entirely to her. With the coming of this governess,
                  wisteria ceased to pay her annual visits to her father’s house. He himself came to
                  the palace instead, once every year. Upon these occasions Wistaria was brought
                  into his presence. He would put a few stern questions to her <pb n="7"/>
                  concerning her knowledge of her duty to her parents, to which Wistaria would
                  respond with expressions of filial submission to his will in all things.</p>
               <p>From the governess, Wistaria learned the elegancies of conversation and how to act
                  on meeting great personages at court. She had even been drilled in certain graces
                  which should not fail to enchain her lover, when he, the proper one, should be
                  chosen for her. </p>
               <p>Now that she had reached the age of fifteen years, this perfect person had
                  departed from the palace to teach maidens of younger years. The Lady Wistaria had
                  arrived at an age when she could be said to have been graduated from her
                  governess’s hands as competent to pass the rest of her life without further
                  instruction, save that constant restraint exercised over her by her aunt, the Lady
                  Evening Glory of Catzu.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>II</head>
               <p>The education of a Japanese maid is not alone a matter of cultivating the mind; it
                  is an actual <choice>
                     <sic>moulding</sic>
                     <corr>molding</corr>
                  </choice> of her whole character. The average girl under such discipline succumbs
                  to the hereditary instinct of implicit obedience to her dictators, and becomes
                  like unto their conception of what she would be. But the Lady Wistaria was not an
                  average girl. That is the reason her appearance at the court of the <foreign
                     xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> in Yedo created a <choice>
                     <sic>furore</sic>
                     <corr>furor</corr>
                  </choice>. Her fresh, young beauty, her grace and bewitch-<pb n="9"/>ing charm,
                  were a revelation to the jaded court.</p>
               <p>The Lady Evening Glory, who had spent years of thought and preparation for this
                  event, had warned her repeatedly that upon such an auspicious occasion she was to
                  tread across the vast hall with downcast eyes and an attitude of graceful
                  humility. She was on no account to look about her. While all eyes might gaze upon
                  her, she must see no one. And this is how the Lady Wistaria carried out her
                  instructions.</p>
               <p>When first she began the slow parade towards the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shogun</foreign>’s throne, my lady’s head was drooped in the correct pose,
                  with her eyes modestly downcast. She had proceeded but a few paces, however, when
                  she was thrilled by the intuition that the spectacle was worthy of any sacrifice
                  necessary to see it. Her small head began to erect itself. Her eyes, wide open,
                  with one great sweep viewed the splendor of the picture—the graceful courtiers,
                  the lovely women in their costumes of the sun. A sharp pinch upon the arm brought
                  her back to the exacting presence of the Lady Evening Glory beside her. Down
                  drooped her head again. Gradually the eyelids fluttered. My lady peeped!</p>
               <p>There was a low murmur throughout the hall. The waving of fans ceased a space. The
                  Lady Evening Glory recognizsed the significance of that murmur, and then the <pb
                     n="10"/> hush that ensued. A tremendous fluttering pride arose in her bosom.
                  Her experience of many years assured her that her niece’s beauty was compelling
                  its splendid tribute.</p>
               <p>Then the Lady Wistaria was presented to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shogun</foreign>. Her prostration was made with inimitable grace. Her beauty
                  and charm called forth words of praise from the Shogun himself to her uncle.</p>
               <p>A young noble, more daring and ardent than all the others, separated himself from
                  the assembled company, and, crossing to where the Lady Wistaria stood, kissed a
                  hyacinth and dropped it at the girl’s feet.</p>
               <p>The Lady Evening Glory could have shrieked aloud with fury at the action of her
                  niece, due solely to her innocence. She had no thought whence it had come. A
                  flower in her path was not something she could tread upon, or even pass by. There
                  in the centre of the gorgeous hall she stooped tenderly and picked up the pleading
                  flower.</p>
               <p><q>Wild girl!</q> cried her aunt, in a suffocating whisper.</p>
               <p> Wisteria started with a little cry of genuine dismay. She had forgotten in one
                  moment the instruction of years. In her confusion she stopped short in her
                  progress across the hall. As if impelled by some great subtle force within her,
                  helplessly the Lady Wistaria raised her eyes. They gazed immediately into the
                  depths of another pair, afire with an <pb n="11"/> awakening passion. The next
                  moment the young girl had blushed, red as the tints a masterful sun throws to
                  coquetting clouds at sunset. </p>
               <p>All the journey through, to their temporary palace in Yedo, her aunt abused the
                  Lady Wistaria. The training of years wasted! Ingratitude was the basest of crimes!
                  Was this the way she repaid her aunt’s labor and kindness? Well, back to Catzu
                  they should go. It would be unsafe to remain longer in the capital. Certainly her
                  niece had much to learn before she could continue in Yedo longer than a day.</p>
               <p>The Lady Wistaria sat back in her palanquin, pouting. What, to be taken from the
                  gay capital one day after arriving—before she had had the chance to meet or even
                  speak to any one! Oh! it was cruel, and she the most stupid of maidens not to have
                  comported herself correctly at her presentation! </p>
               <p><q>Dearest, my lady aunt</q>, said she, <q>pray you, do let us continue in the
                     capital for the season</q>.</p>
               <p><q>What! And be laughed at by the whole court for our shocking and magnificently
                     bad manners? People will declare that you have been reared in the fields with
                     the peasants</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Do not, I beg, blame me for an accident, dear, my honorable aunt. It was not,
                     in truth, my own fault</q>.</p>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p><q>Indeed!</q></p>
               <p><q>Indeed, I do assure you it was the fault of that honorably silly
                  flower</q>.</p>
               <p><q>TSHH!</q></p>
               <p><q>And of that magnificent and augustly handsome courtier who dropped it</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Dropped it! My lady niece, I saw the impudent fellow throw it at your
                  feet!</q></p>
               <p><q>What! You saw! Oh, my aunt, then it is you who are jointly guilty with
                  me!</q></p>
               <p><q>What is that?</q> cried the aunt, angrily.</p>
               <p><q>Why, my lady, your honorable eyes were improper also</q>.</p>
               <p>The Lady Evening Glory turned an offended shoulder.</p>
               <p><q>We will start to-morrow for home</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, my lady!</q></p>
               <p><q>I have spoken</q>.</p>
               <p><q>But, dear aunt—</q>
               </p>
               <p><q>Will you condescend to tell me, girl, who is guarding, thou or I?</q></p>
               <p>With the Lady Evening Glory, <q>thou</q> was the end of discussion.</p>
               <p>The following day, therefore, the returning cortège set out for Catzu. As fortune
                  would have it, the Lady Evening Glory travelled in her own train, while her niece
                  had also her personal retinue about her. Consequently the journey was joyous for
                  the Lady Wistaria.</p>
               <p>When first the cortège began to move through the city a strange little procession
                  followed in its wake. It was made up of the love-<pb n="13"/> sick suitors, who,
                  having but once gazed upon the beauty of the Lady Wistaria, wished to serve and
                  follow her to the end of the world. The following was quite large when the cortège
                  started. A number dropped off as they reached the city limits, then gradually the
                  hopeless and disappointed swains with drooping heads turned back to Yedo, there to
                  dream of the vision of a day, but to dream hopelessly. </p>
               <p>Wherever the Lady Wistaria’s personal train travelled there lay scattered upon the
                  ground, and blowing in the air above and about her, tiny bits of white or
                  delicately tinted and perfumed paper. They were, alas! The love-letters and poems
                  penned by the ardent lovers, which the hard-hearted lady, tearing into
                  infinitesimal bits, had saucily tossed to the winds. It was thus she tossed their
                  love from her, she would have them believe. </p>
               <p>Hopeless, and finally indignant, therefore, backward turned these erstwhile
                  hopeful suitors. </p>
               <p>Sir Genji, the big <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, who had especial
                  charge of Wistaria’s train, reported to her, with a smile of satisfaction, that
                  she would suffer no further annoyance, as all save one of her suitors had finally
                  retreated. </p>
               <p><q>Bring closer your honorable head</q>, said the lady to Genji, who strode beside
                  her <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimono</foreign>, ever and anon ordering and,
                  scolding the runners.</p>
               <p>He brought his ear closer to the girl’s lips.<pb n="14"/> She leaned over and
                  whispered, while a pale pink flush came, fled, and grew and deepened again in her
                  face.</p>
               <p><q>Tell me</q>, said she, <q>which of the honorably bold and silly cavaliers is it
                     that remains?</q></p>
               <p><q>The one, my lady, who, not content with despatching his love-letters and tokens
                     to you by underlings, has had the august impertinence to deliver them himself
                     in person</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Yes—ye-es—of course</q>, said Wistaria, blushing deliciously, <q>and that was
                     honorably right. Fo you not think so, my brave Genji?</q></p>
               <p><q>Perhaps</q>, admitted the astute <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>,
                  frowning at the same time upon a portion of the parade belonging to the Lady
                  Evening Glory. Wisteria laughed with infinite relish. </p>
               <p><q>Well</q>, she said, <q>if my honorable aunt or august uncle were to learn of
                     his boldness, I fear me they would command that the curtains of my
                     insignificant <foreign xml:lang="ja">norimon</foreign> be drawn so tightly that
                     I should surely suffocate</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Fear not</q>, said Genji, <q>I shall take immediate measures to prevent such an
                     occurrence, my lady</q>.</p>
               <p>Wisteria pouted, and frowned as heavily as it is possible for bright eyes and rosy
                  lips to do. She toyed with her fan, opening and closing it several times.</p>
               <p><q>You are honorably over-zealous, Sir Genji</q>, she said. </p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p><q>My lady</q>, he replied, <q>know you aught of this stranger?</q></p>
               <p><q>He has a pretty grace</q>, said Wistaria, <q>and the bearing of one of noble
                     rank. Have you not noted, Sir Genji, the beauty and richness of his magnificent
                     attire?</q></p>
               <p><q>I have, my lady. It is of that attire I would speak</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Do so at once, then</q>.</p>
               <p><q>It is the attire, my lady, of the Mori family</q>.</p>
               <p><q>The Mori! What! Our honorably hostile neighbors?</q></p>
               <p><q>Exactly</q>, said Genji.</p>
               <p><q>Oh, dear!</q> murmured Wistaria, as she sank back in her cushions in troubled
                  thought. After a moment her little black head again appeared.</p>
               <p><q>Gen</q>, she cried, <q>come hither once more</q>.</p>
               <p><q>My lady?</q></p>
               <p><q>A little closer, if you please. So! Know you not, Sir Gen, that my lady aunt,
                     and indeed also my own august father, once served this odious Mori
                  prince?</q></p>
               <p><q>I have herd so, my lady</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Well, then, truly <emph>all</emph> of the members of this honorable clan cannot
                     be augustly bad!</q></p>
               <p>Sir Genji could not restrain a smile.</p>
               <p><q>Indeed, my lady, this Choshui people have many worthy and admirable
                     qualities</q>.</p>
               <p><q>You are a very clever fellow, my dear Sir Gen</q>, said Wistaria, smiling
                  engagingly <pb n="16"/>now, <q>and I shall bespeak you to my honorable uncle. And
                     now—now—if you would really wish to serve me, do you pray show some
                     kindness—some little insignificant courtesy to this unfortunate Mori courtier.
                     Perhaps he may have some good attributes</q>.</p>
               <p><q>Undoubtedly, my lady</q>.</p>
               <p><q>And do be careful to allow my lady aunt to know naught concerning him, for she,
                     having come from this Mori, is actually more sour against them than we, you and
                     I, Sir Gen, who have not indeed</q>.</p>
               <p>Just then my lady heard a familiar tramp to the left of her <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >norimono</foreign>. There were but few horses in the cortège, and most of them
                  had gone ahead with her father’s <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>.
                  Consequently the beat of a horse’s hoofs was plainly to be heard. The Lady
                  Wistaria wavered between lying back in her carriage and drawing about her
                  discreetly the curtains, or sitting up and feigning indifference to the horseman. </p>
               <p>The rider had fallen into a slow trot behind her <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >norimono</foreign>, and seemed to be making no effort either to overtake or
                  ride beside her. For the space of a few minutes the Lady Wistaria, with a bright,
                  expectant red spot in either cheek, waited for some sign on the part of the rider.
                  His stubborn continuance in the background at first thrilled, then irritated, and
                  finally distracted her. My lady put her shining little head out of the vehicle,<pb
                     n="17"/>then, leaning quite far out, she looked backward. Instantly the rider
                  spurred his horse forward. In a flash his hitherto melancholy face became luminous
                  with hope. A moment later he was beside the lady’s <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >norimono</foreign>. Before her officious maid had time to draw the curtains a
                  love-letter had fallen into my lady’s lap. </p>
               <p>It was possibly the fiftieth appeal he had penned to her. Hitherto he had born the
                  bitter chagrin of seeing the torn bits of paper fall from a little hand that
                  parted the silken curtains of her gilded norimono and scattered them to the
                  winds.</p>
               <p>The lover rode within sight of his mistress’s palanquin until the first gray
                  darkness of approaching night crept like an immense cloud over the heaven, chasing
                  away the enchanting rosy tints that the departing sun had left behind. </p>
               <p>Undaunted by the fact that his letter received no response, encouraged rather by
                  the fact that it had not shared the fate of its predecessors, the lover now set
                  himself to the task of composing more ardent and flowery epistles. What time was
                  not occupied in eagerly watching for the smallest glimpse of the little head to
                  appear was spent in writing to her. He wrote his love-letters and poems with a
                  shaking hand even while his horse carried him onward. He wrote them by the light
                  of the moon when the train halted<pb n="18"/>for the night. He wrote them in the
                  early dawn before the cortège had awakened. And he delivered them at all hours,
                  whenever he could obtain opportunity.</p>
               <p>Though the Lady Wistaria by this time must have acquired a goodly quantity of
                  useless literature, she took no measure to relieve herself of the burdensome
                  baggage. Nevertheless the lover began to despair. A few hours before they reached
                  her uncle’s province but into the very grounds surrounding his palace—into the
                  palace itself if necessary. He besought her that she would send him one small word
                  of favor.</p>
               <p>He waited in impatient excitement for a response to this last fervid appeal. He
                  felt sure she must at least deign to express her wish in the matter. But when they
                  reached the province he saw her carried across the borders without having given
                  him one sign or token.</p>
               <p>In his despair he dismounted, and was divided between returning to Yedo or
                  continuing his hopeless quest.</p>
               <p>As he remained plunged in his gloomy reflections and uncertainty of purpose, an
                  enormous <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> touched him sharply upon the
                  arm. In his irritation he was about to<pb n="19"/>resent the fellow’s familiarity,
                  when he perceived a little roll of rice-paper protruding from his sleeve.
                  Stealthily the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> reached out his arm to the
                  lover. The latter seized the scroll eagerly. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="20"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>III</head>
               <p>The palace, and indeed the whole domain of the Lord Catzu, presented the
                  appearance of being constantly armed as though for attack, a not uncommon thing in
                  the latter days of feudalism. The <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> had been
                  artful in his disposal of the various lords of the provinces. Families attached
                  personally to him were stationed in provinces lying between those administered by
                  families friendly to the Emperor. Thus none of the Emperor’s friends could meet to
                  revolt against the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>.</p>
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p>So it happened that while the Lord Catzu was one of the most intimate and
                  confidential of the advisers of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>, his
                  neighbor, the old Prince Mori, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> of the
                  province of Choshui, desired to see the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Mikado</foreign>
                  once more, the real, instead of the nominal, ruler of Japan.</p>
               <p>Consequently the two neighboring clans, while displaying extravagant courtesy
                  towards each other in public, were in reality unfriendly. Only during that portion
                  of the year when the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>’s edict ordered a
                  Yedo residence for all <foreign xml:lang="ja">daimios</foreign>, did the lords of
                  the provinces meet one another, and that under the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shogun</foreign>’s eyes in his Yedo seat of government. In the capital they
                  simulated suavity and cordiality, but once back at their provincial capitals they
                  preserved towards each other an attitude of polite defiance which made all
                  intercourse between them impossible save that of the sword, when their respective
                     <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> and vassals, coming in contact with
                  one another, fought out their lords’ political differences. </p>
               <p>Imbittering still more the feeling existing naturally between the Mori and Catzu
                  clans, there was a personal element in the situation. When Catzu had first been
                  made lord of the province he had met on a visit to the <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >Shogun</foreign>’s Yedo court the Lady Evening Glory, whose brother and
                  guardian (she being an orphan) was a young <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samurai</foreign> in the service of the <pb n="22"/> Prince Mori. Having
                  fallen a victim to the lady’s beauty and charms, the lord of Catzu was determined
                  to have her for wife despite the opposition of the Mori Prince. Bold, brave,
                  fearless, and with a grand contempt for the power of his rival, the Lord Catzu had
                  carried off the fair lady from his neighbor’s dominions, though it was generally
                  understood that both the lady herself and her <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >samurai</foreign> brought lent their assistance to the young lord. The young
                  samurai, incurring thereby the deep displeasure and enmity of his Prince, was
                  deprived of his title and estates and sent into exile upon the first convenient
                  pretext. Strange talks told without shadow of authority diversified the nature of
                  the crime for which the <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign> had been exiled,
                  but the two lords remained silent. All who had been concerned in the affair were
                  commanded to the same silence by the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign>.</p>
               <p>Whatever were the many reasons responsible for the constant attitude of antagonism
                  of these two clans towards each other, the lords carefully guarded their
                  lands—more aces—with all the rigor of a fortress prepared for the fiercest
                  onslaught. Seemingly unapproachable and impenetrable as were the grounds of the
                  Catzu palace, yet there must have existed at some spot in their watchful walls a
                  vulnerable point, the heel of the stone Achilles. </p>
               <pb n="23"/>
        
            <p>A courtier, by his dress and demeanor plainly a member of the Mori household,
               lingered in the private gardens of the palace. The day had long since folded its
               wings of light, but an early March moon was enveloping the land in an ethereal glow.
               The courtier remained under the friendly shadow of a grove of pine-trees. His eyes
               were cast upon the stately Catzu <foreign xml:lang="ja">shiro</foreign> (palace). It seemed as though the moon-rays
               had singled out the graceful old castle and was bathing it tenderly in a halo of soft
               light.</p>
            <p>It was cold, not bitterly so, but sharply chill, as it is at night betwixt the winter
               and the spring. But unconscious of the chill, erect and graceful, the courtier leaned
               against a tree-trunk, ih sarms crossed over his breast, his eyes full of moist
               sentiment, drinking in the beauty of the night scene, which had an added enchantment
               for him, a man in love.</p>
            <p>All about him, before, behind, and around him, graceful pine-trees raised their
               slender, pointed heads up to the silver light. In the distance, like a strange, white
               mirage set in the moonlit sky, a snow-capped mountain seemed hung as in mid-air. The
               grass beneath his feet was young and intensely soft, with dewy moisture upon it.</p>
            <p> A nightingale on the tip of a tall bamboo sang with such passionate sweetness that
               it brought the lover out from the shelter of the shadow. Quivering with emotion, his<pb n="24"/>soul responding and vibrating to the song of love, he strode into the light of the moon. Unmindful of the danger of his exposure to possible observation, he drew forth from the bosom of his haori a little roll of rice-paper. Once more he read it through, and yet once again. 
            </p>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
