<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="WooingOfWistaria14">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Wooing of Wistaria</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl copyOf="bibl:197"/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="wdt:docPrimarySource" scheme="wdt:docType"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:genre" target="wdt:genreNovel"/>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:exhibit" target="wdt:Japan"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="inProgress">
         <change who="pers:SC1" when="2020-08-17" status="inProgress">Begin transcribing and proofreading</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" when="2020-06-14" status="empty">Changed id from WooingOfWistaria12 to WooingOfWistaria14.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-08-23">Added facs.</change>
         <change who="pers:SL1" status="empty" when="2019-07-08">Added catRef genre and exhibit.</change>
         <change who="pers:JT1" status="empty" when="2019-04-11">Created file from bibliography entry bibl197 using XSLT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <body>
         <head>The Wooing of Wistaria</head>
         <opener>
            <byline>By <name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></byline>     
         </opener>
         <head type="subtitle">A Love Story of Japan</head>
         <div type="content">
           <div type="chapter">
              <head>I</head>
               <p>When after a life that had never lacked variety the Lady Wistaria came to the
                  years of <choice><sic>tranquillity</sic> <corr>tranquility</corr></choice>, she was wont to say, with the philosophy that follows
                  dangerous times: <q>No one, man or maid, ever really began to live before the time
                     to which the first memory reverts</q>.</p>
               <p>The first recollection of the Lady Wistaria goes back to an earlier childhood than
                  that of most mortals. This she ascribed to its terrible and awful import. She
                  could scarcely do more than move with the uncertain direction of babyhood, when<pb
                     n="2"/>her father, always now in her memory as gaunt, lean, haggard, tall, had
                  taken her upon a long journey. They had travelled partly by <foreign xml:lang="ja"
                     >kurumaya</foreign>, and, towards the end, on foot. That is, her father had
                  walked, carry8ing her on high in his arms. </p>
               <p>When they halted at Yedo they stood amid a vast concourse of people, who remained
                  silent and respectful against the background of the buildings, while in the centre
                  of the road marched steadily and pompously a great glittering pageant.</p>
               <p>Wisteria had clapped her hands with glee and delight at the mass of color, the
                  glimmer of shield and breastplate, the prancing, snorting horses. But her father
                  suddenly had raised an enormous hand and in a moment had stopped her delight.
                  Wisteria lapsed into an acute silence.</p>
               <p>Instantly she was awakened from her painful apathy by her father, who moved her
                  higher in his arms, and turned her head slowly about with one hand, while with the
                  other he pointed to a shining personage reclining in a palanquin borne high on the
                  shoulders of ten stout-legged attendants.</p>
               <p><q>My daughter</q>, said her father’s hollow voice in her ear, <q>yonder rides the
                  man who killed your mother. It is through his crime that you are orphaned and have
                  no mother to care for you and love you. Look at him well! Hush! Do not weep or
                  shake with <pb n="3"/>fear, but turn your eyes upon him. Look at him! Look! Look! Yonder rides your mother’s murderer. Do not forget his face as long as you live. It is your duty to remember it!</q></p>
               <p>Whereupon Wistaria, who, in obedience to her father’s commands, had stared with
                  wide eyes fixedly at the reclining noble, set up a most extraordinary cry. It was
                  unlike that of a little child—a wild, wailing shriek, so weird and piteous that
                  the bystanders started in horror and fear. The noble raised himself lazily on his
                  elbow, starting across the heads of all, until his eyes rested upon the man with
                  the child held on high. He fell back with an uneasy shrug of the shoulders. </p>
               <p>That was the Lady Wistaria’s oldest memory. There were others, but none so vivid
                  as this, the first of all. Even later, when she had ceased to be a child, she had
                  been unable to pierce the mystery of her father’s life, or indeed her own.</p>
               <p> One half of her earlier years had been spent in a small, whitewashed cottage,
                  built on the crest of a little wind-blown hill, far enough removed from the
                  dwellings in the village below to be entirely cut off from them.</p>
               <p>There was a touch of the uncanny and weird about the little village, whose slender
                  streets, ascending and descending, zigzagging up and down, disappeared among
                  hillocks <pb n="4"/> / and bluffs, though built in reality in the hollow outskirts
                  of a flourishing city at the foot of a small chain of mountains. Through the land
                  here was green and beautiful at all times of the year, there came no one from the
                  great city beyond to this solitary settlement, whose inhabitants bore the impress
                  of toil, pain, and oppression.</p>
               <p>Why her father, who, she had been told, was of noble blood, resided here on this
                  hilltop, isolated even from the strange people who dwelt in the silent village
                  below, the Lady Wistaria had never learned. When she had questioned her uncle and
                  aunt, she had been frigidly informed that curiosity and inquisitiveness were
                  degrading traits, which a maiden should strive with all her strength to overcome.
                  Neither did she ask her father, who, taciturn and cold during her brief residence
                  each year in his house, gave her no opportunity for winning his confidence. His
                  love Wistaria had never dreamed of possessing. </p>
               <p>Nevertheless, whenever she went to her father’s house, a wistful longing and
                  yearning for him possessed her whole being, and when she departed she would hide
                  her face in her sleeve, weeping silently, not knowing why she should weep, and
                  scarcely conscious of the fact that she wept for lack of her father’s love.</p>
               <p> In her father’s house there were no servants, <pb n="5"/> no maids, no attendants—only one
                  weazened, blind, and infinitely old woman, who wept tears from her sightless eyes
                  upon her arrival, who sang and crooned to her at night in a sobbing, sighing
                  voice, that was as sweet and pure as a girl’s.</p>
               <p>She addressed the old woman as <q>Madame Mume</q>, and preserved always towards
                  her the reserved and dignified attitude of the mistress to the maid. Yet her
                  father addressed her as <q>Mother</q>. Wisteria knew the old woman was not his
                  mother, and she could not believe she was even akin to them; for had she not
                  always been taught that the family from which she was descended was one of the
                  oldest and noblest in Japan, while old Madame Mume, though gentle and good, wore
                  the garb of the poor <foreign xml:lang="ja">heimin</foreign>.</p>
               <p> The other half of her childhood had been spent at the home of her uncle. Here
                  were countless retainers and servants, besides a host of <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>, petty vassals,
                  soldiers, peasants, and citizens, who lived upon his land and owed their direct
                  allegiance to him. </p>
               <p> The garden walls surrounding her uncle’s palace were tall and of massive
                  structure, built of solid stone. Its gates were guarded by handsome, bold <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>
                  clad in thick armor. The steel upon their breasts and shoulders glistened with a
                  sinister sheen, and beneath their blazing helmets fierce eyes burned out their
                  unswerving allegiance and <pb n="6"/> loyalty to their lord and their scorn and defiance of
                  all his enemies. Their coats, all emblazoned and embroidered with golden dragons,
                  bore two crests, that of the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Shogun</foreign> Iyesada, and that of the powerful <foreign xml:lang="ja">Daimio</foreign> under
                  whom they served, the Lord of Catzu, uncle of the Lady Wistaria. </p>
               <p> Here in her uncle’s palace, Wistaria was watched over, cared for, nurtured, and
                  refined. Lackeys and servants were about her on all sides, ready to spring to her
                  service. As a child she had attended a private school, kept by an old <foreign xml:lang="ja">samurai</foreign>,
                  where with half a dozen other little girls she had squatted on small, padded mats
                  before writing-tables but twelve inches high, and had been taught the intricacies
                  of the language. Two gorgeously liveried attendants always accompanied her to and
                  from the school-house, carrying her books, her writing-box, her keeling-cushion,
                  and her little table. </p>
               <p>When she grew older she attended the elementary school. After she had left this, a
                  silent woman of perfect manners and exquisite appearance had come to her uncle’s
                  palace and attached herself entirely to her. With the coming of this governess,
                  wisteria ceased to pay her annual visits to her father’s house. He himself came to
                  the palace instead, once every year. Upon these occasions Wistaria was brought
                  into his presence. He would put a few stern questions to her <pb n="7"/> concerning her
                  knowledge of her duty to her parents, to which Wistaria would respond with
                  expressions of filial submission to his will in all things.</p>
               <p>From the governess, Wistaria learned the elegancies of conversation and how to act
                  on meeting great personages at court. She had even been drilled in certain graces
                  which should not fail to enchain her lover, when he, the proper one, should be
                  chosen for her. </p>
               <p>Now that she had reached the age of fifteen years, this perfec person had departed
                  from the palace to teach maidens of younger years. The Lady Wistaria had arrived
                  at an age when she could be said to have been graduated from her governess’s hands
                  as competent to pass the rest of her life without further instruction, save that
                  constant restraint exercised over her by her aunt, the Lady Evening Glory of
                  Catze.</p>
               
               <p> </p>
              
           </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
