<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsschematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="organizations">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Organization Database</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docBornDigitalListing"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-13" status="published">Added details to what Sam Bowen built.</change><change who="pers:JT1" when="2019-04-04" status="published">Created file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Organization Database</head>
         <p>This documents includes all publishers and distributors of Eaton’s works.</p>
         <listOrg>
            <org xml:id="Ainslee" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Ainslee’s</orgName>
               <note><p>American monthly journal that was in circulation from February 1898 to December 
                  1926. Based in New York. Contents largely consisted of popular fiction and entertainment. 
                  Succeeded the <title level="j">Yellow Book</title>/<title level="j">Yellow Kid</title> magazine. Was later absorbed into 
                  <title level="j">Far West Illustrated</title> magazine and briefly revived in the mid-1930s as 
                  <title level="j">Ainslee’s Smart Love Stories</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Albertan" resp="pers:SB2 pers:JT1 pers:MC1">
               <orgName>Albertan</orgName>
               <note><p>Also known as the <title level="j">Calgary Albertan</title>. First established as 
                  the <title level="j">Calgary Tribune</title> in 1886. Would be called variations of the 
                  <title level="j">Albertan</title> from 1899 until 1980. Had a variety of names until the 
                  newspaper was sold to the Toronto Sun Publishing Corporation and renamed the 
                  <title level="j">Calgary Sun</title> in 1980.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="AmericanHome" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>American Home Journal</orgName>
               <note><p>Illustrated monthly periodical that featured sheet music in each issue. 
                  The precursor to <title level="j">Conkey’s Home Journal</title> (both published by the W.B. Conkey Co. based in Chicago, IL), 
                  <title level="j">American Home Journal</title> was only in print from 1897-8.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="AmericanYouth" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>American Youth</orgName>
               <note><p>Weekly organ of Chicago Waifs Mission, edited by Susan Gibbons Duval (1837-1920). Published Hamlin Garlin and other popular authors.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Anderson" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Anderson Intelligencer [SC]</orgName>
               <note><p>Newspaper in print from 1860-1916; published at the Anderson Court House in South Carolina. 
                  Was also called the <title level="j">Anderson Conservator</title> and the <title level="j">Anderson Daily Intelligencer</title>. 
                  Published weekly, delved into politics, literature, news, morals, agriculture, science, and reported on daily events.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Blue" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Blue Book</orgName>
               <note><p>Early twentieth-century pulp magazine, ran from 1905 to 1975. First launched as 
                  <title level="j">The Monthly Story Magazine</title>, known as <title level="j">Blue Book Magazine</title> from 1907 to 1952. 
                  Often linked to <title level="j">The Red Book Magazine</title> and <title level="j">The Green Book Magazine</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Book" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Book News</orgName>
               <note><p>An illustrated magazine of literature and books published from 1882-1918. 
                  Published monthly with the intent to survey general literature; likely the first publication 
                  devoted to book reviews.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Bookman" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Bookman</orgName>
               <note><p>A literary journal published in New York that was in publication from 1895 to 1933. 
                  Established by Dodd, Mead and Company. Offered conservative commentary and fiction from prominent American authors.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Boston" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Boston Journal</orgName>
               <note><p>Also known as the <title level="j">Boston Sunday Journal</title>. Newspaper published in Boston, Massachusetts from 1903-1917.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Burt" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>A. L. Burt</orgName>
               <note><p>New York publisher</p></note>
            </org><org xml:id="Calgary" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Calgary Daily Herald</orgName>
               <note><p>First published in Calgary, Alberta in 1883, now known as the <title level="j">Calgary Herald</title>. 
                  Became a daily in 1885. Was a supporter of the pioneer ranching industry.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="CdnBookman" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Canadian Bookman</orgName>
               <note><p>Initially a quarterly journal when founded in 1919, later a monthly journal from 1922 
                  until it ceased publication in 1939. Published by St. Anne de Bellevue, P.Q: Industrial and Educational Press Limited. 
                  Merged with <title level="j">Canadian Author</title> in 1940 to form <title level="j">Canadian Author and Bookman</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="CartersMonthly" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Carter’s Monthly</orgName>
               <note><p>Chicago-based general story magazine first published in 1898. Would cease publication within a year.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Chicago" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Chicago Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Chicago-based periodical first published in 1899 by Chapin Magazine Co.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="ChristianScience" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Christian-Science Monitor</orgName>
               <note><p>First print edition published in 1908; now a daily online newspaper that publishes on a variety of topics. Headquartered in Boston.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Cincinnati" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Cincinnati Commercial Tribune</orgName>
               <note><p>Daily newspaper printed in Cincinnati, Ohio from 1896-1898, when it was renamed the <title level="j">Commercial Tribune</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Columbian" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Columbian Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>The twentieth-century iteration of <title level="j">The Columbian Magazine</title> was edited by Henry Mann in New York; 
                  its byline was <q>a treasury of entertainment and the latest useful information</q>. Appears to have issued only around 
                  4 volumes spanning—at minimum—1910-1911. Would later be titled <title level="j">Hampton’s Magazine</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Conkey" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Conkey’s Home Journal</orgName>
               <note><p>Succeeded <title level="j">American Home Journal</title>, was in print from 1897-1903.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Critic" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Critic</orgName>
               <note><p>New York-based magazine focused on literary criticism. In print from 1881-1906, 
                  when it was absorbed into <title level="j">Putnam’s Monthly</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Current" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Current Literature</orgName>
               <note><p>New York-based magazine in print from 1888-1912, when its name was changed to <title level="j">Current Opinion</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Day" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Day Book</orgName>
               <note><p>Published in Chicago, the <title level="j">Chicago Day Book</title> was published six days a week from 1911-1917. 
                  Geared towards the working class and published in a small tabloid format, it was an experiment in advertisement-free newspaper publishing. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Doubleday" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Doubleday</orgName>
               <note><p>Founded in 1897, Doubleday is a publishing company with both American and Canadian subsidiaries underneath the Penguin Random House corporation.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Eclectic" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>The Eclectic Magazine of Foreign Literature, Science, and Art</orgName>
               <note><p>A monthly periodical published in New York from 1844 until 1907 by the Eclectic Magazine Printing and Publishing Company. 
                  Eaton (as Watanna) appears to have been published in one of its final—if not the final—volumes in 1907.</p></note>
            </org>   
            <org xml:id="Edmonton" resp="pers:SB2">
                  <orgName>Edmonton Journal</orgName>  
               <note><p>Daily newspaper (Sundays excepted) published in Edmonton, Alberta.  Established in 1903 and still in print today.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Farm" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Farm and Ranch Review</orgName>
               <note><p>Popular and respected Calgary-based monthly periodical focused on Western-Canadian agriculture foundd by Malcolm Geddes, E. L. Richardson, and C. W. Peterson in 1904 and in print from 1905-1966. Tied to the Country Life Movement.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="FarmersAdvocateHomeJournal">
               <orgName>Farmer’s Advocate and Home Journal</orgName>
               
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Frank" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Frank Leslie’s Popular Monthly</orgName>
               <note><p>First published in 1876, this monthly magazine focused on popular literature. 
                  Renamed <title level="j">Leslie’s Monthly Magazine</title> in 1904, and <title level="j">Leslie’s Magazine</title> in 1905. 
                  Ceased publication in 1956.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Galls" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Gall’s Daily News Letter</orgName>
               <note><p>Kingston-based Jamaican newspaper published daily from 1857 until 1999. 
                  Audience described <q>as ‘fairly liberal white elites and successful mixed-race planters and manufacturers’</q> (Womack).</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Good" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Good Housekeeping</orgName>
               <note><p>Originated in Massachusetts in 1885, later moved to New York City. In addition to publishing columns on housekeeping, 
                  the women’s magazine published the works of famous writers like Waugh and Woolf. Eaton’s sister, Edith Eaton (using the pseudonym <q>Sui Sin Far</q>) 
                  was also published in the magazine. Still published today.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Greenfield" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Greenfield Gazette and Courier</orgName>
               <note><p>A Massachusetts-based newspaper that was in publication from 1841-1932; 
                  the first daily newspaper in Greenfield, MA. Survives today as the <title level="j">Greenfield Recorder</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="HarpersMonthly" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Harper’s Monthly</orgName>
               <note><p>A monthly magazine publishing literature and commentary published by New York publishers Harper and Brothers. 
                  Began publication as <title level="j">Harper’s New Monthly Magazine</title>, before later being named <title level="j">Harper’s Monthly Magazine</title>, 
                  and finally <title level="j">Harper’s Magazine</title>. First published in 1850, still published today.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="HarpersWeekly" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Harper’s Weekly</orgName>
               <note><p>Began publication in 1857 and ran until 1916 as a political magazine. 
                  Today, <title level="j">Harper’s Weekly</title> survives as a blog associated with <title level="j">Harper’s Magazine</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Hearsts" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Hearst’s</orgName>
               <note><p>American monthly magazine first published as <title level="j">Hearst’s Magazine</title> in 1912. 
                  When acquired by Hearst Magazines in 1911, publication was called <title level="j">The World Today</title>. 
                  Would combine with <title level="j">Cosmopolitan</title> in the 1920s.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Home" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Home and Flowers</orgName>
               <note><p>Magazine published monthly from 1900-1906; publisher based in Springfield, Ohio. The full title is <emph>Home and Flowers: An Illustrated Monthly Magazine Devoted to the Home Beautiful</emph>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Hutchinson" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Hutchinson’s Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>British publishing company, which published standalone texts and magazines like <emph>Hutchinson’s Magazine</emph> (1919-1929) and <emph>Hutchinson’s Story Magazine</emph> (1919-1921). Eaton’s work was published in the former.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="IConfess" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>I Confess</orgName>
               <note><p>American pulp magazine published biweekly from 1922-1932. Aimed at young women.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Idler" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Idler</orgName>
               <note><p>A British illustrated magazine in print from 1892 until 1911; published monthly.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Iroquois" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Iroquois</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="LadiesHomeCompanion" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Ladies’ Home Companion</orgName>
               <note><p>Also known as <emph>Woman’s Home Companion</emph> after 1896. An American monthly magazine published from 1873-1957.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="LadiesHomeJournal" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Ladies’ Home Journal</orgName>
               <note><p>Initially published as <title level="j">The Ladies’ Home Journal and Practical Housekeeper</title>. In print from 1883 until 2016.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="LadysMagazine" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Lady’s Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>British magazine published by C. Arthur Pearson that aimed to be a comprehensive publication for all subjects pertaining to women. This particular iteration was in print from 1901-1904; the magazine would be renamed multiple times.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Lippincott" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Lippincott’s Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Monthly magazine focused on publishing literature and science-related materials 
                  from 1868 until its absorption into <title level="j">Scribner’s Magazine</title> in 1915. 
                  Initially published in Philadelphia, before being relocated to New York in 1915.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="LosAngelesHerald" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Los Angeles Herald</orgName>
               <note><p>Daily newspaper established in 1873 with an emphasis on local agricultural, 
                  business, and cultural news for a working-class audience. 
                  Merged with other Los Angeles newspapers in 1931.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Lyttleton" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Lyttleton Times [NZ]</orgName>
               <note><p>The first newspaper established in Canterbury, New Zealand. 
                  Initially published biweekly, later increased to triweekly. Ran from 1851 until 1935.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Macleans" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Maclean’s</orgName>
               <note><p>Toronto-based weekly magazine initially titled <title level="j">The Busy Man’s Magazine</title>, 
                  which was renamed to <title level="j">Maclean’s</title> in 1911. The Canadian news magazine is still in publication today.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MetropolitanNY" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Metropolitan (New York)</orgName>
               <note><p>In publication from 1895 until 1925 in New York; 
                  focused on literature, politics, and theatre, among other interests.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MetropolitanMag" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Metropolitan Magazine (Montreal)</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MHL">
               <orgName>Margaret Herrick Library</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MGM">
               <orgName>Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studios</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Montreal" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Montreal Daily Star</orgName>
               <note><p>English-language Canadian newspaper in print from 1869 until 1979. Printed in Montreal, Quebec.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MontrealGazette" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Montreal Gazette</orgName>
               <note><p>Founded in 1778; one of the oldest newspapers in North America. Still in print today.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MotionPictureClassic" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Motion Picture Classic Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>An American movie fan magazine in print from 1915 until 1937. Headquartered in New York. The sister magazine of <emph>Motion Picture Magazine</emph>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="MotionPictureMag" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Motion Picture Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>An American movie fan magazine published from 1911 until 1977 under various names. Similarly named <emph>Motion Picture Classic Magazine</emph> was its sister publication. Headquartered in New York.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Munsey" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Munsey’s</orgName>
               <note><p>Pulp fiction magazine in print from 1889 until 1929; published by Frank Munsey’s own publishing company. In addition to <emph>Munsey’s</emph>, the New York-based firm also published journals like <emph>The Puritan</emph>.  </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="NewMag" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>New Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Short-lived Toronto-based magazine published by Periodical Press of Canada Ltd.; inaugural issue’s managing editor was Theodore H. Rand-McNally. Only the first issue was ever published; the magazine was intended to be <q>For Canada – By Canada – About Canada</q>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="NewMetro" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>New Metropolitan Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Edited by John Kendrick Bangs from 1903 onwards. Appears to be a renaming of the New York-based <title level="j">Metropolitan Magazine</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Puritan" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>The Puritan</orgName>
               <note><p>In print from 1897-1901, when it was absorbed by <title level="j">The Junior Munsey</title>. 
                  Described as a <q>journal for gentlewomen</q>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Red" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Redbook</orgName>
               <note><p>Still in publication today, <title level="j">Redbook</title> is an American women’s magazine first published in 1903. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="SFCall" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>San Francisco Call</orgName>
               <note><p>A daily morning newspaper based in San Francisco that was in print from 1895 until 1913, 
                  when it was purchased by William Randolph Hearst and became <title level="j">The San Francisco Call and Post</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="SaskatoonDailyStar" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Saskatoon Daily Star</orgName>
               <note><p>A daily newspaper in Saskatoon, Saskatchewan that has had a variety of names: <title level="j">The Phoenix</title> (1902–1907), <title level="j">The Daily Phoenix</title> (1907–1910); <title level="j">The Saskatoon Capital</title> (1910–1912); <title level="j">The Saskatoon Daily Star</title> (1912–1928); and <title level="m">The Saskatoon Star-Phoenix</title> (1928–present).</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Saturday" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Saturday Evening Post</orgName>
               <note><p>An American general interest magazine first published in 1821 and is still published today. Initially a weekly magazine, now bimonthly.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Screen" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Screen Secrets</orgName>
               <note><p>Monthly periodical published in Louisville, Kentucky by Fawcett Publications. Magazine named <emph>Screen Secrets</emph> from 1928-1930. The earlier titles <emph>So this is—Paris</emph> and <emph>Paris and Hollywood screen secrets</emph> suggest the magazine’s broad scope.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Smart" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Smart Set</orgName>
               <note><p>New York-based magazine focused on literature and culture; its byline was <q>a magazine of cleverness</q>. In print from 1900-1930. Gave many emerging writers the chance to reach a large audience. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Smith" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Smith’s Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Fiction magazine in print from 1905-1922. Published in New York by Smith Publishing House on a monthly basis.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Sovereign" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Sovereign Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Published in London from 1919-1927. Would be incorporated into <q>The Jolly Magazine</q>. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Spanish" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Spanish Fork Press</orgName>
               <note><p>Weekly newspaper based in Spanish Fork, Utah. First printed in 1902, the press is still in publication today.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Spokane" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Spokane Press</orgName>
               <note><p>Daily newspaper (Sundays excepted) published in Spokane, Washington from 1902-1939.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="StLouisDispatch" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>St. Louis Dispatch</orgName>
               <note><p>Weekly newspaper printed from 1864 until 1878 in St. Louis, Missouri.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Canterbury" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>The Press [Canterbury, NZ]</orgName>
               <note><p>Initially a weekly newspaper when it was first printed in 1861, 
                  <title level="j">The Press</title> would later become the province’s first daily paper. Ran until 1945.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Quill" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>The Quill</orgName>
               <note><p>Published in Toronto by the Quill Publishing Society. Magazine’s byline was <q>The Canadian short story magazine</q>. First issue published in October 1922.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="TrueStory" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>True Story Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>American magazine first published in 1919 by Bernarr Macfadden; still in print today. Published first-hand accounts of social problems and taboos in a <q>confessional</q>-style format.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Universal" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Universal</orgName>
               <note><p>American film studio founded in 1912. Initially located in Chicago, 
                  later moved to New York and Hollywood. Eaton assisted with scriptwriting 
                  and adaptation on select films.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Washington" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Washington Times</orgName>
               <note><p>Daily newspaper (Sundays excepted) published in Washington, D.C. from 1902 until 1939.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="WomansHomeCompanion" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Woman’s Home Companion</orgName>
               <note><p>American women’s magazine published from 1896 until 1957. 
                  Prior to 1896, the magazine was called the <title level="j">Ladies’ Home Companion</title>, 
                  but the name was changed to distance the publication from <title level="j">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, their rival publication. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="WomansHomeJournal" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Woman’s Home Journal</orgName> <!--The only listing under Woman’s Home Journal should technically fall under Woman’s Home Companion?-->
               <note><p>Published in Springfield, Ohio by Crowell-Collier. The American women’s magazine was in print from 1873-1957; a continuation of Ladies’ Home Companion and other earlier titles.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="WomansWorld" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Woman’s World</orgName>
               <note><p>Chicago-based women’s magazine published from 1884-1940. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Blakely" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Blakely Press</orgName>
               <note><p>Chicago-based, also known as the Blakely Printing Company. Established in 1871. 
                  Company established a newspaper in 1898. </p></note>
            </org>

            <!--What’s the different between Century and Century press? // Leaving Century Press listed just in case-->
            <!--The Century Magazine now refers to Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, Century, and Century Magazine-->
            <org xml:id="Century" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>The Century Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Successor to <title level="m">Scribner’s Monthly Magazine</title> based in New York City, publishing
                  journalism, fiction, and poetry from 1881-1930 when it was absorbed into <title level="j">The Forum</title>.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="CenturyCompany" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Century Company</orgName>
               <note><p>New York-based American publishing company founded in 1881 (also known as Century Press). 
                  Ran independently until 1933, when it merged with D. Appleton and Company. Now defunct.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="CenturyPress" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Century Press</orgName>
               <note><p>New York-based American publishing company founded in 1881 (also known as Century Company). 
                  Ran independently until 1933, when it merged with D. Appleton and Company. Now defunct.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Dodd" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Dodd, Mead, and Company</orgName>
               <note><p>New York City-based publishing house that was in operation from 1839 to 1990. </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Harper" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Harper and Brothers</orgName>
               <note><p>Book-publishing firm that also founded and distributed <title level="j">Harper’s Magazine</title>. Headquartered in New York City.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="McClelland" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>McClelland and Stewart</orgName>
               <note><p>Toronto-based Canadian publishing company founded in 1906. In its infancy, went by McClelland and Goodchild Limited before its name change in 1918. Now owned by Penguin Random House LLC.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Macmillan" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Macmillan</orgName>
               <note><p>English publishing company headquartered in New York City. Founded in 1843.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Musson" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>The Musson Book Company</orgName>
               <note><p>Canadian publisher based in Toronto. Founded in 1894 and was absorbed into 
                  General Publishing in the 1960s.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Rand" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>Rand, McNally</orgName>
               <note><p>American publishing company based in Illinois; best known for its maps and travel books. 
                  Also published children’s books beginning in 1900.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Watt" resp="pers:SB2">
               <orgName>W. J. Watt and Company</orgName>
               <note><p>New York City-based publishing company.</p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="WERFonds" resp="pers:JT1">
               <orgName>Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds</orgName>
               <note><p>Collection of Winnifred Eaton’s papers and unpublished manuscripts, which were transferred to the University of Calgary in 1982. The finding aid for this material is located here: <ref target="https://searcharchives.ucalgary.ca/winnifred-eaton-reeve-fonds">https://searcharchives.ucalgary.ca/winnifred-eaton-reeve-fonds</ref> </p></note>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="PhonographicMagazine" resp="pers:JT1">
               <orgName>Phonographic Magazine</orgName>
               <note><p>Official publication for the Cincinnati-based Phonographic Institute. Founded in 1887 and published articles about the practice of short-hand and professional matters related to stenographers in the United States.</p></note>
            </org>
            
<!--            
            <org xml:id="HathiTrust">
               <orgName>Hathi Trust</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="LibraryOfCongress">
               <orgName>Library of Congress</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Google">
               <orgName>Google</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="RaunerLibrary">
               <orgName>Rauner Special Collections Library</orgName>
               <placeName>Darthmouth College</placeName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="ProjectGutenbergCanada">
               <orgName>Project Gutenberg Canada</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="AmericanPeriodicals">
               <orgName>American Periodicals</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="FreeLibraryPhiladelphia">
               <orgName>Free Library of Philadelphia</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="UNewHampshireLibraries">
               <orgName>University of New Hampshire Libraries</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Newberry">
               <orgName>Newberry Library</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="InternetArchive">
               <orgName>Internet Archive</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="ProjectGutenberg">
               <orgName>Project Gutenberg</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="SchlesingerLibrary">
               <orgName>Schlesinger Library</orgName>
               <placeName>Harvard University</placeName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Winterthur">
               <orgName>Winterthur Library</orgName>
               <placeName>Delaware</placeName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Newspapers">
               <orgName>Newspapers.com</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="UIllinoisChicago">
               <orgName>University of Illinois-Chicago</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="CenterResearchLibraries">
               <orgName>Center for Research Libraries</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="BritishPeriodicals">
               <orgName>Proquest British Periodicals</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="Yale">
               <orgName>Yale University</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="PerryCastaneda">
               <orgName>Perry-Castañeda Library</orgName>
               <placeName>UT Austin</placeName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="UBC">
               <orgName>UBC Libraries</orgName>
            </org>-->
         </listOrg>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
