<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="taxonomies">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Taxonomies</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               
               <name ref="pers:JT1"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>There has been no normalization.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation marks="none">
               <p>We eliminate all quotations mark programatically using the Schematron/XSLT quickfixes contained in the ODD file. Every attempt has been made, in the proofing process, to convert all quotation marks to <gi>q</gi> elements. We do not retain the styling information about the forms of quotation marks nor necessarily the placement of such marks. See the documentation for more specific details on how we handle quotations, block quotations, and floating texts.</p>
            </quotation>
            <correction method="markup">
               <p>We do not correct the text unless the error is obvious and somehow severely impedes the reading process. In the rare cases where there has been editorial correction, we use the <gi>choice</gi>, <gi>sic</gi>, and <gi>corr</gi> elements when correcting.</p>
            </correction>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>All end-of-line hyphens have been removed; however, all other forms of hyphenation (compound words, et cetera) have been retained.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>There is little interpretative markup contained within the WEA project. We do tag entities mentioned in the text.</p>
            </interpretation>
            <punctuation placement="external">
               <p>All original punctuation marks have been retained, other than quotation marks (as mentioned above). All trailing punctuation marks that are not necessarily part of the <gi>q</gi> element (i.e. periods or commas) have been moved outside of the <gi>q</gi> element; hard punctuation (like exclamation and question marks) have been retained within the <gi>q</gi>.</p>
            </punctuation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            
            <!--hort story, non-fiction, autobiography, film scenario, film treatment, poem, serialized novel plus some of the more visual “objects” like photograph, portrait, film clip, ) I’m wondering if we would like to complicate the non-fiction category, I.e. Autobiography, dedication, interview, introduction, ethnography-->
            <taxonomy xml:id="docClassTaxonomies">
               <taxonomy xml:id="docType" n="Document Types">
                  <bibl>Document Type</bibl>
                  <category xml:id="docPrimarySource">
                     <catDesc>
                        <term>Primary Source</term>
                     </catDesc>
                     <category xml:id="docPrimarySourceMS">
                        <catDesc>
                           <term>Manuscripts</term>
                        </catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="docPrimarySourcePublished">
                        <catDesc>
                           <term>Published Primary Sources</term>
                        </catDesc>
                     </category>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="docBornDigital">
                     <catDesc><term>Born Digital document</term></catDesc>
                     <category xml:id="docBornDigitalListing">
                        <catDesc>
                           <term>Listing Pages</term>
                           
                        </catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="docBornDigitalDocumentation">
                        <catDesc>
                           <term>Documentation</term>
                        </catDesc>
                     </category>
                  </category>
               </taxonomy>
               
               <taxonomy xml:id="genre">
                  <bibl>Genre</bibl>
                  <category xml:id="genreShortStory">
                     <catDesc>
                        <term>Short Stories</term>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="genreNF">
                     <catDesc><term>Non-fiction</term></catDesc>
                     <category xml:id="genreNFAuto">
                        <catDesc><term>Non-fiction: Autobiography</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="genreNFDedication">
                        <catDesc><term>Non-fiction: Dedication</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="genreNFInterview">
                        <catDesc><term>Non-Fiction: Interview</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="genreNFIntroduction">
                        <catDesc><term>Non-fiction: Introduction</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="genreNFEthnography">
                        <catDesc><term>Non-fiction: Ethnography</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="genreFilm">
                     <catDesc><term>Film</term></catDesc>
                     <category xml:id="genreFilmScenario">
                        <catDesc><term>Film: Scenario</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="genreFilmTreatment">
                        <catDesc><term>Film: Treatment</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                     <category xml:id="genreFilmScreenplay">
                        <catDesc><term>Film: Screenplay</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="genrePoem">
                     <catDesc><term>Poem</term></catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="genreNovel">
                     <catDesc><term>Novel</term></catDesc>
                     <category xml:id="genreNovelSerial">
                        <catDesc><term>Novel: Serial</term></catDesc>
                     </category>
                  </category>
               </taxonomy>
               
               
               <!--<taxonomy xml:id="object">
                 <bibl>Object</bibl>
                 <category xml:id="objectText">
                    <catDesc>Object: Text</catDesc>
                 </category>
                 <category xml:id="objectPhoto">
                    <catDesc>Object: Photo</catDesc>
                 </category>
       
                 <category xml:id="objectFilm">
                    <catDesc>Object: Film</catDesc>
                 </category>
                 <category xml:id="objectPoster">
                    <catDesc>Object: Poster</catDesc>
                 </category>
              </taxonomy>-->
               
               <taxonomy xml:id="exhibit">
                  <bibl>Exhibits</bibl>
                  <category xml:id="Japan" n="2">
                     <catDesc>
                        
                        <term>Playing Japanese <date>1897–1922</date></term><note>
                           <p>After her return from Jamaica in 1897, Eaton worked as a stenographer, first in Cincinnati, then in Chicago. At this time, she assumed the identity of <q><name ref="pers:WE1">Kitishima Tackehasche</name></q>, a young Yokohama-born  writer who published under the pseudonym <q><name ref="pers:WE1">Onoto Watanna</name></q>, the name under which Eaton would become best known. For the next decade, Eaton indulged readers’ seemingly endless appetite for the Orient, depicting with exotic flair Japanese gardens, tea-houses, <foreign xml:lang="ja">geishas</foreign>, and matchmakers. Her Eaton’s earliest Japanese story, <title level="a">A Japanese Girl</title> purportedly published in Cincinnati’s <title level="j">Commercial Tribune</title> has yet to be located, but the overwhelming majority of her Japanese-themed works are collected here. Between 1897 and 1922, Eaton published 12 Japanese novels, scores of short stories and ethnographic pieces, and poetry, and even co-authored <ref target="doc:ChineseJapaneseCookbook1"><title level="m">A ChineseJapaneseCookbook</title></ref> with her sister Sara Eaton Bosse.</p>
                     </note></catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Alberta" n="4">
                     <catDesc><term>Alberta <date>1919–1933</date></term><note>
                        <p>Eaton divorced Bertrand Babcock, married businessman Frank Reeve, and moved west to the Canadian province of Alberta in 1917. At Bow View Ranch in Morley, Alberta, Eaton experienced life on the wide open prairie, populated only by ranchers, indigenous people, cattle, and horses. This far-flung locale sparked a new phase in Eaton’s career. She wrote two realist novels set in the Canadian west and published a number of journalistic features about the people, places, and happenings of her new home. She also began to experiment with a new form of publication, the <q>pulps</q>--cheaply produced magazines featuring genre fiction of various sorts, including romance, mystery, and adventure fiction--the more sensational, the better.</p>
                     </note></catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Hollywood" n="5">
                     <catDesc><term>In Hollywood <date>1921–1935</date></term><note>
                        <p>Eaton flirted with the film industry as early as 1915 but did not actually sign on with a studio until 1924, when she was hired by Universal Pictures. Eaton proved <q>able to turn out scripts rapidly and to order</q>, according to biographer Diana Birchall. She later worked for Metro-Goldwyn Mayer and Twentieth-Century Fox, writing original screenplays as well as adaptations. William Faulkner, F. Scott Fitzgerald, and many other seasoned writers found writing for the film industry difficult. Eaton, however, flourished. She found herself assigned to write film vehicles for two stars, Mary Nolan (<ref target="doc:BarbaryCoast1"><title level="m">Barbary Coast</title></ref>, <ref target="doc:ShanghaiLady1"><title level="m">Shanghai Lady</title></ref>) and Mary Philbin (<title level="m">Phantom of the Opera</title>), and was able to translate her experience writing Japanese romances into scripts featuring exotic locales and peoples--which made up about 25% of the work to which she was assigned.</p>
                        
                     </note></catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="EarlyExperiment" n="1">
                     <catDesc>
                        <term>Early Experiments <date>1890s–1901</date></term>
                        <note>
                           <p>Winnifred Eaton’s writing apprenticeship began in Montreal where, as a young girl, she invented <q>stories and fairy songs</q>. Eaton probably exaggerated when she claimed that she was 14 when her first publication, a serialized short story, appeared in Montreal’s <title level="j">Metropolitan</title> (probably <ref target="doc:PoorDevil1"><title level="a">Poor Devil</title></ref>, a fragment of which Eaton preserved in her scrapbook). During this early stage of her career, Eaton published short stories, several of which are set in Montreal, and  also experimented with journalism. Her experience writing for a Montreal newspaper, she claimed, got her a job as a writer and reporter for the daily <title level="j">Gall’s Newsletter</title> in faraway Kingston, Jamaica, for a few months in 1895-6, where she purported to have published pieces signed <q>Busybody</q> and <q>Man on the Street</q>. Her works for <title level="j">Gall’s Newsletter</title> have yet to be located.</p>
                        </note>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="NewYork" n="3">
                     <catDesc>
                        <term>New York Years <date>1902–1916</date></term>
                        <note>
                           <p>By 1903, the novelty of Eaton’s Japanese romances had faded. Newly married to writer Bertrand Babcock and living in New York City, Eaton attempted to recreate herself. She wrote two anonymously published memoirs: the semi-autobiographical <ref target="doc:Me6"><title level="m">ME: A Book of Remembrance</title></ref> and <ref target="doc:Marion1"><title level="m">Marion</title></ref>, based on her sister Sara’s experience as an artist’s model. She experimented with other ethnic personae in <ref target="doc:DiaryOfDelia5"><title level="m">The Diary of Delia</title></ref>, a first-person narration from the perspective of an Irish maid speaking in a rich, if stereotypical, brogue. Eaton also wrote autobiographical journalism about her Long Island home and, with Babcock, co-authored a story set in New York State. During this period, she turned closer to home and wrote more directly from lived experience, while ironically further obscuring her identity by adopting new pseudonyms and publishing anonymously.</p>
                          
                        </note>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
               </taxonomy>
               
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="facs" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="facsimiles/$1.pdf"/>
            <prefixDef ident="pers" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="people.xml#$1"/>
            <prefixDef ident="wdt" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="taxonomies.xml#$1"/>
            <prefixDef ident="doc" matchPattern="(.+)(#.+)?" replacementPattern="$1.xml$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="media" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="media/$1_sm.png"/>
            <prefixDef ident="fig" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="media.xml#$1"/>
            <prefixDef ident="org" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="organizations.xml#$1"/>
            <prefixDef ident="bibl" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="bibliography.xml#bibl$1"/>
            <prefixDef ident="img" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="images/$1"/>
            <prefixDef ident="cite" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="bibliography.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="published">
         <change when="2019-02-13"
            who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
      
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
