<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="about">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>About</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JLC1">Jean Lee Cole</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change when="2020-08-13" who="pers:MC1" status="published">Updated comments about her racism.</change>
            <change when="2020-07-29" status="published">Updated dates.</change><change when="2020-06-13" status="published">Fixing up some of the language regarding XML downloading and adding links.</change>
            <change when="2020-04-29"
                who="pers:MC1" status="published">added content.</change>
            <change when="2020-02-21"
                who="pers:MC1" status="published">added content.</change>
            <change when="2019-02-19"
                    who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>About</head>
            <div>
                <head>About</head>
                <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive is an accessible, fully searchable, digital scholarly edition of the collected works of Winnifred Eaton Babcock Reeve, best known for the popular Japanese romances she signed <q>Onoto Watanna</q>. It comprises page images and transcriptions of nearly 200 located publications and manuscripts, as well as supplemental materials that will aid students and scholars of Eaton’s work. Ultimately, it aims to collect all known publications, manuscripts, and films by Eaton in one location.</p>
                
                <p>The original Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive was created by Jean Lee Cole (Loyola University Maryland) in 2004 in conjunction with the University of Virginia E-text Center. It contained edited transcriptions of two serialized novels and dozens of periodical publications held in the Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds at the University of Calgary and/or discovered by Cole over the previous decade through manual searching. These texts were encoded using the Textual Encoding Initiative P4 schema. These texts are still available in the UVa Text Collection accessible through the <ref target="https://search.lib.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia Libraries’ VIRGO catalog</ref>.</p>
                
                <p>In the Winnifred Eaton Archive’s second phase, Mary Chapman (University of British Columbia), together with her research team in collaboration with Cole, updated Cole’s original archive to conform with the Textual Encoding Initiative P5 schema and added edited encoded transcriptions of dozens of additional periodical publications she discovered, as well as additional manuscripts held in the Winnifred Eaton Reeve Fonds. Chapman also added to the site biographical information, a bibliography, a timeline, a list of pseudonyms, a copy of a film for which Eaton wrote the screenplay, and numerous photographs relevant to Eaton and her family. The aim of the Archive is to provide a full survey of Eaton’s work--its generic and stylistic range, its aesthetic experiment, as well as its often problematic politics.</p> 
                
                <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive is organized into exhibits that roughly correspond to periods in Eaton’s career. These periods overlap chronologically somewhat: <ref target="doc:EarlyExperiment"><q>Early Experiments</q></ref> features texts written in the 1890s and early 1900s during Eaton’s writing apprenticeship in Montreal and Jamaica, and/or before she had taken up her identity as <q>Onoto Watanna</q>; <ref target="doc:Japan"><q>Playing Japanese</q></ref> collects all texts written on Japanese subjects and themes from 1896 until 1922; <ref target="doc:NewYork"><q>New York Years</q></ref> collects texts marking a period of reinvention, from 1901-1916 after the novelty of Eaton’s Japanese romances had faded; <ref target="doc:Alberta"><q>Alberta</q></ref> collects texts written about Western ranch country, during her years living off and on in Alberta, roughly from her marriage to Frank Reeve in 1917 until her death in 1954; and finally, <ref target="doc:Hollywood"><q>In Hollywood</q></ref> collects her screenplays, treatments, extant films, as well as fiction about the movie business written from 1916-1935.</p></div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Our Audience and Contributors</head>
                <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive is committed to providing complete, current, and reliable information that is both suitable for scholarly citation and accessible to students, teachers, and community members outside the university. We welcome contributions from scholars, community experts, and advanced students. The site provides an opportunity to contribute transcriptions of and headnotes for all Winnifred Eaton works as well as facsimiles of recently recovered texts by Winnifred Eaton. All contributions (headnotes, editions, etc.) will be refereed.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                
                <head>Our Principles</head>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Open Peer Review</head>
                    <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive is committed to new forms of peer review, including cross-reviewing inspired by the <ref target="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/about.htm"><title level="m">The Map of Early Modern London</title></ref> and research apprenticeships. We currently give our reviewers the choice of anonymity or full credit. </p>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Open Access</head>
                    <p>All of our pages are freely available to anyone with an internet connection and a web browser. We do not charge fees for access or restrict any aspect of our site’s functionality. We link to other open-access resources preferentially. Whenever possible, we supplement what is available from subscription databases by obtaining fresh scans of materials from institutions willing to share their resources with the world and making these scans freely available.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="about_openSourceCode">
                    <head>Open-Source and Open-Code</head>
                    <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive team makes all of its code and data available to the public. All of the code and stylesheets used to create the web application is available via  our <ref target="https://github.com/winnifredeatonarchive/wea_data">Github repository</ref>, which also includes the source data for the project. In keeping with <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca/">The Endings Project</ref> as well as to ensure that our data is as interoperable with other projects as possible, the WEA makes available multiple versions of the source XML, all of which can be downloaded from the <q>Credits and Citations</q> menu on every page under the <q>Download</q> heading.</p>
                        
                        <p>There are three versions:
                        
                        <list>
                            <item>Source XML: The source XML is basically a duplicate of what is in the Github repository and is exactly the same version of the XML encoded by the project. Note that not all documents will contain a source XML file; some documents are created <q>on the fly</q> from larger files during the creation of the <q>Original</q> XML.</item>
                            <item><q>Original</q> XML: The <q>original</q> XML is a lightly modified version of the source XML. This is a slightly cleaned up version of the source XML with project specific shortcuts resolved and standardized.</item>
                            <item><q>Standalone</q> XML: The <q>standalone</q> XML is built from the <q>original</q> XML and contains all of the standoff entities (people, organizations, bibliographic citations, and taxonomies) referenced in that document. This means this document is most amenable for re-use. </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>

                
                <div>
                    <head>Transparent Work Practices</head>
                    <p>We aim to be fully transparent about all Winnifred Eaton Archive work practices. Our <ref target="docs/index.html">extensive documentation</ref> gives detailed instructions to team members. These instructions are openly published as a guide to how we work. </p></div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Credit</head>
                    <p>We give credit where credit is due, in keeping with the Collaborators’ Bill of Rights and A Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights. We do not distinguish between paid and unpaid labour. In our view, all paid research assistants deserve credit for their critical input; by the same token, our paid RAs take intellectual responsibility for their work. We do not consider any labour to be mechanical; all labour is critical and worthy of acknowledgement.</p> </div>
                
                
                <div><head>Creative Commons License</head>
                    <p>All of our content is licensed under a CC BY-SA 4.0 license, which gives anyone the right to download and repurpose our content and/or associated mark-up, provided the use is non-commercial and gives full credit to the Winnifred Eaton Archive and its contributors. </p>  </div>              
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Contact Us</head>
                
                <list>
                    <item>Contact us: <ref target="mailto:winnifredeatonarchive@gmail.com">winnifredeatonarchive@gmail.com</ref></item>
                    <item>Youtube: <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCfs9T99vknkqhx3X2Jj6ZGw">https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCfs9T99vknkqhx3X2Jj6ZGw</ref></item>
                </list>
                
            </div>
            
            <div>
                
                
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
