<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="acknowledgements">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JLC1">Jean Lee Cole</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change when="2020-08-05" who="pers:MC1" status="published">fixed Loyola and Academy of Motion Picture details.</change><change when="2020-08-01" who="pers:MC1" status="published">wrote content.</change>
            <change when="2019-07-30" who="pers:MC1" status="published">wrote content.</change>
            <change when="2019-07-13" who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <div>
                    
                    <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive would not have been possible without the creativity and support of many institutions and individuals. We wish to thank the University of British Columbia, Loyola University Maryland, and the University of Victoria for their sustained support of this project. We also gratefully acknowledge the Social Sciences and Humanities Council of Canada (www.ssshrc.ca) and UBC’s Department of English Language and Literatures. Special thanks to Susan Brown and Dean Irvine for DH support and inspiration, to Martin Holmes and Stewart Arneil for their e-hospitality, and to Megan Meredith Lobay (Advanced Research Computing, UBC), Eka Grguric (Research Commons, UBC Library), and Ricardo Serrano (Arts ISIT, UBC) for helping us navigate UBC’s DH support infrastructure. Eternal gratitude to Dr. Serina Patterson, web designer extraordinaire.</p>
                        
                        <p>We also would like to thank Winnifred Eaton Babcock Reeve descendants Diana Birchall, Elizabeth Rooney, Frank Rooney, and Eileen Hathaway for their generosity, interest, and shared stories about their inspiring ancestor. Winnifred Eaton Babcock Reeve scholars from around the world, particularly Karen Skinazi, Jennifer Harris, Dominika Ferens, and Shaun Hunter, also generously contributed photographs, facts, scans, critical input and ideas. </p>
                         <p>This site would not have been possible without around-the-clock service by UBC interlibrary loans librarians before and during the COVID pandemic and the generous loan of materials from the following libraries and collections:
                        Special Collections at the University of Calgary Library, Hathi Trust, Google Books, Project Gutenberg, American Periodicals, Library of Congress, Free Library of Philadelphia, New Hampshire Libraries, Newberry Library, Schlesinger Library at Harvard University, the Winterthur Library, the University of Illinois-Chicago Library, the Center for Research Libraries, Perry Castañeda Library at University of Texas-Austin, Yale University Libraries, Rauner Library at Dartmouth College, Koerner Library at the University of British Columbia, Anderson Library at the University of Minnesota, Anderson Library at the University of Michigan Library, and the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences.
                       </p>
                </div>
    
                
                
                
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
