<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="contribute">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Contribute</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change who="pers:JT1" when="2021-09-08" status="published">Added edits from MC.</change>
            <change when="2020-09-22"
                who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Contribute</head>
            <div>
                <p>Eventually, each text included in the Archive will be preceded by a peer-reviewed headnote of 75-100 words that will provide some sense of the theme, style and/or significance of that text and note any unusual features, in order to help a curious reader decide whether or not to read that particular text. Each of the Featured Items on the <ref target="doc:About">About</ref> page currently has a headnote. Together, they give a sense of the <q>headnote</q> genre. Please email the director about texts you might be interested in writing headnotes for. When you’ve drafted a headnote, please email a Word Doc of the headnote without any author identification to the director. There is no particular deadline. Groups of headnotes will be sent out for peer review every few months and you may be asked to revise in response to these reviews.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="contribute_package">
                <head>Download Contributor Package</head>
                <p>Below is a list of texts that have not yet been transcribed. Select the text(s) that you would like to transcribe below and click the <q>Download</q> button to download an encoding package for that text, which will include:
                    <list>
                        <item>The facsimile of the document</item>
                        <item>The TEI XML files</item>
                        <item>The RelaxNG schema</item>
                        <item>A custom oXygen project</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>To transcribe a text, you must have the software tool oXygen installed on your computer. UBC and other libraries have a license for this tool. Once you have installed oXygen and downloaded the appropriate encoding package, unzip the package file somewhere on your computer (i.e. in your <code>Documents</code> folder) and then open the <code>wea_encoder.xpr</code> file. On some systems, this might be as simple as double-clicking the file, which should open and load it within oXygen automatically; if that does not work, then open oXygen, and then click <q>Open New Project</q> and open the <code>wea_encoder.xpr</code> file.</p>
                <divGen xml:id="contribute_package_texts"/>
            </div>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
