<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="contribute">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Contribute</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change when="2020-09-22"
                who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Contribute</head>
            <div>
                <p>Eventually, each text in the Archive will be preceded by a peer-reviewed headnote of 75-100 words that will provide some sense of the theme, style and/or significance of the text, note any unusual features, in order to help a curious reader decide whether or not to read this particular text. Each of the Featured Items on the <ref target="doc:About">About</ref> page has a headnote. Together, they give a sense of the <q>headnote</q>genre. Please email the director about texts that interest you. When you’ve written a headnote, please email a Word Doc of the headnote without any author identification to the director. There is no particular deadline. We will send a group of headnotes out for peer review every few months.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="contribute_package">
                <head>Download Contributor Package</head>
                <p>Below are a list available that are not yet transcribed. Select the texts that you would like to transcribe below and click the <q>Download</q> button to download an encoding package that includes:
                    <list>
                        <item>The facsimiles for the document</item>
                        <item>The TEI XML files</item>
                        <item>The RelaxNG schema</item>
                        <item>A custom oXygen project</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>To transcribe these documents, you must have oXygen installed on your computer. Once the package is downloaded, unzip the file somewhere on your computer (i.e. in your <code>Documents</code> folder) and then open the <code>wea_encoder.xpr</code> file. On some systems, this might be as simple as double-clicking the file, which should open and load it within oXygen automatically; if that does not work, then open oXygen, and then click <q>Open New Project</q> and open the <code>wea_encoder.xpr</code> file.</p>
                <divGen xml:id="contribute_package_texts"/>
            </div>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
