<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="legal">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Legal Information</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-06-30" status="published">Proofread</change><change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-06-21" status="readyForProof">Wrote technical content and added content from MC. Set to ready for proof.</change>
            <change when="2019-02-19"
                who="pers:JT1" status="empty">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Legal</head>
            <div>
                <head>Texts and Transcriptions</head>
                <p>No explicit permission is required to use the Winnifred Eaton Archive materials for personal research, teaching, or other purposes. The majority of materials on this site are governed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode">CC BY 4.0 license</ref>. This means that you are free to use the material for this site for whatever purpose, so long as credit is given to the Winnifred Eaton Archive; each transcription page contains the recommended citation, which can be found in the <q>Credits and Citations</q> block at the top of any page. Many of our texts are adaptations of earlier encoding work housed at the University of Virginia and Emory University; the licensing for each text is embedded within the header of the individual text.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Images</head>
                <p>Information regarding images of periodical publications is located in the  <q>Credits and Citations</q> block at the top of any page. Commercial users should contact the institution listed as holding the original manuscript.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Code and Technical Licensing</head>
                <p>We use open-access software for development and testing of the site. We use:
                <list>
                    <item><ref target="https://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="http://www.saxonica.com/welcome/welcome.xml">Saxon 9HE</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://validator.github.io/validator/">The NU HTML Validator (W3C)</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://relaxng.org/jclark/jing.html">RelaxNG Validator</ref></item>
                </list>
                    Licenses for all libraries can be found in the <ref target="https://github.com/winnifredeatonarchive/wea_data/tree/master/lib">WEA’s Github repository</ref>.
                </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Search</head>
                    <p>Our search functionality builds on work by Martin Holmes and Joey Takeda. The primary search Javascript (<ref target="js/search.js">search.js</ref>) was written by Martin Holmes and subsequently adapted by Joey Takeda. It relies on a <ref target="js/porterStemmer.js">Javascript implementation</ref> of the <ref target="https://tartarus.org/martin/PorterStemmer/">Porter Stemming algorithm</ref>, created by Github user <ref target="https://github.com/kristopolous/Porter-Stemmer">Kristopolous</ref>.</p>
    
                </div>
            </div>     
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
