<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="note_on_language">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Note on Language</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1"/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1"/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1"/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1"/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change when="2022-12-05" who="pers:JT1" status="published">Small fixes (with SL).</change>
            <change when="2022-11-22" who="pers:SL1" status="published">Updated and published note on language page.</change>
            <change when="2022-11-11" who="pers:SL1" status="inProgress">Created note on language page.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>A Note on Harmful and Historical Language</head>
            <p>The Winnifred Eaton Archive (WEA) contains the collected material of a complicated, mixed-race Chinese North American author who appropriated a Japanese persona from the turn-of-the-century through the 1920s. The content featured in this archive explores connections and tensions between classed, gendered, and racialized identities and the social contexts of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries (e.g. North American settler-colonialism, anti-Asian racism, anti-miscegenation, and anti-immigration movements). Eaton lived and worked in Canada, Jamaica, as well as in Cincinnati, Chicago, New York, and Los Angeles. However, the archival content expands beyond these geographic borders and includes images, films, and writings about historically marginalized people, including various immigrant groups, Africans, Asians, and Black and Indigenous people of North America. As such, the WEA contains some digital facsimiles and texts that feature historical language, ideas, and content that is outdated, harmful, and/or offensive. Items in the collection and their content reflect the time period in which they were created and the views of their creator. While this language can provide important insight into the creator and the historical context of their creation, it can also reveal hurtful biases and prejudices and thus may be difficult to view.
            </p>
            <p>The WEA team condemns discrimination and hatred on any grounds, including but not limited to racism, sexism, homophobia, transphobia, and other forms of bigotry. The WEA team believes that it is also important to preserve a record of these views, in order to accurately understand and learn from our past and effect change in the present. In this view, we do not censor our records or prevent people from accessing them, but we strive not to reproduce harmful language in our contextual materials, and will only do so if it is preserved in the historic name of a publication, organization, or legal statute. This is an ongoing process.</p>
        </div>
            <div>
                <head>Sources Consulted</head>
                <list>
                    <item>The American Library Association’s <q><ref target="https://www.ala.org/tools/ethics">Code of Ethics</ref></q> and <q><ref target="https://www.ala.org/advocacy/intfreedom/freedomreadstatement">Freedom to Read Statement</ref></q></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://blackwomenssuffrage.dp.la/harmful-language-statement">The Black Women’s Suffrage Digital Collection</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://idnc.library.illinois.edu/">The Illinois Digital Newspaper Collections</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://bibliotheque-archives.canada.ca/fra/Pages/avis-collection.aspx#shr-pg0">Library and Archives Canada</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://www.nps.gov/long/learn/historyculture/statement-on-harmful-language-in-collections.htm">The Longfellow House Washington’s Headquarters</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://guides.nyu.edu/archival-collections-management/inclusive">New York University Libraries</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://cdm16118.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/custom/harmfullanguage">The Seattle Public Library</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="https://library.pitt.edu/potentially-harmful-archival-language">University of Pittsburgh Library System</ref></item>
                    <item><ref target=" https://www.lib.washington.edu/about/edi/critical-cataloging-and-archival-description">University of Washington Libraries</ref></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

