<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="technical">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Technical Information</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change when="2019-08-27"
                who="pers:MC1" status="published">fixed typos.</change>
            <change when="2019-02-19"
                who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Encoding</head>
                <p>All of our documents are encoded using a small subset of the Text Encoding Initiative P5 schema. A fuller account of our encoding practices is given in our <ref target="docs/index.html">documentation</ref>. Primarily, we have encoded the structure of the texts (divisions, sections, et cetera), page beginnings, quotations, and any variants of <name ref="pers:WE1">Winnifred Eaton</name>’s name. While later phases of the project may involve more rigorous encoding protocols—-like tagging distinct speakers, frequency and directionality of speech acts, settings, images, and marginalia—-our initial goal was to encode the texts to make them readily available and easily readable for those interested in Eaton’s prolific career.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Processing</head>
                <p>All of our processing relies on open-source and open-access technologies. We follow the <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca/principles.html">Endings Principles for Digital Longevity</ref>, and thus all of our pages are built <q>statically</q>, which means that there is no dependence on server side processing.</p>
                <p>All of our processing and source code is open-source and available through our <ref target="https://github.com/winnifredeatonarchive/wea_data">Github repository</ref>.</p>
                <p>All of the pages in the archive are valid XHTML5 and use CSS3 and minimal <q>vanilla</q> Javascript (ES6). All pages should display similarly across any modern browser.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Search</head>
                <p>The WEA has served as a flagship project for the development of <q>staticSearch</q>: a completely client-side search engine build specifically for digital edition and written by Martin Holmes and Joey Takeda. It is currently in active development; the code and documentation can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/projectEndings/staticSearch">Github</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Documentation</head>
                <p>All of the technical and encoding documentation for the WEA can be found <ref target="docs/index.html">here</ref>. This documentation—written entirely within our TEI ODD file (<q>One Document Does It All</q>)—provides instructions for how to build the WEA site locally as well as outlines our encoding practices.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
