<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="timeline">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Biographical Timeline</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JLC1">Jean Lee Cole</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:DC1">Daisy Couture</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-09-06" status="published">added info about George in Cincinnati</change><change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-23" status="published">added parentheses with info for images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-15" status="published">added parentheses with info for images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-14" status="published">added more pointers</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-14" status="published">added pointers</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-12" status="published">added photo details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-10" status="published">added Scarboro house details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-04" status="published">added Grace Harte details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">added Reeve Theatre info</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">updated French street names</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">added film details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">added film details</change>
            <change who="pers:DC1" when="2020-07-30" status="published">added details</change>
            <change who="pers:DC1" when="2020-07-29" status="published">fixed typo</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-22" status="published">added silent film</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-13" status="published">added Orienta Point info</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-20" status="published">fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-19" status="published">added more details, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-19" status="published">added more details, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-08" status="published">added more details, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-04-29" status="published">added more details, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-04-18" status="published">added more details, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-25" status="published">added more images, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-24" status="published">added more images, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-20" status="published">revised file names of images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-18" status="published">added images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-10-07" status="published">revised Authors Association date</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-10-04" status="published">revised Authors Association info</change>
            <change when="2019-07-13" who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Biographical Timeline</head>
            <div xml:id="timeline_content">
                <listEvent>
                    <event when="1839">
                        
                        <p>Eaton’s father, Edward Henry Eaton, born in Macclesfield, Cheshire,
                            England.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1846">
                            <ab type="graphic">
                                <graphic url="media:achuengraceamoySalterportrait.png">
                                    <desc>Portrait of a young Achuen Amoy.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </ab>
                            <p>Eaton’s mother, Achuen Amoy (pictured in the etching above), born in China, perhaps in/near Shanghai. As
                            a young child, she is sold to Chinese acrobat and knife-thrower Tuck Quy
                            (Teh-Kwei) and tours China, the United States, France, England,
                            Scotland, and Ireland with the <q>Chinese Magicians</q> (also known as
                                <q>Chinese Jugglers</q>), beginning in 1851.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1855">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:drurylanebestposter.jpg">
                                <desc>Drury Lane Poster for Chinese Magicians.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>The Chinese Magicians perform at Drury Lane (poster featured above). Achuen Amoy is rescued from her knife-throwing owner Tuck Quy in London’s East End
                            by Christian missionaries just before he and his wife Wang Noo sail for
                            China. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1860">
                        <p>Edward Eaton’s father purchases a chemical manufacturing business.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1861">
                        <p>Achuen Amoy is baptized <q>Grace</q> in London and travels to China to work as a
                            missionary.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1863">
                        <p>Edward Eaton and Achuen Amoy marry more formally at Shanghai’s Trinity Church, after being married on
                            board ship.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1864">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:CEEatonNov191902McCordNotman.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of Charles Edward Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward (pictured above) is born in China. The Eatons return to
                            England soon afterward, settling in Macclesfield. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1865">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:SuiSinFarphotofromAutryCenter.png">
                                <desc>Portrait of Sui Sin Far.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Edith Maude (who later writes under the pseudonym <q>Sui Sin Far</q>, pictured above)
                            born on 15 March in Macclesfield. Edward sails for New York City in May. His
                            wife Grace and the two children sail to New York from Liverpool in June
                            aboard the <q>City of London</q>. Family settles in Jersey City and
                            Edward opens a drug and dye wholesale outfit on Pine Street in New
                            York City.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1867">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:graceh.hartephoto.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of Grace Helen Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen (pictured above) born in Jersey City on 24 January.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1868">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1868RoseSaraKarlBosse.jpg">
                                <desc>Early Portrait of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Eatons sail back to England in February on the <q>Denmark</q> and settle
                            in Bow/Poplar area of London. Winnifred’s sister Sarah (pictured above, on right, with husband Karl Bosse and sister Rose) born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1869">
                        <p>Winnifred’ brother Ernest George born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1871">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                        <graphic url="media:MayChristinaAgnes.jpg">
                            <desc>Portrait of Christiana Agnes Eaton Perrault.</desc>
                        </graphic>
                    </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Christiana Mary <q>Agnes</q> (pictured above with her children) born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1872">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:Montrealmap.jpg">
                                <desc>Late 19th-century Map of Montreal.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Eaton family sails from England back to North America via New York and settles in Montreal. Edward is listed in <title level="m">Lovell’s City Directory</title> as commission merchant, based at 16 St.
                            Sacrament (a centrally located building that includes offices of
                            brokers, mining companies, merchants, and notaries).</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1873">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:MayEatonWinkleman.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of May Eaton Winkleman.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>                        
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister May Darling (pictured above), named after the Darling family who lived next-door, born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1874">
                        <p>Edward listed in <title level="m">Lovell’s City Directory</title> as a clerk with the Grand Trunk
                            Railway. The growing Eaton family settle in working-class French-Canadian
                            neighbourhood of Hochelaga in row housing leased from John Bombreary, at rue d’Iberville. Winnifred’s brother Ernest George dies in February.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1875">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:fig1.png">
                                <desc>Early Portrait of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winifred Lily born August 21, the eighth of fourteen children, two of
                            whom die in childhood. Baptized, with sisters Christiana Mary
                                <q>Agnes</q> and May Darling, at Montreal’s American Presbyterian
                            Church as <q>Lillie Winifred</q>, although she soon drops the
                                <q>Lillie</q> and adds a second ‘n’ to Winifred (Birchall 5). </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1876">
                        <p>Family live at 101 rue d’Iberville, leased from J. Rolland. Edward working as a clerk. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1877">
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother George born. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1879">
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Lawrence born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1880">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:RoseEatonrooney.jpg">
                                <desc>Photograph of Rose Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Winnifred’s sister Rose (pictured above) born. Eatons living at 42 rue Seaver, company housing for Hudon
                            Mills workers.</p>
                    </event>


                    <event when="1881">
                                            
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Hubert born.</p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1882">
                        <p>United States government passes Chinese Exclusion Act limiting immigration to US. Winnifred’s father Edward stops working as clerk, allegedly
                            to devote himself to art career. Family live at 97 rue d’Iberville near Ste.
                            Catherine. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1883">
                        <p>Winnifred’ father Edward Eaton listed in <title level="m">Lovell’s</title> as an <q>artist</q> living at 104 rue Drolet at Roy. Winnifred’s sister Edith working in composing room of the <title level="m">Montreal Star</title>.</p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1884">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1884FlorenceEatonSiblings.jpg">
                                <desc>Florence Eaton with her sisters</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Lawrence dies at age two, possibly of smallpox during the epidemic, and is buried in Mount Royal Cemetery in Montreal. Winnifred’s sister Florence (pictured above, left)
                            born. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1885">
                        <p>Canada passes the Chinese Immigration Act, levying a $50 head tax on each
                            Chinese labourer entering the country.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1886">
                        <p>Gilbert and Sullivan’s light opera <title level="m">The Mikado</title>, a favourite of the Eaton girls, staged in Montreal. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1887">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:BerylEatonbacksaysToGeorgeandMaywithlovefromBerylXmasrooney.jpg">
                                <desc>Photoggraph of Beryl.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Eaton family listed as living at 488 boulevard St. Laurent. Winnifred’s sister Beryl (pictured above) born.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1888">
                        
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward marries Isabelle Carter at Montreal’s St. Bartholomew’s Episcopal Church.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1889">
                       
                        <p>Family living at 610 boulevard St. Laurent, leased from Napoleon Deschamp. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen working as stenographer
                            and typewriter in an office she rents in the Standard Life Building at 157 rue St. Jacques. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1890">
                        <p>Winnifred stays in school until age fifteen, at which time she begins to
                            work (possibly as an apprentice dressmaker). Family living at 180 avenue
                            Cadieux.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1891">
                        <p>Eaton family living at 619 rue St. Urbain, leased from Catharine Mitcheson, widow. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen marries British immigrant
                            journalist-editor Walter Blackburn Harte in Montreal on 20 April and moves to
                            Boston where Harte has been appointed, three months earlier, Assistant Editor of <title level="m">The New England Magazine</title>. Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward and his young family living at 122 rue Crescent. Winnifred’s Japanese-born cousin Alfred Eaton arrested in San Francisco for bribing a
                            Customs Officer to permit his Japanese fiancee and her aunt to land. Alfred’s father, Isaac Eaton, returns to Macclesfield after living
                            for several decades in Japan.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1893">
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Sarah advertises her services as an artist and art teacher in Montreal.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1894">
                        <p>Eaton family living at 828 avenue St. Laurent. Winnifred’s sister Edith opens own stenography
                            office.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1895">
                        <p>Eaton family living at 83 rue de l’Arcade. Winnifred publishes her first serialized story in a Montreal magazine. Winnifred goes to Jamaica as general writer
                            and reporter, covering legislative council meetings, stenography; her
                            fare is paid by the <title level="m">Gall’s Daily News Letter</title>, and her salary includes
                            free board and lodging at Myrtle Bank hotel (owned by Gall). Winnifred
                            stays in Jamaica for about five months.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1896">
                        <p>A poem <ref target="doc:SneerNot1"><title level="a">Sneer Not</title></ref>, by Winnifred Eaton, published in <title level="m">Gall’s Daily
                            News Letter</title>, in March. Winnifred leaves Jamaica, goes to Boston, via the
                            <q>Barnstable</q> in early April. Her father Edward is arrested in New York State in June for smuggling Chinese into the US and he is put in Plattsburgh, NY, prison; he and his accomplice escape and he returns to
                            Montreal in August. Winnifred moves to Cincinnati, where her brother George lives, probably in October. Assumes
                            Japanese persona as <q>Kitishima Taka Hasche</q>, or <q>Kitishina</q>,
                            or <q>Tacki Hashi</q> a Yokohama-born girl whose pen name is <q>Onoto
                                Watanna</q>. In November, publishes her first Japanese-themed story, <ref target="doc:JapaneseGirl1"><title level="a">A Japanese Girl</title></ref>, signed Onoto Watanna, in the <title level="m">Cincinnatti Commercial Tribune</title>, a newspaper that Japanese poseur Lafcadio Hearn contributed to in the 1870s. By November, Winnifred working as chief stenographer in Cincinnati, probably at the Commercial McKinley Club, during the 1896 presidential campaign.
                            Winnifred’s sister Edith assumes Winnifred’s <title level="m">Gall’s Newsletter</title>
                            job in Jamaica beginning in December.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1897">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:Onoto3.jpg">
                                <desc> Photograph of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred (pictured above) settles in Chicago, probably in May. Does stenographic work in the stockyards, probably for the soap department of Philip Armour and Company, and writes. In September, she claims to be heading to Alaska with
                            the Woman’s Alaska Gold Club, a group with 150 members founded by Chicago patent lawyer Florence King, to pan for gold. Sister Edith returns to North America, probably to Montreal, from Jamaica in April or May.
                        </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1898">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1898evrymonth.jpg">
                                <desc>Article and portrait from Ev’ry Month.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Onoto Watanna’s work prompts notices in numerous literary publications including <title level="m">Ev’ry
                            Month</title> and <title level="m">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, many of which Winnifred pastes into her scrapbook (pictured above). As Onoto Watanna, Winnifred writes an <ref target="doc:IntroLoveLyrics1"><title level="a">Introduction</title></ref>
                            to <title level="m">Love Lyrics</title>, a book of poems by her friend Chicago journalist Frank
                            Putnam. Publishes stories in Chicago magazines such as <title level="m">American Home
                                Journal</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s Home Journal</title>, and <title level="m">Carter’s Monthly</title>. Nephew Horace
                            Blackburn Harte is born to Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen. Winnifred’s sister
                            May moves to San Francisco. Winnifred’s sister Edith also moves west, first to San Francisco, then to Los Angeles.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1899">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1901PortraitfromNotesofaBookman_HarpersWeekly45_Dec211901_1300.bmp">
                                <desc>Portrait of Eaton as Onoto Watanna.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Publishes short stories in <title level="m">Chicago Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Puritan Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s
                            Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, and <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s Popular Monthly</title>;
                            non-fiction in <title level="m">Book News</title>, the <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title> and the <title level="m">St. Louis Dispatch</title>; and poetry in the <title level="m">Christian-Science Monitor</title>.
                            Claims to have published in Japanese magazines <title level="m">Kokumin-no-Tomi</title> and
                            <title level="m">Hansei Zasshi</title> although none of these publications has been located. Publishes her first novel <ref target="doc:MissNumeJapaneseRomance1"><title level="m">Miss Nume of Japan</title></ref> (Rand &amp; McNally),
                            a controversial story of interracial romance. This publication makes her
                            the first person of Asian descent to publish a novel in the U.S. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen’s husband Walter Blackburn Harte dies in New York on June 8, probably from amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1900">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1900Chicagocensus.jpg">
                                <desc>1900 Chicago Census.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>According to the 1900 Census (pictured above), Winnifred boards at 3105 Groveland Avenue in Chicago, a house owned by feminist Dr. Helen R. Kellogg. Meets and becomes close friends with Japanese poet
                            Yone Noguchi, who visits Chicago for several weeks after living in California for seven years, where he met San Francisco bohemians including Gelett Burgess, Adeline Knapp, Blanche Partington, Ina Coolbrith, Edwin Markham, Joaquin Miller, and Charles Warren Stoddard. Noguchi uses Winnifred’s address as his Chicago mailing address. Winnifred publishes stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>,
                            <title level="m">Conkey’s</title>, and <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, and serializes a novel (<title level="m">The Old Jinrikisha</title>) in
                            <title level="m">Conkey’s</title>. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen and her son Horace visit both Eaton and Harte relatives in England.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1901">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:PersianCombingJackets.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of Winnifred Eaton as Onoto Watanna.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>         
                        <p>Winnifred moves to New York,where her sister Grace Helen works as a legal secretary. While writing and modeling for the Women’s Pages of the <title level="m">Brooklyn Eagle</title>, (pictured above), beginning as early as February, Winnifred meets writer-journalist
                            Bertrand Whitcomb Babcock, whom she marries July 16, 1901 in New York.
                            Winnifred claims to have worked as private secretary to Frank Munsey but quit once she started selling her fiction. Publishes stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, <title level="m">Harper’s
                                Monthly</title>, <title level="m">The Idler</title>, and <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, also releasing novel <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6"><title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title></ref> (Harper and Brothers), which she claims sold 200,000 copies.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1902">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1902Watannaillustrationandjapanesesignature.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait and Signature from Frontispiece of The Wooing of Wistaria.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Publishes another novel, <ref target="doc:WooingOfWistaria14"><title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title></ref> (the frontispiece of which is pictured above), as well as
                            various stories and non-fiction articles in <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, New York’s 
                            <title level="m">Metropolitan Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Harper’s Monthly</title>, <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, and
                            <title level="m">Critic</title>. Accuses playwright David Belasco of stealing her characters and incidents from <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> and <title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title> in his
                                new Japanese play <title level="m">The Darling of the Gods</title>. Belasco sues Winnifred for libel.
                            She is arrested but quickly released on bail (Birchall 79).
                            Winnifred’s brother Hubert drowns in the St. Lawrence River.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1903">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1903JNBroadway.jpg">
                                <desc> Japanese Nightingale on Broadway.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>William Young’s adaptation of <title level="m">A
                            Japanese Nightingale</title> (pictured above) opens at Broadway’s Daly’s Theater to scathing reviews. The play
                            runs for only forty-four performances on Broadway but is later successfully staged across the continent. Winnifred and Babcock’s first child, Perry, is born June 23. The family are living at 2445 Grand Avenue in Fordham Heights. Winnifred
                            publishes in <title level="m">Century Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">New
                                Metropolitan Magazine</title>, and <title level="m">Current Literature</title>. She also publishes a
                            novel, <ref target="doc:HeartOfHyacinth1"><title level="m">The Heart of Hyacinth</title></ref> (Harper and Brothers). Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen and her son Horace move to Chicago where Grace Helen works as stenographer while attending Law School.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1904">
                        <p>Winnifred is accused by Professor John Van Cleve of reproducing a sonnet by him in <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> without
                            attributing it to him. Winnifred denies the accusation, claiming sole
                            authorship of the sonnet, and Van Cleve eventually drops the case.
                            Winnifred and Babcock’s second child, Bertie, is born September 29 while the family are living on 183rd Street in Fordham Heights.
                            Russo-Japanese War creates further demand for Winnifred’s writings on
                            various aspects of Japanese culture. She publishes stories and
                            non-fiction in <title level="m">Woman’s Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">New Metropolitan Magazine</title>, and
                            <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, as well as two novels: <ref target="doc:DaughtersOfNijo1"><title level="m">Daughters of Nijo</title></ref>
                            (MacMillan) and <ref target="doc:LoveOfAzalea4"><title level="m">The Love of Azalea</title></ref> (Dodd, Mead, &amp; Co). Reviews,
                            beginning with a review of <ref target="doc:DaughtersOfNijo1"><title level="m">Daughters of Nijo</title></ref> in the <title level="m">Baltimore Sun</title>, begin to
                            suggest that Winnifred is not entirely or even half Japanese.</p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1905"> <ab type="graphic">
                        <graphic url="media:1905twaindinner.jpg">
                            <desc> 70th Birthday Party for Mark Twain in New York City.</desc>
                        </graphic>
                    </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred attends 70th birthday party (pictured above) for her friend, author Mark Twain. Family live, with three female servants, at 146 Walton Avenue in Long Island’s Orienta Point, later known as <q>Hollywood in the East</q> because it was considered a desirable neighborhood by movie stars such as Lillian and Dorothy Gish and filmmakers such as D. W. Griffiths. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1906">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:na-4320-8WEandDorisonsleigh.png">
                                <desc>Portrait of Winnifred Eaton and Doris.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>     
                        <p>Winnifred and Babcock’s third child, Doris (pictured above with Winnifred), born. Winnifred publishes <ref target="doc:JapaneseBlossom1"><title level="m">A Japanese Blossom</title></ref>.</p></event>
                    
                    <event when="1907">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:na-4320-14WEsSon.png">
                                <desc>Photograph of Charley.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Yone Noguchi rebukes Eaton for her masquerade in an article. Writing as <q>Winnifred Mooney</q>, Winnifred begins to try to publish works that are not on a Japanese theme or signed <q>Onoto Watanna</q>. Winnifred publishes an Irish comedy, <ref target="doc:DiaryOfDelia5"><title level="m">The Diary of Delia</title></ref>                  
                            (Doubleday, Page and Company). Fourth child, Charley (pictured above), is born. Profiles
                            of <q>Onoto Watanna</q>begin to claim that her mother is part Chinese and part
                            Japanese.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1908">
                        <p>Winnifred’s play <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> is staged at Winnipeg’s Theatre.</p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1909">
                        <p> Winnifred’s son Bertie dies, weeks before his fourth birthday, from convulsions and heart failure
                            caused by encephalitis. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1911">
                        <p>Winnifred’s eldest brother, Edward Charles dies of accidental gunshot
                            wound in Montreal, while sleeping. Her sisters Edith and Florence working as stenographers and living with family at 1737 rue Mance.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1912">
                        <p>Winnifred publishes <ref target="doc:HonorableMissMoonlight1"><title level="m">The Honorable Miss Moonlight</title></ref> (Harper Brothers).
                            Her sister Edith, under pen name <q>Sui Sin Far</q>, publishes a collection of stories about Chinese and diasporic Chinese entitled <title level="m">Mrs. Spring Fragrance</title>. Her sister Grace Helen, after studying at Chicago-Kent College of Law, qualifies for the Illinois bar and begins a career specializing in real estate law, particularly landlord-tenant law.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1914">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1914EdithGrave.jpg">
                                <desc> Edith Eaton’s gravestone in Montreal.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Edith dies April 7 of heart disease in Montreal and is buried in Mount Royal Cemetery (gravestone pictured above). Winnifred
                            co-authors <ref target="doc:ChineseJapaneseCookbook1"><title level="m">A Chinese Japanese Cookbook</title></ref> with her sister Sara
                            Eaton Bosse. Winnifred’s works begin to be optioned by filmmakers such
                            as Selig Polyscope Company in Chicago.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1915">
                        <p>Winnifred’s father Edward is arrested again for smuggling Chinese into New York State but he dies of cancer before going to trial. Winnifred anonymously publishes
                            <ref target="doc:Me1"><title level="m">Me</title></ref>, a fictionalized memoir of her early career in Jamaica and Chicago, first in
                            monthly installments in <title level="m">Century</title>, and then as <ref target="doc:Me6"><title level="m">Me: A Book of Remembrance</title></ref>. After completing
                            <title level="m">Me: A Book of Remembrance</title>, Winnifred writes first two chapters of silent film <ref target="doc:GloriasRomance1"><title level="m">Gloria’s
                                Romance</title></ref> as an entry in a <title level="m">Chicago Tribune</title> contest and wins the $10000 prize.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1916">
                        <p>In eight monthly installments, <title level="m">Hearst’s Magazine</title> serializes <ref target="doc:Marion2"><title level="m">Marion: The Story of an Artist’s Model</title></ref>, based on Winnifred’s sister Sara’s biography. It is
                            published anonymously by <q>Herself and the author of <title level="m">Me</title></q>. Winnifred
                            goes to Reno and divorces Babcock. She finds it difficult to write afterward.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1917">
                        <p>Winnifred’s divorce from Babcock granted February 3. She gains full custody of her three         children and marries Francis (Frank) Reeve, an American businessman who owns a New
                            York tugboat firm, in Greenwich, Connecticut in April. They move to
                            Calgary, Alberta, then to a farm in Beddington, a village north of Calgary. Winnifred begins to publish in Canadian magazines. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1918">
                        <p> Frank buys the 4000-hectare Bow View Ranch, <q>a mecca for all aspiring fishermen and hunters</q>, near Morley, Alberta, 60 kilometers west of Calgary, and he and Winnifred relocate there with the children. <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> is made into a silent film starring Fannie Ward as Yuki, W. E. Lawrence as John Bigelow, and Japanese actor, newspaper editor, and Vitagraph technical director Aoyama Yukio as Taro. Her story <ref target="doc:FiveThousandDollar1"><title level="a">$5000 Reward</title></ref> also made into a silent film.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1919">
                        <p>Publishes a serialized novel <ref target="doc:OtherPeoplesTroubles"><title level="m">Other People’s Troubles: An Antidote to Your Own</title></ref> in Alberta’s <title level="m">Farm and Ranch Review</title>.</p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1920">
                       
                        <p>Winnifred rents a small house at 1737 26th Avenue West, Calgary, in order to have a <q>room of her own</q> in which to write. She returns to writing <q>as if I had turned on a mental faucet</q> and writes <ref target="doc:SunnySan1"><title level="m">Sunny-San</title></ref>, her first Japanese-themed work in over 6 years, in five weeks. Her children board at Calgary’s Mount Royal College and Western Canadian College. Winnifred begins to write fiction set in Alberta. </p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1921">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1920sinCaliforniaGlenbow.jpg">
                                <desc>Photograph of Eaton in Japanese dress in California.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred reads her complete story <ref target="doc:Sinners1"><title level="a">Sinners</title></ref> aloud at Canadian Women’s Press Club luncheon in Calgary after the magazine in which she had published the first instalment folds. Attends a talk by John Murray Gibbon (founding president of Canadian Authors Association), an event that turns into a founding meeting of the Calgary branch of the Canadian Authors Association. Winnifred is elected Vice President of the branch. Works as screenwriter, title writer, literary advisor, and scenario
                            editor for Universal and Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer intermittently between 1921 and 1930. Winnifred adapts Wilbur Daniel Steel’s play <title level="m">Ropes</title> for the silent feature film <ref target="doc:FalseKisses1"><title level="m">False Kisses</title></ref> (Universal Pictures) and receives her first screenplay credit.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1922">
                         <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:na-4320-9WEatRanch.png">
                                <desc>Winnifred Eaton Reeve at Alberta Ranch.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s mother Grace dies in New York City while Winnifred is visiting. Winnifred publishes <ref target="doc:SunnySan1"><title level="m">Sunny-San</title></ref>,
                            her first Japanese novel in ten years, in both UK and North America, with the help of her friend and literary agent, fellow Calgarian author and feminist Nellie McClung. Winnifred lives with husband on Bow View Ranch but also rents house at 902 20th Avenue West in Calgary (pictured above) where she can write. Winnifred attends Canadian Authors Association meetings and convention in Ottawa and lobbies federal Minister of Justice about updating the Canadian copyright act.  </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1923">
                        <p>Publishes <ref target="doc:Cattle1"><title level="m">Cattle</title></ref> in Great Britain first. Elected President of the Calgary branch of the Canadian Author Association. Organizes Calgary’s <q>Book Week</q>. Rents house owned by Sam Nickle with a fabulous view of downtown Calgary at 330 Scarboro Avenue until at least April. Depression in cattle prices due to American tariffs nearly ruins her husband Frank and makes it difficult for her to continue to afford <q>a room of her own</q> in Calgary. Assists in the founding of, and named first honorary President of, Calgary’s Little Theatre.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1924">
                        <p> Publishes <ref target="doc:Cattle2"><title level="m">Cattle</title></ref> (W. J. Watt) in Canada and the US under her married name: Winifred
                            Eaton Reeve. Icelandic-Canadian author Laura Salverson publishes a critical review of it in January. Winnifred reacts by accusing Salverson of paying for a positive review of her own novel, <title level="m">Viking Heart</title>. Canadian poet Bliss Carman gives a recital of his poetry in Calgary. Alberta is in the middle of a depression. Foreclosure on Bow View Ranch threatened because of collapse of cattle prices. Winnifred negotiates a four-year contract to run Universal
                            Pictures’ East Coast scenario department and be the new story editor
                            (Birchall 155). Universal’s head Carl Laemmle Sr. wants her to encourage her
                            network of literary contacts to write for Universal. Winnifred and children take train to New York in December and live at 593 Riverside Drive. She hopes husband Frank will follow. Winnifred’s son Charley gets job with the <title level="m">New York Mirror</title>, first as copy boy, then Bronx reporter. Winnifred’s daughter Doris elopes. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1925">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1925StudiosUniversal.jpg">
                                <desc> Picture of Universal Studios.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Dedicates her final published novel, <ref target="doc:HisRoyalNibs1"><title level="m">His Royal Nibs</title></ref> (W. J. Watt), which she publishes under the signature Winifred
                            Eaton Reeve, to Carl Laemmle Sr.. Over the next seven years, she turns
                            her energies to screenplay writing and commutes between New York, and later Los Angeles, and Alberta. Universal Studios hires her as scenario editor, <q>Editor-in-chief and literary advisor</q>. She spends July through September at Universal’s Hollywood studios (pictured above). Gives lecture at MacDowell Club of Allied Arts in December. Sells film rights to <title level="m">Cattle</title>. Blind Players perform <title level="m">From Far Japan</title>, a dramatic adaptation of Winnifred’s novel <ref target="doc:SunnySan1"><title level="m">Sunny-San</title></ref>. Daughter Doris has son, Paul George Rooney (<q>Tim</q>), then separates from her husband and returns to live with Winnifred in California when the baby is four months old. Francis Reeve sells Bow View Ranch and founds F. F. Reeve and Company, a brokerage firm, in Calgary and invests in what becomes an oil boom in Alberta’s Turner Valley.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1926">
                        <p>Winnifred quits job at Universal Studios in December due to lack of creative
                            license. Her son Perry develops severe mental illness, perhaps schizophrenia,
                            and is eventually committed to a state hospital (DB 167). Winnifred moves to Metro-Goldwyn Meyer where she is
                            given an opportunity to write original screenplays as well as do
                            adaptations.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1927">
                        <p>Winnifred does ghostwriting.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1928">
                         <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:PA38362WinnifredCdnAuthorsAssoc1928.jpg">
                                <desc>Winnifred Eaton Reeve at Canadian Authors Association meeting.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                           
                        <p>Winnifred attends Canadian Authors Association meeting (pictured above). Returns to Universal Studios as a screenwriter rather than as a story
                            editor. Continues to work on silent films but also begins to work on <q>talkies</q>. Begins contributing fiction and interviews to movie
                            magazines.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1929">
                        <p>Winnifred loses all her savings in stock market crash. First Hollywood picture for
                            which she is credited with writing the dialogue--<ref target="doc:MississippiGambler1"><title level="m">Mississippi Gambler</title></ref>--is released. Also credited for writing <ref target="doc:ShanghaiLady1"><title level="m">Shanghai Lady</title></ref>. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1930">
                        <p>Winnifred living in Los Angeles with daughter Doris and grandson. Writes screenplays for
                            <ref target="doc:Undertow1"><title level="m">Undertow</title></ref>, <ref target="doc:YoungDesire1"><title level="m">Young Desire</title></ref>, and <ref target="doc:EastIsWest1"><title level="m">East Is West</title></ref> (Universal). Universal lays her
                            off. Winnifred learns husband Frank has a mistress (Mrs. Margaret Hill) in Calgary. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1931">
                        <p>Frank Reeve files for divorce but he and Winnifred reconcile by August and spend a romantic week at Lake Tahoe.
                            Frank returns to Calgary to end relations with his mistress. Winnifred
                            returns to Calgary. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1932">
                        <p>Winnifred and her husband live in Suite 19, Barnhart Apartments, considered one of the finest apartment buildings in Calgary at the time, located at 1121 6th St. NW Calgary, where she writes <ref target="doc:SecondHoneymoon1"><title level="m">Second Honeymoon</title></ref>. </p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1933">
                        <p>Winnifred at work on novel about Calgary’s economy called <ref target="doc:BoomCity1"><title level="m">Boom City</title></ref>. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1935">
                        <p>Daughter Doris, after ten years in Hollywood, moves back to Calgary with young son Paul and works as stenographer for her stepfather Frank until his death in 1956.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1936">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1936FrankOil.jpg">
                                <desc> A picture of Frank in the oil fields.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred and her husband live at 1205 19th Ave. SW, where Winnifred writes <ref target="doc:SinsFathers1"><title level="m">Sins of the Fathers</title></ref>. Frank’s oil investments do well and he (pictured above, centre) becomes one of the wealthiest men in the province.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1937">
                        <p>Winnifred continues to be a member of the Canadian Authors Association, Calgary branch, executive committee.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1938">
                        <p>Frank named President and Managing Director of Commonwealth Drilling Company and named Vice-President of Commoil. Frank, his stepdaughter Doris Rooney, and her son Tim cross border at Montana en route to legendary Hollywood hotel, the Hotel Roosevelt, where they plan to stay for three weeks, perhaps to visit Winnifred. In November, in her Calgary home at 801 Royal Avenue, Winnifred hosts a tea for author Laura Salverson--the author she accused in 1924 of paying for a positive review. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1939">
                        <p>Winnifred and Frank buy 801 Royal Avenue, former home of American diplomat, journalist, author James Davidson. Frank serves on board of YMCA  and is member of Glencoe Club and Petroleum Club. In May, Winnifred hosts annual general meeting for Calgary branch of Canadian Authors Association at her home.</p>
                    </event><event when="1944">
                        <p>Winnifred’s son Charley, a writer, now going by the pen name <q>Paul Eaton
                            Reeve</q>, marries Helen Finkelstein.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1945">
                        <p>Winnifred’s only granddaughter, Diana, born to Charley and Helen in December. In the aftermath of World War Two, Winnifred expresses regret
                            for having posed as Japanese. Winnifred writes plays for the Calgary Little Theatre
                            community.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1947">
                        <p>Ex-husband Bertrand Babcock dies of diabetes and alcoholism.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1950">
                        <p>Winnifred and Frank take cruise to Honolulu from Los Angeles in February.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1953">
                        <p>Winnifred being treated for diabetes at the Mayo Clinic. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1954">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1954WEGrave.jpeg">
                                <desc> The gravestone for Frank Reeve and Winnifred Eaton in Calgary.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred dies of heart attack in Butte, Montana, en route with Frank to Calgary
                            from California. She is buried in Queen’s Park Cemetery in Calgary. Her estate is worth $313,000.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1956">
                        <p>Husband Frank Reeve dies.</p>
                    </event>
 
 
                    <event when="1957">
                        <p>Sister Grace Helen dies, 8 February.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1980">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1980ReeveTheatre.jpg">
                                <desc> A picture of the architect rendering of the Reeve Theatre at the University of Calgary.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Reeve Theatre (pictured above) at University of Calgary opens, funded in part by a $1 million donation from the Reeve Foundation founded by Frank Reeve after Winnifred’s death.</p>
                    </event>



                </listEvent>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
