<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="timeline">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Biographical Timeline</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JLC1">Jean Lee Cole</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-25" status="published" >added more images, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-24" status="published" >added more images, fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-20" status="published" >revised file names of images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-18" status="published" >added images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-10-07" status="published" >revised Authors Association date</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-10-04" status="published" >revised Authors Association info</change>
            <change when="2019-07-13" who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Biographical Timeline</head>
            <div xml:id="timeline_content">
                <listEvent>
                    <event when="1839">
                        
                        <p>Eaton’s father, Edward Eaton, born in Macclesfield, Cheshire,
                            England.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1846">
                            <ab type="graphic">
                                <graphic url="media:achuengraceamoySalterportrait.png">
                                    <desc>Portrait of a young Achuen Amoy.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </ab>
                            <p>Eaton’s mother, Achuen Amoy, born in China, perhaps in/near Shanghai. As
                            a young child, she is sold to Chinese acrobat and knife-thrower Tuck Quy
                            (Teh-Kwei) and tours China, the United States, France, England,
                            Scotland, and Ireland with the <q>Chinese Magicians</q> (also known as
                                <q>Chinese Jugglers</q>), beginning in 1851.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1855">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:drurylanebestposter.jpg">
                                <desc>Drury Lane Poster for Chinese Magicians.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Achuen Amoy is rescued from her knife-throwing owner in London’s East End
                            by Christian missionaries just before he and his wife Wang Noo sail for
                            China. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1861">
                        <p>Achuen Amoy is baptized <q>Grace</q> in London and travels to China to work as a
                            missionary.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1863">
                        <p>Edward Eaton marries Achuen Amoy in Shanghai more formally, after being married on
                            board ship.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1864">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:CEEatonNov191902McCordNotman.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of Charles Edward Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Edward Charles born in China. Eatons return to
                            England soon afterward, settling in Macclesfield. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1865">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:SuiSinFarphotofromAutryCenter.png">
                                <desc>Portrait of Sui Sin Far.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Sister Edith Maude (who writes under the pseudonym <q>Sui Sin Far</q>)
                            born on 15 March in Macclesfield. Edward sails for New York City in May. His
                            wife Grace and the two children sail to New York from Liverpool in June
                            aboard the <q>City of London</q>. Family settles in Jersey City and
                            Edward opens a drug and dye wholesale outfit on Pine Street in New
                            York.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1867">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:graceh.hartephoto.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of Grace Helen Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Sister Grace Helen born in Jersey City.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1868">
                        <p>Eatons sail back to England in February on the <q>Denmark</q> and settle
                            in Bow/Poplar area of London. Sister Sarah born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1869">
                        <p>Brother Ernest George born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1871">
                        <p>Sister Christiana Mary Agnes born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1872">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:Montrealmap.jpg">
                                <desc>Late 19th-century Map of Montreal.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Eatons sail from England back to New York. Family settle in Montreal. Edward
                            listed in <title level="m">Lovell’s City Directory</title> as commission merchant, based at 16 St.
                            Sacrament (a centrally located building that includes offices of
                            brokers, mining companies, merchants, and notaries).</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1873">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:MayChristinaAgnes.jpg">
                                <desc>Portrait of May Darling Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Sister May Darling born in Montreal.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1874">
                        <p>Edward listed in Lovell’s Directory as a clerk with the Grand Trunk
                            Railway. The growing Eaton family settle in working-class French
                            neighbourhood of Hochelaga in row housing provided for Hudon mill
                            workers, at rue du Iberville. Brother Ernest George dies in February.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1875">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:fig1.png">
                                <desc>Early Portrait of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winifred Lily born August 21, the eighth of fourteen children, two of
                            whom die in childhood. Baptized, with sisters Christiana Mary
                                <q>Agnes</q> and May Darling, at Montreal’s American Presbyterian
                            Church as <q>Lillie Winifred</q>, although she soon drops the
                                <q>Lillie</q> and adds a second ‘n’ to Winifred (Birchall 5). </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1876">
                        <p>Family live at 101 Iberville. Edward working as a clerk. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1877">
                        <p>Brother George born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1879">
                        <p>Brother Lawrence born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1880">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:RoseEatonrooney.jpg">
                                <desc>Photograph of Rose Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Sister Rose born. Eatons living at 42 Seaver, company housing for Hudon
                            Mills workers.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1882">
                        <p>US Chinese Exclusion Act passed. Father stops working as clerk, allegedly
                            to devote himself to art career. Family live at 97 Iberville near St.
                            Catherine. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1884">
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Lawrence dies at age two, possibly in the smallpox
                            epidemic. Buried at Mount Royal Cemetery in Montreal. Sister Florence
                            born. Sister Edith working in composing room of the <title level="m">Montreal Star</title>.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1883">
                        <p>Edward, Artist, listed in <title level="m">Lovell’s</title> as living at 104 Drolet at Roy.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1885">
                        <p>Canada passes the Chinese Immigration Act, levying a $50 head tax on each
                            Chinese labourer entering the country. </p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1887">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:BerylEatonbacksaysToGeorgeandMaywithlovefromBerylXmasrooney.jpg">
                                <desc>Photoggraph of Beryl.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Family listed as living at 488 St. Lawrence. Sister Beryl born.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1889">
                       
                        <p>Family living at 610 St. Lawrence. Sister Grace working as stenographer
                            and typewriter at 157 St. James. Winnifred claims to have published her
                            first story, <q>A Poor Devil</q> in Montreal’s <title level="m">Metropolitan Magazine</title> around this
                            time.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1890">
                        <p>Winnifred stays in school until age fifteen, at which age she is sent to
                            work (possibly as an apprentice dressmaker. Family living at 180
                            Cadieux.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1891">
                        <p>Family living at 619 St. Urbain. Sister Grace Helen marries British immigrant
                            journalist-editor Walter Blackburn Harte in Montreal and moves to
                            Boston where Harte becomes Assistant Editor of <title level="m">The New England Magazine</title>. Cousin Alfred Eaton arrested in San Francisco for bribing a
                            Customs Officer. His father, Winnifred’s uncle Isaac Eaton, returns to Macclesfield after living
                            for several decades in Japan.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1894">
                        <p>Family living at 828 St. Lawrence. Sister Edith opens own stenography
                            office. Sister Sarah working as an artist in Montreal.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1895">
                        <p>Family living at 83 Arcade. Winnifred goes to Jamaica as general writer
                            and reporter, covering legislative council meetings, stenography; her
                            fare is paid by the <title level="m">Gall’s Daily News Letter</title>, and her salary includes
                            free board and lodging at Myrtle Bank hotel (owned by Gall). Winnifred
                            stays in Jamaica for about five months.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1896">
                        <p>A poem <title level="a">Sneer Not</title>, by Winnifred Eaton, published in <title level="m">Gall’s Daily
                            News Letter</title>, in March. Winnifred leaves Jamaica, goes to Boston, via the
                            <q>Barnstable</q>. Moves to Cincinnati. Claims to have been the
                            chief stenographer in Cincinnati during the presidential campaign.
                            Father is arrested in New York State and put in Plattsburgh, NY, prison
                            for smuggling Chinese into US in June; he escapes and returns to
                            Montreal in August. Winnifred’s sister Edith takes her <title level="m">Gall’s Newsletter</title>
                            job in Jamaica beginning in December.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1897">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:Onoto3.jpg">
                                <desc> Photograph of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred settles in Chicago. Does stenographic work and writes. Assumes
                            Japanese persona as <q>Kitishima Taka Hasche</q>, or <q>Kitishina</q>,
                            or <q>Tacki Hashi</q> a Yokohama-born girl whose pen name is <q>Onoto
                                Watanna</q>. In September, she claims to be heading to Alaska with
                            the Woman’s Alaska Gold Club, a group with 150 members, to pan for gold.
                        </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1898">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1898evrymonth.JPG">
                                <desc>Article and portrait from Ev’ry Month.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Attracts attention in numerous literary publications including <title level="m">Ev’ry
                            Month</title> and <title level="m">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>. As Onoto Watanna, she writes the
                            introduction to a book of poems by her friend Chicago journalist Frank
                            Putnam. Publishes stories in Chicago magazines such as <title level="m">American Home
                                Journal</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s Home Journal</title>, and <title level="m">Carter’s Monthly</title>, and New York
                            magazines such as <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s Popular Monthly</title>. Nephew Horace
                            Blackburn Harte is born to Winnifred’s sister Grace. Winnifred’s sister
                            May moves to San Francisco.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1899">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1901PortraitfromNotesofaBookman_HarpersWeekly45_Dec211901_1300.bmp">
                                <desc>Portrait of Eaton as Onoto Watanna.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Publishes short stories in <title level="m">Chicago Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Puritan Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s
                            Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, and <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, and
                            non-fiction in <title level="m">Book News</title>, and poetry in the <title level="m">Christian-Science Monitor</title>.
                            Claims to have published in Japanese magazines <title level="m">Kokumin-no-Tomi</title> and
                            <title level="m">Hansei Zasshi</title> although these publications have not been located. Publishes novel <title level="m">Miss Numè of Japan</title> (Rand &amp; McNally),
                            a controversial story of interracial romance. This publication makes her
                            the first person of Asian descent to publish a novel in the U.S. Sister
                            Grace’s husband Walter Blackburn Harte dies in New York.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1900">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1900Chicagocensus.jpg">
                                <desc>1900 Chicago Census.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred boarding at 3105 Groveland Avenue in Chicago, a house owned by
                            Helen R. Kellogg. Meets and becomes close friends with Japanese poet
                            Yone Noguchi. Publishes stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>,
                            <title level="m">Conkey’s</title>, and <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, and serializes a novel (<title level="m">The Old Jinrikisha</title>) in
                            <title level="m">Conkey’s</title>. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1901">
                        <p>Moves to New York. While working at the <title level="m">Brooklyn Eagle</title>, she meets
                            Bertrand Whitcomb Babcock, whom she marries July 16, 1901 in New York.
                            Publishes stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, <title level="m">Harper’s
                                Monthly</title>, <title level="m">The Idler</title>, and <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, also releasing novel <title level="m">A Japanese
                            Nightingale</title> (Harper and Brothers).</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1902">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1902Watannaillustrationandjapanesesignature.JPG">
                                <desc>Portrait and Signature from Frontispiece of The Wooing of Wistaria.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Publishes another novel, <title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title> (Macmillan) as well as
                            various stories and non-fiction articles in <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, <title level="m">Smart Set</title>,New York’s 
                            <title level="m">Metropolitan Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Harper’s Monthly</title>, <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, and
                                <title level="m">Critic</title>. Accuses playwright David Belasco of plagiarizing her work in his
                                new Japanese play <title level="m">The Darling of the Gods</title>. Belasco sues her for libel.
                            Winnifred is arrested and then quickly released on bail (Birchall 79).
                            Winnifred’s brother Hubert drowns.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1903">
                        <p>Winnifred and Babcock’s first child, Perry, is born June 23. Winnifred
                            publishes in <title level="m">Century Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">New
                                Metropolitan Magazine</title>, and <title level="m">Current Literature</title>. She also publishes a
                            novel, <title level="m">The Heart of Hyacinth</title> (Harper and Brothers). Adaptation of <title level="m">The
                                Japanese Nightingale</title> opens on Broadway to scathing reviews. The play
                            runs for only forty-four performances. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1904">
                        <p>Is accused of plagiarism by Professor John Van Cleve, who claims
                            Winnifred reproduced a sonnet by him in <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> without
                            attributing it to him. Winnifred denies the accusation, claiming sole
                            authorship of the sonnet, and Van Cleve eventually drops the case.
                            Winnifred and Babcock’s second child, Bertie, is born September 29.
                            Russo-Japanese War creates further demand for Winnifred’s writings on
                            various aspects of Japanese culture. She publishes stories and
                            non-fiction in <title level="m">Woman’s Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">New Metropolitan Magazine</title>, and
                            <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, as well as two novels: <title level="m">Daughters of Nijo</title>
                            (MacMillan) and <title level="m">The Love of Azalea</title> (Dodd, Mead, &amp; Co). Reviews,
                            beginning with a review of <title level="m">Daughters of Nijo</title> in the <title level="m">Baltimore Sun</title>, begin to
                            suggest that she is not Japanese.</p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1905"> <ab type="graphic">
                        <graphic url="media:Twainimg010.jpg">
                            <desc> 70th Birthday Party for Mark Twain in New York City.</desc>
                        </graphic>
                    </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred attends 70th birthday party for Mark Twain.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1906">
                        <p>Winnifred and Babcock’s third child, Doris, born. Publishes <title level="m">A Japanese
                            Blossom</title> (Harper Brothers).</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1907">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:na-4320-14WEsSon.png">
                                <desc>Photograph of Charley.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab><p>Winnifred begins to try to publish works pseudonymously that are not on a
                            Japanese theme. Publishes an Irish comedy, <title level="m">The Diary of Delia</title>
                            (Doubleday, Page and Company). Fourth child, Charley, is born. Profiles
                            begin to claim that Onoto Watanna’s mother is part Chinese and part
                            Japanese.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1908">
                        <p>Buys Orient Point house from Mrs. Guy Bates Post. Son Bertie dies,
                            weeks before his fourth birthday from convulsions and heart failure
                            caused by encephalitis. </p>
                    </event>
                    
                    <event when="1911">
                        <p>Winnifred’s eldest brother, Edward Charles, dies of accidental gunshot
                            wound in Montreal.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1912">
                        <p>Winnifred publishes <title level="m">The Honorable Miss Moonlight</title> (Harper Brothers).
                            Sister Edith, under pen name <q>Sui Sin Far</q>, publishes a collection of stories about Chinese and diasporic Chinese entitled <title level="m">Mrs. Spring
                                Fragrance</title>.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1914">
                        <p>Sister Edith dies April 7 of heart disease in Montreal. Winnifred
                            co-authors <title level="m">A Chinese-Japanese American Cookbook</title> with her sister Sara
                            Eaton Bosse. Winnifred’s works begin to be optioned by filmmakers such
                            as Selig Polyscope Company in Chicago.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1915">
                        <p>Winnifred’s father Edward dies of cancer. Winnifred anonymously publishes
                            <title level="m">Me: A Book of Remembrance</title> (Century), a fictionalized memoir, first in
                            monthly installments in <title level="m">Century</title>, and then as a book. After completing
                            Me, Winnifred writes first two chapters of silent film <title level="m">Gloria’s
                                Romance</title>.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1916">
                        <p>In eight monthly installments, <title level="m">Hearst’s Magazine</title> serializes <title level="m">Marion: The
                            Story of an Artist’s Model</title>, based on Sister Sara’s biography. It is
                            published anonymously by <q>Herself and the author of <title level="m">Me</title></q>. Winnifred
                            goes to Reno and divorces Babcock. Unable to write afterward.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1917">
                        <p>Winnifred’s divorce decree granted. She gains full custody of her
                            children and marries Francis (Frank) Reeve, an American businessman who owns a New
                            York tugboat firm, in Greenwich, Connecticut in March. They move to
                            Calgary, Alberta. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1918">
                        <p> <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> made into a silent film starring Fannie Ward as Yuki, W. E. Lawrence as John Bigelow, and Japanese actor, newspaper editor, and Vitagraph technical director Aoyama Yukio as Taro</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1921">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:1920sinCaliforniaGlenbow.jpg">
                                <desc>Photograph of Eaton in Japanese dress in California.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Adapts Wilbur Daniel Steel’s play <title level="m">Ropes</title> for the silent feature film <title level="m">False
                            Kisses</title> (Universal Pictures) and receives her first screenplay credit.
                            Works as screenwriter, title writer, literary advisor, and scenario
                            editor for Universal and Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer between 1921 and 1930.
                            Lives in Los Angeles</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1922">
                         <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:na-4320-9WEatRanch.png">
                                <desc>Winnifred Eaton Reeve at Alberta Ranch.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s mother Grace dies in New York City. Winnifred writes <title level="m">Sunny-San</title>,
                            her first Japanese novel in ten years. She lives with husband on
                            4000-hectare Bow View Ranch. Children attend boarding school in Calgary.
                            Winnifred rents house in Calgary where she can write. Active in Calgary Little
                            Theatre. Founding Member of Calgary chapter of Canadian Authors
                            Association. Serves as president of the Calgary branch of the Canadian Author Association</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1924">
                        <p>Winnifred publishes <title level="m">Cattle</title> (W. J. Watt) under her married name: Winifred
                            Eaton Reeve. New tariff law causes cattle business to be less
                            profitable. Reeve loses money with ranch and tries real estate in
                            Calgary. Winnifred moves back to New York in December to run Universal
                            Pictures’ East Coast scenario department and be the new story editor
                            (Birchall 155). Universal’s Carl Laemmle Sr. wants her to encourage her
                            network of literary contacts to write for Universal. Winnifred takes all
                            three children with her, leaving husband Frank behind in Calgary.
                            Daughter Doris elopes. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1925">
                        <p>Dedicates <title level="m">His Royal Nibs</title> (W. J. Watt), which she publishes under Winifred
                            Eaton Reeve, to Carl Laemmle Sr.. Over the next seven years, she turns
                            her energies to screenplay writing. Universal Studios hires her as West
                            Coast story/scenario editor and transfers her to Los Angeles in late
                            1925. Works as Universal’s <q>Editor-in-chief and literary advisor</q>.
                            Daughter Doris has son, Paul George Rooney (<q>Tim</q>), then separates
                            from her husband and returns to live with Winnifred in California.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1926">
                        <p>Winnifred quits job at Universal in December due to lack of creative
                            license. Son Perry develops severe mental illness, perhaps schizophrenia
                            and is hospitalized. Winnifred moves to Metro-Goldwyn Meyer where she is
                            given an opportunity to write original screenplays as well as do
                            adaptations.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1927">
                        <p>Does ghostwriting.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1928">
                         <ab type="graphic">
                            <graphic url="media:PA38362WinnifredCdnAuthorsAssoc1928.jpg">
                                <desc>Winnifred Eaton at Canadian Authors Association meeting.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                        </ab>
                           
                        <p>Attends Canadian Authors Association meeting. Returns to Universal Studios as a screenwriter rather than as a story
                            editor. Works on both sound and silent films. Begins writing for movie
                            magazines.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1929">
                        <p>Loses all her savings in stock market crash. First Hollywood picture for
                            which she is credited with writing the dialogue--<title level="m">The Mississippi
                                Gambler</title>--is released. Also credited for writing <title level="m">Shanghai Lady</title>. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1930">
                        <p>Winnifred living in Los Angeles with daughter Doris and grandson. Writes screenplays for
                            <title level="m">Undertow</title>, <title level="m">Young Desire</title>, and <title level="m">East is West</title> (Universal). Universal lays her
                            off. Winnifred learns husband Frank has a mistress (Mrs. Hill) and wants
                            a divorce. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1931">
                        <p>Reunites with Frank Reeve. They spend a romantic week at Lake Tahoe.
                            Frank returns to Calgary to end relations with his mistress. Winnifred
                            returns to Calgary. </p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1944">
                        <p>Winnifred’s son Charley, a writer, now going by the pen name Paul Eaton
                            Reeve, marries Helen Finkelstein.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1945">
                        <p>Winnifred’s only granddaughter, Diana, born. Winnifred expressed regret
                            for posing as Japanese. Writes plays for the Calgary Little Theatre
                            community.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1947">
                        <p>Ex-husband Bertrand Babcock dies of diabetes and alcoholism.</p>
                    </event>
                    <event when="1954">
                        <p>Winnifred dies of heart attack in Butte, Montana, en route to Calgary
                            from California.</p>
                    </event>




                </listEvent>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
