<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../sch/wea.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="timeline">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Biographical Timeline</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JLC1">Jean Lee Cole</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:DC1">Daisy Couture</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:JT1">Joey Takeda</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:LW1">Leean Wu</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:LA1">Lillie Adamson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="wdt:docType" target="wdt:docBornDigital"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change who="pers:LA1" when="2026-07-06" status="published">Updated timeline prose and encoded biographical footnotes as editorial pop-up notes.</change>
            <change who="pers:JT1" when="2026-06-15" status="published">Updated figure encoding.</change>
            <change who="pers:SL1" when="2025-01-31" status="published">Corrected factual errors.</change>
            <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-07-06" status="published">added graphic and caption for 1950 and 1952.</change>
            <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-02-01" status="published">Corrected typos.</change>
            <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-02-01" status="published">added graphic and desc of Diana, the granddaughter of Winnifred. Corrected typos.</change>
            <change who="pers:LW1" when="2024-02-01" status="published">added info and corrected
                errors</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2022-01-31" status="published">added info about Christina
                children</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2021-03-31" status="published">added film info</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2021-03-02" status="published">corrected Florence
                birthdate</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-11-19" status="published">added info about mothers
                death and Imperial Press visit</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-09-09" status="published">added info about Scarboro
                home</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-09-06" status="published">added info about George in
                Cincinnati</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-23" status="published">added parentheses with info
                for images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-15" status="published">added parentheses with info
                for images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-14" status="published">added more pointers</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-14" status="published">added pointers</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-12" status="published">added photo details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-10" status="published">added Scarboro house
                details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-04" status="published">added Grace Harte
                details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">added Reeve Theatre
                info</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">updated French street
                names</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">added film details</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-08-03" status="published">added film details</change>
            <change who="pers:DC1" when="2020-07-30" status="published">added details</change>
            <change who="pers:DC1" when="2020-07-29" status="published">fixed typo</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-22" status="published">added silent film</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-07-13" status="published">added Orienta Point
                info</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-20" status="published">fixed typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-19" status="published">added more details, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-19" status="published">added more details, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-05-08" status="published">added more details, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-04-29" status="published">added more details, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-04-18" status="published">added more details, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-25" status="published">added more images, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-24" status="published">added more images, fixed
                typos</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-20" status="published">revised file names of
                images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2020-02-18" status="published">added images</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-10-07" status="published">revised Authors Association
                date</change>
            <change who="pers:MC1" when="2019-10-04" status="published">revised Authors Association
                info</change>
            <change when="2019-07-13" who="pers:JT1" status="published">Created file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Biographical Timeline</head>
            <div xml:id="timeline_content">
                <listEvent>
                    <event when="1839">
                        <p>Eaton’s father, Edward Henry Eaton (pictured above), born September 30 in Macclesfield, Cheshire, England, the eldest son of drysalter and savings bank clerk Edward Downes Eaton and Ellen McDonnell.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">"Death Closes Varied Career: Edward Eaton Lived in Far East before Coming to Montreal." <title level="m">Montreal Gazette</title>, 22 Feb. 1915, p. 4. Folder 16, file 17, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1846">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:achuengraceamoySalterportrait.png">
                                    <desc>Portrait of a young Achuen Amoy.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Eaton’s mother, Achuen Amoy (pictured above), born somewhere in China around 1846. As a young child, she is sold to a Chinese acrobat and tours China, North America, France and the British Isles with the <q>Chinese Magicians</q> beginning in 1852.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Mary Chapman et al., "Following Achuen Grace Amoy and the Chinese Magicians," <title level="m">ArcGIS StoryMaps</title>, <ref target="https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/90fb3ac0df6f434d9953d2938bd25e4a">storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/90fb3ac0df6f434d9953d2938bd25e4a</ref>. See also Joseph Salter, <title level="m">The Asiatic in England: Sketches of Sixteen Years’ Work Among Orientals</title>, Seeley, Jackson, and Halliday, 1873, pp. 168–170. The etching appears in Salter, on the page between pp. 170 and 171.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1855">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:drurylanebestposter.jpg">
                                    <desc>Drury Lane Poster for Chinese Magicians.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>The Chinese Magicians perform at Drury Lane (poster featured above).<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Theater bill for the Theatre Royal Drury Lane, London, 1854, printed by R. S. Francis, London.</note> Achuen Amoy is rescued from her knife-throwing owner in London’s East End by Christian missionaries just before he and his wife sail back to China.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Salter, <title level="m">Asiatic in England</title>, p. 169.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1860">
                        <p>Edward Eaton’s father purchases a chemical manufacturing business.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1861">
                        <p>Achuen Amoy is listed as a visitor and Naturalized British Subject and dressmaker in a London home on the 1861 census.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Listed as “Achina Amoy,” 18-year-old visitor and dressmaker at 188 Waterloo Road, <title level="m">British Census Returns of England and Wales, 1861</title>, RG 9, piece 348, folio 102, p. 10, GSU roll 542619.</note> Edward Eaton has been sent to Shanghai on behalf of his father’s drysalter business by 1861.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Ships associated with Edward Eaton and/or Edward Eaton and Co. appear in Shanghai’s harbour as early as January 1862. See <title level="m">North China Herald</title>, 4 Jan. 1862, p. 2.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1862">
                        <p>Achuen Amoy is baptized Achuen Grace Trefusis on August 31 at St. Paul’s Church in Southwark, south London.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Achnen [sic] Grace Trefusis,” baptism, St. Paul, Westminster Bridge Road, Southwark, Surrey, 31 Aug. 1862, p. 26, FHL 291758.</note> She then sails to China to serve as a medical missionary, one of the few unmarried women missionaries to venture to China without a missionary husband or other family member.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Achuen Grace Trefusis, undated letter to Joseph Salter, qtd. in Salter, <title level="m">The Asiatic in England</title>, p. 169.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1863">
                        <p>According to Winnifred, Edward and Achuen Amoy meet in Shanghai when Amoy tends to Edward’s fever. Edward and Achuen Amoy marry on 7 November in Shanghai’s Trinity Church.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Marriage registry for Edward Eaton and Grace Eaton, late Trefusis, 7 Nov. 1863, General Register Office: Foreign Registers and Returns, RG 33, piece 12, The National Archives of the UK, Kew, Surrey, England.</note> Winnifred’s mother henceforth known as Mrs. Grace Eaton.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1864">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:CEEatonNov191902McCordNotman.jpg">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Charles Edward Eaton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Edward Charles (pictured above) is born in China in May.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, citing White-Parks, <title level="m">Sui Sin Far</title>, p. 14. Photograph of Charles Edward Eaton by William Notman, 19 Nov. 1901, Notman Photographic Archives, McCord-Stewart Museum, Montreal.</note> Eatons return to England later that year.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1865">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:SuiSinFarphotofromAutryCenter.png">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Sui Sin Far.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Edith Maud (pictured above),<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Black-and-white photographic portrait of Sui Sin Far by [George H.] Braas, Seattle, 1900, gelatin silver print, P.36157, Braun Research Library Collection, Autry Museum of the American West, Los Angeles, gift of Mr. Charles F. Lummis.</note> who later writes under the pseudonym <q>Sui Sin Far</q>, is born on 15 March at Upton Cottage, a house Edward’s parents have rented on the outskirts of Macclesfield, Cheshire.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptismal certificate for Edith Maud Eaton, 5 Apr. 1865, St. Michael’s Church, p. 11, Parish Registers, reference P 85/2/12, Cheshire West and Chester Council, Cheshire, England. Edith was baptized a second time in New Jersey; see “New Jersey, U.S., Births and Christenings Index, 1660–1931,” database online, Ancestry.com Operations, 2011, FHL 4210084.</note> Edward sails for New York from Liverpool in cabin class on the <title level="m">City of London</title> in late April.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">Passenger Lists of Vessels Arriving at New York, New York, 1820–1897</title>, Microfilm Publication M237, 675 rolls, arrival New York, 1865; microfilm roll 250, line 17, list number 304, and microfilm roll 252, line 6, list number 495.</note> Grace Eaton and two children follow in June, sailing in cabin class aboard the <title level="m">City of London</title>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">Passenger Lists of Vessels Arriving at New York, New York, 1820–1897</title>, Microfilm Publication M237, arrival New York, 1865; microfilm roll 250, line 17, list number 304, and microfilm roll 252, line 6, list number 495.</note> Family settles in Hudson, NJ (newly named Jersey City)<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">In Sui Sin Far, “Leaves from the Mental Portfolio of an Eurasian,” <title level="m">The Independent</title>, vol. 66, 21 Jan. 1909, p. 125, Edith Eaton says the family lived in Hudson, NY, but other records locate the family in Hudson, New Jersey, later incorporated into Jersey City, suggesting that her handwritten “NJ” was misprinted as “NY.” See also birth certificate for Grace Helen Eaton, 24 Jan. 1867.</note> and Edward opens a drug and dye wholesale outfit on Pine Street, a few blocks from Wall Street in New York.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">A city directory for 1866–67 lists Edward and Isaac Eaton as “imp[orters]” at 66 Pine St. in New York. <title level="m">New York City Directory, 1866–1867</title>, p. 297.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1867">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:graceh.hartephoto.jpg">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Grace Helen Eaton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen (pictured above)<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Photograph of Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen Eaton (later Grace Eaton Harte), “Harte, Grace Eaton: Women Lawyers’ Journal [biographies],” <title level="m">Women Lawyers’ Journal</title>, Summer 1947, item CU112046864. Courtesy of the Canadian Literary and Cultural Archives, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, Libraries and Cultural Resources Digital Collections, University of Calgary.</note> is born in Jersey City, NJ on 24 January.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1868">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1868RoseSaraKarlBosse.jpg">
                                    <desc>Early Portrait of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Eatons sail back to England, in cabin class aboard the S.S. <title level="m">Denmark</title> in February.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">"Passengers Sailed." <title level="m">New York Times (1857-1922)</title>, 24 Feb., 1868, p. 8.<title level="m">ProQuest</title>, <ref target="https://proquest.com/newspapers/passengers-sailed/docview/92430543/se-2">proquest.com/newspapers/passengers-sailed/docview/92430543/se-2</ref>.</note> Winnifred’s sister Sarah, sometimes spelled <q>Sara</q> (pictured above, on right, with husband Karl Bosse and sister Rose),<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Photograph of Rose and Sara Eaton with Sara’s husband, Karl Bosse, reproduced in Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, illustrations following p. 90 (captioned “Winnifred’s sisters Rose and Sara, showing a Japanese influence in the 1890s, with Sara’s husband, Karl Bosse”).</note> born, probably in July in the textile town of Blackburn, north of Manchester.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">The National Archives, Kew, London, England, 1871 England Census, Class RG 10, piece 576, folio 44, p. 28, GSU roll 824893.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1869">
                        <p>Winnifred's brother Ernest George born in Didsbury, five miles south of Manchester.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1871">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:MayChristinaAgnes.jpg">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Christiana Agnes Eaton Perrault.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Christiana Mary Agnes (pictured above with her children Henri Laurent and Joseph François Perrault) born 13 October in Bethnal Green, in the Bow/Poplar area of London. Edward working as a clerk.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">The National Archives, Kew, London, England, 1871 England Census, RG 10, piece 576, folio 44, p. 28, GSU roll 824893.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1872">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:Montrealmap.jpg">
                                    <desc>Late 19th-century Map of Montreal.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Eatons sail from England again to New York, this time in steerage aboard the <title level="m">Egypt</title>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">Passenger Lists of Vessels Arriving at New York, New York, 1820–1897</title>, Microfilm Publication M237, roll 363, list no. 828, line 8, Records of the U.S. Customs Service, Record Group 36, National Archives, Washington, D.C., 1872.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1873">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:MayEatonWinkleman.jpg">
                                    <desc>Portrait of May Eaton Winkleman.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>By March, the Eatons have arrived in Montreal.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">Montreal Gazette</title>, 20 Mar. 1873, p. 4; the paper lists “Eaton, Edward” among gentlemen with unclaimed letters at the Montreal Post Office.</note> The growing family live in row housing in the working-class French neighbourhood of Hochelaga. Edward a commission merchant with an office at 16 St. Sacrament. Winnifred’s sister, May Darling Eaton (pictured here), named after the Darling family who lived in the same neighbourhood, born August 26 in Hochelaga, a village east of Montreal. Winnifred’s mother is one of the only Chinese persons living in the city.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1874">
                        <p>Edward a clerk with the Grand Trunk Railway. Winnifred’s five-year-old brother Ernest George dies on 19 February, perhaps of smallpox.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec, Canada, 19 Feb. 1874, p. 52, St. Mark’s Anglican Church. Ernest George Eaton is buried in section L, lot 718, of Mount Royal Cemetery, Montreal.</note> In April, family move to rowhouse leased from John Bombreary on rue d’Iberville in Hochelaga.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1875">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:fig1.png">
                                    <desc>Early Portrait of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred Lillie (pictured here) born August 21, the eighth of fourteen children.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 5.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1876">
                        <p>With sisters Christiana Mary Agnes and May Darling on 28 January 1876 at Montreal’s American Presbyterian Church, Winnifred baptized <q>Lillie Winifred</q>, although she soon drops the <q>Lillie</q> and adds a second ‘n’ to <q>Winifred</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record, American Presbyterian Church, Montreal, 27 Jan. 1876, folio 5, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec.</note> Family lived at 101 Iberville. Edward a clerk.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1877">
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother George born 24 March.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record, American Presbyterian Church, Montreal, 24 Mar. 1877, folio 28, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec.</note> Family rents a modest house opposite the Canadian Northern Quebec Railway yards for $72 plus tax annually, beginning June 1.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1879">
                        <p>Winnifred’s brother Hubert born 21 January.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record, St. Mary’s Anglican Church, Montreal, 2 Apr. 1882, folio 48, p. 94, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1880">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:RoseEatonrooney.jpg">
                                    <desc>Photograph of Rose Eaton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Rose (pictured above) born 16 October.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record, St. Mary’s Anglican Church, Montreal, 2 Apr. 1882, folio 48, p. 95, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec.</note> Eatons living at 42 Seaver, company housing for Hudon Mills workers.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Annette White-Parks, <title level="m">Sui Sin Far / Edith Maude Eaton: A Literary Biography</title>, U of Illinois P, 1995, p. 20.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1882">
                        <p>US passes Chinese Exclusion Act 6 May.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">For background on the Chinese Exclusion Act, signed into law by President Chester A. Arthur on 6 May 1882, see “Chinese Exclusion Act,” <title level="m">Wikipedia: The Free Encyclopedia</title>, Wikimedia Foundation, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_Exclusion_Act">en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_Exclusion_Act</ref>.</note> Family living at 97 rue d’Iberville near Ste. Catherine.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">John Lovell, comp., <title level="m">Lovell’s Montreal Directory for 1883–84: Containing an Alphabetical Directory of the Citizens, a Street Directory, an Advertisers’ Classified Business Directory, and a Miscellaneous Directory</title>, John Lovell &amp; Son, 1883, p. 319, <title level="m">BAnQ numérique</title>, <ref target="https://numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5289999">numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5289999</ref>.</note> Edward stops working as clerk, allegedly to devote himself to art career.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Rather than being listed as a clerk, Edward is listed as an artist. See: John Lovell, comp., <title level="m">Lovell’s Montreal Directory for 1883–84</title>, John Lovell &amp; Son, 1883, p. 319.</note> Rose and Hubert baptized 2 April.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record, St. Mary’s Anglican Church, Montreal, 2 Apr. 1882, folio 48, p. 95, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec.</note> Winnifred’s brother Lawrence born 24 September.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record for Lawrence Eaton, 18 May 1883, folio 36, p. 36, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1883">
                        <p>Edward, artist, and family living at 104 Drolet at Roy.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">John Lovell, comp., <title level="m">Lovell’s Montreal Directory for 1884–85</title>, John Lovell &amp; Son, 1884, p. 375.</note> Winnifred’s sister Edith working in the composing room of the <title level="m">Montreal Star</title>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Edith Eaton, “Leaves from the Mental Portfolio of an Eurasian,” <title level="m">The Independent</title>, vol. 66, no. 3138, 21 Jan. 1909, pp. 125–32.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1884">
                        <p>Edward, Artist, and family living at 118 Drolet, near Roy. Neighbours clerks and contractors.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">John Lovell, comp., <title level="m">Lovell’s Montreal Directory for 1884–85</title>, John Lovell &amp; Son, 1884, p. 375.</note> Winnifred’s brother Lawrence dies 19 May, age two, possibly of smallpox. Buried at Mount Royal Cemetery in Montreal.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1885">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1884FlorenceEatonSiblings.jpg">
                                    <desc>Florence Eaton with her sisters</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s sister Florence (pictured above, left) born 22 February and baptized 5 July, Trinity Memorial Chapel.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Baptism record for Florence Eaton, Trinity Memorial Chapel, Montreal, 5 July 1885, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec, Canada; “Quebec, Canada, Vital and Church Records (Drouin Collection), 1621–1968,” database with images, Ancestry.com, <ref target="https://ancestry.com/search/collections/1091/">ancestry.com/search/collections/1091/</ref>, image 35 of 60 (record unpaginated).</note> Canada passes the Chinese Immigration Act, levying a $50 head tax on each Chinese labourer entering the country.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">See: "The Chinese Immigration Act, 1885." <title level="m">Canadian Museum of Immigration at Pier 21</title>, 2025, <ref target="https://pier21.ca/research/immigration-history/the-chinese-immigration-act-1885">pier21.ca/research/immigration-history/the-chinese-immigration-act-1885</ref>.</note> Opponents of the smallpox vaccine riot across Montreal.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">See “The 1885 Montreal Smallpox Epidemic,” <title level="m">PMC</title>, <ref target="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8049636/">pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8049636/</ref>.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1886">
                        <p>Gilbert and Sullivan’s orientalist light opera <title level="m">The Mikado</title>, a favourite of the Eaton girls, staged in Montreal.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 18; Birchall’s endnote (p. 215, note 51) cites a Notman photograph of “Le Mikado, en 1886” reproduced in Michel Lessard, <title level="m">Montréal, métropole du Québec: Images oubliées de la vie quotidienne, 1852–1910</title>, Éditions de l’Homme, 1992, photograph 149.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1887">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:BerylEatonbacksaysToGeorgeandMaywithlovefromBerylXmasrooney.jpg">
                                    <desc>Photograph of Beryl.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Eaton family listed as living at 488 St. Lawrence near Sherbrooke; neighbours include dressmakers and confectioners. Winnifred’s sister Beryl (pictured above) born 16 February.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1888">
                        <p>Edward, Artist, 488 St. Lawrence, down the street from Chalmers Church, a church the family may have attended at this time. Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward marries Isabelle Carter at Montreal’s St. Bartholomew’s Episcopal Church.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1889">
                        <p>Family living at 610 St. Lawrence. Edward listed as <q>Artist</q>. Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward living on 122 Crescent. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen working as stenographer and Typewriter in an office in the Standard Life Building, 157 rue St. Jacques.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1890">
                        <p>Eaton family living at 180 Cadieux. Edward is listed as an <q>Artist</q>; Winnifred’s brother Charles listed as bookkeeper living at 122 Crescent. Winnifred leaves school and is sent out to work (possibly as an apprentice dressmaker).<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 15.</note> Grace Helen moves into a new, bigger stenography office in the New York Life Building on rue St. James.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Personal.” <title level="m">The Montreal Daily Star</title>, vol. 22, no. 216, 13 Sept. 1890, p. 7. Collections de BAnQ, <ref target="https://numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5303523">numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5303523</ref>.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1891">
                        <p>Eaton family living at 619 St. Urbain at Duluth, leased from widow Catharine Mitcheson. Neighbours are grocers, carpenters, painters, machinists, and bricklayers. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen marries writer-editor Walter Blackburn Harte in Montreal and moves to Boston where Harte has been appointed Assistant Editor of the <title level="m">New England Magazine</title> three months earlier.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Marriages.” <title level="m">The Montreal Daily Star</title>, vol. 23, no. 94, 22 April 1891, p. 7. Collections de BAnQ, <ref target="https://numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5303707">numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5303707</ref>.</note> Winnifred’s brother Charles and his young family living at 122 rue Crescent. Winnifred’s cousin Alfred Eaton (son of Edward’s brother Isaac) is arrested in San Francisco for bribing a Customs Officer to permit his Japanese fiancée and her aunt, suspected of being sex workers, to land. Edward’s brother Isaac returns to Macclesfield after living for several decades in Japan.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1892">
                        <p>Family living at 619 St. Urbain at Duluth.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1893">
                        <p>Family living at 642 St. Lawrence at Roy. Sister Christiana Agnes marries Joseph Emmanuel Perrault, a widower thirty years her senior and with two children, on 13 October at the Notre Dame Basilica.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">Répertoires de Notaires</title>, marriage contract, 9 Oct. 1893.</note> Sister Sarah advertises her services as an artist and art teacher with a studio at 20 Cathcart.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Personal.” <title level="m">The Montreal Daily Star</title>, vol. 25, no. 124, 29 May 1893, p. 7. Collections de BAnQ, <ref target="https://numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5319983">numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5319983</ref>.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1894">
                        <p>Family living at 828 St. Lawrence where neighbours are a pianoforte maker, a saddler, and a carriage maker; Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward is a bookkeeper living at 129 Hutchison; Miss Edith Eaton listed as Stenographer and Typewriter, with an office at 157 St. Jacques.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1895">
                        <p>Eaton family living at 83 rue de l’Arcade near Pine. Winnifred’s brother Charles Edward a bookkeeper living at 129 Hutchison. Sister Edith has office at 157 St. Jacques, stenog and Typewriter. Winnifred goes to Jamaica as <q>general writer and reporter</q>, covering legislative council meetings, stenography;<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Annette White-Parks, <title level="m">Sui Sin Far / Edith Maude Eaton: A Literary Biography</title>, U of Illinois P, 1995, p. 33.</note> she may have sailed on the <title level="m">Atlas</title> steamship from New York (as suggested in <ref target="doc:Me1"><title level="m">Me</title></ref>); this ship leaves New York on a Saturday, arrives in Kingston on a Friday. Her fare—about $40—is paid by the <title level="m">Gall’s Daily News Letter</title>, and her salary includes free board and lodging at Myrtle Bank hotel. An article in <title level="m">Interocean</title> says Winnifred published original articles, and stories under bylines <q>Busybody</q> and <q>Man on the Street</q>. Winnifred stays in Jamaica for between three and six months.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1896">
                        <p>A poem <ref target="doc:SneerNot1"><title level="a">Sneer Not</title></ref>, by Winnifred Eaton, published in <title level="m">Gall’s Daily News Letter</title>, in March.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Winnifred Eaton, “Sneer Not,” <title level="m">Gall’s Daily News Letter</title>, 10 Mar. 1896, n.p.</note> Winnifred leaves Jamaica on April 7th and arrives back in Boston, via the <title level="m">Barnstable</title>, April 13, 1896.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">A “Miss W. Eaton” is mentioned as traveling to Boston in <title level="m">Jamaica Gleaner</title>, 8 Apr. 1896, p. 2. A “Miss Min. E. Eaton” from Montreal listed in the passenger list of vessels arriving in Boston from Jamaica in April 1896 is almost certainly Winnifred.</note> Later interviews say she left Jamaica after a severe attack of yellow fever and went to the United States, possibly first to father’s relations in the South, then to Cincinnati (where her brother George lives). Winnifred claims to have been the chief stenographer in Cincinnati during the last presidential campaign. In June, her father Edward is arrested in New York State and put in Plattsburgh, NY, prison for smuggling Chinese into US.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Three Celestials Caught.” <title level="m">The Ogdensburg Journal</title>, 6 June 1896, p. 2.</note> In August, he escapes and returns to Montreal.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Montrealer’s Escape: From a United States Gaol.” <title level="m">Montreal Daily Star</title>, 7 Aug. 1896, p. 8.</note> In November, publishes first Japanese story, <ref target="doc:JapaneseGirl1"><title level="a">A Japanese Girl</title></ref>, signed <q>Onoto Watanna</q> in <title level="m">Cincinnati Commercial Tribune</title>, a newspaper that Japanophile Lafcadio Hearn contributed to in the 1870s.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Onoto Watanna, “A Japanese Girl,” <title level="m">Cincinnati Commercial Tribune</title>, 8 Nov. 1896, p. 27; recovered by Joey Takeda. A profile, “A Bright Japanese Girl,” in the <title level="m">Cincinnati Commercial Tribune</title> says she arrived a few weeks before 8 November 1896, was employed by the Commercial McKinley Club before the presidential election on 3 November, and that she “was married not long ago to a young Kentucky travelling man.”</note> In late 1896, an advertisement in <title level="m">The American Youth</title> includes <q>Onoto Watanna</q> in a list of “Writers Who Will Contribute to <title level="m">The American Youth</title> for 1897.” In December, Winnifred’s sister Edith replaces her in her Galls Newsletter job in Jamaica.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1897">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:Onoto3.jpg">
                                    <desc> Photograph of Winnifred Eaton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred (pictured above)<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Photograph of Winnifred, reproduced in Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, illustration following p. 90 (captioned “The young Winnifred Eaton in Chicago about the time her first novel, <title level="m">Miss Numè of Japan</title> (1899), was written”).</note> settles in Chicago by July 1897 and does stenographic work, probably for Armour’s Union Stock yards (as rep in <title level="m">ME</title>) which employed thousands.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 42 (“she probably did not actually settle in Chicago until May of 1897”). In <title level="m">Me</title>, Winnifred mentions seeing the statue of General Logan unveiled, which happened on 22 July 1897.</note> Winnifred assumes Japanese persona as <q>Kitishima Taka Hasche</q>, or <q>Kitishina</q>, or <q>Tacki Hashi</q> a Yokohama-born girl whose pen name is <q>Onoto Watanna</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Now Chicago Boasts of Having a Japanese Woman Writer Destined to Make a Hit,” <title level="m">Detroit Free Press</title>, same year <title level="m">Miss Numè</title> pub’d, i.e. 1899, excerpted from <title level="m">Chicago Chronicle</title>; “Chicago’s Japanese Writer: A writer from Japan,” <title level="m">New York World</title>, 6 Feb. 1898.</note> She claims to have published a <q>Japanese love story</q> in <title level="m">Iroquois Magazine</title> under the name <q>Onoto Watanna</q>. An article in the November 26, 1897 <title level="m">Dixon Evening Telegraph</title> claims she stayed in New York City after Jamaica for a while, then moved to Chicago and met patent lawyer and stenographer Florence King. Articles say that by this point her Japanese stories have been accepted by <title level="m">Munsey’s</title>, <title level="m">Ladies Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">Black Cat</title>, and <title level="m">Iroquois Magazine</title>; that <title level="m">Metropolitan Magazine</title> was the first to bring out her work; that she has also contributed to eastern newspapers; and that a Japanese novel written by her will be dramatized by W[illiam] Gillette. In September, she claims to be heading to Alaska with the Woman’s Alaska Gold Club, a group with 150 members, to pan for gold with Chicago lawyer Florence King. Edith returns to North America, probably to Montreal, from Jamaica in April or May.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1898">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1898evrymonth.jpg">
                                    <desc>Article and portrait from Ev’ry Month.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Attracts attention in numerous literary publications including <title level="m">Ev’ry Month</title>. <title level="m">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, whose notices she pastes into her scrapbook (picture above).<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">University of Calgary scrapbook, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary.</note> As Onoto Watanna, she writes the introduction to <title level="m">Love Lyrics</title>, a book of poems by her friend Chicago journalist Frank Putnam, which he dedicates to her.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 48. The book of poems is Frank Putnam, <title level="m">Love Lyrics</title>, 1898.</note> She also publishes stories in Chicago magazines such as <title level="m">American Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s Home Journal</title>, and <title level="m">Carter’s Monthly</title>. Although most of her earliest located stories are about Japan or Japanese-Americans, her <q>Li Ching’s Baby</q>, a story about a Chinese merchant in Canada, appeared in Chicago’s <title level="m">Carter’s Monthly</title> in April. At an August lawn fete in Evanston, for the benefit of sick American soldiers fighting in the Spanish American War, Winnifred tears off an American flag that has been pinned to her gown and burns it. An article in <title level="m">Current Literature</title> (October 1898) claims that her real name is Kitishima Kata Hasche.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Onoto Watanna, the Japanese Woman Writer,” <title level="m">Current Literature</title>, vol. 24, no. 4, Oct. 1898, p. 306. The item appears in the magazine’s “General Gossip of Authors and Writers” department and reproduces an account first published in the <title level="m">Chicago Times-Herald</title>. Diana Birchall cites the same article (<title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 44) but dates it to October 1897; the issue itself confirms October 1898.</note> Nephew Horace Blackburn Harte is born to Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen, 5th November. Winnifred’s sister May moves west, first to San Jose, then to San Francisco.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1899">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1901PortraitfromNotesofaBookman_HarpersWeekly45_Dec211901_1300.bmp">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Eaton as Onoto Watanna.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred (pictured above) publishes stories in <title level="m">Chicago Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Puritan Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, and <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s Popular Monthly</title>; non-fiction in <title level="m">Book News</title>, <title level="m">Ladies Home Journal</title>, and the <title level="m">St. Louis Dispatch</title>; and poetry in the <title level="m">Christian-Science Monitor</title>. Claims to have published in Japanese magazines <title level="m">Kokumin-no-Tomi</title> and <title level="m">Hansei Zasshi</title> although none of these publications has been located. Publishes <ref target="doc:MissNumeJapaneseRomance1"><title level="m">Miss Numè of Japan</title></ref> (Rand &amp; McNally), a controversial story of interracial romance. This publication makes her the first person of Asian descent to publish a novel in the U.S. The edition of 1500 sells out immediately. Sister Grace’s husband Walter Blackburn Harte dies in New York in June, probably from amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Winnifred’s sister Christiana Agnes gives birth to Henri Laurent on June 10.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">James Doyle, “Sui Sin Far and Onoto Watanna: Two Early Chinese-Canadian Authors,” <title level="m">Canadian Literature</title>, no. 140, Spring 1994, pp. 50–58.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1900">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1900Chicagocensus.jpg">
                                    <desc>1900 Chicago Census.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>According to the 1900 Census (pictured above), she is boarding at 3105 Groveland Avenue in Chicago, a house owned by feminist Dr. Helen R. Kellogg. Meets and becomes close friends with Japanese poet Yone Noguchi in July, who visits Chicago for several weeks after living for seven years in California. Winnifred publishes stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, <title level="m">Conkey’s</title>, and <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, and serializes a novel (<title level="m">The Old Jinrikisha</title>) in <title level="m">Conkey’s</title>. Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen and her son Horace visit Eaton and Harte relatives in England.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1901">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:PersianCombingJackets.jpg">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Winnifred Eaton as Onoto Watanna.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred moves to New York, where her sister Grace Helen works as a legal secretary and works for <title level="m">Munsey’s</title> Magazine.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Winnifred claimed this in her own writing, and her wedding announcement in the <title level="m">Montreal Star</title>, 19 July 1901, p. 12, says so as well.</note> Claims she lived on East Sixteenth between Union Square and Third Avenue with two other young women. Winnifred writes and does modeling for the Women’s Pages of the <title level="m">Brooklyn Eagle</title>. She meets Bertrand Whitcomb Babcock, whom she marries July 16, 1901 in New York City.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 68. See also “Miss Winifred Eaton Married,” <title level="m">The Montreal Daily Star</title>, vol. 33, no. 168, 19 July 1901, p. 12. Collections de BAnQ, <ref target="https://numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5322759">numerique.banq.qc.ca/patrimoine/details/52327/5322759</ref>.</note> She continues to write prolifically during this year, publishing stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, <title level="m">Harper’s Monthly</title>, <title level="m">Idler</title>, and <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, also releasing <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6"><title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title></ref> (Harper and Brothers), which she claims sold 200,000 copies.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 75.</note> Winnifred’s sister Christiana Agnes gives birth to Joseph François Perrault on September 1.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1902">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1902Watannaillustrationandjapanesesignature.jpg">
                                    <desc>Portrait and Signature from Frontispiece of The Wooing of
                                        Wistaria.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Publishes another novel, <ref target="doc:WooingOfWistaria14"><title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title></ref> (the frontispiece of which is pictured above) as well as various stories and non-fiction articles in <title level="m">Frank Leslie’s</title>, <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, <title level="m">Metropolitan Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Harper’s Monthly</title>, <title level="m">Woman’s Home Companion</title>, and <title level="m">Critic</title>. Accuses playwright David Belasco of copying characters and incidents from <ref target="doc:WooingOfWistaria14"><title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title></ref> in his new play <title level="m">The Darling of the Gods</title> (co-written with John Luther Long). Belasco responds by suing her for libel. Winnifred is arrested but quickly released on bail.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 79. See also Winnifred Eaton, “Notes for Lawyer regarding Infringement by Belasco of ‘The Wooing of Wistaria,’” n.d., Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary. Eaton’s account identifies the disputed work as primarily <title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title> (published September 1902): Belasco’s manager Benjamin Roeder had access to both <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> and a synopsis of <title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title>, and Eaton enumerates eight specific plot resemblances between Belasco’s play and <title level="m">The Wooing of Wistaria</title>. Dramatic rights to <title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title> had been sold separately to Klaw &amp; Erlanger (United States) and Marie Tempest (England) by dramatic agent Elisabeth Marbury.</note> Winnifred’s brother Hubert drowns in Shawinigan Falls, a waterfall on the Saint-Maurice River near Shawinigan, Quebec.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Burial record for Hubert Eaton, All Saints Church, Montreal, died 10 Aug. 1902, folio 12, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec, Canada. See also “Lost His Life While Bathing,” <title level="m">Montreal Daily Star</title>, 11 Aug. 1902, p. 5.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1903">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1903JNBroadway.jpg">
                                <desc> Japanese Nightingale on Broadway.</desc>
                            </graphic>
                                </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred publishes in <title level="m">Century Magazine</title>, <title level="m">Smart Set</title>, <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">New Metropolitan Magazine</title>, and <title level="m">Current Literature</title>. She also publishes a novel, <ref target="doc:HeartOfHyacinth1"><title level="m">The Heart of Hyacinth</title></ref> (Harper and Brothers). Winnifred and Babcock’s first child, Perry, is born June 23, when the family are living at 2445 Grand Avenue, Fordham Heights. William Young’s adaptation of <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6"><title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title></ref> (pictured above) opens at Broadway’s Daly Theater to scathing reviews. The play runs for only forty-four performances but is later restaged successfully across the continent.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, pp. 81–82. Photograph now held at the University of Calgary archives.</note> Winnifred’s sister Grace Helen and her son Horace move to Chicago where Grace Helen works as a stenographer while attending Chicago-Kent College of Law at night. Winnifred’s sister Christiana Agnes gives birth to Leo Henri Perrault on October 11.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1904">
                        <p>In February, Winnifred is accused by Professor John Van Cleve of reproducing a sonnet by him in the fifth chapter of <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6"><title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title></ref> without attributing it to him. Winnifred denies the accusation, claiming sole authorship of the sonnet, and Van Cleve eventually drops the case.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, pp. 87–90.</note> Winnifred and Babcock’s second child, Bertie, is born September 29 while family living at 183rd street, in Fordham Heights. Russo-Japanese War creates further demand for Winnifred’s writings on various aspects of Japanese culture. She publishes stories and non-fiction in <title level="m">Woman’s Home Journal</title>, <title level="m">New Metropolitan Magazine</title>, and <title level="m">Ladies’ Home Journal</title>, as well as two novels: <ref target="doc:DaughtersOfNijo1"><title level="m">Daughters of Nijo</title></ref> (Macmillan) and <ref target="doc:LoveOfAzalea4"><title level="m">The Love of Azalea</title></ref> (Dodd, Mead, &amp; Co). Reviews of <ref target="doc:DaughtersOfNijo1"><title level="m">Daughters of Nijo</title></ref>, beginning with one in the <title level="m">Baltimore Sun</title>, begin to suggest that Winnifred is not entirely or even half Japanese.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">See <title level="m">The Baltimore Sun</title>, 19 May 1904, p. 8. The author writes that Winnifred “is not a Japanese, as her name [Onoto Watanna] might seem to indicate.” See also the earlier <title level="m">Los Angeles Evening and Sunday Herald Examiner,</title> 15 Nov. 1902, p. 5., which says she “is only half Japanese” because her sister, Edith Eaton, is "known to be of Anglo-Chinese parentage.”</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1905">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1905twaindinner.jpg">
                                    <desc> 70th Birthday Party for Mark Twain in New York City.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred attends her friend Mark Twain’s 70th birthday dinner (pictured above).<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Photograph of guests at the dinner in honor of Mark Twain’s seventieth birthday, Delmonico’s, New York, 5 December 1905. <title level="m">Harper’s Weekly</title>, vol. 49, 1905, p. 1910. <title level="m">HathiTrust</title>, <ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=umn.31951002098781l&amp;seq=30">babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=umn.31951002098781l&amp;seq=30</ref>.</note> For about three years, Winnifred’s family live with three female servants at 146 Walton Avenue, on Long Island’s Orienta Point; known as <q>Hollywood of the East</q> because it was considered a desirable neighborhood by movie star Dorothy Gish and filmmaker D. W. Griffiths. Winnifred enjoys riding horses in Central Park.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1906">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:na-4320-8WEandDorisonsleigh.png">
                                    <desc>Portrait of Winnifred Eaton and Doris.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred and Babcock’s third child, Doris (pictured above), is born January 13. Winnifred publishes <ref target="doc:JapaneseBlossom1"><title level="m">A Japanese Blossom</title></ref> (Harper Brothers). Winnifred’s sister Beryl moves to Brooklyn to enter Brooklyn City Hospital’s Nurse-in-training program.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">The Montreal Daily Star</title>, 3 Apr. 1906, p. 14.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1907">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:na-4320-14WEsSon.png">
                                    <desc>Photograph of Charley.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred rebuked by Noguchi for masquerade. Writing as <q>Winnifred Mooney</q>, she begins to try to publish works pseudonymously that are neither on a Japanese theme nor signed <q>Onoto Watanna</q>. Winnifred publishes an Irish comedy, <ref target="doc:DiaryOfDelia5"><title level="m">The Diary of Delia</title></ref>, with Doubleday, Page and Company, a major departure from her usual Japanese themes.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Onoto Watanna [Winnifred Eaton], <title level="m">The Diary of Delia: Being a Veracious Chronicle of the Kitchen</title>, Doubleday, Page, 1907. See also Agreement between Mrs. B. W. Babcock [Winnifred Eaton] and Doubleday, Page &amp; Co. for <title level="m">The Diary of Delia</title>, 31 Jan. 1907, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary (10% royalty on first 2,500 copies, scaling to 20% beyond 10,000).</note> Her fourth child, Charley (pictured above), is born on July 27. Profiles of Onoto Watanna begin to claim that her mother is part Chinese as well as part Japanese.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1908">
                        <p>Buys Oriental Point house from actress Mrs. Guy Bates Post mentioned in <q>My Neighbour’s Garden</q>. On January 13, Winnifred formalizes her theatrical agency arrangement with Elisabeth Marbury, appointing her sole agent for the play <title level="m">The Japanese Nightingale</title>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Agreement between Winifred Babcock and Elisabeth Marbury for the play <title level="m">The Japanese Nightingale</title>, 13 Jan. 1908, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary. Marbury’s address is listed as 1430 Broadway, New York City; her commission was 10% of all sums received from productions of the play.</note> Winnifred’s son Bertie dies September 11, weeks before his fourth birthday. Death certificate says <q>he had suffered from chronic encephalitis for two years and died from convulsions and heart failure</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 102.</note> This loss of her son cast shadow upon her life for the next seven years, making it difficult for her to write.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1909">
                        <p>Winnipeg Theatre stages <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6"><title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title></ref>. Winnifred’s grief over Bertie’s death casts <q>a shadow</q> on her life, and she ceases to write regularly for seven years.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1911">
                        <p>Winnifred’s eldest brother, Edward Charles, dies of accidental gunshot wound while sleeping.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">"Edward Eaton death announcements [articles]", 1915-10, (CU111976266) by Literary Digest. Courtesy of Canadian Literary and Cultural Archives, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds Collection, Libraries and Cultural Resources Digital Collections, University of Calgary.</note> Sisters Edith and Florence both working as stenographers and living with family at 1737 rue Mance, in Montreal.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1912">
                        <p>Winnifred publishes <ref target="doc:HonorableMissMoonlight1"><title level="m">The Honorable Miss Moonlight</title></ref> (Harper Brothers). Sister Edith, under pen name <q>Sui Sin Far</q>, publishes <title level="m">Mrs. Spring Fragrance</title>, a collection of stories about Chinese and diasporic Chinese. Her sister Grace Helen qualifies for the Illinois Bar and begins a career specializing in real estate law, particularly landlord-tenant law.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1914">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1914EdithGrave.jpg">
                                    <desc> Edith Eaton’s gravestone in Montreal.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Sister Edith dies April 7 of heart disease in Montreal and is buried in Mount Royal Cemetery (pictured above). Winnifred co-authors <ref target="doc:ChineseJapaneseCookbook1"><title level="m">A Chinese-Japanese American Cookbook</title></ref> with her sister Sara Bosse, the first Asian cookbook in English published in the US. Winnifred’s fiction begins to be optioned by filmmakers such as Selig Polyscope Company in Chicago. Winnifred’s father Edward is arrested again for smuggling Chinese into New York State.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1915">
                        <p>Winnifred’s father Edward dies of cancer on February 20, before going to trial.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Edward Eaton Lived in Far East Before Coming to Montreal,” <title level="m">Montreal Gazette</title>, 22 Feb. 1915, p. 4.</note> Winnifred anonymously publishes <ref target="doc:Me6"><title level="m">Me: A Book of Remembrance</title></ref> (Century), a fictionalized memoir of her early career in Jamaica and Chicago, first in five monthly installments in <title level="m">Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine</title> beginning in April, and then as a book. According to the preface by Jean Webster, she wrote the book in 5 or 6 weeks while in hospital.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 117. See also the Century Company contract (agreement between Jean Webster, agent, and The Century Co., 7 Jan. 1915, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary), which confirm Century Magazine paid $2,500 for serial rights and $500 advance on book royalties (15% royalty), both payable on signing.</note> After completing <ref target="doc:Me1"><title level="m">Me</title></ref>, Winnifred begins writing a story for <q>motion picture serial men</q>. Writes first two chapters of silent film <ref target="doc:GloriasRomance1"><title level="m">Gloria’s Romance</title></ref> and enters a <title level="m">Chicago Tribune</title> screenwriting contest.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1916">
                        <p>Wins $10,000 prize for scenario of short silent film sequel to <title level="m">A Diamond in the Sky</title>, also known as <title level="m">The Fate of the Child</title> and <title level="m">The Gypsy’s Trust</title> directed by Edward Sloman and starring William Russell and Rhea Mitchell.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">See "Category: Sequel to the Diamond in the Sky." <title level="m">Wikimedia Commons</title>, Wikimedia Foundation, 19 Feb. 2024, <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Sequel_to_the_Diamond_in_the_Sky">commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Sequel_to_the_Diamond_in_the_Sky</ref>.</note> In eight monthly installments beginning in April, <title level="m">Hearst’s Magazine</title> serializes <ref target="doc:Marion2"><title level="m">Marion: The Story of an Artist’s Model</title></ref>, based on her sister Sara Eaton Bosse’s biography. It is published anonymously by “Herself and the author of <ref target="doc:Me1"><title level="m">Me</title></ref>.” <title level="m">Hearst’s</title> pays $7,500 for it, enabling Winnifred to go to Reno and divorce Babcock.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 128.</note> Finds herself unable to write afterward.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1917">
                        <p>Winnifred’s divorce decree granted February 3. She gains full custody of her three children: Perry Whitcomb Babcock, Doris Elizabeth Babcock, and Charles Whitcomb Babcock.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Decree, <title level="m">Winifred Babcock v. Bertrand Whitcomb Babcock</title>, No. 12037, Second Judicial District Court of the State of Nevada, In and for Washoe County, filed 3 Feb. 1917; signed by District Judge Thomas F. Moran; attorneys James Glynn, A. A. Heer, and W. D. Jones (200–201 Clay Peters Building, Reno, Nevada). Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary. Note: the legal filing spells the plaintiff’s first name “Winifred” (one ‘n’). The decree was presented on 23 Apr. 1947 at the American Consulate, Calgary, by Francis F. Reeve in connection with his application for registration as an American citizen.</note> She marries Frank Reeve, an American businessman who owns a New York tugboat firm, in Greenwich, Connecticut on March 26, 1917 and begins to go by name <q>Mrs. Francis Reeve</q> or <q>Winnifred Reeve</q> in private life. The couple move to a grain farm in Beddington, Alberta, a village 15 miles north of Calgary, Alberta. Winnifred begins to publish in Canadian magazines such as <title level="m">Maclean’s</title>.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1918">
                        <p>Frank Reeve buys 4000-hectare Bow View Ranch on forks of Bow and Ghost rivers near Morley, Alberta, a <q>mecca for all aspiring fishermen and hunters</q> and he and Winnifred and her children relocate there.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Mrs. Francis Reeve,” Charlotte Gordon, <title level="m">The Leader-Post</title>, Sat., Dec. 9, 1922, p. 26.</note> Ranch was previously owned by Mrs. Goddard, and by Captain Henry Tomkins who sold it to Calcutt and Harris in 1912 for $2,100 for 2,100 acres. The house is <q>a very comfortable and well set up home consisting of seven or eight rooms</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Frank Reeve affidavit, Glenbow/Special Collections, M-6840-6370.</note> <ref target="doc:JapaneseNightingale6"><title level="m">A Japanese Nightingale</title></ref> is made into a silent film starring Fannie Ward as Yuki, W. E. Lawrence as John Bigelow, and Japanese actor, newspaper editor, and Vitagraph technical director Aoyama Yukio as Taro. Winnifred’s story <ref target="doc:FiveThousandDollarReward1"><title level="a">$5000 Reward</title></ref> also made into a silent film. Winnifred sister’s Florence gave birth to her son Robert F. on April 9, 1919, while Florence and her husband and son Ted were visiting Winnifred.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1919">
                        <p>Winnifred publishes a serialized novel <ref target="doc:OtherPeoplesTroubles"><title level="m">Other People’s Troubles: An Antidote to Your Own</title></ref> in Alberta’s <title level="m">Farm and Ranch Review</title>. Publishes <ref target="doc:LendMeYourTitle1"><title level="m">Lend Me Your Title</title></ref> in <title level="m">Maclean’s Magazine</title>.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1920">
                        <p>Lord Burnham (Imperial Press Association) brings a party of English publishers and editors including Frank Newnes (publisher of the Westminster Gazette) to Bow Valley Ranch. Winnifred rents a small house at 1737 26th Avenue West where she returns to writing <q>as if I had turned on a mental faucet</q><note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Linda Popp Di Biase, “The Alberta Years of Winnifred Eaton,” <title level="m">Alberta History</title>, vol. 39, no. 2, Spring 1991, pp. 1–8.</note>; writes <ref target="doc:SunnySan1"><title level="m">Sunny-San</title></ref>, her first Japanese-themed work in over six years, in 5 weeks (published instalments beginning in Feb 1922). Even though she had long ago tired of writing Japanese stories, she followed advice of colleague Arthur Stringer who had counselled her not to abandon the Japanese theme until she had re-established her literary position.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Linda Popp Di Biase, “The Alberta Years of Winnifred Eaton,” <title level="m">Alberta History</title>, vol. 39, no. 2, Spring 1991, pp. 1–8.</note><note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Linda Popp Di Biase, “The Alberta Years of Winnifred Eaton,” <title level="m">Alberta History</title>, vol. 39, no. 2, Spring 1991, pp. 1–8.</note> Her children attend Mount Royal College. Begins to write fiction set in Alberta. She writes a scenario for an Alberta ranching story that will become <ref target="doc:Cattle2"><title level="m">Cattle</title></ref>.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1921">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1920sinCaliforniaGlenbow.jpg">
                                    <desc>Photograph of Eaton in Japanese dress in California.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Adapts Wilbur Daniel Steel’s play <title level="m">Ropes</title> for the silent feature film <ref target="doc:FalseKisses1"><title level="m">False Kisses</title></ref> (Universal Pictures) starring Miss DuPont, Pat O’Malley, and Lloyd Whitlock and directed by Paul Scardon, and receives her first screenplay credit, although the film is poorly received.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 135.</note> She works as screenwriter, title writer, literary advisor, and scenario editor for Universal and Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer between 1921 and 1930. Lives at 1462 E. 58th in Los Angeles and at 7027 Lanewood Ave., Hollywood. Reads her story <ref target="doc:Sinners1"><title level="a">Sinners</title></ref> aloud at Canadian Women’s Press Club Calgary branch luncheon. Attends talk by John Murray Gibbon (founding president of Canadian Authors Association) at Calgary’s Hudson Bay Company Tapestry Room; event turns into founding meeting of Canadian Authors Association, Calgary Branch, at which Winnifred is elected Vice Chair of branch.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1922">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:na-4320-9WEatRanch.png">
                                    <desc>Winnifred Eaton Reeve at Alberta Ranch. </desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred’s mother Grace Achuen Amoy Eaton dies in New York in May while Winnifred visiting.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">A service was held at Trinity Church, New York City, on 6 May 1922. “New York, U.S., Episcopal Diocese of New York Church Records, 1767–1970,” database online, Ancestry.com Operations, 2017, Joseph William Sutton Registers, p. 10. Grace Eaton is buried at Mount Royal Cemetery, Montreal, after a funeral at St. Cuthbert’s Church; St. Cuthbert’s burial records, May 1922, p. 7, Drouin Collection, compiled by Gabriel Drouin, Institut Généalogique Drouin, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</note> Winnifred publishes <ref target="doc:SunnySan1"><title level="m">Sunny-San</title></ref> in serial form, beginning in February 1922, and in book form in Toronto and New York and England, with help from her friend and fellow Calgarian Nellie McClung who acted as an agent for the book. Winnifred and her family continue to live, intermittently, on Bow View Ranch (pictured above) but Winnifred also rents house at 902 20th Avenue West in Calgary. Winnifred attends Canadian Authors Association meetings and convention in Ottawa and, with others, lobbies federal Minister of Justice re: updating copyright act. Her friend, author Arthur Stringer, visits Bow View Ranch.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1922">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1922-LakeWindermere.jpg">
                                    <desc>Winnifred Eaton Reeve at Lake Windermere for the David
                                        Thompson Memorial dedication.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                                <bibl><title level="a">Group at David Thompson memorial celebration, Windermere Valley, British Columbia</title>. 
                                    1922, (CU176277) by Unknown. Courtesy of Glenbow Library and Archives Collection, Libraries and Cultural
                                    Resources Digital Collections, University of Calgary.</bibl>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>In August, Winnifred attends the opening of the David Thomson Memorial Fort at Lake Windermere (photographed above with Bliss Carman and Frederick Niven and other authors), which coincided with the opening of the Banff Windermere Highway;<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Indians and Whites Together: A Celebration of Some Moment,” <title level="m">Calgary Herald</title>, 30 Aug. 1922.</note> <q>Rivalling the vividness of Kootenay grandeur, was Mrs. Francis Reeve, of Calgary, who appeared on the links in a beautiful Chinese costume</q>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Landscape &amp; Literati,” <title level="m">Canadian Bookman</title>, Oct. 1922.</note> Children attended boarding school in Calgary. Assists in the founding of, and named first honorary President of, Calgary Little Theatre.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1923">
                        <p>Rents 330 Scarboro Avenue, a house with a fabulous view of downtown Calgary. Owned by Sam Nickle, the house becomes <q>a centre for people of literary inclinations and literary aspirations</q>. Winnifred is appointed president of CAA Calgary branch.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Calgary Branch Report, <title level="m">Canadian Bookman</title>, April 1923.</note> Key organizer of Calgary’s <q>Book Week</q>. Depression in cattle prices due to American tariffs makes it difficult to afford a <q>room of [her] own</q> in Calgary. Gives talk to Canadian Club of Calgary—<q>The Canadian Spirit in our Literature</q>.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1924">
                        <p>Publishes her novel <ref target="doc:Cattle2"><title level="m">Cattle</title></ref> in Canada and the US under a slightly different spelling of her married name: Winifred Eaton Reeve. Icelandic-Canadian author Laura Salverson publishes a critical review of it in January. Winnifred reacts by accusing Salverson of paying for a positive review of her own novel, <title level="m">Viking Heart</title>. In December, Winnifred and her three children take train to New York. Winnifred signs a contract with Universal Pictures Corporation as East Coast scenario editor and literary adviser at $200 per week.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 155. See also the contract (Agreement between Universal Pictures Corporation and Winifred Eaton Reeve [Onoto Watanna], 1924, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary), which confirms her title as Literary Adviser, compensation at $200 per week, and Universal’s option to purchase her original stories at $3,000–$5,000 each.</note> Universal’s Carl Laemmle Sr. hopes she will encourage her broad network of literary contacts to write for Universal. She rents a house at 593 Riverside Drive and hopes husband Frank will follow.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 155.</note> On December 12 Doris elopes.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1925">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1925StudiosUniversal.jpg">
                                    <desc> Picture of Universal Studios.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Dedicates <ref target="doc:HisRoyalNibs1"><title level="m">His Royal Nibs</title></ref> (W. J. Watt), her final published novel, which she publishes as Winifred Eaton Reeve, to Carl Laemmle Sr. Over the next seven years, she turns her energies to screenplay writing and commutes between New York (and later Los Angeles) and Calgary.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 151.</note> Universal Studios hires her as West Coast story/scenario editor and transfers her to Los Angeles in late 1925. She is also described as Universal’s Editor-in-chief and literary advisor. She spends July through September at Universal’s Hollywood studios (pictured above). While Eaton worked with production studios, she also contributed articles to Hollywood magazines like <title level="m">Motography</title>, <title level="m">Motion Picture News</title>, and <title level="m">The Writers Bulletin and Literary Reporter</title>.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Vito Adriaensens, “Winnifred Eaton,” <title level="m">Women Film Pioneers Project</title>, edited by Jane Gaines, Radha Vatsal, and Monica Dall’Asta, Center for Digital Research and Scholarship, Columbia University Libraries, 2013, <ref target="https://wfpp.columbia.edu/pioneer/winnifred-eaton/">wfpp.columbia.edu/pioneer/winnifred-eaton/</ref>.</note> Gives lecture at MacDowell Club of Allied Arts in December. Sells film rights to <ref target="doc:Cattle2"><title level="m">Cattle</title></ref>. Daughter Doris gives birth to Paul George Rooney (<q>Tim</q>) July 14, then separates from her husband and returns to live with her mother in California in November.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, pp. 166–67.</note> Frank Reeve sells Bow View Ranch and founds F. F. Reeve and Company, a brokerage firm, in Calgary and invests in what becomes an oil boom in Alberta’s Turner Valley.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1926">
                        <p>Quits her job at Universal in December due to lack of creative license<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 164.</note> and moves back to Calgary, renting a house at 322 19th Ave west. Her son Perry develops a severe mental illness, perhaps schizophrenia at age twenty-three and is eventually committed to a State Hospital.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, pp. 167–68.</note> By late 1926, Winnifred moves to Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer where she is given an opportunity to write original screenplays as well as do adaptations.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1"><title level="m">Film Year Book 1927</title>. The Film Daily, 1927, p. 236. <title level="m">Lantern: Media History Digital Library</title>, <ref target="https://lantern.mediahist.org/catalog/filmyearbook19271927newy_0236">lantern.mediahist.org/catalog/filmyearbook19271927newy_0236</ref>.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1927">
                        <p>Does ghostwriting.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 165.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1928">
                        <p>Returns to Universal Studios as a screenwriter rather than as a story editor. She works on both sound and silent films. She also begins writing for movie magazines.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, pp. 165 and 169.</note> On February 20, Winnifred confirms two ghostwriting agreements with actress Anita Stewart for the novels <title level="m">Yola</title> and <title level="m">Gipsy</title>: Stewart pays Winnifred 35% of royalties plus $250 on account and $250 on completion for each novel.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">"Agreement between Anita Stewart and Winnifred Eaton Reeve regarding "Yola" and "Gipsy"", February 1928, (CU111992724) by Reeve, Winnifred Eaton, Stewart, Anita. Courtesy of Canadian Literary and Cultural Archives, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds Collection, Libraries and Cultural Resources Digital Collections, University of Calgary.</note> On September 7, Winnifred assigns the motion picture rights to her original story <q>The Man from the Gutter</q> (also known as <q>The Wolf of Wall Street</q>) to Paramount Famous Lasky Corporation for $1,000.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">"Agreement between Paramount-Famous-Lasky and Winnifred Eaton Reeve regarding "The Wolf of Wall Street"", September 1926, (CU111992721) by Paramount-Famous-Lasky, Reeve, Winnifred Eaton. Courtesy of Canadian Literary and Cultural Archives, Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds Collection, Libraries and Cultural Resources Digital Collections, University of Calgary.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1929">
                        <p>Loses all her savings in the stock market crash. <ref target="doc:MississippiGambler1"><title level="m">The Mississippi Gambler</title></ref>, the first Hollywood picture for which she is credited with writing the dialogue, is released on November 3.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 173.</note> <ref target="doc:ShanghaiLady1"><title level="m">Shanghai Lady</title></ref>, a film she is credited as writing, is released Nov. 17, 1929.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1930">
                        <p>Writes screenplays for <ref target="doc:Undertow1"><title level="m">Undertow</title></ref>, <ref target="doc:YoungDesire1"><title level="m">Young Desire</title></ref>, and <ref target="doc:EastIsWest1"><title level="m">East is West</title></ref>; all by Universal Studios. Then Universal lays her off.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 176.</note> She learns that her husband Frank has a mistress (Mrs. Margaret Hill) and wants a divorce.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 177.</note> She offers him his freedom in February while living at 1953 Ivar Avenue, LA with her daughter Doris and grandson.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1931">
                        <p>Frank Reeve files for divorce but he and Winnifred reconcile by August and spend a romantic week at Lake Tahoe.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 181.</note> Frank returns to Calgary to end relations with his mistress and Winnifred returns to Calgary to live with Frank again.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 181.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1932">
                        <p>Winnifred and Frank live in Suite 19, Barnhart Apartments, 1121 6th St. NW, considered one of the finest apartment buildings in Calgary at the time (where she writes <ref target="doc:SecondHoneymoon1"><title level="m">Second Honeymoon</title></ref>).</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1933">
                        <p>Winnifred at work on novel about Calgary’s economy called <ref target="doc:BoomCity1"><title level="m">Boom City</title></ref>.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1935">
                        <p>Daughter Doris, after ten years in Hollywood, moves back to Calgary with young son Paul and works as stenographer for her stepfather Frank until his death in 1956.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1936">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1936FrankOil.jpg">
                                    <desc> A picture of Frank in the oil fields.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred and Frank live at 1205 Nineteenth Ave. W, Calgary (where she writes <ref target="doc:SinsFathers1"><title level="m">Sins of the Fathers</title></ref>). Frank’s oil investments do well and he (pictured above, centre) becomes one of the wealthiest men in the province.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1937">
                        <p>Winnifred continues to be a member of the Canadian Authors Association, Calgary branch, executive committee.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1938">
                        <p>Winnifred and Frank buy 801 Royal Avenue, former home of American diplomat, journalist, and author James Davidson. Frank named President and Managing Director of Commonwealth Drilling Company and named Vice-President of Commoil. In November, in her Calgary home at 801 Royal Avenue, Winnifred hosts a tea for author Laura Salverson—the author she accused in 1924 of paying for a positive review.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1939">
                        <p>Frank serves on board of YMCA and is member of Glencoe Club and Petroleum Club. In May, Winnifred hosts annual general meeting for Calgary branch of Canadian Authors Association at her home.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1944">
                        <p>Winnifred’s son Charley, a writer, now going by the pen name Paul Eaton Reeve, marries Helen Finkelstein.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 194.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1945">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:Diana_granddaughter.jpg">
                                    <desc>Winnifred’s only granddaughter, Diana.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>In the aftermath of World War Two, Winnifred expresses regret for having posed as Japanese. Winnifred writes plays for the Calgary Little Theatre community. Winnifred’s only granddaughter, Diana (pictured above), born to Charley and Helen in December. Her son Charley’s drinking and inability to keep a job causes tensions with the Finkelsteins, who are convinced he is mentally ill and eventually refuse him access to his daughter. For some of this period, Winnifred pays Charley an allowance.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 197.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1947">
                        <p>Ex-husband Bertrand Babcock dies of diabetes and alcoholism.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Diana Birchall, <title level="m">Onoto Watanna: The Story of Winnifred Eaton</title>, U of Illinois P, 2001, p. 70.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1950">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:WE_Frank1950s.jpg">
                                    <desc>Winnifred and Frank Reeve in the 1950s.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred and her husband Frank Reeve (pictured above) take cruise to Honolulu from Los Angeles in February.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1952">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:WE_Doris_JoCarlisle_FrankRooney.jpg">
                                    <desc>Winnifred, Jo Carlisle holding baby Frank Rooney, and Doris Rooney in Edmonton.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred Eaton Reeve (left) in Edmonton, Fall of 1952, with her daughter Doris Rooney (right) and Jo Carlisle (centre), who is holding baby Frank Rooney, grandson to both Jo and Doris.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1953">
                        <p>Winnifred treated for diabetes at Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota in May<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">Mayo Clinic appointment envelope for Mrs. Francis F. Reeve, registration no. 1-920-511, [May 1953]; address given as 801 Royal Ave., Calgary, Alta. Winnifred Eaton Reeve fonds, University of Calgary. Note: the envelope, dated 19 May 1953, records appointments for “Metabolism Therapy” (insulin and diabetic management), confirming both the date and nature of treatment.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1954">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1954WEGrave.jpeg">
                                    <desc>The gravestone for Frank Reeve and Winnifred Eaton in
                                        Calgary.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Winnifred dies April 8 of a heart attack in a hotel in Butte, Montana, en route with Frank to Calgary from California.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“$313,000 Will Filed.” <title level="m">The Calgary Albertan,</title> 26 Nov. 1954, p. 11.</note> She is buried in Queen’s Park Cemetery in Calgary.</p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1956">
                        <p>Husband Frank Reeve dies.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Francis Fournier Reeve,” <title level="m">Find a Grave</title>, 2026, <ref target="https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/82779467/francis_fournier-reeve">www.findagrave.com/memorial/82779467/francis_fournier-reeve</ref></note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1957">
                        <p>Sister Grace Helen dies, February 8.<note type="editorial" resp="pers:MC1">“Grace Helen Harte,” <title level="m">Find a Grave</title>, 2026, <ref target="https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/82885727/grace-helen-harte">www.findagrave.com/memorial/82885727/grace-helen-harte</ref>.</note></p>
                    </event>

                    <event when="1981">
                        <ab type="graphic">
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="media:1980ReeveTheatre.jpg">
                                    <desc> A picture of the architect rendering of the Reeve Theatre at
                                        the University of Calgary.</desc>
                                </graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </ab>
                        <p>Reeve Theatre (pictured above) at University of Calgary opens, funded in part by a $1 million donation from the Reeve Foundation founded by Frank Reeve after Winnifred’s death.</p>
                    </event>
                </listEvent>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
