<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="${cfn}">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>${ask('What is the title of this document?', string, '', @title)}</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Author</resp>
               <name ref="pers:WE">Winnifred Eaton</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Transcriber',radio,('SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio'),'SE1', @transcriber)}"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Copy Editor</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Copy Editor',radio,('SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio'),'SE1', @copyeditor)}"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Encoder',radio,('SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio'),'SE1', @encoder)}"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><!--Encode bibliographic citation for the source here--></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Document Type',radio,('docPrimarySource':' Primary Source ';'docPrimarySourceMS':' Manuscripts ';'docPrimarySourcePublished':' Published Primary Sources ';'docBornDigital':'Born Digital document';'docBornDigitalListing':' Listing Pages ';'docBornDigitalDocumentation':' Documentation '),'docPrimarySource', @doctype)}"/>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:genre"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Genre',radio,('genreShortStory':' Short Stories ';'genreNF':'Non-fiction';'genreNFAuto':'Non-fiction: Autobiography';'genreNFDedication':'Non-fiction: Dedication';'genreNFInterview':'Non-Fiction: Interview';'genreNFIntroduction':'Non-fiction: Introduction';'genreNFEthnography':'Non-fiction: Ethnography';'genreFilm':'Film';'genreFilmScenario':'Film: Scenario';'genreFilmTreatment':'Film: Treatment';'genrePoem':'Poem';'genreNovel':'Novel';'genreNovelSerial':'Novel: Serial'),'genreShortStory', @genre)}"/>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:category"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Exhibit',radio,('Japan':'Japan Biscuit bear claw candy toffee danish carrot cake lollipop lemon drops. Chocolate brownie soufflé tootsie roll pastry donut jujubes powder. Macaroon topping topping tiramisu tart cupcake pie ice cream. Croissant gummi bears icing fruitcake lemon drops lollipop. Oat cake marshmallow chupa chups wafer cupcake wafer jujubes topping sesame snaps. Pastry lemon drops donut apple pie chocolate cake gingerbread. Jujubes sugar plum topping chocolate. Dragée dessert carrot cake candy canes oat cake tart tootsie roll lollipop soufflé. Apple pie sugar plum lemon drops. Carrot cake cake fruitcake toffee. Gummies cake apple pie sugar plum cotton candy pastry chocolate cake. Cupcake pie donut tart gummi bears icing cotton candy. Chocolate cake halvah tiramisu. Chocolate croissant jujubes chocolate bar chupa chups chocolate bar brownie sugar plum topping. Jelly beans apple pie macaroon soufflé cookie. ';'Alberta':'Alberta Biscuit bear claw candy toffee danish carrot cake lollipop lemon drops. Chocolate brownie soufflé tootsie roll pastry donut jujubes powder. Macaroon topping topping tiramisu tart cupcake pie ice cream. Croissant gummi bears icing fruitcake lemon drops lollipop. Oat cake marshmallow chupa chups wafer cupcake wafer jujubes topping sesame snaps. Pastry lemon drops donut apple pie chocolate cake gingerbread. Jujubes sugar plum topping chocolate. Dragée dessert carrot cake candy canes oat cake tart tootsie roll lollipop soufflé. Apple pie sugar plum lemon drops. Carrot cake cake fruitcake toffee. Gummies cake apple pie sugar plum cotton candy pastry chocolate cake. Cupcake pie donut tart gummi bears icing cotton candy. Chocolate cake halvah tiramisu. Chocolate croissant jujubes chocolate bar chupa chups chocolate bar brownie sugar plum topping. Jelly beans apple pie macaroon soufflé cookie. ';'Hollywood':'Hollywood Biscuit bear claw candy toffee danish carrot cake lollipop lemon drops. Chocolate brownie soufflé tootsie roll pastry donut jujubes powder. Macaroon topping topping tiramisu tart cupcake pie ice cream. Croissant gummi bears icing fruitcake lemon drops lollipop. Oat cake marshmallow chupa chups wafer cupcake wafer jujubes topping sesame snaps. Pastry lemon drops donut apple pie chocolate cake gingerbread. Jujubes sugar plum topping chocolate. Dragée dessert carrot cake candy canes oat cake tart tootsie roll lollipop soufflé. Apple pie sugar plum lemon drops. Carrot cake cake fruitcake toffee. Gummies cake apple pie sugar plum cotton candy pastry chocolate cake. Cupcake pie donut tart gummi bears icing cotton candy. Chocolate cake halvah tiramisu. Chocolate croissant jujubes chocolate bar chupa chups chocolate bar brownie sugar plum topping. Jelly beans apple pie macaroon soufflé cookie. ';'EarlyExperiment':' Early Experiments Biscuit bear claw candy toffee danish carrot cake lollipop lemon drops. Chocolate brownie soufflé tootsie roll pastry donut jujubes powder. Macaroon topping topping tiramisu tart cupcake pie ice cream. Croissant gummi bears icing fruitcake lemon drops lollipop. Oat cake marshmallow chupa chups wafer cupcake wafer jujubes topping sesame snaps. Pastry lemon drops donut apple pie chocolate cake gingerbread. Jujubes sugar plum topping chocolate. Dragée dessert carrot cake candy canes oat cake tart tootsie roll lollipop soufflé. Apple pie sugar plum lemon drops. Carrot cake cake fruitcake toffee. Gummies cake apple pie sugar plum cotton candy pastry chocolate cake. Cupcake pie donut tart gummi bears icing cotton candy. Chocolate cake halvah tiramisu. Chocolate croissant jujubes chocolate bar chupa chups chocolate bar brownie sugar plum topping. Jelly beans apple pie macaroon soufflé cookie. ';'NewYork':' New York Biscuit bear claw candy toffee danish carrot cake lollipop lemon drops. Chocolate brownie soufflé tootsie roll pastry donut jujubes powder. Macaroon topping topping tiramisu tart cupcake pie ice cream. Croissant gummi bears icing fruitcake lemon drops lollipop. Oat cake marshmallow chupa chups wafer cupcake wafer jujubes topping sesame snaps. Pastry lemon drops donut apple pie chocolate cake gingerbread. Jujubes sugar plum topping chocolate. Dragée dessert carrot cake candy canes oat cake tart tootsie roll lollipop soufflé. Apple pie sugar plum lemon drops. Carrot cake cake fruitcake toffee. Gummies cake apple pie sugar plum cotton candy pastry chocolate cake. Cupcake pie donut tart gummi bears icing cotton candy. Chocolate cake halvah tiramisu. Chocolate croissant jujubes chocolate bar chupa chups chocolate bar brownie sugar plum topping. Jelly beans apple pie macaroon soufflé cookie. '),'Japan', @category)}"/>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="${xpath_eval(format-date(current-date(),'[Y0001]-[M01]-[D01]'))}"
                 who="pers:${answer(@encoder)}">Created file.</change>
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
