<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="${cfn}">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>${ask('What is the title of this document?', string, '', @title)}</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Author</resp>
               <name ref="pers:WE">Winnifred Eaton</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Transcriber',radio,('IG1':'Isobel Gibson';'SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'CG1':'C. Allan Gilbert';'KA1':'Karl J. Anderson';'KS2':'Kiyokichi Sano';'JC1':'John Cecil Clay';'HH1':'Henry Hutt';'CP1':'C. F. Peters';'LP1':'L. A. C. Panton';'EB1':'Edward Butler';'AP1':'Alden Peirson';'MP1':'May Wilson';'MM1':'M. McKinlay';'GW1':'Gustavus C. Widney';'KI2':'Kyohei Inukai';'BC1':'B. West Clinedinst';'WK1':'W. H. D. Koerner';'CA1':'Clare Angell';'GF1':'Gazo Foudji';'HT1':'Harry E. Townsend';'LZ1':'L. W. Ziegler';'CW1':'C. D. Weldon';'JG1':'John C. Gilbert';'LB1':'Louis Betts';'AC1':'Alfred S. Campbell';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'HB2':'Howard V. Brown';'JD1':'J.E. Dean';'CR2':'JC. Relyea';'MH1':'Mark Hayne';'CR1':'Capel Rowley';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MF1':'Margaret Fernie';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'DC1':'Daisy Couture';'SB2':'Samantha Bowen';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio';'DB1':'Diana Birchall';'KS1':'Karen Skinazi';'SH1':'Shaun Hunter';'SC1':'Sijia Cheng'),'IG1', @transcriber)}"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Copy Editor</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Copy Editor',radio,('IG1':'Isobel Gibson';'SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'CG1':'C. Allan Gilbert';'KA1':'Karl J. Anderson';'KS2':'Kiyokichi Sano';'JC1':'John Cecil Clay';'HH1':'Henry Hutt';'CP1':'C. F. Peters';'LP1':'L. A. C. Panton';'EB1':'Edward Butler';'AP1':'Alden Peirson';'MP1':'May Wilson';'MM1':'M. McKinlay';'GW1':'Gustavus C. Widney';'KI2':'Kyohei Inukai';'BC1':'B. West Clinedinst';'WK1':'W. H. D. Koerner';'CA1':'Clare Angell';'GF1':'Gazo Foudji';'HT1':'Harry E. Townsend';'LZ1':'L. W. Ziegler';'CW1':'C. D. Weldon';'JG1':'John C. Gilbert';'LB1':'Louis Betts';'AC1':'Alfred S. Campbell';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'HB2':'Howard V. Brown';'JD1':'J.E. Dean';'CR2':'JC. Relyea';'MH1':'Mark Hayne';'CR1':'Capel Rowley';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MF1':'Margaret Fernie';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'DC1':'Daisy Couture';'SB2':'Samantha Bowen';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio';'DB1':'Diana Birchall';'KS1':'Karen Skinazi';'SH1':'Shaun Hunter';'SC1':'Sijia Cheng'),'IG1', @copyeditor)}"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Encoder',radio,('IG1':'Isobel Gibson';'SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'CG1':'C. Allan Gilbert';'KA1':'Karl J. Anderson';'KS2':'Kiyokichi Sano';'JC1':'John Cecil Clay';'HH1':'Henry Hutt';'CP1':'C. F. Peters';'LP1':'L. A. C. Panton';'EB1':'Edward Butler';'AP1':'Alden Peirson';'MP1':'May Wilson';'MM1':'M. McKinlay';'GW1':'Gustavus C. Widney';'KI2':'Kyohei Inukai';'BC1':'B. West Clinedinst';'WK1':'W. H. D. Koerner';'CA1':'Clare Angell';'GF1':'Gazo Foudji';'HT1':'Harry E. Townsend';'LZ1':'L. W. Ziegler';'CW1':'C. D. Weldon';'JG1':'John C. Gilbert';'LB1':'Louis Betts';'AC1':'Alfred S. Campbell';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'HB2':'Howard V. Brown';'JD1':'J.E. Dean';'CR2':'JC. Relyea';'MH1':'Mark Hayne';'CR1':'Capel Rowley';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MF1':'Margaret Fernie';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'DC1':'Daisy Couture';'SB2':'Samantha Bowen';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio';'DB1':'Diana Birchall';'KS1':'Karen Skinazi';'SH1':'Shaun Hunter';'SC1':'Sijia Cheng'),'IG1', @encoder)}"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><!--Encode bibliographic citation for the source here--></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Document Type',radio,('docPrimarySource':' Primary Source ';'docPrimarySourceMS':' Primary Source: Manuscripts ';'docPrimarySourcePublished':' Primary Source: Published ';'docBornDigital':'Born Digital document';'docBornDigitalListing':' Listing Pages ';'docBornDigitalDocumentation':' Documentation '),'docPrimarySource', @doctype)}"/>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:genre"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Genre',radio,('genreShortStory':' Short Story ';'genreNF':'Non-fiction';'genreNFAuto':'Non-fiction: Autobiography';'genreNFDedication':'Non-fiction: Dedication';'genreNFInterview':'Non-Fiction: Interview';'genreNFIntroduction':'Non-fiction: Introduction';'genreNFEthnography':'Non-fiction: Ethnography';'genreFilm':'Film';'genreFilmScenario':'Film: Scenario';'genreFilmTreatment':'Film: Treatment';'genreFilmScreenplay':'Film: Screenplay';'genrePoem':'Poem';'genreNovel':'Novel';'genreNovelSerial':'Novel: Serial'),'genreShortStory', @genre)}"/>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:category"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Exhibit',radio,('Japan':' Playing Japanese 1896–1922 After her return from Jamaica in 1896, Eaton worked as a stenographer, first in Cincinnati, then in Chicago. At this time, she assumed the identity of Kitishima Tackehasche, a young Yokohama-born writer who published under the pseudonym Onoto Watanna, the name under which Eaton would become best known. For the next decade, Eaton indulged readers’ seemingly endless appetite for the Orient, depicting with exotic flair Japanese gardens, tea-houses, geishas, and matchmakers. Her Eaton’s earliest Japanese story, A Japanese Girl was published in Cincinnati’s Commercial Tribune in 1896. Between 1896 and 1922, Eaton published 12 Japanese novels, scores of short stories and ethnographic pieces, and poetry, and even co-authored A Chinese Japanese Cookbook with her sister Sara Eaton Bosse. ';'Alberta':'Alberta 1919–1936 Eaton divorced Bertrand Babcock, married businessman Frank Reeve, and, with her three children, moved west to the Canadian province of Alberta in 1917. At the Bow View Ranch in Morley, Alberta, Eaton experienced life on the wide open prairie, populated only by ranchers, indigenous people, cattle, and horses. This far-flung locale sparked a new phase in Eaton’s career. She wrote two realist novels set in the Canadian west and published a number of journalistic features about the people, places, and happenings of her new home. She also began to experiment with a new form of publication, the pulps--cheaply produced magazines featuring genre fiction of various sorts, including romance, mystery, and adventure fiction--the more sensational, the better. ';'Hollywood':'In Hollywood 1921–1935 Eaton flirted with the film industry as early as 1915 but did not actually sign on with a studio until 1924, when she was hired by Universal Pictures. Eaton proved able to turn out scripts rapidly and to order, according to biographer Diana Birchall. She later worked for Metro-Goldwyn Mayer and Twentieth-Century Fox, writing original screenplays as well as adaptations. William Faulkner, F. Scott Fitzgerald, and many other seasoned writers found writing for the film industry difficult but Eaton flourished. She found herself assigned to write film vehicles for two stars, Mary Nolan (Barbary Coast, Shanghai Lady) and Mary Philbin (Phantom of the Opera), and was able to translate her experience writing Japanese romances into scripts featuring exotic locales and peoples--which made up about 25% of the work to which she was assigned. ';'EarlyExperiment':' Early Experiments 1895–1902 Winnifred Eaton’s writing apprenticeship began in Montreal where, as a young girl, she invented stories and fairy songs. Eaton exaggerated when she claimed that she was 14 when her first publication, a serialized short story, appeared in Montreal’s Metropolitan (Poor Devil, a fragment of which Eaton preserved in her scrapbook). During this early stage of her career, Eaton published short stories, several of which are set in Montreal, and also experimented with journalism. Her experience writing for a Montreal newspaper, she claimed, got her a job as a writer and reporter for the daily Gall’s News Letter in faraway Kingston, Jamaica, for a few months in 1895-6, where she purported to have published pieces signed Busybody and Man on the Street. Her works for Gall’s News Letter, other than one poem, have yet to be located. ';'NewYork':' New York Years 1901–1916 By 1903, the novelty of Eaton’s Japanese romances had faded. Newly married to writer Bertrand Babcock and living in New York City, Eaton attempted to recreate herself. She wrote two anonymously published memoirs: the semi-fictional ME: A Book of Remembrance and Marion, based on her sister Sara’s experience as an artist’s model. She tried on another pseudonym, Winnifred Mooney, when she submitted to a publisher a manuscript about other ethnic personae, The Diary of Delia, a first-person narration from the perspective of an Irish maid speaking in a rich, if stereotypical, brogue. Eaton also wrote autobiographical journalism about her Long Island home and, with Babcock, co-authored a story set in New York State Eyes That Saw Not. During this period, she began to write more directly from lived experience, while ironically further obscuring her identity by adopting new pseudonyms and publishing anonymously. '),'Japan', @category)}"/>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="${xpath_eval(format-date(current-date(),'[Y0001]-[M01]-[D01]'))}"
                 who="pers:${answer(@encoder)}">Created file.</change>
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
