<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="${cfn}">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>${ask('What is the title of this document?', string, '', @title)}</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Author</resp>
               <name ref="pers:WE">Winnifred Eaton</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcriber</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Transcriber',radio,('SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio'),'SE1', @transcriber)}"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Copy Editor</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Copy Editor',radio,('SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio'),'SE1', @copyeditor)}"/>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoder</resp>
               <name ref="pers:${ask('Encoder',radio,('SE1':'S. Ehrhart';'AB1':'Albert Blashfield';'SB1':'Sara Bosse';'CH1':'Charles Horell';'GY1':'Genjiro Yeto';'MC1':'Mary Chapman';'JLC1':'Jean Lee Cole';'SL1':'Sydney Lines';'KI1':'Ken Ip';'JT1':'Joey Takeda';'SP1':'Serina Patterson';'HB1':'Hilary Ball';'XY1':'Xine Yao';'PP1':'Pavlina Pajot';'LM1':'Lucia Maggio'),'SE1', @encoder)}"/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><!--Encode bibliographic citation for the source here--></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:docType"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Document Type',radio,('docPrimarySource':' Primary Source ';'docPrimarySourceMS':' Manuscripts ';'docPrimarySourcePublished':' Published Primary Sources ';'docBornDigital':'Born Digital document';'docBornDigitalListing':' Listing Pages ';'docBornDigitalDocumentation':' Documentation '),'docPrimarySource', @doctype)}"/>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:genre"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Genre',radio,('genreShortStory':' Short Stories ';'genreNF':'Non-fiction';'genreNFAuto':'Non-fiction: Autobiography';'genreNFDedication':'Non-fiction: Dedication';'genreNFInterview':'Non-Fiction: Interview';'genreNFIntroduction':'Non-fiction: Introduction';'genreNFEthnography':'Non-fiction: Ethnography';'genreFilm':'Film';'genreFilmScenario':'Film: Scenario';'genreFilmTreatment':'Film: Treatment';'genreFilmScreenplay':'Film: Screenplay';'genrePoem':'Poem';'genreNovel':'Novel';'genreNovelSerial':'Novel: Serial'),'genreShortStory', @genre)}"/>
           <catRef scheme="wdt:category"
                    target="wdt:${ask('Exhibit',radio,('Japan':' Playing Japanese 1897–1922 In 1897, when she was working as a stenographer either in Cincinnati or Chicago, Winnifred Eaton assumed the identity of Kitishima Tackehasche, a young Yokohama-born Japanese writer who published under the pseudonym Onoto Watanna. Eaton’s earliest Japanese stories, A Japanese Girl purportedly published in Cincinnati’s Commercial Tribune and A Japanese Love Story in American Youth Magazine, have not been located, but most of Eaton’s located Japanese-themed short stories, novels, poetry, and ethnographic journalism are collected here. From 1897 to 1922, Eaton published 12 Japanese novels, scores of short stories and ethnographic pieces, poetry, and even a co-authored cookbook. ';'Alberta':'Alberta 1919–1933 Eaton moved out to Alberta after divorcing Bertrand Babcock and marrying Frank Reeves in 1917. Living on the Bow View Ranch in Morley, Alberta, that her husband owned or at an apartment she kept in Calgary, Eaton wrote two realistic novels about the challenges of living in the Canadian west, some Alberta-oriented journalism, some reminiscences about her childhood, and some sensation fiction. ';'Hollywood':'Hollywood Years 1921–1935 Biscuit bear claw candy toffee danish carrot cake lollipop lemon drops. Chocolate brownie soufflé tootsie roll pastry donut jujubes powder. Macaroon topping topping tiramisu tart cupcake pie ice cream. Croissant gummi bears icing fruitcake lemon drops lollipop. Oat cake marshmallow chupa chups wafer cupcake wafer jujubes topping sesame snaps. Pastry lemon drops donut apple pie chocolate cake gingerbread. Jujubes sugar plum topping chocolate. Dragée dessert carrot cake candy canes oat cake tart tootsie roll lollipop soufflé. Apple pie sugar plum lemon drops. Carrot cake cake fruitcake toffee. Gummies cake apple pie sugar plum cotton candy pastry chocolate cake. Cupcake pie donut tart gummi bears icing cotton candy. Chocolate cake halvah tiramisu. Chocolate croissant jujubes chocolate bar chupa chups chocolate bar brownie sugar plum topping. Jelly beans apple pie macaroon soufflé cookie. ';'EarlyExperiment':' Early Experiments 1890s–1901 Winnifred Eaton’s writing apprenticeship began in Montreal where, as a young girl, she invented stories and fairy songs. Eaton probably exaggerated when she claimed that her first publication was a serialized short story that appeared in Montreal’s Metropolitan when she was 14. This is probably Poor Devil, a fragment of which Eaton preserved in her scrapbook. While publishing early short stories, several of which are set in Montreal, Eaton also wrote journalism. She claimed to have written for a Montreal newspaper, experience that got her a job as a general writer and reporter for Kingston, Jamaica’s daily Galls Newsletter for a few months in 1895-6, publishing pieces signed Busybody or Man on the Street. However, none of her early journalism has been located. ';'NewYork':' New York Years 1902–1916 By 1903, many reviewers were beginning to question the validity of the Japanese background that Eaton had claimed and publishers were not soliciting any more of Eaton’s Japanese romances. Newly married to journalist/author Bertrand Babcock and living in New York, Eaton therefore tried to to move away from her Japanese persona and to write different content. For example, she submitted manuscripts for Marion, based on her sister Sarah’s experience as an artist’s model; the autobiographical ME: A Book of Remembrance; and Diary of Delia, dialect fiction featuring an Irish maid, to publishers under pseudonyms. ME was published anonymously. Eaton also wrote autobiographical journalism about her home on Long Island and co-authored a story set in New York State with her husband. '),'Japan', @category)}"/>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="${xpath_eval(format-date(current-date(),'[Y0001]-[M01]-[D01]'))}"
                 who="pers:${answer(@encoder)}">Created file.</change>
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
